Hello traders, Joanne again from Binary Trader, the
YouTube channel focusing solely on binary options trading.
Today I'm gonna make a $10 challenge, using
the fractal indicator and moving average crossover based
strategy, that I showed in my previous video.
Before diving in, let me kindly ask you
to like the video, and subscribe to the
channel.
Thank you very much for the support.
Let's start.
I am trading at pocket option, you can
find the platform link in the description as
usual.
In my previous video, I showed this simple
yet profitable strategy.
Let's add a fractal indicator with period 3.
Let's add a moving average with a period
of 3.
Apply a brighter color and make the line
thicker.
Add another moving average with a period of
7.
Make it more visible as well, with a
different color.
I trade this strategy on the 1 minute
time frame, and the trade duration is also
1 minute.
Set the trading amount to $10.
Choose instruments with decent payout levels.
The $10 challenge means I start trading with
$10 and risk everything I won on the
subsequent trades.
Basically throughout the whole session, I will only
risk the $10 I started with.
See how far I can get.
So this strategy in short.
When the 3 period moving average, referred to
as the faster SMA, set to white on
my screen, crosses above the 7 period one,
referred to as the slower SMA, yellow on
my screen, and the fractal indicator printed a
red spike below the turning point candle, we
take it as a bullish sign and bet
the price will go higher in the next
minute.
When the faster SMA crosses under the slower
one, and a green spike is printed above
the turning point candle, we bet the price
will go lower.
It's that simple.
Though to make the strategy really shine, an
understanding of the surrounding market structure, identifying supply
and demand zones, key price levels, trending in
the market is crucial.
Here the white moving average crossed below the
yellow one.
Wait for the green fractal spike.
There it is, bet the price will go
lower.
If you want to start trading, follow the
platform link in the video description below to
join Pocket Option.
Remember, after signing up, you should practice on
demo balance first.
You should invest real money only after you
completely understand how the platform works and gained
enough confidence with the strategy of your choice.
If you use my link, you may also
use the promo code 50START, also found in
the description, to get an extra 50%
on your first deposit.
Price went down.
Set trading amount to $19.20 and look
for another setup.
This came fast.
Fractal already printed a red spike.
Slower SMA is going to cross above the
faster one.
Wait for the close of the current candle
to confirm the cross and bet the price
will go higher.
While waiting here, you are welcome to share
your thoughts in the comment section.
Well, it tries to go down.
It might cancel the cross.
This was a perfect example for the importance
of patience.
It seemed to turn into a big bearish
candle at the middle of the frame, which
could have canceled the cross, but it ended
up as a doji candle instead.
A candle without a meaningful body, but long
wicks is called a doji candle.
It confirmed the cross and we have our
entry.
It went down quite a bit, but we
have a lot of time until the trade
ends.
So do not worry.
It does not matter where the price is
during the trade.
Only the level at the end is what
matters.
As you've seen, it was not too promising
during the trade, but at the end, it
went up.
Another potential setup here.
This is the perfect time to press the
like button and subscribe to my channel, so
you don't miss any upcoming content.
Don't forget to select all notifications after subscribing.
Don't forget to check the payout levels regularly,
as those might decrease over time.
I only keep instruments with high payouts on
my watch list.
This was also a bit tough at the
middle of the candle, but it worked out.
If you want to try trading at this
platform, press on the link in the video
description and sign up.
You can then start practicing on Demo Balance
for free.
When the current green fractal was printed, looking
at it in combination with the previous one,
you should be able to identify the slight
downtrend here, which gives a good confidence in
our entry here.
The big bearish candle together with the small
bullish one forms a bearish engulfing candle pattern,
which is a strong indicator of an upcoming
downward trend.
The cross has a wide opening due to
the huge bearish candles.
This and the bearish engulfer tell me there
is a high chance this reversal will continue
here.
I'm trading for roughly half an hour.
I feel like I need a short break
now.
I am back.
It's good to have short breaks during a
session, so you can clear your mind a
bit, fresh yourself up.
Here we have a steep and clear downtrend.
The signal from our strategy in combination with
this huge bearish candle gives some confidence in
the current trade.
If you want to start trading, follow the
platform link in the video description below to
join Pocket Option.
Remember, after signing up, you should practice on
Demo Balance first.
You should invest real money only after you
completely understand how the platform works and gained
enough confidence with the strategy of your choice.
If you use my link, you may also
use the promo code 50START, also found in
the description, to get an extra 50%
on your first deposit.
I'm almost starving, so I'm gonna keep another
short break.
You might say the current amount is almost
$1,000.
That's a great amount.
You gonna either lower your risk level or
end your trading session.
That's perfectly right.
End your session, close your computer and go
do the things you like.
Many times I keep short sessions like that.
But since this is a challenge video and
I'm still focused, I will keep trading and
probably catch a few more nice setups.
Please like the video, subscribe to the channel.
It's just a few clicks for you, but
helps me a lot.
Thank you for the support.
I love these huge bullish candles.
Yes, with a binary option it does not
matter how big the candle is, but the
bigger the candle, the better your analysis might
have been.
Look at the bullish engulfer.
That will give confidence in the signal when
we receive it.
Let's risk the whole balance again into splits.
On this platform, 1,000 is the maximum
amount to risk on a single trade.
But you can place any number of trades.
Probably it would have been easier and safer
to place two trades with $900.
Next time.
Please like the video if you enjoy it.
If you want to see more, subscribe to
the channel, so you not miss any upcoming
content.
Share your thoughts in the comment section.
As you see, 90% of the time
is just waiting.
Looking for a potential setup, then doing the
analysis, then waiting for the entry signal.
Waiting for the trade after entered.
Then starting the process over again.
With the next trade I can go up
to gaining slightly above 11,000, while technically
I was only risking the $10 I started
with.
Though I left $300 out of the trade.
So I will keep that and be in
minor profit still.
To be honest, I had a few attempts
prior to this, where I failed at different
levels.
But I was only losing $10 on each.
So my total loss is somewhere around $60.
That's not comparable to the 11 grand.
Not even to the 6,000, you would
say.
So it would make sense to stop now
either.
But just for the sake of the video,
I will do one more trade.
If I lose, my total loss will be
$70, while I keep the $300.
That would mean a minor profit of $230.
Which is still more than my daily salary
was at my last job.
But you can consider it as free tokens
for 23 upcoming $10 challenges for future trading
sessions.
Or $230 for $1 challenges.
That's a bag of opportunities.
Let's do the analysis.
Clear downtrend, check.
Cross was confirmed on the previous candle, check.
Green fractal is highly likely to be printed
in a few seconds.
Though the consolidation zone here bothers me quite
a bit.
But this bearish engulfing pattern gives confidence.
Let's do it.
I am trading now for almost an hour.
So I will end my session regardless of
the outcome.
Always keep your trading session short.
After a while it becomes stressful, you likely
lose focus, and that will lead to bad
decisions, which lead to losses.
This was tough.
Perfect ending to a session.
Hope you enjoyed today's video.
If you did, please press the like button
and subscribe to my channel.
Feel free to share your thoughts in the
comment section.
If you haven't done it yet, use the
platform link in the description to join Pocket
Option today and start trading binary options.
Thank you very much for watching my video.
I wish you successful trading.
See you next time.