Hey, hey, what's up, my friend?
So in today's video, I'll share with you
three swing trading strategies that you can use
to profit in the financial markets.
Doesn't matter whether you're trading forex, stocks, or
whatever, right?
These strategies can be applied the same.
So are you ready?
Then let's begin.
Okay, now before I begin, right, I want
to explain to you what is swing trading
because some of you are wondering, hey, what
is swing trading, right?
So let me explain to you quickly.
So swing trading, the idea is just to
capture one swing in the market.
So for example, let's say the market is
in a range, okay?
So over here, you can see that there
are swings in this range.
This is a swing, right?
This is a swing.
This is another swing, and this is another
swing, right?
So likewise, in a trend, right, you would
see swings in a trend as well.
So this is, let's say, an uptrend, right?
This is one swing.
This is another swing, another swing, another swing,
and another swing.
You get my point, right?
So swing trader, right?
Basically, right, what you're trying to accomplish is
to capture just one swing in the market.
That's it, one swing.
So here's an example.
So for example, this market is in a
range, and let's say, you know, you are
a swing trader and you buy support, right?
You buy over here at this area of
support.
So where will you exit your trade?
Well, as a swing trader, you typically exit
your trade before the opposing pressure comes in,
right?
Let me repeat that once again.
As a swing trader, you usually exit your
trade before the opposing pressure comes in.
So if you are long, right, where is
the opposing pressure?
The opposing pressure is traders who are looking
to sell.
So where will traders be looking to sell,
right?
If you look at this, chances are traders
will be looking to sell at this level,
right?
This resistance or swing high, right?
So you want to exit your long trades
before this opposing pressure kicks in.
So this means that you go long near
the lows and you try to capture this
one swing, right?
Exiting your trade before this area of resistance,
okay?
And likewise, if you are short the markets
at this resistance, right?
You want to exit your trades before this
area of support, okay?
So this is the core idea behind swing
trading.
And moving on, I want to share with
you three swing trading strategies that you can
use to profit in the markets.
The first one is what I call stuck
in a box where the price is pretty
much stuck in a range, stuck in a
box, right?
Similar to what you've seen earlier.
So this, the core idea here is that
the market is in a range, right?
You want to buy low and sell high.
So how you go about doing it is
to let the price come into an area
of value, an area of support, okay?
And let the price reject the lower prices.
So this, as you can see, right, is
rejecting lower prices over here, right?
The market, at one point in time, it
was trading lower and lower and lower, and
then suddenly the buyers step in and push
price all the way up higher, and finally
closing near the highs over here.
So this, right, is a swing trading setup
for you to actually go along.
So when this happens, when you see a
price rejection of the lows of support, okay,
you can look to get long, right, on
a next candle, right?
And look to set your stop loss, right?
Ideally a distance away from this low, right?
Because you don't want to set it at
the precise low because it's very common for
the price to just take out the previous
low, like this one over here, take out
this low, and this candle over here, take
out this low over here.
So you don't want to set it just
below it because there's a good chance that
you might get stopped up before the price
reverses in your favor.
So what I'll suggest is that, you know,
give it some distance, right, some buffer, set
it somewhere around here, right, somewhere about here,
and you can enter the next candles open
somewhere here.
So now, your goal as a swing trader
is to capture one swing.
So now the question is, where is the
opposing pressure likely to come in, right?
And if you ask me, right, chances are
it would come in somewhere about here, right,
somewhere about here.
So if you look left, right, there is
some resistance over here.
So you want to take your profit somewhere
about here, right?
And as you can see in this example,
clearly this one, the market didn't reach far
enough, right, before it reversed back into this
area of support, and then finally the second
attempt, it did hit your target profit.
So depending how you manage your trade, this
could be a break-even trade, a small
winner or even a loser, right?
So I'm not going too much detail into
trade management, because that would be a video
for another time, but I just want to
share with you the core concepts of swing
trading.
So the other one is what I call
catch the wave.
So this is used, right, when the market
is in an uptrend, right?
When the market is trending, you're trying to,
you know, time your entry and capture just
one swing in an uptrend.
And one thing to point out, right, is
that in an uptrend, okay, there are multiple
swings.
As a swing trader, if you ask me,
I will say, your best chance of, you
know, riding a swing is to capture the
swings, right, that is in line with the
trend.
So you can see that the moves that
are in line with the trend are usually
stronger, right, stronger, right?
This portion is stronger than this counter-trend
move.
This portion over here is stronger than this
counter-trend move.
So you usually want to trade with the
move, right, that is in line with the
trend.
I call this the trending move, okay?
And how we can go about doing it
is, again, over here, right?
I've just pulled out the 50-period moving
average.
In an uptrend, right, if it's in a
healthy uptrend, right, the market tends to, you
know, bounce off the 50MA.
So it's being shown on this blue line
over here.
So what you can do is that, wait
for the price to come to an area
of value which is this 50-period moving
average.
And again, look for a form of a
price rejection.
It can be a hammer, it can be
a, what do you call, a bullish engulfing
pattern and etc.
So in this case, you've got somewhat of
a bullish engulfing pattern.
Notice the price came in, right?
At one point in time, it was near
the 50-period moving average and then the
buyer stepped in and finally, you know, pushed
the price higher, closing near the highs, right?
As a trader, you can look to get
long.
Again, stop loss, right?
Give you some buffer below this low somewhere
here, entry over here, right?
And then you can look to exit your
trade, right, just before this swing high.
Again, we mentioned exiting your trade, right, before
the opposing pressure kicks in.
And this over here, if you ask me,
right, is where potential sellers could come in.
So you want to exit your trades just
before this swing high, ideally somewhere about here,
okay?
So you can see that you have, in
essence, what you've done in this, right, is
just to capture one swing in this uptrend.
Okay, so this is the second strategy, catch
the wave.
And the final strategy I want to share
with you is a little bit more, obviously
it's more aggressive, right?
But still, it offers a favorable risk to
reward on your trade if you execute it
correctly.
So it's what I call, fade the move,
right?
So this is actually a counter-trend trade.
Okay, so because, right, when the market is
trending, right, and it has actually travelled quite
a distance, right, towards the swing high, towards
resistance, there is actually opportunity for you to
actually take a counter-trend trade.
But I'll share with you a little bit
on how to manage this type of trade
because if you're not careful, the price can
actually reverse quickly against you.
So in this case, right, you can see
that this market is in an uptrend, right?
And price, right, actually came and retested back
towards this swing high over here.
Notice it travelled quite a bit, right, from
this swing low all the way up into
this swing high and then next candle, bam,
got rejected, forms a bearish engulfing pattern and
the market collapsed in the reverse lower.
But prior to this, right, if you think
about this, right, at one point in time,
the market, as it was breaking out higher,
there are traders who are actually going, or
rather went long on the break of this
highs, because they are thinking, hey, the market
is breaking out, right, man, I better go
long, the train is up, I want to
long the break out, I want to catch
the next move up higher, I don't want
to miss the train.
And then what happened?
Well, the next candle, it did a 180
degree reversal towards the downside.
That's why you got this bearish engulfing pattern.
And now this group of traders who went
long earlier, who went long on the break
out, are now trapped, right, because the markets,
they thought it's going up higher and then
it reversed against them suddenly, so they are
now trapped.
So this group of traders, right, where will
they put their stop-loss?
Chances are their stop-loss is possibly, right,
somewhere here, here, or even below this swing
low over here.
So what happens is that as the price
hits lower, you would actually hit this cluster
of stop-loss, right, from the break-out
traders, and that would fuel further selling pressure.
So that's the logic behind this trick.
So what you can do is that, when
you see this pattern where the price did
a false break, right, you can go short
on the next candles, open, again, stop-loss,
right, you can set it a distance away
from this highs, right, in anticipation that you
can capture one swing down back towards this
swing low over here.
Just a quick one swing down.
So now as I mentioned, right, this trade
is a counter-trend trade.
It's slightly more aggressive than the earlier ones
because you are trading against the trend.
So for trade management, what I suggest in
this instance is that you don't want to
hold your trades for too long.
So what usually I do, right, is that
if the price breaks and close, let's say
for example, let's say this candle, we are
currently looking at this candle, if it breaks
and close above this candle's high, okay, I
will exit the trade because I know I'm
trading against the trend.
I don't want to overstay my, I don't
know, you know, stay too long.
If it shows signs of reversal, chances are,
right, the pullback might end and the trend
would continue itself.
So this is where my trade management comes
in.
It will be more, I would say, conservative,
right, where my trailing stop loss, right, will
be tighter in this case.
All right, so this is what I call
fade the move.
So for the earlier trades, right, let's say
like catch the wave in this case, right.
So in this instance, right, you can be
a little bit more, I would say, giving
your trade more room to breathe because after
all, you're trading with the trend.
So there are a few ways you can
go about it.
Number one, you can use this market structure.
As long as the lower high remains intact,
you can hold on to the trade till
the price hits your target profit.
Or you can also, you know, use a
trailing stop loss approach, right, to trail your
stop loss, right, until the price hits your
target profit because after all, this one, you're
trading with the trend.
Whereas this one over here, the fade the
move, right, you don't want to overwhelm your
state.
You're trading against the trend, you want to
get out, right, when the market is starting
to show signs of a strain, right, in
the direction of the trend, okay.
So with that said, right, let's do a
super quick recap, right, what you have learned
today.
Number one, we talk about the swing trading
strategy, which is called stuck in a box
where the market is in range, you want
to buy low, and you want to sell
high.
We talk about catch the wave, right, for
trending market on how to capture a swing.
Ideally, you want to long at the area
of value, like the moving average, for example,
I shared with you earlier, it's the 50
-period moving average, and then exiting your trades
just prior to the swing high.
And finally, this is a counter-trend trade,
fade the move where the market makes a
strong rally into a key resistance or a
key level and then got rejected, right.
You can take a short position, right, and
capture a swing down lower and see whether
you can get a swing down lower thereby
profiting from traders who are actually long from
the breakout.
Okay, so with that said, right, I have,
you know, if you want to learn more
about what I do, you can go down
to my website over here, tradingwithrainer.com, right,
tradingwithrainer.com, right, Rainer is mining here, you
should know that, right.
And you can actually scroll down a little
bit and actually have a couple of trading
guides over here, right.
So one is called the ultimate guide to
trend following where I'll share with you practical
trading techniques, right, on how to write big
trends and market, and then the ultimate guide
to price action trading on how to better
time your entries and exits, right.
These two guides, completely free, right, just click
the blue button, right, and I'll send it
to your email address for free.
Okay, so with that said, I have come
to the end of this video, I hope
you find it insightful.
If you did, right, could you please, you
know, hit the like button, right, and subscribe
to my YouTube channel.
And if there's anything, right, that you want
to ask me or any questions, leave it
in the comment section below, and I'll do
my best to help.
With that said, right, I'll talk to you
soon.