In this video, I will reveal the best
strategy that you can use with the Moving
Average Indicator.
So, this strategy is called the Moving Average
Crossover.
It is a very simple and famous strategy,
but most traders are actually trading it the
wrong way.
The biggest mistake that everyone makes when trading
this strategy is every time the moving average
crosses over, they immediately take a position.
When the faster moving average crosses above the
slower moving average, they immediately take a buy
position.
And when the faster moving average crosses below
the slower moving average, they immediately take a
sell position.
This is actually the worst way of trading
the moving average crossover because using the strategy
this way only works if the market is
If the market is on a range like
this, you will receive so many false signals
and this will wipe out your account very
quickly.
The next mistake that people make when trading
the moving average crossover is that they use
too many moving averages.
Remember, the more moving averages that you use,
the later your entry signals will be.
For example, let's say you're using two moving
averages, the 20 and the 50 period.
So, if the 20 period crosses above the
50 period, you take a buy position here.
But if you added another moving average, let's
say the 200 period, then you would instead
enter here, which is a much later entry
compared to if you only used two moving
averages.
So the lesser, the better.
Another mistake that people make when trading the
crossover strategy is that they're trading it on
lower time frames.
Lower time frames tend to have less trend
and more range markets.
So that is why most traders lose money
when trading the crossover on lower time frames.
So instead, this is how I would trade
the moving average crossover.
I'm only going to be using two moving
averages, the 20 and the 50 period.
The first step is that I would choose
a high time frame.
I recommend using the daily time frame for
this strategy, but if you think that that's
too high, then you can just use the
one hour chart instead.
Next, I would pick a pair.
Then, what I'm trying to look at is
how the market is reacting to the moving
average crossover.
Let me show you what I mean.
If you zoom out and look closely at
the 20 and 50 period, you can see
that the price tend to not react to
the crossover.
Here we can see that the moving average
crosses over downwards, but instead of following the
crossover and also heading downwards, the price instead
reverses and heads back up.
And now you can see it again here.
The moving average crosses upwards, but the price
instead went downwards.
So clearly, this market has a history of
not reacting to the crossover, and so I
will not use the crossover strategy on this
market.
So let's look at another pair instead.
Here's the Euro GBP.
If you zoom out and look closely at
the 20 and 50 period, we can actually
see that the market tends to react to
the crossover.
Over here, we can see that the moving
average crosses over upwards, and the price followed
that signal and made an uptrend.
Next, you can see it happening again here.
The moving average crosses over downwards, and the
price made a downtrend.
This has actually happened multiple times in this
chart.
Every time the moving average crosses over, the
market tends to follow that same direction.
And so now we know that this market
has a history of following the crossover, so
I will confidently trade the crossover strategy on
this market.
But remember, just because a market reacted to
the crossover in the past doesn't guarantee 100
% that it's going to do that again
in the future.
However, it will still have a much higher
chance of doing so compared to the market
that never reacted to the crossover in the
first place.
So once you identified the right market, it's
time to trade the crossover.
For your entry signal, if the 20MA crosses
above the 50MA, you take a buy position.
And if the 20MA crosses below the 50MA,
you take a sell position.
And for your exit signal, you can use
an exit indicator like the ATR trailing stop
loss to exit your trades.
This will give a much better exit compared
to if you waited for the average to
cross over again.
For example, let's say you took a buy
position here.
If you waited for the lines to cross
over again, you would've exited your trade here
and wasted so many pips.
But if you had used a better exit
indicator like the ATR trailing stop loss, you
would instead exit here.
Notice that it gave a much better exit
signal and you would've kept more pips.
So that's my approach when trading the moving
average crossover.
Another way of using the moving average is
by trading it like support and resistance.
And another indicator that is perfect for the
strategy is the stochastics.
So here's an example on how the strategy
works.
In this chart, we can see that the
price went up to this level, it hit
and reverses downwards.
This happened multiple times which further confirms that
the moving average is acting as a resistance.
Next, we also noticed a pattern.
Every time prices went up to the resistance
while the stochastics is at overbought, the price
tends to reverse downwards.
And now, as you can see in the
current price, we are back at the resistance
level while the stochastics is at overbought.
So this is a good opportunity to take
a sell position.
Let's look at another example.
In this chart, we can see that the
moving average is acting as a support.
As prices went down to this level, hit
and reverses upwards multiple times.
And we also noticed that the same pattern
has formed.
Every time prices went down to the moving
average while the stochastics is at oversold, the
price tends to reverse back up.
So now, as we look at the current
price, you can see that it is back
at the support line while the stochastics is
at oversold.
So this is a good opportunity to take
a buy position.
Another moving average strategy that you can use
is by combining the 200 exponential moving average
with any indicator and automatically increase its win
rate.
Let me give you an example.
If you're just trading only using the parabolic
star, it will give you a win rate
of only 38%.
But if you combine it with a 200
EMA, it will increase the win rate to
46%.
It also works with other indicators as well.
For example, the super trend.
If you're trading only using the super trend
indicator, it will give a win rate of
only 39%.
But if you combine it with a 200
EMA, it can boost that win rate to
48%.
So adding the 200 EMA with any indicator
can automatically increase its win rate.
And the way you combine the 200 EMA
with other indicators is very simple.
If the price is above the 200 EMA,
you only take buy positions.
And if the price is below the 200
EMA, you only take sell positions.
So let me give you an example.
If an indicator, in this case, the super
trend, gave a buy signal while the price
is above the 200 EMA, you take a
buy position.
But if the super trend gave a buy
signal but the price is below the 200
EMA, then you ignore this buy signal.
This also works for sell signals as well.
If the super trend gave a sell signal
and the price is below the 200 EMA,
you take a sell position.
But if the super trend gave a sell
signal but the price is above the 200
EMA, then you ignore this sell signal.
So that's how you combine any indicator with
the 200 EMA.
So I just gave you the best moving
average strategy that you can implement in your
trading system right now.
And all I ask for in return is
for you to take 2 seconds of your
time into liking the video and subscribe to
the channel.
It literally takes only 2 clicks but it
means so much to me.
And you can also check out my other
videos as well.
So thank you guys for watching and I'll
see you in the next video.