Okay, first to demonstrate how call options work,
I'm going to tell you a little story.
And by the way, if calls and puts
are old hat to you, then you've already
got a leg up.
So the method I'm going to teach you
afterward will be even easier for you to
apply with options.
Okay, here we go.
So Susie's selling her house for $500,000
in a neighborhood that has a nearby parcel
of land that is for sale as well.
There are two parties interested in the land.
And Peter plans to develop the land into
a beautiful park and bird sanctuary.
And Harry plans to build a low-cost
housing development.
Now Sammy comes along and is interested in
buying Susie's house for a cash deal.
But he has a problem.
He won't have the cash available for three
months.
So he's of course worried that the house
will be sold to someone else in the
meantime.
So he decides to offer Susie $5,000,
or the option premium, right now if she'll
take the house off the market and give
him the option.
This would be a call option to buy
the house for $500,000, which is referred
to as the strike price, anytime within the
next three months, which is the expiration date.
Now if he does not elect to buy
the house, Susie keeps the $5,000 premium
and Sammy walks away from the deal.
If he does elect to buy the house,
or exercise the option, Susie still gets to
keep the $5,000 and he pays her
$500,000 for the house.
Now, three things could happen in this story.
In Scenario 1, Peter buys the nearby parcel
of land.
This of course will increase the value of
Susie's home to say $600,000, in which
case Sammy will be very happy to exercise
his option to buy the house for $500
,000.
In Scenario 2, Harry buys the nearby parcel
of land.
This of course will decrease the value of
Susie's home to say $400,000, in which
case Sammy will not exercise his option to
buy at $500,000 and he'll just walk
away from the deal having lost only $5
,000.
Then there's Scenario 3 where neither party buys
the nearby parcel of land.
Susie's house is still worth $500,000 and
Sammy can elect to exercise his option to
buy the house for $500,000 or not
and simply walk away from the deal losing
only $5,000.
In effect, Sammy is controlling a $500,000
asset for three months for only $5,000.
No matter what happens during that time, the
most he can lose is $5,000.
Susie on the other hand is happy to
take the $5,000 as she had no
guarantee anyone else would buy the house at
her asking price, nor did she feel the
nearby parcel of land would sell any time
soon.
Here's a footnote to this story.
Depending on the circumstances, if Susie felt she
was likely to attract another buyer in the
near term, she would have demanded more than
$5,000 from Sammy to take the house
off the market for three months.
Likewise with call options, the more the underlying
asset is perceived to appreciate, the higher the
premium demanded by the market for that call
option.
So now let's define this in trading terms
and look at an actual example trade.
A call option is a contract between two
parties to exchange a stock at a strike
price by a predetermined date.
One party, the buyer of the call, has
the right, but not an obligation, to buy
the stock at the strike price by the
future date, while the other party, the seller
of the call, has the obligation to sell
the stock to the buyer at the strike
price if the buyer exercises the option.
For example, if a stock is trading at
$50 and you think it's going to go
up to $60, you might buy a $55
call option for say $0.20. If the
stock rose to $60, that would allow you
to buy the stock at $55 even though
it's valued at $60 netting you a $4
.80 profit on each share.
On the other hand, the person that sold
you the call would be obligated to sell
you the stock at $55 at a loss
of $4.80. If the stock never rises
above $55 by expiration date, the call expires
worthless and the call buyer is out $0
.20 and the call seller keeps the $0
.20. Okay now let's look at how put
options work by revisiting Susie and Sammy from
our earlier story.
Sammy owns a truck worth $40,000.
He's concerned that his truck might be damaged
in an accident or even stolen.
So Sammy decides to buy a zero deductible
insurance policy, or a put option, on the
truck for the full amount of $40,000,
which would be the strike price, from Susie's
auto insurance company.
Susie charges him $1,500, that would be
the option premium, for a one year policy.
One year being the expiration date.
Now three things could happen in this story.
In the first scenario, Sammy's truck is not
damaged or stolen during the year.
So Susie keeps the $1,500 premium.
Sammy's okay with losing the $1,500 for
the protection it provided him for the year.
In scenario two, Sammy's truck is damaged in
an accident, requiring $10,000 in repairs.
He exercises his insurance policy, or his put
option, by filing a claim.
And Susie pays him $10,000 for the
repairs as agreed.
Sammy is happy he purchased protection for this
possibility.
In the third scenario, Sammy's truck is stolen.
He exercises his insurance policy, which is his
put option, and files a claim, but this
time for the full replacement value of his
truck.
And Susie pays him the full amount of
$40,000 to buy a new truck.
Sammy, of course, is very happy he purchased
protection for this possibility.
In any case, Susie's happy because she's sold
many such insurance policies, different put options, to
other drivers, most which never filed a claim
or never exercised their options, providing her with
a net profit overall.
And here's a footnote to this story.
If Sammy had a poor driving record, that's
more risk to Susie, so she would have
charged him more than $1,500 for the
one-year insurance policy.
On the other hand, if Sammy had an
exemplary driving record, Susie could have charged him
less as the risk would be lower.
Likewise, with put options, the higher the perceived
risk, the higher the premium demanded by the
market.
Let's look again at a definition and a
trading example.
A put option, then, is a contract between
two parties to exchange a stock, or an
ETF, at a strike price by a predetermined
date.
One party, the buyer of the put, has
the right, but not an obligation, to sell
the stock at the strike price by the
future date, while the other party, the seller
of the put, has the obligation to buy
the stock from the buyer at the strike
price if the buyer exercises the option.
For example, if a stock is trading at
$50 and you think it's going to go
down to $40, you might buy a $45
put option for, say, $0.20. If the
stock dropped to $40, that would allow you
to sell the stock at $45 even though
it's valued at $40, netting you a $4
.80 profit on each share.
On the other hand, the person that sold
you the put would be obligated to buy
the stock from you at $45 at a
loss of $4.80. If the stock never
drops below $45 by expiration date, the put
expires worthless, and the put buyer is out
$0.20, and the put seller keeps the
$0.20. Thanks for watching this video and
I hope you enjoyed it.
For more free training, go ahead and subscribe
to our YouTube channel, like us on Facebook,
and visit ProfitsRun.com.
This is Bill Poulos wishing you good trading.