If you can master supply and demand, you
will be able to make so much more
money from trading.
These are what I'm gonna be covering in
this course.
But if you want this course to work
for you and you really want to master
supply and demand, please do not skip through
the video.
I'm gonna start off by teaching you what
is supply and demand, why you should trade
it, and then how to draw, how to
find supply and demand zones, and how to
actually trade these zones.
When should you enter for the trade.
Last but not least, I'm gonna teach you
how I personally trade supply and demand.
My own secret supply and demand strategy.
So what is supply and demand?
Supply and demand is basically aggressive selling and
buying.
That's it.
We want to see aggressive buying and selling
because this tells us that all the big
boys like big banks and institutions are entering
into the market and pushing the market in
that direction.
I want you to look at this candlestick
right here.
Big fat momentum candlestick tells us that there
is a lot of aggressive selling.
There is a lot of momentum and volume
pushing the price down.
On the right side, we see green momentum
candlestick which tells us that there is a
lot of aggressive buying, a lot of buying
pressure, a lot of momentum pushing the price
up.
So these are what you should be looking
for when trading supply and demand.
This momentum candlestick tells us that smart money
is in the market.
On the other hand, if you see small
candlesticks just like this, this is not demand.
This is small baby buyers.
We do not want to see small candlesticks
like this because there is no volume or
momentum by the smart money at all.
Why should you trade supply and demand?
Let me tell you why I trade supply
and demand.
Because I want to trade with the big
boys who have a lot of money.
I want to react to the price when
these big boys enter the market.
The best way to see them entering into
the market is by waiting for supply and
demand.
Supply is when the market is going down
aggressively and demand is when the market is
going up aggressively.
So I want to see this nice momentum
candlestick that tells me that the big boys
have come out to play.
Remember, we are retail traders.
We are brokies.
We do not have enough money to move
the market while these guys are dealing with
millions and billions of dollars.
Let's say that you have insider information and
you know that the big boys, smart money,
billionaire traders, whatever you like to call them
are buying at this key level right here.
So will you enter for a buy?
You are a dumbass if you said no.
Of course you would.
It's literally free money.
If insider trading wasn't illegal.
Because you know that these people have the
money and the power to move the market.
So obviously you want to ride the wave
with them.
Because the last thing you want to do
is to trade against them.
But that is what a lot of retail
traders do.
Now that you have understood why you should
trade supply and demand, let's talk about how
to actually find these supply and demand zones.
The first step is that you want to
look for at least 3 momentum candles in
a row.
So you can see right here we have
spotted 3 green momentum candles in a row.
It can be more, it can be 4
or 5 green candles in a row.
But the minimum is at least 3 momentum
candles in a row.
Remember, you do not want to see tiny
small little candlesticks just like this.
You want momentum candles.
The big boys.
So in this example, I will just use
these 3 green momentum candles right here.
So the next step is that you want
to find the area where the move started.
So this up move right here started from
the previous candle.
So this is the previous candle right here.
So in this case, what you want to
do is to take out your rectangle tool
and mark the high and the low of
the previous candle.
So just draw like a little box and
drag it all the way out here like
this.
So now, the area between these 2 lines
will become the demand zone.
So right now, what we want to do
is to wait for price to come back
down to this area and then enter for
a buy.
But price already did that right?
Price literally went down to retest the demand
zone before shooting back up.
So if you enter for a buy here,
you have made a load of money.
Here's another example.
There is literally 3 momentum candles in a
row right here.
So we take our box tool and we
box the previous candle.
The high, drag it all the way down
to the low and then drag it to
the right side just like this.
So this will be your supply zone because
the last time price was here, it got
pushed all the way down here.
So this is your supply zone and we
are waiting for price to come back up
to this area and look at what happen
next.
Boom boom boom.
So right now, price has managed to come
back up to this area and I want
you to observe to see what price does.
It literally collapsed.
Do you saw that?
I hope you saw that.
It literally went back up to this supply
area that we have drawn and collapsed.
So that's the first way that you can
use to identify your supply and demand zones.
The next way is consolidation.
You can see right here, price is just
going sideways, not going anywhere.
So what you can do is that you
can draw a box to box up this
entire consolidation and look at what price does.
Price literally went up all the way to
touch this consolidation box before heading back down.
So that is your second way.
The third way is to identify an area
with weeks.
So weeks basically show us that price is
rejecting that area, right?
So you can see right here, there is
multiple long week candles at this area here.
So what you can do is that you
can draw a box around this area here
and just drag it all the way right
here.
So you can see, the next time price
came back down to this area, price literally
shoot all the way up there.
So this was a very good demand zone.
That is also another supply area right here.
You can see there is multiple long weeks
being formed at this area, which show us
that this area is like a very strong
area that price is always rejecting.
So if you draw to the right, you
can see that next time price came back
all the way up here, it literally collapsed
all the way down to the demand zone.
Now that we have understood how to identify
supply and demand zones, we have to know
how to trade them.
So right here, I have spotted 3 green
momentum candles, which means that the demand zone
is somewhere right around here.
So after I spotted these 3 momentum candles,
I will be looking at the previous candle
before this up move is formed, which is
this red candle right here.
So I will take my box tool and
literally mark from the high all the way
down to the low and drag it to
the right just like this.
So this is your demand zone.
So right now, we are waiting for price
to come back down to this demand zone
to retest it before entering for the trade.
So there are basically 2 ways where you
can trade this.
You can either place a buy order at
the demand zone so that when price gets
down there, your broker will automatically get you
into a buy position.
Or you can manually enter the trade after
you see what price is doing at that
area, which is the one that I like
more.
Because remember, no matter how strong the demand
area is, there is always a chance that
price is going to break past it.
So right now, I'll be patiently waiting for
price to come back down to this area.
So we see what price does.
And as you can see, price is approaching
this area right now.
And the second price come back down to
this area and touch this area, you should
not enter yet.
You must wait for confirmation.
That is a very important point.
You have to wait for price to show
you that it is going to head back
up.
So right now, you saw that price has
come back all the way down here to
this demand zone and it gave us a
long weak doji.
And also multiple long weak candlesticks, which show
us that price is rejecting this demand zone
and it's going to shoot back up.
What does this candlestick tell us?
It tells us indecision in the market.
It tells us that price is rejecting this
area.
But we cannot assume that price is going
to go back up yet.
We have to wait for the next candlestick
or the next few candlesticks.
Let's look at the next candlestick.
So right here, price give us a big
green bullish engulfing candlesticks.
This tells us that, you know what, the
buyers are back into this market.
The big boys is at this demand zone,
loading up their buy orders and you already
know price is going to go to the
moon now.
So this is where I will enter for
a buy position right here.
Place my stop loss below this last higher
low or if you want to play it
safe, you can always place it below the
demand zone.
For this example, I'll just place my stop
loss below the last higher low right here.
So for your take profit, I want to
place my take profit at a key resistance
area or a key supply area.
So I'm going to be looking towards the
left and see where price last stop at.
If you look towards the left, you will
see that right here, price gave us three
red momentum candlesticks.
So right here, there is a supply zone.
So how I mark up my supply zone,
remember, is that you want to look at
a previous candlestick, mark the high to the
low and literally drag it up just like
this.
So I'll place my take profit all the
way up at this supply area right here
and place my stop loss a little bit
tighter somewhere right around here below this bullish
engulfing candlestick.
And this is like one to two.
Let's see how this trade plays out.
Price went up and smashed our take profits.
I want you to look at what price
did when it came up to this supply
area that we have drawn here.
It gave us one week right here, this
upper week right here, which show us that
there was sellers at this part of time
that was pushing the price down.
But the buyers are way too strong.
That is exactly why price continue to go
up even further.
Literally just rinse and repeat this strategy.
So after I've closed this trade, let me
just remove this and I'll just keep on
drawing my new supply and demand zones.
Since price has just broken past this supply
area and invalidated it, I'm just going to
remove this and I can see there's another
like demand zone somewhere right around here because
there is multiple weeks being formed right here,
which show us that maybe this is like
a little demand area.
So we can see like right now price
has came back all the way down here
and you can see what price did after
it came back all the way down to
this demand area.
It should back up.
At this point of time, price has just
confirmed to us that this is a valid
demand zone because price gave us three green
momentum candlesticks.
So I can just like redraw this demand
zone because I want to draw it at
this previous candle.
You know what I mean?
So I'll just like drag it from this
previous candle, the mark, the high, the low,
drag it to the right side just like
this.
And right now I'm waiting for price to
come back down to this area and show
me some sort of confirmation before entering for
the trade.
I almost forgot to mention to you guys,
but I also draw like a little supply
area right here because price gave us multiple
long week rejection at this area.
So this is like a little supply area.
And right now we just wait and see.
You can see right now price has came
back all the way down to this demand
zone and he has broken past it just
like a little bit.
So do you think we should enter for
a sell here?
This is what retail traders are doing.
Retail traders will just enter for a sell
when price break through like a little support
area or whatever.
And look at what price did next.
It went back up.
So this was ending up like a little
fake out.
So at this point of time, this gave
us a confirmation that price is not breaking
past this demand zone.
This demand zone is solid and we're going
to head back up.
This is the bullish confirmation that we are
waiting for.
You can see like the green candlesticks are
getting bigger and bigger.
So at this point of time, I'll just
enter for a buy somewhere right around here.
Place my stop loss below this demand zone,
take profit at the supply area that is
being formed right here.
And look how this trade play out.
Okay.
You can see price went up and right
there, boys, boys right there.
We just smashed our take profit, making this
a very nice supply and demand strategy.
Two wins in the bag, baby.
Now, since you're still watching this, I'm going
to give you a little secret.
I'm going to show you how I personally
trade this supply and demand strategy.
My own strategy, my own supply and strategy.
When I am trading, I do not just
like to rely on one confirmation.
I need multiple confirmation.
So what I like to do is that
I like to use all the other technical
analysis tools in my arsenal to give me
more confirmation for me to enter for the
trade.
For example, this trade right here, the moment
price starts retracing right here, just like this,
right?
I will pull my Fibonacci.
So I pull up my Fibonacci, drag it
from this swing low all the way up
to this swing high right here, and literally
just drag it across like this.
So right now I am waiting for price
to retrace all the way down to either
one of these retracement levels.
I've done like a full length tutorial on
Fibonacci retracement and how you can use this
to get high win rate trades, which you
can check it out after this video.
But basically how this Fibonacci retracement tool works
is that I'm waiting for price to come
back down to any of these retracement levels,
this 38.2, 50, 61.8 and 78
.6. And then I see some sort of
confirmation and I will enter for a buy
and I'll take profit at the negative 27,
the extension level right here.
So basically, the moment I start seeing price
retracing, I'll just pull out my Fibonacci retracement
and I'm waiting for price to come back
down to either one of my retracement levels.
So we still wait and see, you can
see price is like heading back down and
it came down all the way down to
this 61.8 level before it starts retracing
right here.
At this point of time, I'm not going
to be entering because I know that most
of the time when you are using Fibonacci,
you cannot be entering when price just bounce
off one time.
You need to wait for price to come
back down to retest this same ARL, which
makes it like a more solid ARL before
getting into the trade.
Now, this is where the real fun begins.
This is where the magic happens.
You can see right here, this is the
61.8 retracement level, but at the same
time, it is also our demand zone.
It's also our demand zone right here.
We have just discussed that this is our
demand zone, right?
So I'm not going to explain it again,
obviously.
So right now we are waiting for to
come back down to this demand zone or
this 61.8 level and give us some
sort of confidence for us to enter for
a buy somewhere right around here.
You can see this is literally like the
additional confluence that you need.
My Fibonacci retracement level lines up with my
demand zone.
So in this case, what I will do
is that instead of risking my usual 1
% per trade, I will risk even more.
I will risk maybe 2% on this
trade because right now I am more confident
in myself.
So right now I'm still waiting for price
to come back down to this ARL before
entering for the trade.
So we see price has came back down
to this ARL and you can see price
is just showing us that it's going to
reverse and head back up.
At this point of time, I would have
entered from my buy position right here.
Once again, place my stop loss below this
61.8 retracement level or demand zone whatever
and then place my take profit at the
negative 27 extension level.
You can see just now I place it
at the supply zone, right?
But now I'm going to be placing it
at the negative 27 extension level because I
trust the Fibonacci, it will do the thing
it does.
So we wait.
You can see price is like going up.
Okay.
And right here, we have just smashed our
take profit guys.
It's really, really just as simple as that.
You have to understand how to use Fibonacci
retracement.
If you still don't understand how to use
Fibonacci, you are doing yourself a huge disservice,
which is why I want you to check
out this video next where I literally give
you a complete course just like this on
the Fibonacci retracement to help you become profitable.
Click on this video to find out more.
And remember, you are just one trade away.