What's going on guys?
We're here today in Connecticut and we're going
to be hanging out at the ticker talker
office checking out what Stephen Kalasian is doing
every day from 8 a.m till 4
p.m when the market is open, how
it works, what he's doing, what he's looking
for, and everything that's going on inside of
Steve's room.
You're going to see it here in a
minute.
You've seen it before but now we're going
to get a more in-depth look at
kind of what goes on, what Steve's looking
for, so come along.
I'm taking you inside where most people will
never be able to go, so feel lucky.
Stay tuned.
Come on.
What's going on?
Good man.
So Steve, here he is, the man, the
myth, the legend.
All right, break down what you're doing right
now.
It's eight o'clock in the morning.
What are you looking for?
What are you kind of focused on?
So I'm just getting my eyes, you know,
zeroed in on what's going on.
I just walked in about 10 minutes ago
to start getting my desk organized, and then
I'm just starting my live room at eight,
checking my economic calendar because I don't like
to trade into any economic news.
So if there's any 8.30 numbers coming
out or 10 o'clock, I want to
get ready and prepared for it.
But just right now, I'm just going left
to right, just, you know, checking out the
futures contracts, where the overall markets are, looking
at some of the 4Xs, the pound, the
euro, the dollar, yen, and looking at the
index futures.
I'm trying to buy the S&P futures
because the future is eight o'clock in
the morning.
Equity markets start at 9.30, but I
got a lot of guys who trade futures
when I come in at eight o'clock
in the morning.
So whether it's the index futures, the crude
oil, currency markets, I have a GDP number
coming in at 8.30. So the economy
looks like it's strong.
It could be a sign that the Federal
Reserve is going to start raising interest rates
again.
And if it's a weak GDP, well, it
could be taking two ways that the economy
is starting to falter.
And that may be that it would be
offset by the Federal Reserve not looking to
raise interest rates again.
So there's a combination.
It's a whole way of, you have to
interpret it, but hey, S&P sell 90
or better here, and then not cancel the
balance.
So, you know, all day long, we're in
here.
But right now, after this trade, I probably
won't do much, you know, because of the
fact that, you know, you don't want to
have a position going into a big, big
number like GDP at 8.30. All my
life, I've never traded into an economic news.
I mean, I have what, 30 minutes, 25
minutes before, okay, S&P is 9.25.
So I probably, you know, I wouldn't be
doing much here.
So I'm going to get on in 10
seconds.
And people who are normally on a little
bit before would have probably caught that, you
know, one little trade, scalp trade on the
S&Ps.
If you look at all the four ETFs
reversed yesterday, and continued to be in a
solid uptrend.
What are we looking at?
You got a lot of screens.
A lot of people are like, Oh, we
need all the screens for tell us kind
of what we're looking at on the screens
and kind of break it down.
I think I was trying to explain to
people how you know, every screen is a
either a different instrument or different equity, correct
future.
So because I have so many screens up
is not because of any ego or anything
like that.
It's because of the way I've been doing
this for well over 25, 30 years.
And that's because of the fact that I
want to be able, even though technology, which
I have behind me, I put my three
assistants, I have my algos running behind me,
and they're blurting out stuff for me.
Yeah, right.
But it's important that, you know, when I
am more of a visual guy, too, right.
So when I'm able to have all my
different instruments that I look at that I
trade that my, my customers and my traders
look at, right, it's good that, you know,
I'm in a rhythm with it.
So instead of just having the algo, just
say, okay, you know, buy S&Ps, then
I want to watch the pattern.
And then I can trade in that pattern
all that long.
Number one thing is you want to be
on the right side of the market, right?
So I'm able to identify the trend, whether
it's a negative or a positive trend.
And then I, like yesterday, we caught the
whole reversal up.
You're also looking for kind of like correlations
to spy.
How does that work?
Like, let's say I'm trading the E-minis,
right?
What am I looking for in the spy?
So when I trade, you can trade the
futures contracts before.
My research has shown me you can trade
during the Tokyo and the European session outright
using my technology.
And then you can trade up until 9
.30. So what happens is, is that once
the bell rings at 9.30, and all
the markets open, equities, ETFs.
So yesterday, for example, if you look here,
I caught the buy reversal using my proprietary
algorithm on the 15 minute timeframe.
I caught the buy reversal here at 12
.45 on the spiders, right?
But if you look back, and I have
to scroll back here, you can see that
when I got the buy signal on the
S&P futures, right here at I think
it was about 15 minutes before 11.45,
like an hour earlier.
So at 11.45, I caught the buy
signal.
And I said to everybody that I thought
the lows were in for the day.
And then at 12.45, when the spiders,
which trade like a stock correlated with the
with the continuous contract, now they both lined.
So now I knew the lows were definitely
in and I was trade trading from the
from the long side on the S&Ps
or the equity markets as a whole.
I've done so much research on this that
I wrote this and the way they line
up very powerful and you should be going
in in that direction.
So that's why I'm able to see and
I teach this to people who are in
my live room, who use my software as
well.
High alpha generated trading ideas in and out,
you know, market direction, seeing things that a
lot of people you know, I feel can't
see and this is what I do to
try to help them.
How long are you typically in a trade?
Anywhere from one to six bars, which means
anywhere from one minute to 30 minutes on
a trade, I watch, I just absorb.
And then I you know, I'll wait.
Sometimes I've seen, you know, big drops and
then huge reversals up.
And so I just want to be able
to let the dust settle a little bit.
Usually the second move is the right direction
for my years of experience.
10 year bond still bullish here on the
15 and 30 minute time frames.
Alright, markets about to open.
What are you looking at right now?
What's kind of the game plan?
The indexes are down, S&P futures are
down six and Nasdaq futures are down 23.
That's the market right there.
Overall, I have buys of all my ETFs,
the spiders, the Russell, the Q's and the
diamonds.
So right now we're still in buy mode,
even though the market's going to open up
a little weaker.
So right now I'm just going to be
patiently waiting here and see which way the
market's going to dictate eventually.
How quickly do you normally try to get
in once the market opens?
Today it's there's not no umph to it,
but normally sometimes like if you see like
a, you know, an 1820 handle move up,
I try to fade it and short it
right on the opening and then try to
look for a quick scalp.
You know, how does the market open affect
the futures?
Obviously the futures are already trading, but they're
kind of trading on the idea that the
future price.
Right.
So right now you're just going to wait
to see where a lot of the underlying
stocks are going to open, like the Amazons,
you know, the names that are the apples
that are going to like right now, Apple,
I'm in buy mode, right?
The Nasdaq futures is down 22.
Okay.
Here we go.
All right.
So, um, all right.
Apple's still in buy mode here.
Tesla.
Wow.
New highs here in Tesla.
All right.
We have sales in, uh, Intel takes out
the 5296 level.
We're going to Intel.
You take out the 5296 and Intel.
You're going to get a sell signal here.
All right.
10 year bond.
Look to cover here.
Four and a half shouldn't have been able
to sell all fives.
No way you were selling all five and
a half.
Use a, use a five stop if it
starts going, but you should be complete here.
Half bid's going to get hit out here
at a half.
So you should be filled.
Let me give you some key numbers to
watch here.
Spiders need to hold above the 278.43.
Russell 156.73. Q's 172.86 and the
diamonds 259.27. These are all really big
numbers here.
If any of them get, start taking out,
we're going to see a reversal to the
downside right now.
The Dow's on the Dow's right up a
dollar here.
It's a 10 Oh three.
Now we probably, how many trades we do
today?
About 24, 20, about 20 trades.
We probably going to be in the mid
60, 70 range right now.
We have buys on the S and P's
the spiders, the Russell just reversed negative.
So one of the four ETFs are now
in sell mode here.
So I just feel like the market's really
heavy and this pattern on the bigger timeframe
has got to be complete.
So I'm still looking for another, you know,
20 to 30 handle push down the next
couple of days to complete that before we
get another push back up on the bigger
timeframe.
So normally when I'm trading, I'm looking for
opportunities in terms of a stock being overextended
the upside to go short or un, you
know, oversold to the downside to get down
to support area to get long.
Kind of how you, what are you kind
of looking at?
I mean, other than looking just at the,
well, I use my own proprietary algorithms.
Um, so I really never look at anything,
you know, I can show you examples, my
36 years of an overbought condition and the
market still rally 2000 points.
So the way I designed everything that took
me eight years of my life, I'm able
to identify the trends and reversals and the
patterns that set up.
And I have, you know, using my overbought
oversold oscillators.
So I'm, I'm pretty in tune to like
how I use them and use them with
other indicators so I can pick up divergence
patterns and oversold conditions that I know how
to use.
And I teach that all day long.
Is there a reason you have a preference
between the tick charts and bar charts?
I'm just so used to, you know, the,
the bar data like that I've been looking
at.
And to me, it's the only way to
look at it.
Um, I get into a rhythm with it
more, a flow.
So it's what my eyes are pretty much
trained on a daily basis.
Can you give us a quick little explanation
of how a bar chart works?
Yeah.
So basically looking at the traded fund spiders
SPY, uh, it's just data coming in and
just the prices, you know, within that, I'm
looking at a five minute timeframe.
So the data is just coming in and
out.
And then basically the way I have my,
uh, charting applications set up with using my
own proprietary algorithms, I'm able to, you know,
identify the patterns and the price action.
So obviously on that bar, the little, you
have the, on the left side of the
open.
Yes.
The open of that bar.
Now you can see the yellow digits right
here to the right because my right eye
is always currently on that bar.
So when I trade, I'm always looking at
the current bar and all these numbers to
the right house, very meaningful data for me.
So right now you can see, uh, it's
just dropping here.
Um, you can see that the, the high
on this bar and I click on it
and I can see the high is 278
.97 and it just got down to the,
uh, 86 levels.
So from high to low, it just dropped
11 cents.
So I'm able to identify much better visually
what works for me.
It may not work for someone else, but
most of the people that I teach and
who are training are using at bar data.
Okay.
Cause I think for me, when I'm looking
at candles, I'm looking, I see the red
and the green on the candles in terms
of, you know, obviously if it's selling off,
I'm seeing that and taking that into account.
Yeah.
You're not really.
I, you know, I'm using my own way
of my methodologies and how I'm, I'm trading
using my own proprietary algorithms.
And so I never really used candles.
I looked at them once on maybe some
30 plus years ago, but I, I just
not something that I look at.
Yeah.
You're not really looking at volume.
No.
There's no volume.
Well, I mean, the only time I look
at volume is just like when it's super
slow, I just wanted to see how many
contracts are trading on the S and P's.
And normally they'll do 20,000 contracts on
a five minute bar.
And you know, right now we're, uh, I
had a, you know, pretty, pretty much in,
in, in tune for that number on this
five.
I don't look at volume when I trade.
Is that what you're asking?
Yeah.
Cause I mean, no, some people are like,
Oh, if I see, you know, I'm not
going to get volume.
No, I'm not going to do that.
I only time I, I'm not going to
trade a symbol that has no volume where
it's like, maybe it does 500 shares in
an hour.
I don't illiquid.
I don't go anywhere near illiquid, uh, symbols.
So we're at 27 trades right now.
It's almost lunchtime.
Well, let's say 11 o'clock.
It's almost 11 o'clock.
We're on pace through 60 to 75 today.
On a really just when the market's just
rallying, rallying, rallying.
Like what's the, what do you think the
most trades that are made like in one
day in the kind of like in the
ticker talker room and stuff?
Probably North of a hundred.
Yeah.
Easy.
And then obviously you see what slow day
when the market's kind of just flat, it
just, yeah, you know, anywhere between 40 and
70.
So obviously that comes into play.
Like you said, you know, I'm waiting for
the setups being patient.
You got to be patient.
If the market isn't showing you the entries,
you're not buying.
No, no way.
Um, I'm not just, I'm just not gonna
have people commit capital just for the sake
of committing capital.
Well, I think a lot of people sit
there on the computer all day and they're
like, they feel like if they're not in
a trade, they're not doing, they're not, you
know what I mean?
Like they're not working.
Yeah.
I get that all the time.
That's a great point.
A lot of people say like, you know,
what do I do next?
I'm like, dude, you got to chill out.
You know, you just got to wait until
the pattern's set up.
Let the market, you want to be right
or you want to just gamble?
I'm not the gambler.
I'm waiting.
I want the odds on my side.
Do you ever notice, obviously like in the
middle of the day, it kind of just
slows down because you get those, you know,
you get the bigger moves in the morning,
kind of, I mean, trends kind of develop
and start moving through the middle of the
day.
And then like yesterday, the market right at
the end of the day kind of rallied
into closing.
You know, the markets in my point of
view doesn't have a predictive pattern like that.
I mean, there are days when it's like
you look up, it's three o'clock and
you're not stopped.
Yeah.
The last week or two, I would say
that it's been pretty much just quiet.
I could never, you know, there were periods
of time when you couldn't even do this,
this interview like this right now.
Every day is a different day.
So I don't come into the day knowing,
okay, from 11 to 1130, I'm just going
to, you know, relax.
You know, it's not like take a nap,
go to lunch.
We eat at our desks.
This is military.
In terms of, you know, as like somebody
from the outside to see like, oh, the
market crashed.
How'd you make money today?
But there's opportunities in a bear market.
There's opportunities in a bull market.
Do you have a preference really?
I mean, I think the markets, you make
more money when the markets go down.
I'm just saying like, in general, like, would
you, if we go into a bear market
for the next two years?
No, because you could trade like instruments like
the TZAs, which are the inverse of betting
the market going up, the SDAL, the QIDs.
So there's other instruments to trade from the
long side, you know, to capture that.
And, you know, you can always short, you
know.
So if you don't feel comfortable shorting, but
you want to buy instruments like the TZAs
or the QIDs or the SDALs, which are
the inverse of the market going up.
So, you know, there's always opportunities.
So there's other vehicles to trade.
It's got to expand your horizon.
Yeah.
That's one thing I've learned is obviously volatility
is pretty much what you need in terms
of, I'm not so much worried about if
it's green or red, I'm more worried about
if I'm getting action up or down.
Right.
But even like today, for example, it's pretty
slow at, what, 1046 in the morning.
But there's been opportunities here across the board.
I'm not going to deny that.
Some good opportunities in the futures contracts, gold
dropped from the time we got the sell
signal, I think almost six, seven dollars on
crude oils all over the place.
So there's opportunities.
It's just, you know, having the technology and
the asset classes that you want to trade.
And you know what?
Guess what?
If there's nothing there, there's nothing there.
Preservation of capital.
You just want to wait.
Because truth, I've been around a long time.
Things happen.
Yeah.
So let's say you get a day where
it's just like the end of the world.
We're down 700, 800 points.
Are you just the whole time just banging,
banging, banging?
Yeah.
All day.
You know, it depends on the type of
trader.
I have guys who are with me on
every trade because some guys are like they
just wait.
You know, it depends.
It really does.
You know, but I'm here to do one
job.
I give it up a million percent every
single day.
So I'm not thinking I'm just seeing what
I'm seeing and letting the technology tell me
and and the direction that I'm able to
see using my proprietary software.
I'm just calling out what I'm seeing.
I can't.
There's so many DNAs involved.
I don't know who's trading what with me
or what.
Like today, you know, we were short the
10 year bond all the way down.
So there may be some guys who don't
trade a 10 year bond, but there are
guys that do.
So other guys who are S&P traders
or guys who are trading oil or Forex
or waiting for moves like in Netflix, when
I said Netflix, take out the 360 one
and a half level and then it drops,
you know, almost more than a dollar and
a half.
So everybody's it's up to the trader overall
to get the comfort level of what they
want to trade.
So like with your with your algorithm, is
it always the more and more data you're
gathering, the more and more time you're using
it, is it getting better and better over
time?
I've never tweaked it since the time I
started running it forward.
So it is what it is.
And I always I believe in forward testing.
So I always just ran it.
And I've been I never once touched it
since I had it implemented on my software.
So on my chart.
So I just I believe in it.
I stuck with it.
I've taught many, many people how to use
it.
And this is what I use every single
day.
And I teach people how to use it
every single day.
To people go on to your talker and
see past performance of kind of.
Yeah.
Under my verified because I use this to
do my verified trades.
Yeah.
When I there's a section I'm a leader
on the platform.
So I'll be using that my technology there
to to, you know, trade and people can
actually see my real life, my performance.
OK.
Forty five trades, two o'clock.
What do you think?
How many more trades a day?
Two more hours.
Mark, let's say 45.
We'll push it to about 60, 65.
All right.
Yeah.
Have you.
That's what's been averaging with these slow days
when the ball when there's no ball.
I mean, look, the Nasdaq futures are less
down less than the dollar.
The Dow's down 30.
Is there one day that really stands out
like you remember, like back when you're trading,
like one day that you really remember, like
that was historical in a sense?
Well, that Monday.
Was it October 19th?
Yeah.
October 9th.
Black Monday.
I never forget that.
Shortest goal 1610.
Yeah, I think that day was it.
The Friday before was pretty wild because I
had to come in that Saturday morning.
But you're talking volatility that, you know, was
just back then, you know, 500 points on
the Dow.
I mean, that's like earth shattering.
You know, now we see the Dow move
a thousand points a couple of times in
the last year.
You just like, OK, well, it's at twenty
six thousand.
It drops a thousand.
It's not not so bad.
Right.
Yeah.
But, you know, I've seen you know, when
you're in the game, as long as I've
been for 36 years, you get to see
a lot of different things.
And there's nothing that, you know, I probably
haven't seen the most veterans, you know, who've
been in the game as long as I
have.
I mean, seeing the market go from from
a thousand to twenty six, almost twenty seven
thousand, twenty seven thousand.
I mean, now when you see a big
dip, it's just like nothing now.
I mean, you know, it's like anything else.
You don't get psyched out by it.
It's not you're in a mindset where you're
just prepared to see anything at any given
time.
And that's why, like I tell people all
the time, don't overthink things, you know.
So if you're going to trade futures, if
you're going to trade stocks or if you're
going to trade foreign exchange, don't overthink.
Just look at the just learn, look at
the pattern, identify and try to be number
one on the right side of the market
and then wait patiently for the patterns to
set up.
And that's what I do all day long.
Like right now, there's nothing going on and
I'm just waiting for patterns and trends to
develop or reversal here in the market.
So right now, everything is bullish right across
the board here.
So I'm not I'm not looking at anything
really much here.
Hey, let's take an aggressive long here.
S&Ps go 85, go 84, go 84,
89.
Use 83 and 83 stop.
Hey S&Ps, I'm taking an aggressive long
here.
The three and a five minute time frames
are reversing here on the diamonds and the
S&P futures and the NASDAQ.
But any push up, I'm buying this off
the 15 minute time frames.
Let's look to buy these S&Ps for
maybe a maybe a one to two, two
and a half handle scout.
Alright, so the market just closed.
We're going to get a little recap from
Steve, kind of what went down today.
Overall, you know, where they're at, what's going
on, how many trades they ended up at.
I think earlier, Steve said they're looking for
around 60 trades.
So let's find out exactly where they ended
up at.
So Steve, where are we at?
What's going on?
I know guys, what was the number today?
58.
I could have done a little couple more.
You could have got two more.
And I think you had two more just
kind of popping.
Overall, I mean, do you feel a little
bit of pressure?
I mean, 36 years trading.
I mean, kind of like you got to
perform, you know, like.
The only pressure I really get is when
I leave here.
Yeah.
And this is like my environment.
I feel really contained in here.
And I, you know, I know what I'm
doing.
So it's like peace of mind here.
I think they get a little bit of
pressure.
The assistance back there, a little bit of
pressure in there.
A couple moments, you know.
They know me.
They know what's going on.
But yeah, really cool to see kind of
what went down today, seeing the overall.
I think it's interesting definitely to see how
you're trading, you know, Forex, the gold, the
futures, the oil.
It's all in your head.
It's hard to explain, but I mean, you're
seeing it and it's happening and you're not.
It's like that.
It's not even it's like instinct where you're
just like you see you see crude oil
and you're like, oh, right here, let's get
in short.
And then it's bam.
And you're seeing that stuff where most people
would have to pull up a whole chart
and really take a lot of time to
kind of figure that out.
So that's obviously part of your algorithm.
And I spent eight years building this.
And so plus I do this every single
day.
But more importantly, the people who come into
my live room get this technology.
So they see exactly they get that good
as time goes on.
They're if they're committed to it and they
want to learn and they want to see
it and they want to really do well
for themselves.
So they're they're they have the same technology
I have.
Yeah.
So in the actual chat in the live
room, they can see the same chart you're
looking at, the same indicators, they can use
all that, even if they can keep an
eye on it and kind of learn the
same way that you teach them, you know,
keep an eye out for this indicator, this
setup.
Yeah.
And you can you're basically seeing what you're
seeing.
Hundred percent.
And when there's a lull, I'll go in
and I'll explain it.
I'll you know, I'll just bring up the
chart and I'll start explaining why I did
what I did.
And I start pounding it into them.
And remember, I told you patterns repeat themselves
over and over again, whether it's a pattern
based upon the way my algorithms line up
or a pattern based upon price action.
So that to me is, you know, the
way I wrote this, I you know, I'm
pretty much able to see that happening.
And when I do get a reversal or
buy and or sell signal, then I know
how to trade it.
But again, it's all visual.
So I want to be able to be
on the right side of the market.
I'm not guessing.
And I am very disciplined.
I have my stops in place and there's
no averaging down preservation of capital.
You've got to have all this, you know,
in the back of your head.
So.
So what you're telling me here is that
you're not gambling.
Well, anytime you put money at risk, it's
always a fear.
You're not just going in.
It's not 50 50.
You're not going in there.
No, I mean, the bottom line is, you
know, I'm not in this to be right.
50 percent, 60 percent, 70 percent, 80 percent
of the time.
I want to be right.
My consistency is everything for me.
So I want to be right.
Ninety percent, 90 plus.
And that's what I try to get people
to have that mindset, you know.
So that's what my goal is here every
single day.
I mean, I think the biggest thing when
people ask about day trading, oh, it's just
gambling.
I think at the end of the day,
what we're really doing here is we're managing
risk.
You see an opportunity where you see a
small amount of risk, but a reward and
you do that over and over and over
and you're consistent.
You can make money trading as long as
you have a predefined, you know, risk for
every trade.
And you understand that, like you said, you
can't just can't just start buying the E
-minis and just keep buying, buying, buying until
it goes.
Well, I'll be honest with you.
I mean, I've been trading for 36 years
and since I've had this and I wrote
this some 10, 15 years ago, you know,
I was just trading based upon the depth
of the markets.
You know, I was trading, you know, anywhere
from one to four or five million shares
any given day.
And, you know, back then there was depth
of the markets where anytime I saw a
buy or sell program come in, I would
just lift in offers and then, you know,
hopefully that the buy or sell, the buy
program in that example would continue and I
would be getting out into it, you know.
But when the era of decimalization came around,
you know, I would, I tell you right
now, if I didn't have what I have
here, I would never be able to call
the market.
I mean, I spent eight years of my
life building this and this is what I
do.
During the day when there's lulls, I constantly
teaching, I'm constantly educating people.
I just want people to get better, traders
get better and better and better.
Give them the right tools, make them consistent
and make, you know, and hopefully that they're
on the right side of the market with
me in trading.
Really cool to see you in action today.
Hanging out with you.
Thanks again.
Thank you.
For all the knowledge, information.
We got a lot more videos to come
from Steve really soon.
If you want to check out more on
Steve and what's going on at the Ticker
Talker office and everything like that, check out
tickertalker.com.
There's a link down below.
You can hit that link, check it out.
I think there's, like I said before, there's
also a little discount going on right now.
You can check that out down below and
see what's going on.
Free trial.
You might as well.
You might as well check out the free
trial, see what's going on and learn a
little bit.
Worst come to worst, you learn something.
If you don't enjoy it, you can walk
away.
But I think you're gonna enjoy it.
So thanks again, Steve.
Thanks.
We got to go.
We're out of here.