That's right guys, you are using the wrong
strategy and I'm gonna prove it to you
in this video.
I'm gonna also show you how you can
do better very easily, but only for the
ones who watch this video until the end.
I'm gonna show you a couple of strategies.
Two of them are very common.
The chances high that you are using them
and they are pretty bad.
Check out this chart here.
You have three lines.
Those lines represent the money that is in
each portfolio, right?
Each line belongs to a different strategy and
we have the blue line, we have the
black line and the red line.
There are all three different strategies.
Two of them you already know, they are
quite common and the blue one is a
special one and I will tell you all
about it.
But the question is, right, which of these
lines, which of these portfolios would you rather
one I have?
Because they all started at the same time
with the same amount of money as you
can see here on the left side.
But somehow one ended up with more money
than the others.
And also one of them always had money
even in the bear market while the other
ones actually gave it back to the market.
Now, this is called the equity line of
the strategy.
And unfortunately, TradingView does not offer you a
simple way to turn on this line so
you can see it.
But that's why you subscribe to this channel.
I will give you a way to turn
this on and to add it to every
single strategy that you have access to.
If you have access to the code, there
is one line only that you just copy,
paste, save.
And then you will have this line on
any strategy that offers you the code, right?
Very simple.
And you should have access to this information
because otherwise you're using strategies that do this
with your portfolio, right?
All of this in this video.
And make sure to click the bell to
not miss out on any new video that
I'm launching.
And keep in mind, this is not financial
advice.
Crypto is risky.
You can lose all of your money.
That's why I'm doing this channel to give
you higher chances of success.
And now let's get started.
All right, guys, let's look at the chart
and let's understand what can happen to your
portfolio if you're using the wrong strategy and
what can happen if you're using a proper
strategy.
And by the way, there is a high
probability that you are using a strategy that
produces the red line or the black line,
because those two lines, the portfolio lines belong
to very popular strategies.
At the end of the video, I will
reveal which line belongs to which strategy.
But first of all, let's understand how they
impact your life and your profits.
And let's start by looking at how much
money these strategies made.
And for that, we need to understand where
they started off.
They all started off here at the same
amount of money, roughly thirty five thousand dollars.
OK.
And the black and the red strategy, they
ended up now having one hundred seventy thousand
roughly in the portfolio right now, while the
blue strategy has nine hundred and six thousand
dollars in the portfolio.
That is a five X difference in portfolio
value, guys.
OK, keep that in mind.
Same time frame, just that one strategy is
way higher up than the other one.
Now, that is great.
But that's not the only thing that matters,
because if you are looking at what happened
over time, you can see something very important.
You can see that during the bear market,
this strategy had money in the portfolio and
it can be used for whatever you want.
You can buy apartments, you can buy gold,
you can buy jewelry for your partner or
whatever you're buying.
OK, while the other two strategies, they were
quite in a drawdown, because as you can
see here, the strategies were basically in a
drawdown of sixty seven percent.
Whereas this strategy here was only in a
drawdown of about twenty percent.
Right.
So taking out money from the blue strategy
would have been easy.
Right.
So the money is not locked up.
It can move.
It can help you buy things and maybe
invest even better in other assets during the
bear market.
But using these strategies here, it would be
very tough mentally to take money out while
the drawdown is so large, you would say,
like, let's keep the money in.
Let's wait for a recovery.
Right.
So the problem here is not only that
these strategies make less money, but also that
you don't have access to the money while
prices are cheap.
Now, keep that in mind.
This is very important what I'm saying here.
If prices are down, then most likely prices
are down also for other type of assets,
not just crypto.
OK.
So if you have money during a time
where everyone else does not have money, you
can buy stuff cheap, right, because you have
money.
The other people need to make money.
They need to sell their stuff so you
can negotiate.
Right.
But if you're using the wrong strategy and
you're basically giving the profits pretty much back
to the market, then you cannot take advantage
of this.
And this is the important thing that I
want to share with you here.
So it's not only about having more money
in the portfolio, yes, obviously, but also how
did you get there?
So money has to always work for you.
Otherwise, it will work against you because of
inflation and because of opportunity costs.
In the bear market, there is no reason
to hold an asset, a crypto asset that
goes down.
It's a waste of purchasing power.
Right.
You can take that and put it into
better opportunities.
And again, you have to have access to
the money in order to be able to
do that.
Right.
So if you see a drop in your
portfolio value like this or like this or
even like this, right, then you know it's
a bad strategy.
OK, I think now you get it right.
But before we continue and before I reveal
which equity line belongs to which strategy, let
me know which strategy you would like to
have the blue one, the red one and
the black one.
And also let me know down in the
comments which line belongs to which strategy.
What do you think?
Which one it is?
And I'm asking you this for two reasons.
First reason I want to know that you
pay attention.
And second reason is I need more comments
on my videos.
So go down below and let me know.
OK, let's reveal the first strategy that belongs
to the red line.
What do you think is the red line
about which strategy created the red line?
Well, drumroll, please.
We have the hodl strategy.
The hodl strategy is the red line.
And it made 369 percent profit since here
2018 and with a 76 percent max drawdown.
So it's anyway a horrible strategy, full waste
of time.
And also I have another video explaining that
I will link it up top.
But as you can see, here is the
worst of all of these three strategies because
it was in a high drawdown for many
years.
Right.
So this is pretty bad.
OK, so even the other strategy, the black
one is better than the hodl strategies.
Hodl strategy is really the worst thing you
can do.
And the reason is simply it does not
protect you from drawdown and it does not
have a sell signal to protect you from
even the asset going to zero.
So it's a waste of time.
Like whoever tells you to use hodl, you
should immediately unfollow them.
OK, because mathematically it makes absolutely no sense.
All right, cool.
So for individual assets, not for indices, indices.
Yes, but individual assets.
No.
OK, cool.
Now let's go to the next strategy.
What is the black line all about?
And is it better?
Well, it is a bit better because you
can see here it protects the portfolio a
bit better because they all start with the
same amount of money.
Well, the red strategy, the hodl strategy goes
way down and you have way less money
than before for a while.
And then it catches up.
But the black strategy always better is actually
always better than the red strategy.
But which strategy is that?
Well, let me show you.
It is the DCA strategy.
The DCA strategy is the black line.
Right.
It's OK.
It's still not the best or anything, but
it's better than the hodl strategy.
OK.
And I have like I said, I have
a video about these two and why they
are absolutely useless for individual assets, which is
what we're doing in crypto, right?
We're buying individual assets.
So for those type of investments, these strategies
are the worst performing strategies that you can
use the worst mathematically, the worst.
OK.
And that's why you subscribe to this channel,
because I'm showing you this stuff like if
you go to other channels, they tell you
use DCA like no.
OK.
Oh, my God.
Right.
Because DCA, it's way worse than the blue
one.
And the blue one is quite easy to
achieve.
All right.
So if you're listening to other channels and
they tell you to use hodl or DCA,
I mean, listen, after this video, in my
opinion, you should run away because mathematically it's
bad advice.
OK.
Having said that, this is not financial advice
either.
Right.
You can do whatever you want.
I'm just showing you the facts.
But let's go back to the chart and
also look at the net profit of this
strategy of the DCA one.
So we have three hundred eighty five percent
profit.
A bit better than the other one.
We have a max drawdown of only thirteen
point six.
So that's way better than hodl.
OK, like way better.
And also because now the price of Bitcoin
is quite high.
The percent profitable trades is also very high.
But that really depends on when you are
looking right.
If you are in the bear market, then
most of these trades are negative.
So that number will be way lower.
But for right now, when I'm making this
video, that is what it is.
OK, let's get rid of these squiggles here.
And now let's finally reveal what is the
blue line about?
What type of strategy is that?
And that blue line is created by one
of my strategies.
But you don't really need my strategy.
By the way, this is a trend following
strategy.
I will give you a free trend following
strategy at the end of the video that
produces pretty much this line kind of it
has a higher drawdown.
But still, you can do way better than
DCA and hodl with a fully free strategy.
OK, and I wonder why nobody told you
this before.
Interesting, right?
Again, that's why you subscribe to this channel.
So let me show you this strategy had
a profit of two thousand four hundred percent
since the same time as all the others
with a drawdown of 15, making massive amount
of profit compared to the others.
And as you have seen before, keeping your
money protected from large drawdowns.
OK, any trend following strategy is better than
DCA and hodl.
And is it hard to use them?
No, especially not if you subscribe to this
freaking channel, because that's exactly what I'm talking
about for a long time already.
OK, so now let me show you the
strategy that you can start using today.
OK, guys, I've added a new strategy to
the chart and the blue line now belongs
to the breakout trend follower strategy.
And the black and the red line are
the same strategies as before.
We have the hodl and the DCA, right?
Exactly the same as before.
And as you can see, the blue line
is better than the other two.
And fun fact, this breakout trend follower strategy
is completely free.
I have a link down below in the
video description.
It's not for me.
I just found it on Tradingview.
And that's what I'm saying.
It's so easy to perform better than the
typical strategies.
And because you watch this channel, you have
this benefit of me sharing free strategies with
you.
OK, so so check this out.
This strategy made a profit of 1,600
percent on Bitcoin since the same time here,
2018 and 26 percent max drawdown, 50 percent
profitable trades.
It's OK, actually, right?
It's a good strategy, especially for a fully
free strategy.
OK, this is amazing anyway.
So you see what I'm saying now, how
did I get this equity line, the blue
line into this strategy because the strategy itself
doesn't have it.
OK, and I promised you at the beginning
of the video, I will show you how
to do that.
Now, first of all, I have the strategy
here somewhere, and it's called breakout trend follower
here, right?
This is the original one.
And you see here, this icon, this is
the code icon.
So I can click on it to get
the code of that strategy.
When I click on it, it will actually
say that is a read only script, of
course, because it's not my code, but you
can create a working copy.
So click on that.
Right.
And then you can go way down.
You don't have to edit anything else.
You can just go way down and you
can paste this line.
And this line I will also put down
in the video description.
This will simply plot this equity line.
OK.
And now you just have to save it.
You give it some name.
So let's say so I put test here.
Right.
So you just save it and then you
have to click on Add to Chart.
Right.
Add to chart.
You click on that and then boom, it
appears on your chart.
OK.
And yeah, it looks crazy now because now
I have it twice.
And by the way, let me remove my
version here because that version was done before.
If you want to have less clutter on
your chart, simply edit the strategy in the
settings and go to the style and remove
signal labels and quantity.
And then simply you can close this as
well.
And now it looks a bit better.
And by the way, the strategies have to
start with the same amount of money because
otherwise you can't really compare.
And this was thirty five thousand one hundred.
OK.
And this is how I get them to
start at the exact same point in when
it comes to the money that they have
available.
And then they can be compared with each
other.
OK.
So basically you can just take this strategy
and use it right now.
I mean, today.
Right.
And as a mega bonus on top, you
can fully automate the buy and sell signals
of the strategy.
Right.
As you can see here, you have these
buy and sell signals here.
You can take them right.
The blue ones are the buy signals here
and the pink ones are the sell signals.
And this is how you can get the
back test.
This is how you can see all the
trades here and everything.
But you can take all of these trades.
You can automatically send all of these trades
to a trading platform called Signum, and that
will automatically execute the trades on your exchange.
So this is Signum.
Go and create an account and you can
then take the strategy from trading view and
you can tell Signum how to place the
orders.
And then you can connect Signum to your
exchange.
And pretty much basically what's happening is the
strategy is executing the trades.
But they will also happen for you with
your money.
So you don't even have to click the
button to buy and sell when the strategy
does it.
Instead, it's fully automatic.
And why am I telling you this?
Because my freaking channel is called Michael Automates.
OK, because with automation, you can better stick
to the strategy.
Less emotions, less manual mistakes.
Right.
So do that.
And listen, if this video didn't give you
massive value, then just I don't know.
OK, let me know down in the comments
how I could add even more value to
your life, because I don't know.
OK, I think this is huge and massive
and amazing.
But there is one thing, one more thing
right that I can add to your life.
But that's only when you have a portfolio
that is worth more than 10K.
That is basically auto trading dot VIP.
And this is my personal masterclass where I
have all the knowledge that I possess about
trading strategies, automation in this masterclass.
And I give access to my strategies.
Right.
One of the strategies you've seen in the
chart today, the blue line that you've seen
most of the time is from this particular
strategy here.
Right.
So go to this page, click on apply
for access if you want to get access
to this masterclass.
Yes, it's not cheap.
But if you have a bigger portfolio, this
is what you need, in my opinion, because
you don't want to mess around.
You want to have the best education, the
best strategies, the best community possible to protect
your portfolio and grow that portfolio.
Right.
Having said all of that, make sure to
destroy the like button, subscribe to the channel.
And this is the next video you should
watch.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh,
oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh,
oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh