In this video, you will see how people
get rich with options trading.
I will show you the math.
I think that the best way to do
this is running through an example, and I'm
going to be honest with you from the
start.
This is my warning.
You can make a lot of money with
options or screw it up and lose a
ton of money.
So if that sounds appealing to you, then
strap yourself in and let's do this.
First, let me clarify this.
If you're looking for a tutorial on call
options and put options, then please check out
my other video.
That is perfect for beginners.
I will leave a link for you down
below.
Now let's do the math.
So let's say that you have $10,000.
You're flush with cash.
With that $10,000, you have a choice.
You can buy stocks or stock options.
We'll run through two examples where you make
a ton of money and another where you
lose it all.
So you're going to see how crazy this
gets with stock options.
I'm telling you, it's nuts.
So let's use Yelp stock as an example,
and we're going to work with real numbers.
Keeping it real.
Yelp stock is at $36 a share.
If you use your $10,000 to buy
Yelp stock, then you can buy 277 shares.
If Yelp goes up by $10 from 36
to 46, you make $10 a share.
You have 277 shares and you make a
profit of $2,770.
So congratulations.
Okay, now let's do stock options.
Yelp stock is at 36 a share.
The 38 call option that expires in one
month is trading for 80 cents.
And keep in mind that these are real
numbers.
That means that a $38 call option will
cost you $80.
With $10,000, you can buy 125 call
options.
If Yelp stock goes from 36 to 46,
then you will make a profit of $90
,000.
Now let's compare.
Yelp stock went from 36 to 46 in
one month.
If you bought the stock, your profit is
$2,770.
If you bought the options, your profits is
$90,000.
Now listen carefully.
I'm going to show you the math.
If you get lost, or if you're already
lost, then you need to watch my other
video.
The link is down below.
Okay, so here's the math.
Yelp stock is at 36.
The $38 call option that expires in one
month is at 80 cents.
That means that one call option will cost
you $80.
Here's why.
There are 100 shares of stock in each
call option.
You take the cost of 80 cents each,
multiply by 100 shares, and that equals $80
for the call option.
So with $10,000, you can buy 125
call options.
Okay, now if Yelp stock increases from $36
to 46 in one month, then the $38
call option price will be worth at least
$8.
So it's very straightforward.
The stock went up to $46, right?
And your strike price is at 38.
That means that you have an $8 gain
on each share.
And each call option has 100 shares.
So each call option is now worth $800.
And you have to remember that you bought
each call option for $80.
And now each call option is worth $800.
And you have 125 call options.
Okay, so you started with $10,000, right?
Now you have 125 call options.
Each one is worth $800.
That's $100,000.
That means that you turned your $10,000
into $100,000.
And you made a profit of $90,000.
So this is how people get rich by
trading options.
So this is a real life example of
how a stock goes up by 28%
but you 10x your money.
It's because stock options give you leverage, but
it's a double edged sword.
So that's what happens when you get it
right.
If you get it wrong, then you can
guess it, then you're going to lose it
all.
So I want to show you.
Yelp stock is at 36, right?
You buy the $38 call option that expires
in one month.
If Yelp stock does not go above $38
in one month, then your call options will
expire worthless.
And you lose your $10,000.
In other words, to put it simply, there's
a time limit.
The call option has an expiration date.
If you used your $10,000 to buy
Yelp stock at 36, if Yelp stays at
36 after one month, then you don't lose
any money.
There's no time pressure when you buy the
stock.
You can hold the stock for years.
There's no time limits.
The problem with options is that you have
a time limit and that's risky because you
need the stock price to do what you
want it to do before the option expires.
Otherwise, you are at risk of losing all
your money.
Now, if you want to buy a call
option that gives you more time, let's just
say three months or one year, you can.
However, the more time on a call option,
the more expensive the call option will be.
If you want more time, it'll cost you.
So that's the challenge with stock options.
Time is against you.
That's why options are high risk and high
reward.
And buying the stock is lower risk and
lower reward.
So I hope that clarifies the difference between
buying $10,000 worth of stock versus stock
options.
Now, this is very important that you know
this.
You can use options to decrease your risk.
So I use options to hedge and lower
my risk.
That is not what we covered in this
video, clearly.
So I just showed you someone who's trying
to hit it big with the correct prediction,
high risk and high reward.
And a lot of people engage in this
type of behavior.
Some people make a ton of money by
being lucky and getting it right.
doing this strategically.
And other people lose a lot of money
by doing this irresponsibly.
All I'm saying is be careful and just
know what you're getting yourself into.
Please check out my other video.
The support.
Take care.