The Big Short is probably one of the
most popular films on the topic of investing.
It's a star-studded movie that follows the
real story of three groups of people who
short, or bet against, the housing market for
billions of dollars, right before the 2008 real
estate crisis.
As you might expect, our heroes end up
making quite a bit of money.
But how exactly does a short work?
Well, in the movie, the positions are taken
through what are known as swaps, a derivative
agreement that is taken with the banks.
But for common investors, short positions typically involve
individual stocks, making them easy enough to take.
But be warned, shorting comes with a lot
of risks.
On top of charging you expenses you don't
normally see with standard investing, shorting also offers
a skewed payoff, where you face a limited
upside and an uncapped downside, meaning you could
lose an infinite amount of money, theoretically anyway.
So before you decide to short something, let's
go over the strategy and the risks involved
on today's plain bagel.
Shorting, also known as short selling, is a
trading strategy where an investor sells a security
today and buys it back in the future,
hoping that the price of the security will
go down.
It's effectively the opposite approach to a traditional
long position, where investors buy today and sell
at some point in the future to cash
in, hopefully after the price has gone up.
It follows the same buy low sell high
mentality as long investing, but it just reverses
the order of the motto, so investors sell
high today and hope that the price will
go down so they can buy low in
the future.
Now, shorting a stock is a bit more
complicated than going long on a position.
So let's go through a running example to
explain how the strategy works and the risks
it poses.
Imagine you have two investors who decide to
take opposite positions in plain bagel co.
The company's stock currently has a market price
of $10.
Investor A decides to buy 1,000 of
these stocks, thereby investing $10,000.
While investor B decides to short 1,000
stocks, thereby selling $10,000 worth of the
investment.
Now, I know what you're thinking.
How the hell do you sell a stock
that you don't own?
Well, oftentimes the process involves selling a borrowed
security.
For example, in a brokerage account, you can
often sell a position by borrowing a stock
from your broker and then shorting that way,
leaving you with the proceeds from the sale.
The money you make from the sale obviously
doesn't really belong to you, since you sold
someone else's stock to get it.
But eventually, when you buy the security back,
known as covering your short, you'll be able
to return the stock and keep whatever money
is left over, which is how you profit
from the trade.
So going back to our example, if the
stock price falls from $10 to $5, investor
A will lose $5,000 while investor B
will gain $5,000, since they'll be able
to buy the stock back for a lower
price and keep the remaining sales proceeds.
On the other side of things, if the
stock price increases from $10 to $15, investor
A will be up $5,000 while investor
B will be down $5,000.
But this raises an interesting question.
Up until this point, investor B hasn't actually
contributed any of their own money.
So how is he going to buy back
the stock for more money than what's in
the account?
Well, this is where the concept of margins
come into play.
You see, to short a position, an investor
needs to post what's known as an initial
margin of 50% into their account to
act as a buffer should the investment lose
value.
This means that investor B would have contributed
$5,000 of his own funds at the
beginning of our example to accommodate for any
losses.
The amount still belongs to the investor, but
it's held as collateral by the broker to
ensure that investor B can afford to buy
back the share in the future.
Investor B will also be responsible for what
are known as margin calls, a process that
occurs when the margin becomes insufficient.
For example, in the event that the share
price rises to $15, investor B would receive
a margin call to replenish their cash buffer
based on what's known as the maintenance margin,
since there's no more wiggle room in the
account to accommodate for further losses.
So a big difference between shorting and going
long a position is that you can only
short in a margin account.
While this has its downsides, it does add
leverage to the investor's return.
What do I mean by that?
Well, let's go back to our example.
Let's say that our share price falls from
$10 to $5.
This would lead investor A to lose $5
,000 and investor B to gain $5,000.
On an absolute basis, these returns equate one
another, but on a percentage basis, taking into
account margins, they're actually quite different.
You see, investor A has lost roughly 50
% of their investment, but since investor B
has only contributed $5,000 of his own
money to this margin account, he's actually gained
100% of his investment, double the percentage
of investor A.
Because borrowing is involved with shorting, investor B
will see his returns amplified, though this goes
both ways.
Percentage losses in the short position will be
double what they might have been for investor
A.
So a decline of 50% for investor
A would translate into a 100% decline
for investor B.
So short positions not only flip the percentage
return received by investors, but they also amplify
them, both on the way up and the
way down.
But here's where we get into the distinct
disadvantages of a short position.
Namely, short positions come with unique costs that
a standard long investor won't face.
For example, if the stock you borrowed pays
a dividend, you'll actually need to pay this
amount to your broker, meaning that you'll face
a cost equal to whatever dividend the stock
pays.
Short positions also charge investors an interest rate
on the value of the stock you borrowed.
After all, since you are borrowing and selling
someone else's security, you need to compensate them
in the same way that you would compensate
a bank with interest on a loan.
Typically, the rate charged on a short position
can range anywhere from 2.5 to 20%,
but it can be higher for what are
known as hard-to-borrow stocks, highly volatile
or small-cap positions.
So, needless to say, shorting a stock can
be quite a bit more expensive than a
simple buy.
But for the most part, these expenses are
fair.
The interest makes sense since you are taking
a leveraged position, and since you are trying
to inverse the return of a long position,
it's only natural that you pay out the
dividend received from the stock.
But there are some absolute disadvantages involved with
a short strategy, some of which may very
well turn you off the idea of ever
trying to short a stock.
For one, short strategies face what's known as
buy-in risk, the chance that a broker
will make you prematurely cover your position.
This can occur for a number of reasons.
A broker may need to return a stock
to the portfolio they took it from, or
the stock may simply see a surge in
demand.
But the end result is that you may
be forced to close your position at any
time.
This is a pretty significant drawback, especially when
it comes to waiting out market volatility.
In our example, perhaps investor B is confident
that certain factors, whether it be regulation or
technological change, will cause the stock to crash
in two years' time.
But if the price surges in the near
term, they may be forced to realize a
loss even if they end up being right.
On top of this, when shorting a position,
you may experience what's known as a short
squeeze, when a heavily shorted stock sees its
price surge because the investors shorting the stock
need to cover their position.
Since investors who short sell have an appropriately
shorter time horizon than long investors, there's a
chance that they buy back the stock around
the same time, which can lead to a
surge in the price and make it harder
for you to cover your own position without
realizing a loss.
So, as you can see, there are some
distinct disadvantages with shorting a position, which alone
may lead you to stay away.
But perhaps the biggest risk with short positions
has to do with their skewed payoff.
With our two investors longing in shorting the
$10 stock, we face two risk-reward profiles.
On the one hand, investor A can theoretically
earn an infinitely high return.
The $10,000 investment in the $10 stock
could double, triple, quadruple in value as the
stock price climbs to $20, $30, $40 or
higher.
On the downside, the most she can lose
is the money she's invested, the $10,000,
which would only happen if the stock fell
to zero, a pretty drastic outcome.
Now, investor B actually flips the risk-reward
here.
If the stock drops down to zero, ignoring
fees, they can achieve a 200% return
since they are able to keep the $10
,000 profits from their $5,000 investment.
On the other hand, if the stock instead
climbs to $20, $30, $40 or higher, they
can lose 200%, 400%, 600% or more.
This means that you can lose a lot
more money than what you've initially invested.
And indeed, this very feature has had devastating
impacts on investors.
This is why many investors tend to stick
with long-only positions.
For many, the return is simply not worth
the risk.
And on top of the fact that you're
going against the natural upward bias of stocks,
you're more or less betting against a company
that is actively trying to prove you wrong.
Short selling certainly does play an important role
in the world of investments.
And indeed, you can make a lot of
money by placing a short bet against a
deteriorating stock.
But if you're looking to speculate with short
selling, tread lightly.
You may end up buying off a lot
more than you can chew.
Thanks for watching.
If you like this video, make sure to
hit the like button.
And if you like what we're doing here,
make sure to subscribe.
Hit the bell icon if you want notifications
about future videos.
If you have any feedback or topics you
want me to cover in a future video,
leave a comment down below.
For The Plain Bagel, my name is Richard
Coffin.
Thanks for joining me today.