All right, S&P is taking out this
85 in the...
I'm Stephen Klagian.
I'm the chief market strategist of TickerTocker and
co-founder.
I've been trading for 36 years.
I settled on the Florida American Stock Exchange,
then went over to the New York Stock
Exchange, and then went to the COMEX, and
then to the Board of Trade.
Well, I have five key words that I
tell anyone who's trading.
I don't care if you're a novice trader
or even if you're a top professional.
Where I come from, it's very simple.
It's got to be about consistency.
Number one is consistency.
I learned a great story about consistency from
a guy who was trading in the gold
pit.
He was a clerk making $100 a week,
and he just got married, and he was
having a baby.
And he knew that this was the only
time in his life that he could go
from being a clerk to going into the
gold pit to actually become a trader in
the gold pit on the COMEX.
And as a clerk, he was making $100
a day, so $500 a week back then.
And he then took the same philosophy into
the gold pit.
Goal was to make $100 a day.
After one month, he would then bump it
up to $200.
So if he lost $100, he stopped.
If he made $100, he stopped.
No matter what time of the day it
was, he took his trading cards, put it
in his pocket, and that was the end
of it.
So when I started trading upstairs for an
individual at the time, I decided to tighten
it up a little bit.
So I would try to make $100 a
day every week, then bump it up, and
then bump it up each and every week.
So after the first week, $100.
The second week, $200.
The third week, $300, and continually moving forward.
So to me, that's the most important thing
as a trader.
You don't want to make $100 on a
Monday, $100 on a Tuesday, lose $500 on
a Wednesday, lose $200 on a Thursday, make
$100 on a Friday.
And overall, you're net-net in the red
for the week.
And if you continue to do that, you'll
just eat up all your capital.
The second word that I tell everyone that's
super important is about discipline.
So the greatest story I have about discipline
is I had $3,000 to my name.
The first trade I ever did was an
option that was on the floor of the
American Stock Exchange.
And there was a stock that was right
behind me called American Can.
And it was a Dow stock, and the
stock was trading above 51 and change, I
believe, something like that.
And I bought an option.
I think it was October, and I bought
a Feb 50 call.
So a call option is that you're hoping
that by the time, sometime between then and
February, that the stock price would go higher.
And the call option that I bought at
two and three quarters would be higher than
what I purchased to that.
The stock started tanking over the next couple
weeks and then months.
And I think it traded all the way
down to $41 a share.
And my $3,000 investment was actually worth
pennies because I kept on buying all the
way down, utilizing the whole $3,000.
And I would never forget about a couple
weeks before the option expired, standing on the
floor, my head in my hands, and a
guy patted me on the back and said,
hey, kid, go home.
You can't turn the machines back on.
A week before expiration, the stock, if I
remember correctly, to my best recollection, went from
41 to like 54.
And at 3.45 in the afternoon, right
before the markets were going to close, my
father walked over to me, who was a
floor broker.
He was a member.
And he said to me, are you out?
And I said, I'm out because the stock
was trading higher and I sold all my
options out for a pretty nice profit.
He said to me, when I came on
the floor of the exchange on Monday, I
found a penny faced up.
And I said, oh, OK.
He said, what did you learn from this?
I said, whenever you have a losing trade,
you look for a penny faced up.
And he said, no, you never average down.
So to me, that was, again, the fact
that preservation of capital, I learned the hard
way.
I got very, very lucky.
And you basically do not want to average
down.
When you're wrong, you're out and you go
back in.
You can always make it back up again.
And that was probably the greatest lesson I
ever learned.
My first trade, I learned about discipline.
The third key word is confidence.
That to me is like, wake up every
single morning and you do this and traded
my own money for practically my whole life.
You don't think about it.
You just go in and you're confident based
upon the skills and the tools that you
have in front of you.
And that's why I built TickerTocker for.
I built TickerTocker.
And I built all the technology here that's
within TickerTocker to give the novice traders, the
retail traders, the most sophisticated traders, the proper
tools within the platform that I created.
The fourth word is patience.
As you saw today, there are some lows
in the day.
And I'm very patient and waiting for the
opportunity to address and wait patiently for those
patterns to set up.
And then the fifth key word is that
you have to have the passion.
The passion to do this every single day.
I'm 56 years old.
I have more passion in me now than
I did when I first started.
There's nothing greater than at the end of
the day, talking to people and hearing, you
know, their comments and the trades that they
did and how well they did and more
so how they're learning and how they're fully
understanding everything that I designed in this room.
And then on the TickerTocker platform.
So to me, these five key words are
essential to be able to become a great
trader.