Albert Einstein believed that the rule of 72
was a more important discovery than his theory
of relativity.
The first reference of this rule comes from
Luca Pacioli, who is regarded as the father
of accounting.
In his 1494 book Summary of Arithmetic, Geometry,
Proportions and Proportionality, Summa De Arithmetic, Geometria, Proportiono
et Proportionalita, he explains the importance of this
rule.
Being able to double your money in just
a few short years is literally everybody's dream.
How many times have you wished upon a
falling star that you'll wake tomorrow with six
figures in your bank account?
Well, I'm here to tell you that this
is possible.
It is not a fantasy.
In today's practical wisdom video, I'll be talking
about the rule of 72.
So, stay tuned and be ready to learn.
Also, get my free passive income guide using
the link in the descriptions.
Number 1.
The Rule of 72 The rule of 72
is applied while setting financial objectives, when analyzing
economic trends, planning for financial goals, evaluating investments,
and also helping you with debt.
The way it works is by determining how
long it will take for an investment to
double while receiving a fixed interest rate.
Here's how you calculate it.
Take 72 and divide it by the rate
of return you hope to earn.
For example, if you plan on earning an
interest of 5%, divide 72 by 5.
That gives you 14.4. This is the
number of years it will take you to
double your money.
There are many advantages to this rule.
You can, for example, quickly and simply determine
whether you're keeping up with the trends.
Along with that, you can also ensure that
you are on the right track when it
comes to your financial decisions.
It can also be used to calculate inflations
because it shows you how many years it
will require for the value of the starting
sum to fall in half rather than double.
All this being said, using this rule also
comes with disadvantages.
For example, it can only be applied to
assets which calculate compound interest annually.
This rule also has some accuracy problems because
it can't calculate rates below and above 6
% and 10% respectively.
Nonetheless, don't let these disadvantages drive a wedge
between you and the rule of 72.
Get a hold of a financial advisor who
can thoroughly explain this rule in more depth
and guide you appropriately.
Number 2.
Compound Interest.
As stated before, the rule of 72 only
works with compound interest.
When you understand the rule and the power
of compound interest, you have the secret recipe
to financial growth.
Having also discussed the rule itself, let's talk
about compound interest.
The fantastic thing about it is that the
longer your money is invested, the greater your
earnings will be.
In other words, the interest earned on your
initial investments is added on to your initial
investment and this cycle keeps going.
Basically, invest your money in it and then
forget about it.
Now, if you want to know how long
it will take to double your current savings,
you'll use the rule of 72.
Take your interest rate, let's say 6%, and
divide it by 72.
72 divided by 6 gives us 12.
This is how long it will take for
you to double your money.
When it comes to compound interest, look for
one where the interest rate is high because
the higher the interest rate, the quicker you'll
have your doubled amount.
Get in touch with a financial advisor, ask
for the best compound interest and use the
rule of 72 to see just how quickly
you can grow your bank balance.
Number 3.
Investments.
The rule of 72 can also be used
to evaluate your investments.
At some point in life, we all want
to make investments and you can definitely use
this rule to have a key insight on
how long your money will take for it
to double.
Therefore, if you're considering investing, the rule of
72 can help you determine how long it
may take before you receive a 100%
return on your investment.
No matter what kind of investment you make,
the rule of 72 will benefit you as
long as you also use the idea of
compound interest.
For us to better understand this rule, let's
look at these following scenarios.
Investment number 1.
Savings deposit at 1% annual rate of
return.
Investment number 2.
Government bonds at 5% annual rate of
return.
Investment number 3.
Mutual funds at 8% annual rate of
return.
Investment number 4.
Stocks with a 12% annual return.
Now using the rule of 72, try calculating
by yourself how long it will take for
you to see returns on these investments.
Write your answers in the comments and tell
me what pattern you can see.
Also, if you're enjoying the video so far,
do me a huge favor and give this
video a like.
Number 4.
Inflation rate.
You may be hearing on the news that
there's an inflation right now.
But what does this actually mean?
An inflation rate is the rate at which
prices tend to increase over a certain period
of time.
Things like household goods and services, for example,
are affected by the inflation rate.
In simple terms, it costs more to buy
the same thing you bought this time last
year.
The rule of 72 helps us determine how
long it will take us to beat inflation.
If, for example, inflation averages to 3%
year after year, by doing the math, we
will realize that the price will double in
the next 24 years.
However, if the inflation rate stays at the
current 6.8%, 72 divided by 6.8
gives us 10.6. So in just a
span of 10 years, prices will astronomically rise.
By using the rule, you can financially plan
ahead to stay ahead of the curve so
that you are not beaten down by inflation.
Number 5.
Savings.
This rule has a lot of advantages, including
when it comes to your savings, as it
can enable you to project when those savings
will end up doubling.
When it comes to keeping your savings, what
is the first place that you think of?
Is it keeping your savings at home?
Well, this is too risky and easy to
lose.
Is it in the stock market?
Well, this has a higher chance of growing
your money, but also with high chances of
loss.
Perhaps it's opening a savings account with your
local bank.
If you're lucky here, then you might make
1% interest on your savings account.
And to be frank, this is usually the
lowest hanging fruit.
Setting a goal to save is good, and
setting a budget to save is a good
idea as well.
But you should also know how long it
will take until you double your investment.
So now, let's look at a few examples
using the rule.
72 divided by the rate of return equals
time for the investment to double.
For example, let's say you have $1,000
that you want to save in the bank.
Let's also say that you'll earn a 1
% interest rate every year.
So 72 divided by 1% equals 72
years.
That means if you put in $1,000
today, you can expect to have $2,000
in 72 years.
But I'm pretty sure you won't be around
in 72 years to get a $1,000
profit.
There are many investment programs out there that
can guarantee a minimum interest rate of at
least 4% to 7% per year.
You just have to do some research, sit
down with a financial advisor, and they'll show
you much better routes you can take.
So now, let's use the same previous example.
You still have the $1,000, but you
now put it towards a savings program, such
as an index with an interest rate guarantee
of 5% per year.
So 72 divided by 5 equals 14.5
years.
So instead of waiting for 72 years, it
will only take you 15 years to double
your investment with whatever amount you put in.
And it's safe.
5% is just an example.
Realistic rates can be higher.
All in all, the rule of 72 is
a handy-dandy mathematical calculation you can use
to identify a number of things.
This can mean seeing how long you'll have
to wait for your savings to grow or
how much money you'll have to make to
stay ahead of the inflation rates.
Out of all the things you can use
this rule on, the one common thing we
learn each time is to be patient.
Start your journey towards financial freedom today so
that you don't have to be patient for
too long.
I hope you've learned a lot from this
video.
Let me know in the comments how you
aim to use this rule.
And with that being said, have a great
day and see you all in the next
video.
Transcribed by https://otter.ai