What's the best way for beginners to start
investing online with just $100?
As a millionaire investor, this is something I
get asked all the time.
And because of that, four years ago, I
set out to answer this question by creating
a video where I invested $100 into five
different things.
Today, I'm gonna compare the results from those
five investments that you can make from your
laptop and try to finally answer the question
once and for all.
We're gonna be using this grid to judge
each one in these categories.
First up, learning curve.
This is how long it takes to learn
the ins and outs of each method.
Ideally, we want this to be as short
as possible.
Next is passive income potential, which is how
much money an investment can earn for you
passively while you still own it without needing
to sell it.
Then there's tax efficiency, which refers to the
specific tax advantages or benefits available for each
type of investment that can help you pay
less tax.
After that, we have risk level, which is
about how likely you are to lose money
and how much the investment's value might go
up or down.
And finally, we're looking at the results.
This is where I'll reveal my percentage return
over the last four years and exactly how
much my $100 investment is now worth.
Before we jump in, please remember, I'm not
a financial advisor.
I'm just sharing my own results and strategies
that have worked for me over the years.
Please also do your own research.
Okay, first up is individual stocks.
Individual stocks give you the chance to own
a piece of a company you believe in.
This can be really exciting because you're directly
investing in businesses that you think will grow
or succeed.
For LearningCurve, I'm gonna say this is high.
If you want to be successful picking individual
stocks, then it's not just a guessing game.
You'll need to dig into the nitty gritty
of a company's fundamentals.
This includes looking into the financials, who's making
the money, who's leading the company, and how
well known the brand is.
When I invest in individual stocks, I look
through income statements, balance sheets, and cashflow statements.
So when I invest in a stock, I'm
in it for the long haul, which means
at least two to 10 years.
A great way to learn how to do
this is by using an investing app with
a demo account, which lets you play around
with fake money until you're confident with your
strategies.
For passive income potential, I'm gonna say this
is good.
You see, when you own a stock, there
are two ways you can make money.
Firstly, if the price of the stock goes
up during the time you own it, you
can sell it for more than you paid.
Secondly, you can receive dividends.
Dividends are regular payments to shareholders.
Not all stocks pay dividends, but if they
do, this means you can receive money without
ever selling your stock.
This is essentially passive income.
Now, for tax efficiency, this is great.
If you use the right accounts, then you
can reduce your tax burden.
In the UK, these are called stocks and
shares ISAs.
You can set one up on most investing
apps, and any profits you make are safe
from taxes.
In the USA, there's something similar called a
Roth IRA.
These accounts work like a shield, protecting your
profits from the taxman.
While there are different rules depending on where
you live, the idea is the same.
Please bear in mind that I'm not a
tax advisor and you should do your own
research as everyone's circumstances are different.
So what's the risk?
This is definitely high.
Back in 1995, during the dot-com boom,
I got lucky and picked a few great
stocks.
I sold them at the right time and
made a lot of money in a short
period.
But when the bubble burst, some of the
other companies I'd invested in, ones that cost
me very little, went out of business completely,
even though I ended up making money overall.
It just shows how risky investing in individual
stocks can be, especially if you put all
your money into just a few companies.
If they fail, you could lose everything.
So let's look at how much my $100
investment is now worth.
Let me refresh your memory.
Here's what I invested in.
So I'm gonna throw a dart at the
board and as you can see, I've randomly
selected 20 different stocks and wherever the dart
lands, that's what I'm gonna invest in.
Now I've just got to put on a
blindfold.
Okay, here we go.
Right, let's see what we got.
And we've gone into Samsung.
That investment is now worth $67.66. But
don't forget my dividends.
Over the four years, I made 10 cents.
So that leaves me with a total of
$67.76. That's a negative 32.34%
return.
This example perfectly shows how hit or miss
individual stock investing really is.
That dart could have just as easily landed
on Apple, Microsoft, or Nvidia.
So let's have a look at how much
I would have made if that dart had
landed a bit differently.
A $100 investment in Apple four years ago
would now be worth $170.
The same investment in Microsoft would be $188
and, drum roll please, Nvidia would be worth
$908.
Those stocks have boomed in recent years and
luckily I have some of those in my
personal portfolio.
But this just goes to show, you can't
just leave individual stock investing down to luck.
You have to be strategic with your stock
picks and even then the market is unpredictable.
If you wanna try this out, just download
Trading212.
It's a great app for beginner investors because
it lets you use a demo account to
practice trading with fake money.
This way, you can learn how it all
works without risking any real cash, just like
I mentioned earlier.
It also lets you set up a stocks
and shares ISA if you're in the UK,
which protects your investment returns from taxes.
But again, I'm not a tax advisor, so
please do your own research as everyone's situation
is unique.
Trading212 also lets you buy fractional shares, which
means you don't have to buy a whole
stock.
That's how I was able to own just
0.07 of a Samsung stock instead of
having to buy an entire share.
As I was gonna mention Trading212 anyway, I
reached out to see if they'd be interested
in sponsoring this portion of the video.
They agreed and are offering a free fractional
share worth up to 100 pound to anyone
that uses the code Tilbury when they create
an account.
Plus you can get more free shares by
inviting your friends.
Both of you will get a free share
as long as they fund their account.
I'll leave the link in the description if
you're interested.
♪♪ Second is a real estate investment trust,
otherwise known as a REIT.
I know this one sounds pretty complicated, but
it's actually quite cool.
Imagine your friend collects $100 from 3,000
people, giving him $300,000.
He then uses that money to buy a
property, rents it out, and shares the rental
income with all 3,000 people who helped
him buy it.
That's a simple way to explain a REIT.
It allows anyone to invest in properties without
needing to buy one themselves.
Think of it like you own the front
door, someone else owns the window, and a
few others own the bricks, which means together,
everyone owns the entire property and shares in
the profits.
The learning curve, I'm gonna say it's moderate,
and that's because getting started with REITs is
much easier than buying physical property.
It's not like you need a huge down
payment or a mortgage, and there's no need
to deal with agents or solicitors.
However, you do need to understand how REITs
work.
They own things like offices, shopping centers, apartments,
hotels, and much more, and they get their
income through rent.
For passive income potential, I'm gonna say this
is great.
REITs are well-known for paying high dividends.
This is because the law says they have
to pass on at least 90% of
all their profits to investors.
So as long as the REIT is doing
well and its properties are rented out, you
can earn a steady stream of passive income.
Most businesses sign long-term leases on their
commercial properties.
Therefore, most of the time, income is pretty
stable and reliable.
But of course, just keep in mind that
your earnings depend on the REIT you pick
and the types of properties it owns.
For tax efficiency, I'm gonna put this down
as great.
This is because in many countries, REITs offer
great tax benefits.
For example, in the UK, you can hold
REITs in a stocks and shares ISA, which
means you don't have to pay taxes on
your profits or dividends.
In terms of risk, I'd have to say
this is medium.
REITs are generally less risky than buying a
single property because they invest in multiple properties
spreading out the risk.
However, they're not risk-free.
If the real estate market takes a downturn
or if the REIT struggles to keep its
properties rented, you might see both a drop
in dividends and the value of the investment.
So what's my investment worth now?
Let's flashback to me making the investment four
years ago.
As I'm in the UK, I'm gonna use
the Trading212 website to put $100 into a
similar REIT.
Ready for the moment of truth?
Looking at my investment now, I can see
it's worth $98.59. So that's a small
loss of 1.41%. This shows that even
though REITs are normally more stable than individual
stocks, they're not guaranteed to perform well.
My REIT likely underperformed because it invested in
commercial real estate, which struggled during the pandemic.
But that's not the end of the world
as I made $11.93 back in dividends,
meaning I'm actually $10.52 up.
So that's 10.52% up.
♪♪ Third is cryptocurrency.
Imagine a form of digital money that isn't
controlled by any government or bank.
That's what cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Ethereum are.
These currencies run on the blockchain technology, which
makes them secure, transparent, and almost impossible to
counterfeit.
Cryptocurrencies have created massive wealth for some people,
with Bitcoin being the best-performing asset of
the last decade.
But on the flip side, it's highly volatile,
and people have also lost fortunes.
That's why I describe crypto as part investment
and part speculation, and not for the faint
-hearted.
For LearningCurve, I'm gonna say it's moderate.
Crypto might sound complicated, but I'll break it
down for you.
First, you'll need a wallet.
This is where you store your crypto.
Think of it like a digital piggy bank,
and there are different types.
First are online wallets.
These are easy to use, but you'll need
to protect them with very strong passwords.
Second are offline wallets, like hardware wallets.
These are the safest because they're not connected
to the internet.
Next, you'll need to pick an exchange to
buy and sell your crypto.
Some popular ones are Coinbase and Binance.
These platforms make it simple to trade, but
make sure to choose a trustworthy exchange to
avoid any issues.
Then there's tokenomics.
This just means understanding how the supply and
demand of a coin works.
For example, Bitcoin has a limited supply, which
is why it's often called digital gold.
For passive income potential, I'm gonna also say
this is moderate.
Unlike stocks or REITs, crypto doesn't pay dividends,
but there are ways to earn passive income.
The first is called staking.
This is when you lock up your crypto,
like Ethereum, to help the system work and
process transactions.
In return, you get paid rewards, kind of
like earning points for helping out.
The second is yield farming.
This is when you lend your crypto out
to others and earn interest on it, similar
to how a bank pays you interest when
you save money with them.
These methods can generate decent returns, but they
do come with higher risks.
If the coin's value drops or the platform
you're using gets hacked, your income could disappear
along with your crypto.
That's why I personally don't mess with any
of this and just hold mine on a
Ledger wallet.
For tax efficiency, I'm gonna have to say
this one is poor.
Taxes are a tricky part of crypto investing.
In many countries, even swapping one cryptocurrency for
another counts as a taxable event.
And if you earn staking rewards, those are
also taxed as income.
You also can't hold crypto in tax-advantaged
accounts like ISOs or Roth IRAs, which makes
it less tax-efficient than stocks or REITs.
In terms of risk, I'd have to say
it's very high.
Crypto is one of the most volatile investments
out there.
Prices can soar 1,000% in a
year, but they can also crash just as
fast.
Personally, I just invest in Bitcoin and Ethereum.
As they're more established and often referred to
as blue-chip cryptocurrencies, smaller altcoins can be
far more risky.
You've also got to be cautious of scams.
Since crypto isn't regulated, if someone hacks your
wallet or tricks you into sending your coins,
there's no way to get them back.
So keeping your crypto safe is just as
important as learning how to invest in it.
So what's my investment worth now?
Let's rewind to when I made this investment
four years ago.
So I'm gonna jump onto the most popular
Bitcoin app, which is called Coinbase, and invest
my $100 in Bitcoin and forget about it.
Ready for the reveal?
The $100 I invested in Bitcoin is now
worth $652.24. That's a return of 552
.24%. Now, I know what you're thinking.
That's insane, and it is, but I have
to stress that this kind of growth is
not typical.
Bitcoin has been the best-performing asset of
the last decade, but most cryptocurrencies don't see
these kinds of returns.
Many lose their value entirely.
In my opinion, crypto is exciting, and the
technology behind it has the potential to transform
industries.
However, it's not for everyone.
It's highly volatile, speculative, and requires a strong
stomach to handle the wild price swings.
Just remember, crypto is all about high risk
and high reward.
So if you're gonna dive in, make sure
you're doing your research and investing wisely.
Fourth is gold.
This is one of the oldest and most
trusted ways to store and protect wealth.
Gold is often called a safe haven because
it's a great way to protect your wealth
during uncertain times, like when inflation is rising
or the economy is struggling.
For learning curve, I'm gonna have to say
it's low.
Learning how to invest in gold is pretty
simple.
You have two main options.
First, physical gold.
This includes gold bars and coins.
Many people also think you can buy gold
jewelry as investments, but you'll often pay more
than the gold is actually worth because sellers
add a markup for their craftsmanship.
For this reason, I personally stick to gold
coins.
Just bear in mind, if you pick this
option, then you'd have to store it somewhere
safe.
Second is gold ETFs.
These are funds that let you invest in
gold without physically owning it.
For example, in the UK, you can use
Trading212 to buy shares in something like the
iShares Physical Gold ETF.
It's quick, easy, and you can buy or
sell it with just a few clicks.
Passive income potential is absolutely zero.
Unlike stocks, REITs, or crypto, gold doesn't pay
any passive income.
It's not an income-generating asset.
It's purely a store of value.
For tax efficiency, I'm gonna put this as
good.
If you buy physical gold like gold coins
or bars, the tax rules can be a
little tricky.
For example, in some countries, certain gold coins
like the UK's Gold Britannias are considered legal
tender, which means you don't pay capital gains
tax when you sell them.
However, this doesn't apply to all gold coins
or bars, so you'll need to check the
specific rules in your country.
For gold ETFs, they're generally more straightforward.
In countries like the UK, you can hold
them in a stocks and shares ISA, which
makes any profits completely tax-free.
Interestingly, physical gold has another unique advantage.
It can be used to transport wealth across
borders discreetly.
That said, this approach comes with risks, such
as theft or legal restrictions on transporting large
amounts of gold across borders.
While it's not something I'd necessarily recommend, it's
worth mentioning as a unique aspect of owning
physical gold.
In terms of risk, I'd say this is
a medium.
Gold is one of the safest investments you
can make.
It's been used as a form of money
for thousands of years, and it's known to
hold its value during times of inflation or
economic uncertainty.
However, the opportunity cost of investing in gold
can be a downside.
While it's great for protecting your wealth, it
doesn't have the same growth potential as other
investments like stocks or crypto.
So what's my investment worth now?
Let's flash back to when I made this
investment four years ago.
I'm gonna invest using trading 212 in a
similar share, and with just a click of
a button, there you go, I'm now Mr.
Goldman.
So what's Mr. Goldman's investment worth today?
Well, it's currently sitting at $140.10. That's
a return of 40.1%. Now, that's not
as exciting as Bitcoin's performance, but it's solid,
steady growth.
This shows how gold is better for protecting
your wealth rather than rapidly growing it.
Fifth is index funds.
Imagine owning a tiny piece of the largest
companies like Apple, Microsoft, and Amazon all at
once.
That's exactly what an index fund allows you
to do.
It's a basket of stocks that mirrors the
performance of a specific index like the S
&P 500.
So you're investing in the overall market rather
than betting on individual companies.
For learning curve, I'm gonna have to say
this one is low.
Unlike individual stocks where you need to dig
into the financial statements and company performers, index
funds are passive investments.
You don't have to pick and choose stocks
as they're already bundled together for you.
Getting started is simple too.
Platforms like Trading212 let you buy index funds
with just a few clicks.
Once you've invested, all you need to do
is sit back and let the market do
the work.
For passive income potential, I'm gonna say this
is moderate.
Index funds don't directly pay high dividends like
REITs, but they still provide some income.
Many companies in the fund pay dividends and
those are automatically distributed to you or reinvested
back into the fund depending on your choice.
While the main focus of index funds is
long-term growth, the dividend income can be
a nice bonus, especially if you're investing in
funds that focus on dividend paying companies.
For tax efficiency, I'm gonna say this one
is great.
If you hold index funds in a stocks
and shares ISA in the UK or a
Roth IRA in the USA, you can avoid
paying taxes on dividends and capital gains altogether.
This means you get to keep more of
your profits over time, which can make a
huge difference when you're investing for the long
haul.
In terms of risks, I'd say it's pretty
low.
Index funds are much less risky than investing
in individual stocks because they're diversified.
Instead of putting all your money into a
few companies, you're spreading it across hundreds or
even thousands of stocks in different industries.
Historically, the S&P 500 has delivered average
annual returns of around 8% to 10
% over the long term.
While the market can go up and down
in the short term, if you hold onto
an index fund for 10, 20, or even
30 years, it's one of the safest ways
to grow your wealth.
However, of course, there are still risks like
with any investment.
So what's my investment worth now?
Let's rewind to when I made this investment
four years ago.
If we head over to Vanguard's website now
and we find the S&P 500 and
deposit some money and then click, there you
go, job done.
Right, so time for the reveal.
Today, that investment is worth $179.57. That's
a return of 79.57%. This result shows
why index funds are such a great option
for most investors.
They're simple, low cost, and consistently deliver solid
returns over time.
Personally, index funds are my favorite investment, which
is why I've allocated the majority of my
money there.
However, I also understand the importance of diversification.
So I've spread smaller percentages across all the
other investments we've discussed today.
This way, I can balance growth, stability, and
risk in my portfolio.
So whether you're diving into individual stocks, buying
some REITs, exploring crypto, getting into gold, or
sticking with a steady reliability of index funds,
each investment has its pros and cons.
Some are better for growing your wealth quickly,
while others are designed to protect it over
the long term.
The most important lesson is to start early.
Even small amounts like the $100 we've been
working with can grow into something significant thanks
to the power of compounding.
Time is your best friend when it comes
to investing, so don't wait to get started.
If you wanna know what the laziest way
to make money online is, then I'm gonna
leave that video right up there, but don't
click on it just yet.
Make sure to subscribe if you wanna grow
your wealth.
I'll see you over there.