Looking to make some extra cash without breaking
the bank?
With just a small investment of $25 per
week, you can start your journey to earning
over $5,000 a month.
Yes, you heard that right, it's possible.
In this video, I'll show you and John
simple and practical tips that investors keep secret.
I'll show you the drip strategy and how
you can make it even better.
And in the end, I'll show you how
using this strategy, you can turn a $25
per week investment into an over half a
million dollar portfolio paying over $5,000 in
monthly dividends.
So grab your 25 bucks and let's get
started on the path to financial success.
Everything needs a strategy, you need to plan
out what you need and how to get
there.
The same is the case with investing.
In our case, our goal is to retire
and still have free monthly payments as if
you never retired from a job.
But the problem is we only have $25
per week to spare.
So the only strategy for this is using
the drip investment strategy.
Drip or dividend reinvestment plan is a smart
way to grow your investments over time.
Think of it like planting a seed and
watching it grow into a mighty tree.
Instead of soil and water, you use your
dividends to buy more shares, which then generate
more dividends creating a cycle of growth.
Here's how it works.
Imagine you own shares in a company that
pays dividends.
Instead of taking those dividends as cash, you
reinvest them to buy more shares.
This means you own more shares, which in
turn generate even more dividends.
It's like a snowball rolling down a hill
getting bigger and bigger with each revolution.
One of the key benefits of drip is
compound interest.
When you reinvest your dividends, you buy more
shares.
And when those pay dividends, you reinvest them
as well.
This snowball effect leads to exponential growth over
time.
Let's break it down with an example.
Suppose there's a stock that's worth $20 per
share and you own 100 shares of that
company.
It pays a $1 dividend per share each
year.
At the end of year one, you'll have
$100 in dividends.
Instead of cashing out, you reinvest and buy
five more shares of the stock.
Now you have 105 shares of the company.
The next year, instead of receiving $100, you'll
get $105 in dividends.
The following year, you'll own 110 shares, then
120, and so on each time increasing the
dividend amount.
Over time, your investment grows larger and larger
thanks to the power of compound interest.
Another benefit of drip is dollar cost averaging.
Instead of trying to time the market, you
buy shares regularly regardless of whether the market
is up or down.
This helps to smooth out the highs and
lows, averaging out the cost per share over
time.
Let's see how this works.
Suppose you invest $100 every month in a
company's drip.
Some months, the share price might be high,
so you'll buy fewer shares.
In other months, the share price might be
low, so you'll buy more shares.
Over time, your average cost per share will
be somewhere in between, helping to reduce the
impact of market fluctuations.
Finally, drip offers the convenience of automatic investment.
Once you set up a drip with your
broker, it takes care of everything for you.
You don't have to worry about manually reinvesting
your dividends or timing your purchases.
It's a streamlined process that helps you stay
focused on your long-term goals.
In the end, I'll show you how this
drip strategy can turn a small investment of
$25 per week into over a half-million
-dollar portfolio that pays over $5,000 per
month.
But for that, you need to improve the
drip strategy.
Now, here's how you can supercharge the drip
investing strategy by contributing a set amount every
week, month, or year.
For this video, I'm investing $25 per week
in my portfolio.
That's $100 per month, or $1,200 per
year.
Let me break down how this investment can
make a significant impact on my investment journey.
Firstly, by increasing my contribution to $25 per
week, I'm accelerating the pace at which I
buy more shares.
With more money going into my portfolio regularly,
I'll be able to purchase additional shares more
frequently.
This means I'll benefit from compounding at a
faster rate as each new share I acquire
starts generating dividends sooner.
Adding more money every week helps you take
better advantage of dollar-cost averaging.
This means I spread out my purchases over
time so I buy shares when prices are
high and when they're low, reducing the impact
of big price swings.
Putting in $25 each week is simple, and
it fits into my budget without trouble.
And with Drip, I don't have to worry
about remembering to invest.
It's done automatically.
By using Drip and adding money regularly, I'm
setting myself up for more growth.
My portfolio should keep getting bigger over time
as I keep putting money in and reinvesting
dividends.
Now, when it comes to building a successful
drip strategy, choosing the right stocks is key.
By selecting stocks that meet specific criteria, you
can ensure the effectiveness of your drip investments
and maximize long-term returns.
For me, I look into these four categories
of stocks for my investment.
Blue-chip dividend stocks, dividend aristocrats, high-yield
dividend stocks, and growth-oriented dividend stocks.
In the end, I'll show you a selection
of stocks using these criteria that utilize the
drip strategy and have the potential to turn
a small investment of $25 per week into
over a half a million dollar portfolio that
pays over $5,000 per month.
But first, let's see why these categories of
stocks matter.
Blue-chip dividend stocks are a popular choice
for drip investors.
These are reputable companies with a long history
of consistent dividend payments indicating financial stability and
reliability.
Examples include household names like Coca-Cola, Johnson
& Johnson, and Procter & Gamble.
You need to start with blue-chip dividend
stocks for your portfolio.
They provide a solid foundation for long-term
growth because these companies have proven their ability
to generate steady income and reward shareholders with
dividends.
Secondly, dividend aristocrats are another category of stocks
ideal for drip investing.
These are companies that have increased their dividends
for at least 25 consecutive years, showcasing a
strong commitment to returning value to shareholders.
Stocks like AT&T, ExxonMobil, and Walmart fall
into this category.
You need aristocrats to stabilize your investment strategy
over a long period of time.
Since these stocks have been increasing dividends for
over 25 years, they're not likely to cut
back anytime soon.
These companies have a proven track record of
navigating various market conditions and delivering consistent returns
to shareholders.
Additionally, high-yield dividend stocks offer another avenue
for drip investors to explore.
These stocks typically have higher-than-average dividend
yields, making them attractive for income-focused investors.
Examples include Realty Income Corporation, AbbVie Incorporated, and
Verizon Communications.
While high-yield dividend stocks may carry more
risk compared to blue-chip or dividend aristocrat
stocks, they make up an important part of
the portfolio.
Lastly, growth-oriented dividend stocks combine the benefits
of capital appreciation and dividend income.
These are companies with strong growth prospects and
tend to keep increasing dividends to investors.
Examples include technology giants like Microsoft, Apple, and
Visa.
If you're selecting stocks using these criteria, it'll
narrow down the list of available stocks, so
make sure your stock ticks at least three
of the above four boxes.
Based on the above criteria, I've selected the
following five stocks to boost my portfolio.
It includes NextEra Energy, Starbucks, Abbott Laboratories, The
Home Depot, and finally, to combine them all,
ProShares S&P 500 Dividend Aristocrats ETF.
Separately, their current dividend yield, dividend growth, and
share price appreciation look something like this.
NextEra Energy, Incorporated has a current dividend yield
of 2.76 percent, a dividend growth rate
of 10.98 percent, and an annual share
price appreciation of 11.98 percent.
Starbucks Corporation is at 3.01, 16.69,
and 7.89 percent.
Abbott Laboratories at 2.1 percent, 11.4
percent, and 10.31 percent.
The Home Depot is at 2.59 percent,
17.91 percent, and 16 percent.
While ProShares S&P 500 Dividend Aristocrats ETF
has a current dividend yield of 2.04
percent, a dividend growth rate of 20.48
percent, and an annual share price appreciation of
8.17 percent.
If we create a portfolio, our portfolio metrics
might look something like this.
You can calculate this by simply summing all
the individual metrics, then dividing by 5.
Do the same for current dividend yield, growth,
and share price appreciation.
With that, the portfolio has a current dividend
yield of 2.5 percent, a dividend growth
rate of 15.49 percent, and an annual
share price appreciation of 10.87 percent.
Now the question is, can this portfolio return
enough over time for you to retire?
Let's find out.
If John invests $25 every week into this
portfolio, which amounts to $100 per month or
$1,200 per year, in this scenario his
investment strategy would unfold like this.
At the end of the first year, John's
weekly contribution is projected to reach $2,560.
After 10 years, the same investment with weekly
contributions and dividend reinvestment is projected to grow
to $27,832.
That's when the drip and weekly contribution starts
compounding the effect.
After 20 years, John's investment is estimated to
reach $145,504.
Fast forward another 10 years, and in 30
years, John's initial investment has the potential to
soar to a valuation of $823,352.
Alongside this impressive capital appreciation, he'll also receive
$63,395 in dividends every year, translating to
approximately $5,283 every month.
In total, this portfolio has the potential to
add $786,152 to his portfolio investment, with
$464,535 attributed to the growth of the
portfolio, while $321,617 came from reinvested dividends.
Now, if you want to learn how to
build your own dividend kingdom and reach a
million-dollar valuation, click the video on the
screen.