Price tends to move from structure to structure,
squeezing one side of the market participants most
of the time.
It rewards one side of the market, while
punishing the opposite side of participants.
And liquidity clearouts are constant processes observed on
the markets every day.
Today we'll talk about liquidity extraction and you'll
finally understand why the market moves against you
the moment you enter the market.
So if you could, like, subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full video.
Regardless of how long you've been trading, at
some point you should have questioned the depth
of the market you are trading, in other
words its liquidity.
Make no mistake, trading the EURUSD, for example,
offers different conditions than trading an instrument like
the Canadian dollar versus the New Zealand dollar,
or Bitcoin versus Shiba Inu coin, or Tesla
versus some random penny stock.
Liquidity is the number one element to make
a market functionable and competitive.
For a market to be rich in liquidity,
there must be an ample participation of both
buyers and sellers.
This is why it makes sense for the
smart money or the market makers to extract
the liquidity from the market.
Liquidity hunting is a very common practice.
It's nothing more than the art of flushing
the losing players out of the market, which
are known as weak longs or weak shorts.
The larger the liquidity zone buildup, the more
likely it is for that zone to be
targeted by the smart money, especially if it's
a counter-trend setup.
Often liquidity clearouts will form against the main
trend.
For example, in an extended bullish trend structure,
in a consolidation, you will often see a
clearout of highs and a price reversal downwards.
This is more common in very liquid markets,
such as forex or stocks that trade on
strong volume.
And why is that?
Because smart money knows how retail traders think.
Smart money knows how retail traders use different
indicators, moving averages, candlesticks and chart patterns in
their attempt to day trade or scalp the
markets.
Smart money can easily trap retail traders into
the market at poor trade locations, and then
move against their positions, stopping them out.
They know that retail traders are programmed with
the phrase, trend is your friend.
That's why many clearouts will be formed against
the overall trend direction or against overall retail
trader participation.
Here's how liquidity is often positioned around structures
in the market.
Many traders will use these price levels to
place their entries or exits at, but more
frequently their exits or stop losses.
And these are exactly the zones used by
the smart money to trigger a liquidity clearout.
Institutional players cannot trade the same as the
retail trader, because in low liquidity price areas,
they might push price too much with large
orders.
So they use high liquidity zones to put
their own large orders in the market, without
having too much impact on the price.
Clearouts of liquidity are frequent in crypto and
forex markets, because a strong trending market attracts
many unexperienced traders, who step into margin trading,
usually buying around the lows and the highs.
Since they are unaware of the trap, it's
relatively easy for the market maker to replay
the pattern repeatedly, stopping the traders with liquidity
clearouts.
One critical concept for a liquidity clearout is
the consistency of structural symmetry.
Most targeted clearouts will happen around structures where
the price is consistently bouncing from a demand
or a support level, or from a resistance
or a supply level for multiple times before
it actually breaks it.
So very important, you should focus only on
such structures to identify and trade liquidity clearouts.
The more bounces in the structure, the better.
As time passes, and if price cannot break
areas with multiple highs or lows, chances are
the liquidity around those price levels will increase
with time.
The more time it passes, the more the
liquidity will increase, if major highs and lows
don't break.
Because of this factor, if you want to
trade a liquidity hunt pattern, you should be
aware of how time plays a role in
consolidating the orders above or under key liquidity
zones.
Now, a clearout is a liquidation event where
the stop losses of buyers or sellers are
taken out and the breakout traders are trapped
in.
Liquidity clearout and stop loss hunting are similar
concepts.
Stop loss hunting can happen around any price
or no structure at all, while a liquidity
clearout will most of the time happen around
dense price structures with multiple bounces.
So remember, liquidity clearouts are most common around
symmetrical structures, where many traders will watch the
same price level or place stop losses around
the same price level.
Therefore, market makers would want to see that
lever broken and enter their positions while liquidation
is taking place and absorb opposite orders.
For retail traders like you and me, the
aim should be to spot such potential liquidity
zones and join the game of the market
maker, and to avoid being a liquidity target.
A liquidity clearout should always present itself with
a rapid, strong reversal move after a critical
low or high is taken out.
Basically, a rapid rotation of the price back
into the structural support or resistance.
The speed of the rotation back will usually
depend on the market or the liquidity of
the market.
In some markets, the reversal back might take
15 or 30 minutes, as the smart money
needs to collect as many orders as possible
over time, while in forex or crypto, the
reversal will be much quicker on average, between
1 to 15 minutes, since those markets are
much more liquid.
If the structure is not even on highs
or lows positioning, for example, when highs or
lows are connected through a trend line instead
of a flat line, then the main area
to watch is the lowest low or the
highest high of the structure, that is, where
the majority of condensed stop losses will sit
and where breakout traders might initiate other positions.
This is the difference between a flat versus
a trend line positioning of lows and the
importance of the deepest low.
No matter how the structure is positioned, the
low of the structure will be the key
level that the market maker will want to
clear out and where the majority of stops
will likely sit.
There's a difference between a targeted and a
non-targeted liquidity clearout, meaning triggered by a
market maker or triggered by the overall market
action.
On the left side, we have a targeted
attempt and on the right, a non-targeted
one.
The difference between strong quick moves initiated by
the smart money and the move triggered by
the overall market action is usually spotted depending
on where price starts the actual move and
if that move is consistent.
In the case of a targeted attempt, most
of these moves will be initiated in the
middle of the structure, where not much liquidity
sits.
Meanwhile, strong moves triggered by the overall market
action are usually going to be on very
symmetrical and obvious price extremes.
After the liquidity clearout under the lows or
above the highs, the price should start reversing
back inside the structure relatively quickly.
Timing is the key.
Let's say you're a scalper and you're using
the 1-minute chart.
My own rule is that it shouldn't take
more than 10 1-minute candles for the
price to rotate back above support.
This depends a lot on how big the
structure is, how many candles are in each
leg of the structure.
The more candles per leg, the longer it
might take for the liquidity clearout move to
happen.
But it shouldn't be more than 10 candles.
In the best scenario, it happens within the
first 3-5 candles.
Again, it's a relative concept as it scales
with the market and the time frame chosen.
To trade a liquidity clearout, you need a
clear plan to find the pattern.
Using price alerts is a useful way to
support the searching process.
The plan is quite simple.
Once the potential symmetrical structure is spotted, with
variables that fit a potential liquidity clearout, you
place an alert below the structural lows or
above highs, depending if it's a bull or
a bear pattern.
This is important because once an alert is
placed, you can relax and do other stuff
and only come back once the alert rings
and the price clears the required liquidity area.
It's an important tip that helped me a
lot.
Using price alerts is critical to minimize the
screen time and to be more patient and
fresh as a trader.
The key when trading a liquidity hunt is
to focus on volume.
At the clearout price area, there should be
significant volume traded.
Let's analyze this liquidity clearout pattern.
We have a clear downtrend with lower lows
and lower highs in the structure.
This is our main focus point, the lowest
low in the structure.
This is where our price alert should be.
A drop into the lows will usually be
initiated by the market maker with a heavy
market order that will remove liquidity and swipe
price under the lows.
Look at the volume traded in the liquidity
hunt.
It increased considerably once the lowest low in
the structure was taken out.
For an entry, you should wait for the
liquidity clearout and then for the price to
start moving back above support for a long
entry.
Your risk should be the lowest low of
the clearout.
This is where your stop loss should be.
Here's another liquidity hunt.
We first observe a heavy sell-off ahead
of the structure.
We then find a symmetrical structure with approximately
even lows, ensuring even stop loss placement under
them.
High volume on the clearout with the highest
volume candle in the whole structure.
Volatility on the market is high, meaning we
have a wide range.
And we have a sharp and quick reversal
after the clearout and the reclaim of the
previous support.
So after the liquidity clearout, an important sign
should be the volume.
The volume traded was the highest 1-minute
volume candle inside the whole price structure, as
price quickly reclaimed support and then pushed higher.
This was a good moment to open a
buy position, with the stop loss below the
most recent low.
The key component for trading the clearout is
that it has to reclaim the support for
a long trade or the resistance for a
short trade.
If it doesn't reclaim, there is no trade
in the first place, it's a breakout.
Here's an example with high volume clearout under
the lows, as the long traders are stopped
out.
But the price didn't reclaim the support level,
thus this is not a long trade.
Remember this important point.
The faster the price reclaims support and pushes
above after the clearout, the better the trade.
On the best trades, price should reclaim support
within the first 5 candles after the clearout.
If the structure is not symmetrical, with evenly
positioned lows, it's hard to base the entry.
That is why I prefer to trade structures
that are clean and symmetrical.
This allows precise entry conditions across all trades.
Let's look at this asymmetric structure and clearout.
You can observe that the lows are not
evenly positioned.
We even have some higher lows.
This is the deepest lower low, the main
area that you should wait for.
We have the liquidity clearout and the quick
reversal after the clearout.
But now the question is, where's our entry?
This isn't so clear like in a symmetrical
structure, that's why I prefer the symmetrical ones.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we'll know if you'd like to
see more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time.