This is my father, Mervin Tilbury, he's one
of the hardest working people I know and
as a kid I remember him working in
a factory job making cable ties and a
side hustle cutting grass so he could provide
for me and my mum and my three
sisters.
He'd stash away any extra money he made
in a shoebox as well as a bank
account that paid little to no interest, hoping
that one day he could quit his job
working in the factory.
When my uncle invested some of his money
in the stock market, my dad said it
was an extremely risky move.
Unfortunately, what my dad didn't realise is that
he was also playing a risky game.
Can you see where this story's going?
Every year my father's money was losing value
due to inflation.
This is just what happens over time.
As more money is printed, the money in
circulation becomes less valuable.
This meant he was never able to quit
his job in the factory.
The thought of my money being eaten away
by inflation scared me so much that I've
made sure to invest throughout my life.
As a result, not only have I beaten
inflation, but my investments actually now grow by
around $17,000 a week on their own,
which over my lifetime has made me millions.
I'm no financial advisor, but I am someone
that's been there and done it.
That's why I'm making this video.
It's exactly what I wish I had when
I was younger.
How can I make money investing in stocks?
To make money, we first need to beat
the inflation issue.
In the last 60 years, this average is
out to a rate of 3.8%
per year.
So if your money isn't growing by more
than this on its own, then you're getting
poorer by the second.
In a perfect world, you would have a
savings account that provides an average return of
8-10% every year so that you
can both beat inflation and earn some profit.
Unfortunately, such savings accounts don't exist.
However, you can achieve returns like this by
investing in the stock market.
A stock is a small part of a
company, and when you buy it, you become
a shareholder.
And when you're a shareholder, there are two
ways you can make money.
Firstly, if the price of the stock goes
up during the time you own it, you
can sell it for more than you paid.
Secondly, you can receive dividends.
Dividends are regular payments to shareholders.
Not all stocks pay dividends, but if they
do, this means that you can receive money
without ever selling your stock.
The magic really starts to happen when you
own a bunch of stocks that grow at
an average of 10% per year because
the interest applied becomes larger and larger.
This is called compound interest, and I have
to admit a guilty pleasure of mine is
messing around with online compound interest calculators.
Let's do one now.
If you were able to invest $250 per
month at an 8% annual return in
42 years, you'd be a millionaire.
And if you continue to do this for
another 10 years, you would actually have over
2 million in your account.
Of course, if you wanted to invest even
more, then that would just speed up the
process.
This is all based on historical average data,
and it isn't guaranteed, but it's certainly been
my experience.
So as you can see, the real secret
ingredient to this millionaire formula is time, which
brings me on to when should I start
investing?
The short answer to this is as soon
as possible.
The younger you start, the better, as you're
giving your investments more time to grow and
compound.
This also means you can take more risk
as your investments have time to recover if
a stock market crash happens.
And it will happen.
It always happens.
But life isn't as easy as this, as
there are often things in the way preventing
you from investing.
So here's how I would structure things.
First, you need to make sure you've paid
off all high interest debt like credit cards.
Just think about it.
There's no point trying to make 10%
in the stock market if you're paying 15
% to a credit card company.
Secondly, build up an emergency fund.
This should be enough to cover three to
six months of your living expenses.
This way, you're not forced to sell your
stocks in the event of an emergency, which
can really ruin your progress.
Once you've done both of these things, you're
ready to start investing.
If you're younger than 18, then it would
be a great idea to ask a parent
to open up a custodial account, which allows
them to invest for you.
This will give you such an advantage in
the future.
Your next question is probably something along the
lines of how much should I invest?
When you ask an investor, they'll probably say
as much as possible.
However, I have a different opinion.
I made most of my money through starting
different businesses and only used the stock market
to grow my wealth over time.
I've also had a pretty fun life from
flying full-size aeroplanes and racing cars to
competing for my country and traveling the world.
If I'd invested all of that money into
the stock market, then I'd have missed out
on so much.
So my answer would be to invest whatever
you feel comfortable with.
But if you want a more solid answer,
then the 70-20-10 rule is a
pretty good guide.
It states that you should split your money
by these percentages, 70% on living expenses,
20% on investments, and 10% on
the fun stuff.
Research shows that people who invest at this
level are much better equipped to ride the
ups and downs of life and also get
ahead of everyone else.
That's all well and good, but how do
I buy a stock?
There are various different apps out there that
allow you to invest in stocks.
I'll leave some links below.
The key is to open the correct type
of account.
You'll often hear people throwing around the terms
Roth IRA in the USA and Stocks and
Shares ISA in the UK, TFSA in Canada,
and Supers in Australia.
If you don't have one of these accounts,
then you're missing out as they allow you
to avoid paying taxes on your investments.
But they do have limits because they're so
powerful.
A great thing about these investing apps is
they actually give you the ability to buy
fractional shares.
So rather than buying a share of Apple
for $190, you can invest as little as
$1.
I wish I had this option when I
was younger as it would have allowed me
to get some early investing experience without having
to take any big risks.
One of my favorite investing platforms is Trading212
as they do both of these things.
Since I was planning to talk about their
app anyway, I reached out to see if
they'd be interested in sponsoring this portion of
the video.
They agreed and are also offering a free
stock worth up to £100 to anyone that
uses the code Tilbury when they create an
account.
One of the really cool things about Trading212
is they let you practice investing with fake
money so you can get familiar with real
data from the markets without risking any money.
So if you're a little uncomfortable with investing
or just want to try some strategies before
putting your own money on the line, this
is a great way to get started.
Another great feature is called Pies, where you
can see how other investors have allocated their
money into different stocks.
If you wanted to invest $100 into that
pie, then it would just be split amongst
the various allocations that that pie creator has
chosen.
If you live in the UK or Europe,
it's worth trying out Trading212 because signing up
is completely free and there are no commissions.
Of course, don't forget to use the code
Tilbury and you'll receive a free share worth
up to £100.
Or click the link in the description to
sign up and see exactly how to access
the free share.
Now the obvious next question is how do
I pick the best stocks?
There are two main ways to attempt to
predict the stock market.
These are called technical and fundamental analysis.
A good way to think about this is
like a scale.
Usually, short-term day traders are purely focused
on the technical aspects.
This includes looking at charts and patterns.
They believe they can predict how the stock
will change in price by judging the highs
and the lows on the graphs.
As a long-term investor, my strategy is
about keeping it simple.
Lots of people talk about using margin and
options, but that's really not something I worry
about.
I'm a lot more focused on the fundamentals
of a company.
This includes the financials, the leadership, and the
brand recognition, as I believe this is where
the true information lies that indicate the long
-term success of a stock.
When I invest in a stock, I don't
have an intention of selling it for at
least two to five years.
However, like I mentioned, it's a scale, so
I do look at the occasional chart in
order to find the best time to buy.
This approach has helped me find some really
good investments over the years rather than just
dipping in and out trying to make a
profit every day.
But with the majority of my investments, I
don't actually do any of this.
That's because I allocate most of my money
to index funds.
This is definitely the best strategy for most
people.
So what's an index fund?
It's a way for the average person to
make more money than the professionals with very
little effort.
I'm a big football fan, and if you've
ever followed any sports, you'll be familiar with
a league table like this.
The better your team performs, the higher up
they'll be on the list.
On the other hand, if they do really
badly, they might be removed from the league
entirely.
This is almost exactly the same as an
index.
All you have to do is switch out
the teams for companies.
Let's take the S&P 500 for example.
This is a list of around 500 of
the largest public companies in the USA.
The big dogs being Amazon, Google, Apple, and
Tesla.
Just like the league table, if a company
does poorly, then they run the risk of
being removed from the list.
With this league table or index of companies,
you could go and buy stocks in some
of them individually.
However, if something bad happens to those companies
that you've picked, then you can wave goodbye
to your money.
The idea of an index fund is to
be a little bit sneaky, as it allows
you to invest in every single company on
the list with just one click.
Even if a few companies do terribly, then
it's balanced out by all the companies doing
extremely well.
The average annual return of the S&P
500 over the last 10 years has been
13.6%, although this is slightly higher than
the average over time.
No one has ever lost any money if
they've bought and held an S&P 500
index fund for more than 20 years.
The truth is that the average actively managed
fund returned 2% less per year than
the market in general.
This means that the professionals on average are
doing worse than index funds, and even if
they end up losing you money, they still
charge you high fees no matter what.
The reason that index funds can charge really
low fees is because they're passively managed, which
means they look after themselves and don't need
an expert to keep adjusting them, meaning the
fees can be as low as 0.02
% per year.
When I tell people about index funds, it
often blows their minds.
However, when they go onto an investing app,
they get confused at the different options and
ask, what's the best index fund to invest
in?
Well, as I said, I'm not a financial
advisor, but I have had a lot of
success with three different types of index funds.
Number one tracks the S&P 500 index.
This is the one we briefly mentioned before.
The historical return of 8% to 10
% has allowed me to generate a fortune
over the years.
This is due to the power of compound
interest.
The S&P 500 tracks 11 different industries
slash sectors, and no sector is more than
30% of the index.
However, it is worth pointing out that it's
a bit tech heavy these days with five
tech stocks dominating 23% of the entire
fund.
It's up to you if you see this
as a positive or a negative.
I personally don't mind as I believe in
the future of technology.
There are so many different index funds that
track the S&P 500.
So here are some of my favorites.
The best I found in the USA at
the VFIAX index fund or the VUE ETF.
The best in the UK would probably be
the VUSA ETF.
The only real difference between an index fund
and an ETF is that the ETF can
be purchased or sold at any time throughout
the day, just like a stock.
Index funds can only be purchased in full.
So for example, if the price is $500,
you must pay $500.
An ETF on the other hand can be
purchased in fractional shares, which means you don't
have to buy a full share and instead
you can invest whatever amount you like.
This is great if you're just starting out
or want to dollar cost average in.
Personally, I've set up a direct debit every
month so the money leaves my bank account
without me even noticing.
Really and truly there isn't a huge difference
between an index fund and an ETF.
Just consider which one is best for you.
Take the plunge.
Number two is a total stock market index.
The total stock market index has returned investors
an average of 13% each year over
the last 10 years, which isn't bad at
all.
It's the definition of diversification.
You can't really get any more skin in
the game for a lower cost.
If you want to invest for a long
period of time without having to even check
or even think about it, then this is
most likely the fund for you.
Investing in everything means you can experience gains
across the entire market and unless a crazy
crash happens, you should be okay.
But even if it does crash, with time,
things tend to bounce back.
I've seen three crashes since I've been an
investor.
The dot-com bubble, the 2008 financial crisis,
and the 2020 COVID crash.
I'm not going to pretend these crashes didn't
hurt, but long-term every market I've invested
in has bounced back.
The downside to this index is it depends
on the entire market trending upwards.
This means there could be an individual stock
that you really believe in that goes to
the moon, but you might not experience those
gains because that stock doesn't play much of
a role within the index fund.
The best I've found in the USA are
the VTSAX Index Fund and the VTI ETF,
and the best in the UK is the
VWRL ETF.
Number three is the Emerging Markets Index.
Emerging markets are predicted by some experts to
be on the rise and whether I agree
with this or not, I think it's important
for me to have at least a little
bit of exposure to these markets.
It's all well and good buying the S
&P 500, but when China or another emerging
country has some great gains, you'll end up
missing out.
Just as an example of this growth, when
I first traveled to China around 20 years
ago, I looked into buying an apartment in
Shenzhen.
That real estate was $47,000 and now
it's worth over a million.
This just shows the potential growth in these
markets.
Emerging market funds are definitely the most risky
type of index funds we've discussed.
These funds include stocks from lots of different
growing markets and can be very heavy with
Chinese companies.
Taking a look at a list of the
largest economies in the world, a lot of
them are emerging markets, so it just makes
sense to me to throw a little bit
of money in for diversification.
The best I've found in the USA is
the VEIEX ETF and in the UK, the
VFEM ETF, but there are also lots of
other emerging market funds available, so it's worth
having a look around.
Now, I know at some point I need
to address the biggest question around investing, which
is of course, is investing risky?
It really depends on how you define risk.
You may be scared that you'll lose money.
However, you'll also face this risk by not
investing, as my father Mervyn found out.
If you have a diversified portfolio of index
funds and keep investing at a gradual rate
each and every year, then even if there
is a stock market crash, then historical data
shows you should be able to endure the
storm.
A great way to make sure you're protected
in the event of a market crash is
to mix in a few bonds within your
stock portfolio.
These are just a different type of investment
that are far more stable than stocks, and
you can buy these on the same investment
platforms.
In your 20s and 30s, I wouldn't worry
too much about them, but as you move
closer to retirement, it's a good idea to
have more bonds than stocks.
In my opinion, in your younger years, the
biggest risk you can take is not taking
enough risk.
Now for the question on everyone's mind, when
should I sell my stocks?
It's possibly one of the most common questions
in the stock investing world.
Knowing when to sell stocks or hold onto
them mostly depends on your age.
If you're older, you've likely been investing for
a while and can live off them during
retirement by gradually selling when needed.
However, if you're younger, this usually isn't the
case.
In fact, if you're in your 20s to
30s, there are only three good reasons to
sell your investments.
Number one, you need money for an emergency.
Hopefully, if you've followed the video so far,
then you won't need to worry because you've
got an emergency fund to help you out
in times like this.
Number two, you made a bad investment.
If you have individual stocks that appear to
be underperforming consistently, it may be time to
cut your losses before those losses stack up
even higher.
Before panic selling, take a good look at
the wider industry.
If other goods like it are also in
decline, then you know it's the industry, not
just your stock.
If everything's doing poorly, this gives you a
bit of extra context.
Number three, you've achieved a specific goal.
Although I don't really recommend it, if you're
investing for short or medium-term goals like,
I don't know, saving up for a dream
vacation, then it would be a great idea
to set a target price.
This is a figure at which you would
feel satisfied selling the stock and enjoying your
gains.
The most important thing to remember is to
not sell your stocks for as long as
possible so they have the longest time to
grow.
Just invest and forget about it until you
want to stop investing and take your profits.
This thinking will also help you avoid panic
selling.
If you want to know exactly how I
pick my individual stocks, then you can check
out this video next, but don't click on
it just yet.
Make sure to subscribe if you want to
grow your wealth.
Okay, I'll see you over there.