I want you to imagine for a moment
that you started investing in 1985.
For a couple of years, your money keeps
going up and up until...
Black Monday.
They're calling it the Monday Massacre.
Wall Street had its biggest one-day drop
in history.
The results of the decline will hit millions
of people.
Up until this point, your friends probably thought
you were some kind of genius, but now
they're urging you to sell.
But you ignore them and slowly but surely
the market recovers until...
The Nasdaq index in freefall down nearly 10%.
Driven by technology in general and the internet
in particular.
Traders and investors shell-shocked.
Your friends are on their knees begging you
to pour your money out, saying things like
it's time to take your profits before you
lose everything.
But you hold strong and things start going
back up until you're hit with...
It was one of the most profound events
in generations with huge consequences.
Little did you know you're in for the
ride of a lifetime until...
The global economy will contract by 3%
this year.
The worst downturn since the Great Depression.
Surely this is the end of the stock
market.
But as things reopened, the market soared 27
% from its low, setting new records.
What a comeback.
Something I didn't mention is the guy that
invested his money in 1985 was actually me
when I turned 18 years old.
The average return over this time period was
11.23% per year.
So if I'd have only invested $250 per
month during this time, then I would have
made $1,841,521.08. That's a return
of over 6,000%.
But between us, I invested a lot more
than that.
So now you understand the power of investing,
I think it's time to jump into the
details.
Honestly, it's amazing how many people talk about
investing, but don't actually show you how to
do it.
So I'm gonna quickly walk you through how
to invest in stocks on your phone.
Of course, remember, I'm not a financial advisor.
This is just the way I do it.
And before you do any of this, make
sure you have an emergency fund of three
to five months of living expenses.
The first thing on our list is to
set up an account.
A lot of people get stuck at this
stage as there's a lot of different investment
platforms out there and also different types of
accounts.
Trust me, it's much more simple than it
first seems, especially now you can do it
all online.
When I first started investing, I had to
phone up the stock broker every time I
wanted to buy a stock.
Let's use the Trading212 app.
I'm gonna be using my son's account as
my account's pretty messy as it has a
bunch of free shares.
He's actually been running an experiment on here
for the last three months, but we'll talk
about that in a bit.
The account you open should be a tax
advantaged one.
This means you won't have to pay any
unnecessary taxes.
These are known as stocks and shares ISAs
in the UK and Roth IRAs in America.
I think the UK option's much better as
you can invest up to 20,000 pounds
a year without paying capital gains tax on
your profits and you can take out your
money whenever you want.
In contrast, Americans have to wait until they're
old and retired and they have a much
lower limit of $6,500 per year.
Feel free to use whatever app you like.
This is just one of my personal favorites.
Next, we need to deposit some money in
order to start investing.
Most apps make it pretty easy to deposit
money.
We just have to click these three lines
and then select Deposit Funds.
As you can see, this brings up a
screen with lots of different options like Instant
Bank Transfer, Bank Transfer, Debit Card, and what
we're gonna use, Apple Pay.
Let's just put in 400 so we can
invest in some stocks together.
Feel free to invest whatever you feel comfortable
doing.
Curtis, I'm gonna need your face for the
phone.
Hang on.
This next step is super important, getting some
free stocks.
Since I was planning to talk about trading
212 anyway, I reached out to them to
see if they would be interested in sponsoring
this portion of the video.
They agreed and they're offering a free stock
worth up to £100 to anyone that uses
the code TILBRI when they create an account.
Plus, you can get more free shares by
inviting your friends.
Both of you will get a free share
as long as they fund their account.
So don't waste your invites and invite brokies.
And also don't worry if you've already opened
an account within the last 10 days.
You can still use the promo code TILBRI
in the app and receive your free share.
Right, now we need to plan a winning
strategy.
The first thing we need to remember is
that investments go up and down, so it's
very hard to pick winning individual stocks.
That's why I prefer to invest in all
of them.
You probably think this sounds a bit crazy,
but stay with me.
I love listening to music.
I'm a big Deacon Blue and Queen fan
myself.
But whatever you like, if you've ever listened
to the radio or used Spotify, you'll be
familiar with the music charts.
The better the songs perform in sales and
downloads, the higher up they go in the
charts.
On the other hand, if a song drops
in popularity and sales, then it drops out
of the charts.
This is almost exactly the same as investing
in an index fund.
All you have to do is switch out
the songs for companies.
Let's take the S&P 500, for example.
This is a list of around 500 of
the largest public companies in the USA.
The big dogs being Amazon, Google, Apple, and
Tesla.
And just like the music charts, if a
company does poorly, then they risk being removed
from the list.
Here's the cool part about an index fund.
With just one click, you're not just investing
in one or two companies, but in every
single company on the list.
So if one doesn't perform very well, your
money's okay as you'll spread across all of
them.
So how can we put this into practice?
Well, we need to automate our long-term
investments.
Remember I said my son had been running
a little experiment for the last three months
on his account.
Well, he's been investing five pounds into the
S&P 500 every day.
Why five pound?
Because that's about the average price of a
Starbucks coffee.
Automating your investments like this is a great
idea as it means you can just set
it and forget it.
His portfolio is actually doing pretty well.
As you can see in the green, his
return so far is 36 pounds and 46
pence, and that's a return of 5.03%.
Not bad for a little experiment.
If you want me to keep you updated
with this when it reaches the six month
mark, let me know in the comments.
To set something like this up, all you
have to do is select Pies and then
press the plus icon.
Now you can select whatever stocks you want
to include in your pie.
For this demonstration, let's just keep it easy
and pick this S&P 500 index fund.
By the way, look out for if it
says accumulation or distribution in the brackets.
Personally, I always go with accumulation as it
reinvests your dividends back into the stock automatically.
The less I have to think about, the
better.
Now let's tap add to pie and then
the arrow button.
If there was more than one stock in
here, then we'd be able to change the
percentages with this slider.
Right, tap next and then auto invest.
This value projection is really awesome as it
shows you how much money you could make
based on historical averages.
Of course, when you invest, you can get
back less than you invested as investments can
rise and fall.
But it's still a great way to get
an idea of how much you could make
based on data-backed projections.
I mean, say we invested 250 pounds a
month for 31 years.
You'll only have invested 94,000 of your
own money.
Your portfolio would be 1.14 million.
If we expand this to 40 years, your
portfolio would be 3.56 million.
It's worth having a play around with this
as it's quite motivational seeing how much money
you can make with a relatively small amount
invested per month.
And to all the people in the comments
saying, well, what about inflation?
It will make your money worth far less.
As long as you're investing and not just
keeping your money in a bank account, then
inflation is not something you need to be
extremely worried about.
Additionally, I increased the amount I was investing
to keep pace with inflation.
Now, let's pick some individual stocks.
Although I wouldn't recommend that beginners bother with
picking stocks, I know many of you are
gonna try anyway, especially since you've seen people
make millions from the right meme stock that
skyrocketed like GameStop.
All right, so there's basically two ways to
take a stab at figuring out what's going
on in the stock market, technical and fundamental
analysis.
Those quick deal day traders are all about
the technical stuff, poring over price charts and
patterns, thinking they've got the scoop on how
the stock's gonna swing just by eyeballing the
ups and downs.
Now me, I'm more of a long-term
player.
I dig into the nitty gritty of a
company's fundamentals.
You know, the financials, who's steering the ship
and how well-known the brand is.
I reckon that's where the real lowdown is
for predicting a stock's long-term success.
So I sift through income statements, balance sheets,
and cashflow statements.
When I throw money into a stock, I'm
in it for the long haul, at least
two to five years minimum.
To find stocks, simply click on the magnifying
glass icon.
Trading 212 have made it incredibly easy to
find stocks by providing various lists, such as
big tech, popular ETF, banks, and most owned.
There's also lots more.
Take a look when you find a bit
of time.
You can even go on the social feed
tab and see different pies that other users
have created and copy it for yourself with
a single click.
So you don't have to find the stocks
yourself.
On the stock page, you can see the
price graph and by scrolling down, you can
actually access all those important financial documents I
discussed earlier.
Now, let's buy a stock, Tesla will do.
Now this pulls up a page with a
couple of different options.
The first one is a market order.
A market order is just like when you
go to the supermarket and pay whatever the
price tag says.
A limit order, on the other hand, is
like going to a boot fair and haggling
for the best price you want.
You can put in a price that you're
willing to pay and if the price ever
gets to that level, then the app will
purchase the stock for you.
As a beginner, that's all you really need
to know.
There's no point diving into the other options.
Let's buy 400 pounds worth of Tesla so
I can show you how it's done.
The final step is to press send by
order and boom, we're now part owners of
Tesla.
So now you know all the steps and
you've got a free stock with the link
in the description.
What's holding you back?
Well, it all sounds great, Mark, but isn't
investing a bit risky?
Well, take a look at this.
If you're investing a single amount every month
from the age of 25, you would be
around about here if you invested for around
30 years.
Now, if you waited 10 years, this is
the difference it'll make to your growth.
Somewhere around about here.
Look at the difference.
It's absolutely crazy.
So start young.
If you have a diversified portfolio of index
funds and keep investing at a gradual rate
each and every year, then even if there's
a stock market crash, then historical data shows
you should be able to endure the storm
just like I did.
If you wanna know why net worth goes
crazy after 100K, then you can check out
this next video, but don't click on it
just yet.
Make sure to subscribe if you wanna grow
your wealth, okay?
I'll see you over there.