What you are looking at is an option
chain of Netflix, and these options have 37
days until they expire.
Here are the out of the money calls
and puts, and we know that if these
options remain out of the money, they will
gradually go to zero.
And I'll just show you an example here.
Let's just reference the 90 strike put.
It's trading at 335 by 350.
Now let's fast forward to the options that
expire in just two days.
You can see that they are all much
cheaper.
And if you look at the 90 strike
put that expires in two days, it's only
at 11 cents by 15 cents, whereas the
90 strike put with 37 days to expiration
is at 335 by 350.
So each and every day, time premium is
sucked out of these options.
Now if you buy options, you already know
that you are constantly fighting this time decay.
Instead of fighting it, we prefer to let
it work for us and make us money.
Let me show you one of our favorite
option strategies that you can start utilizing immediately
to put time decay in your favor, even
with a small account.
We can achieve this by trading an iron
condor.
So what exactly is an iron condor?
Don't let the name intimidate you, it's actually
very simple.
The first part of an iron condor consists
of selling to open an out of the
money put, and simultaneously selling to open an
out of the money call.
We would do this in hopes that between
now and expiration, the stock will stay in
between the strikes and the options we sold
will go to zero.
If this is the case, we will keep
the entire price we sold these options for.
But since short naked options can have a
lot of risk and can require a lot
of capital, we are also going to buy
a further out of the money put and
call for protection.
These four option trades are collectively called an
iron condor.
But we're selling two options and buying two
options.
So how does this work?
Well let me show you.
Stock XYZ is trading at $75 per share.
Let's sell the 85 call for $2, and
we're also going to sell the 65 put
for $2.
And our idea is that the stock will
stay in between these strikes and the options
we sold will expire worthless.
But again, since naked options theoretically have unlimited
risk, we are going to buy some protection.
So we're also going to buy the 90
call for $1, and the 60 put for
$1.
And I know that keeping track with all
of these individual option trades seems like a
lot to keep up with, but we can
actually trade an iron condor with one order
and view it as one trade.
And I'm going to show you how to
do that in the end of the video,
but for now just stick with me.
Let's say we initiated this trade with 30
days to expiration.
And as time passes and we near expiration,
let's say the stock doesn't move much and
just kind of bounces around and trades sideways.
So as we near expiration, these options remain
out of the money and the price of
each option gradually goes to zero.
If all of these options are worthless, what
does that mean for our trade?
Well we make $200 on the 85 call
and also on the 65 put.
Because we are short those options and they
are now at zero.
So we collected a credit, and since they
are of no value, we get to keep
that credit.
Okay, but we also lost some money on
the options we bought as protection.
We lost $100 on the 90 strike call
and also on the 60 strike put, because
we bought these options and they now have
no value.
Adding all of these numbers up totals to
a net profit of $200, because we made
$400 on the short options and lost $200
on the long options.
So by trading an iron condor, we are
simply betting that the stock will stay within
a certain range and we treat it as
one trade.
We lost money on the long call and
put, but that's exactly what we want to
happen, because we simply bought these options as
protection.
It's kind of like, we pay for car
insurance, but we don't actually want to crash
our car.
So now that you know how we make
money on the trade, let me show you
how we can lose money and also how
much we can lose.
Let's say the stock goes crazy and although
it was completely unexpected, it goes well outside
of our range we wanted it to stay
in and ends up at $96 per share.
Well we already know that both the long
put and the short put are out of
the money and are worthless.
So we made $200 on the short put
and lost $100 on the long put.
So this totals to a net profit of
$100 on the puts.
But what about the calls?
The 85 call is 11 points in the
money, so it's worth 11, and the 90
call is 6 points in the money, so
it's worth 6.
We are short the 85 call at 2,
and it's at 11, so this means we
lost 9 points, or $900 on that leg
of the trade.
So that sucks, but fortunately we bought the
90 call for protection.
We paid $1 for the 90 call, and
it's now trading at 6.
So we made $500 on that leg of
the trade.
This $500 and the $100 we made on
the put side cancels out much of the
$900 we lost on the short call.
Adding up all of these numbers totals to
a net loss of $300 on the entire
trade.
Now this is the cool part.
We lost $300 on the entire trade, but
that's the maximum amount we can lose on
this trade no matter where the stock is.
It doesn't matter if the stock goes to
104, 25, 0, infinity, whatever the case may
be, we can't lose more than $300 on
this trade.
And the way we end up with this
max loss is if the stock is outside
of our long option strikes at the expiration
date.
Now I keep mentioning how we treat this
trade as one trade.
When we trade an iron condor, we are
usually just monitoring the price of the iron
condor as a whole.
Check out this iron condor we just opened
in Facebook.
You can see that when we trade an
iron condor, the platform automatically calculates everything for
us.
We are able to see the individual legs
of the trade, but we are also able
to see the total net prices.
In this example, you can see we sold
this iron condor at $1.12, it's currently
trading at $0.82, and we have a
profit of just $30 on the trade.
When trading an iron condor, our maximum potential
profit is simply the price we sold the
iron condor for.
In this example, we sold the iron condor
for a net price of $2, so our
maximum profit is $200.
Our maximum loss is simply the width between
our short and long strikes minus our net
entry price.
So in this case, our strikes are 5
points wide on both the call and put
side.
And if we subtract our entry price from
that, we get a max loss of 3
points, or $300.
This $300 is also our capital requirement for
the trade.
This is the reason the iron condor is
so powerful, because we can sell option premium
with very little risk, and also without the
large capital requirement.
Now our break-even prices that we need
the stock to stay between is just our
entry price plus the short call strike, and
on the downside, it's our short put strike
minus our entry price.
And at the expiration date, if the stock
stays within this range, then we make money,
and if the stock is outside of this
range, then we lose money.
And I know this seems like a lot
to keep up with, but check this out.
Before entering the trade, the thinkorswim platform will
calculate all of this information for you.
On this pop-up box, you can see
your max profit on the trade is $200,
your max loss is $300, and the range
you need the stock to stay between for
you to at least break-even is 63
and 87.
So before you trade an iron condor, just
be sure to check this pop-up box
before sending the order.
And also, if you are a member of
our website, we will help you with your
first iron condor trades to make sure you
don't click any wrong buttons or mess anything
up.
Now let me show you how to pull
up an order to trade an iron condor.
Let's say that we want to collect time
decay in Tesla options, but we aren't necessarily
bullish or bearish on the stock.
To do this, we're going to trade an
iron condor, and the strikes we choose are
going to give us a neutral stance on
the stock.
First, before we build the iron condor, we
need to add the probability in the money
column to our option chain.
If you are using a platform that doesn't
have this feature, then you can use Delta
instead.
For this example, we're going to trade an
iron condor with 30 days to expiration.
You are free to choose whatever expiration you
want to trade in, but we prefer to
initiate our trades with 30 to 60 days
to expiration.
Now, for starters, let's find a call with
a probability in the money of 13%.
That brings us to the 260 call.
We're going to right click on the bid,
click sell, iron condor.
In this case, it defaulted to 5 points
wide, which is what we're going to stick
with in this example.
So you see we're selling the 260 call
and buying the 265 call for protection.
Now we just have to select our put
strikes.
Since we want to place a trade that
is directionally neutral, we will find a put
that has the same probability in the money
as our call did.
Scrolling up, we can find the put that
has a probability in the money of around
13.
And that brings us to the strike of
187.50. So we're just going to adjust
the short put strike on our order to
187.50 and then adjust the long put
to 5 points further out of the money
to 182.50. Now, if we click confirm
and send, we can see our max profit
is $101.
Our max loss is $399.
And the range we need Tesla to stay
between is 186.49 and 261.01. This
gives us a nice wide range for us
to make a profit.
So the trade has a very high probability
of success, but it has a poor risk
to reward because our max profit is only
101 and our max loss is 399.
What we could do is just simply move
in our strikes a bit.
This will lower our probability of success because
it will narrow the range we need Tesla
to stay within, but in exchange for this,
we will collect a bigger credit for the
trade which improves our risk to reward.
So let's move the strikes in 10 points
on both sides.
You can see our credit is now 170
rather than just 101.
Now let's see what this iron condor will
be trading at in the future if the
stock price and implied volatility doesn't move.
To do this, we can just look at
the same trade but with only 2 days
to expiration rather than 30.
So we're just going to change the expiration
of our order to the July weekly options
that expire in 2 days.
You can see the net price of the
iron condor is just at 1 cent.
We could do one of two things.
We could close this position at 1 cent
for a profit, or we could try and
let the options expire worthless as long as
the stock stays still and the options remain
out of the money.
The choice is yours.
And this is just one way to trade
the iron condor.
There are many variations of the iron condor
that you can learn about.
We are able to adjust our strike selection
and even vary our expirations to achieve different
things.
If you want to learn about these variations
and also see which iron condors we are
trading, head over to our website.
If you liked this video and want more
like it on different trading concepts, be sure
to show us your support by clicking the
like and subscribe button below.
Also check out our website and join our
email list for 3 exclusive free videos.
We even make a live iron condor trade
in the third video.
So I will see you there.