The stock market is over and you should
get out before Trump triggers a full-blown
recession.
That's what the mainstream media want you to
think.
Headlines are screaming disaster, social media is in
a frenzy and everyone is asking the same
question.
Should I sell now before it gets worse?
But there's more to this than meets the
eye.
If you've followed me for a while, you
know I'm a serious investor who's obsessed with
the stock market.
And since so many of you have started
investing because of my videos, I feel a
responsibility to give you my honest take on
the situation.
So before you panic, let's take a step
back and look at the bigger picture together.
Every market crash has a cause and this
one isn't random.
There are three main triggers behind it and
all of them tie back to one man,
Donald Trump.
Now before anyone jumps to conclusions, this isn't
about politics.
I'm not here to take sides and as
a British investor looking in, my only concern
is how this impacts investors like you and
me.
So let's break down the three biggest triggers
behind this crash, why they matter and what
you can do to benefit from all this
mayhem.
Trigger one is Trump's trade war.
Trump has always pitched himself as the ultimate
deal maker.
He's the guy who fights for American jobs
and plays hardball with other countries.
But the trade wars he's fighting could increase
your weekly shopping bill and cause a recession.
The last time the US tried this, it
helped trigger the Great Depression, wiping out jobs
and wrecking the economy.
Now history might be repeating itself.
Stocks are already crashing, prices are rising and
if this spirals, it won't just hurt Wall
Street, it'll hit you where it matters most,
your bank account.
Let me take you back to 1930 when
I was just a boy.
The US government decided to slap massive taxes
called tariffs on imported goods to protect American
businesses from foreign competition.
It was called the Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act
and it turned out to be one of
the worst economic mistakes in history.
At first, it seemed like it would help.
American companies wouldn't have to compete with cheap
imports and more products would be made in
the USA.
But there was a big problem, other countries
fought back.
Nations that used to trade with the US
started raising their own tariffs, making it harder
for American businesses to sell products overseas.
Trade slowed to an absolute crawl, businesses collapsed
and millions lost their jobs.
Instead of fixing the economy, it helped turn
a regular recession into the Great Depression, one
of the worst financial crises ever.
Fast forward nearly a century and Trump has
brought back tariffs in a big way.
In February 2025, Trump announced a 10%
tariff on Canadian energy imports and a 25
% tariff on other Canadian goods.
In retaliation, Canada imposed a 25% tariff
on American imports.
Then in March, Ontario implemented a 25%
surcharge on electricity exports to the US, affecting
states like New York, Michigan and Minnesota.
However, in my opinion, this was more of
a symbolic move that wouldn't have seriously damaged
the US economy.
However, Trump didn't hold back and instead of
just brushing it off, he fired back by
increasing tariffs on Canadian steel and aluminium to
50%.
Unlike Canada's move, this wasn't just for show,
it hit Canada's manufacturing industry hard while also
driving up steel prices for American businesses that
rely on imports.
But why am I telling you all this?
Well this is where the real problem starts.
Tariffs sound good on paper as they're meant
to punish foreign businesses while encouraging more stuff
to be made in America, but in reality
they end up hurting regular people more than
anyone else.
As a business owner who manufactures products and
imports from China myself, I know that when
businesses are forced to pay more for materials,
they don't just absorb the cost, they pass
it on to their customers.
That means higher prices on cars, appliances and
electronics.
In addition to this, food becomes more expensive
because supply chains get disrupted, meaning that everyday
essentials cost more, stretching household budgets even further.
On top of that, other countries aren't just
sitting around while Trump raises tariffs, they are
forming new alliances to trade without the US.
China is leading the charge with the BRICS
alliance, partnering with Brazil, Russia, India and South
Africa to reduce dependence on American trade.
So the more the US isolates itself, the
more other countries look elsewhere for business.
So what's my opinion on all of this
as an experienced investor?
Well if Trump goes all in on this
trade war, history suggests it will do more
harm than good.
While some industries might get a short term
boost, the long term damage, such as higher
prices, weaker global ties and a slowing US
economy could far outweigh any benefits.
But if I'm being completely honest, I don't
think Trump actually wants high tariffs, I know
that sounds crazy but hear me out.
Trump is, at his core, a businessman and
a deal maker, just like me.
That's why I believe he's using tariffs as
a negotiation tactic, not as an end goal.
So if that's true, what does he actually
want?
Well I think he's after free global trade,
but on terms that favour the US, and
if he pulls that off, it could pay
off big time.
However the problem is, his approach is creating
massive uncertainty.
The constant backtracking, new tariffs and mixed signals
are spooking the stock market because investors hate
unpredictability.
If this drags on too long, it could
shake confidence so much that it pushes the
economy towards recession, something even Trump's own administration
has admitted they're willing to risk.
Right now, the market isn't just reacting to
tariffs, it's reacting to uncertainty about what comes
next, and in investing, uncertainty is one of
the biggest killers of confidence.
Trigger two is Trump's stance on NATO.
Trump has openly questioned the role of NATO,
the military alliance that protects western countries.
He's suggested that the US shouldn't keep defending
allies unless they start paying more for their
own protection.
While that might sound like a fair demand,
if the US steps back from its NATO
commitments, it could create a power vacuum that
countries like Russia and China might exploit.
Markets hate uncertainty.
The second investors sense that world stability is
at risk, they panic.
If NATO weakens, it could encourage Russia to
push further into Europe, or even lead to
new conflicts as countries try to adjust to
a world without the USA acting as the
global police force.
More conflicts mean higher military spend unpredictable trade
relationships, and spikes in energy prices, all of
which can rattle the stock market.
Trigger three is Trump's secret plan.
There's been a theory circulating that Trump may
be crashing the stock market on purpose.
I know that sounds crazy, but there is
some evidence for it.
Trump has never been a fan of high
interest rates.
In fact, he's called them ridiculous and has
openly attacked the Federal Reserve for keeping them
high.
Now here's where it gets interesting.
The Fed is technically independent, meaning Trump can't
just tell them to cut interest rates, but
their decisions are based on economic conditions.
If the stock market crashes and a recession
seems inevitable, the Fed has no choice but
to step in and slash interest rates to
prevent a total meltdown.
But why does Trump want lower rates?
Well, because high interest rates slow down the
economy.
Businesses borrow less, stocks struggle, people stop spending
as much, and for Trump, who loves growth
and hates anything that makes America look weak,
they're a problem.
It's not just about making the stock market
go up, it's way bigger than that.
The US government is drowning in $36.5
trillion of debt, and when interest rates are
high, the cost of that debt goes through
the roof.
Think of it like a massive credit card
bill.
Imagine you owe $36,500, and your credit
card company charges 10% interest per year.
That means, before you even start paying down
the actual debt, you're being charged $3,650
every single year just in interest.
Now imagine the credit card company suddenly slashes
the interest rate to 3%.
Instead of paying $3,650 per year, your
interest drops to just $1,095 annually.
That's a saving of $2,555 every single
year.
Now you can put this money towards actually
paying off your debt instead of just keeping
up with your interest payments.
Well, that's exactly what Trump might be doing,
but on a $36.5 trillion scale.
If the Fed lowers interest rates, the government
can refinance its debt at a cheaper rate,
saving billions, if not trillions, in interest payments.
This wouldn't be the first time something like
this has happened.
If Trump can create that opportunity on purpose,
it could go down as one of the
smartest economic power moves in history.
If this theory is true, we're not looking
at a long-term economic collapse, we're looking
at a temporary shake-up before a massive
rebound.
So you're probably wondering, how can you benefit
from this crash?
Well, you need to understand that stock market
crashes aren't rare disasters.
They're a normal part of investing.
Every few years, the stock market takes a
hit.
People panic and headlines scream, the end is
near.
But history tells us a different story.
Every crash of the US market has been
followed by a recovery.
The people who panic and sell usually lose
money, while the ones who stay calm and
invest strategically often come out on top.
Instead of freaking out, this is the time
to prepare, make smart moves, and hopefully set
yourself up for massive gains when the market
bounces back.
Look, I'm not a financial advisor.
However, I have made millions during stock market
crashes, so here are my thoughts on what
you can do to prepare.
Step one is to invest while the market
is down.
Before you even think about investing, you need
a rock-solid financial foundation.
I know I've said it before, but it's
worth repeating.
That means building an emergency fund of at
least three to six months worth of living
expenses, and eliminating any debt with an interest
rate above 8%.
Assuming you've done that, if you've never invested
before, this could be one of the best
times to start.
Stocks are essentially on sale.
During the 2008 financial crisis, I was still
investing at the bottom and saw my investments
double within a few years.
However, many of my friends panicked and sold,
locking in their losses and missing out on
the recovery.
No one can perfectly predict the exact bottom
of the market, but if you invest consistently
while prices are low, you'll be buying assets
at a discount.
If you want to get started, then Trading
212 are currently giving you a free fractional
share worth up to £100 when you use
the code Tilbury in the app and fund
your account.
If you've been waiting for a good time
to do this, then this could be it.
I'll leave a link in the description below
if you're interested.
Step two is to stay disciplined and think
long-term.
Market crashes aren't random, they follow predictable cycles.
There are three types of crashes.
Corrections, which is a 10-20% drop.
These happen frequently and are part of a
healthy market.
Bear markets, which is a 20-40%
drop.
These happen every few years and last about
289 days on average.
And fall collapses, which are more than 40
% drops.
These are rare, but have historically been followed
by huge recoveries in the USA.
The biggest mistake new investors make is letting
emotions dictate their decisions.
When stocks drop, fear kicks in and people
sell at a loss.
When stocks rise, greed takes over and then
they buy at inflated prices.
This cycle is why most people fail at
investing.
So if you're already investing, the worst mistake
you can make is panic selling.
Selling while the market is down locks in
your losses and keeps you from benefiting from
when stocks recover.
Instead, consider increasing your investments while stocks are
cheap.
Stick to a long-term strategy like dollar
cost averaging.
Invest in a fixed amount every month, no
matter what the market's doing.
This reduces the risk of buying in at
the wrong time and ensures you're steadily building
wealth.
Remember the best investors see downturns as a
chance to buy more.
Step three is to diversify your investments.
Putting all your money into one type of
investment is a recipe for disaster.
The key to surviving market crashes is diversification.
This means spreading your money across different types
of assets.
My portfolio includes stocks, bonds, precious metals like
gold, real estate, and even cryptocurrency.
It's also worth considering dividend paying stocks as
they actually perform well during downturns because they
generate passive income even when prices are low.
Just remember market crashes aren't the end of
the world.
If you understand how to navigate them, you
won't be the one panicking.
You'll be the one taking advantage of the
opportunities while everyone else is running for the
exit.
This isn't the time to fear the market.
It's the time to prepare, invest wisely, and
stay patient.
The ones who make the smartest moves now
will be the ones who come out on
top when the market rebounds.
If you want to know how to invest
in 2025, then I'm going to leave that
video right up there.
But don't click on it just yet.
Make sure to subscribe if you want to
grow your wealth, okay?
I'll see you over there.