The video you are about to watch is
going to be a comprehensive video all about
paper trading, including how it works, what it
is, and how to access it.
So we're going to cover all of these
key topics, and by the time you're done
with this video, you're going to be a
master at paper trading, see the value in
it, and use it for many different reasons
to get started in your journey in markets.
So let's go ahead and just get right
to it, which is, when you have a
chart open, just like this, you'll see that
at the bottom of the chart, there's a
button that says trading panel.
Go ahead and click that.
Now, once the trading panel is open, you
of course will see brokerages that are available
to you, and these are real brokerages.
They manage real money, and they are custodians,
or they're account managers, or anything related to
financial services.
You can connect to these brokerages and place
real trades from TradingView, but that's not the
point of this video.
The point of this video is paper trading,
and if you read the fine print here,
it says brokerage simulator by TradingView.
It's exactly what it sounds like.
It's a simulator.
It's essentially a video game for practice trading.
You get to play with real money to
test your strategies or whatever you know about
markets and see if it works.
So let's go ahead and click this.
You'll do the same.
Then you're going to click connect.
Now, once you're connected to paper trading, you'll
have this layout, and we're really going to
walk you through everything here.
So kick your feet up on your desk
or your chair, sit back and relax, because
we're really going to start from the very
beginning.
We're even going to close out this position
so that you literally see nothing here, and
we're going to walk through it step by
step.
Now, the first thing and most exciting part
of paper trading is placing actual trades.
So in this example, let's say we go
to Tesla, and we pull up a chart
of Tesla, and let's say we think we
are the next great Tesla trader.
Rather than risking real money, rather than just
going right in and potentially putting our hard
-earned money to work, let's first see if
we have what it takes to succeed.
So what we might do in this example,
actually, is notice that there is a gap
to fill.
Now, in markets, oftentimes, traders do watch gap
fills.
They sometimes say gaps act as magnets.
And in that sense, there's sort of this
space to fill before it gets up to
the most recent drop that occurred.
You can see the drop.
That's why there's a gap here.
Price closed on one day, and some sort
of news event, probably earnings happened, it opened
it that much lower the next day.
Now, if we want to play a trade
here and assume that Tesla will start from
here and maybe gingerly work its way up
to close this gap, why don't we go
long?
So there are a number of ways we
can do that.
But one of our favorite ways is to
right-click on the chart.
You can see here it says Trade.
Click Create New Order.
And now we've got our order ticket open
here, and we can place a trade directly
on the chart.
What's especially helpful is you can move this
order ticket as needed to any point on
the chart so that you have a view
for you.
Because obviously, if it's right in the center
and you have a different layout, you might
not see the actual price.
So in this example, we are going to
just do a market order because we want
to get you the basics of paper trading.
But as we go deeper, we'll show you
limit order, stops, buys, and sells.
But for now, we want to do a
market order, which means we're just going to
buy it at whatever price we can get
executed at.
So we have 50 units.
Let's click Buy.
And the order has been placed.
You can see the tickets here.
And now you can see positions are filled
as well.
So now we know our order was placed
and our order was executed.
And we can see that it was executed
at $193.07. So let's click Exit.
Let's click Exit.
And let's take a look here at our
position.
Now our position is on 50 shares of
Tesla.
This red numbering here is whether we're down
red or up green.
We are so far down $1.50, $1.
So it's a real-time calculation of how
we're doing on these 50 shares.
And in addition, you'll see a SL and
TP or a reverse position.
And the X here would close your position.
Before we talk about closing the position, let
us just show you something that's just absolutely
fantastic, which is you can add a stop
loss just by clicking, holding, and dragging.
So why don't we make our stop loss
the absolute lows of this recent move?
So once we let go of our mouse,
now a new ticket opens up.
And that new ticket is our stop loss.
We're going to see the ticks, the price,
the dollar, the percentage.
We're going to click Modify to ensure that
that stop loss is placed there.
So we click Modify.
And the stop loss has been placed.
So you'll see it's been placed.
It's not executed.
It's just a stop loss.
A stop loss will only be executed if
price, for example, were to suddenly drop all
the way down this low.
And if it hits those levels, we'll sell.
And what's especially effective is you can see
here how much we would lose on the
trade.
We would lose $911 if it went all
the way down to those levels.
Now you'll notice we did not talk about
TP yet.
That's take profit.
If we click and hold and move the
tick profit to the top here, we are
going to gain $756.
And once again, you can see the ticks,
price, dollar, percentage.
And now you can also view them side
by side.
So take profit, stop loss.
You now have a complete picture of the
bracket trade you're placing.
By the way, you just learned this is
a bracket trade because you can see the
brackets here.
Your entry, your take profit, your exit.
Now this probably isn't the greatest trade of
all time because you can actually see our
stop loss is greater than our potential profit.
These are things for you to think about.
So perhaps you might want to adjust this
trade.
It's just an example.
Everyone has different ways of calculating their trades.
But it is interesting to take note of.
And what's especially helpful is you can see
that data right away once your take profit
and stop loss are placed on the chart.
Now you can go ahead and wait to
see if that trade executes.
Obviously this could take several days, weeks, or
months to play out.
So we won't see it right away.
But you now know the basics of paper
trading.
Now that the trade is placed, let's move
our mouse down here to the paper trading
menu because we want to make sure you
understand what's going on here.
First of all, it says paper trading here.
You can click the drop down and you
can get some really important extra settings as
needed.
You can customize your summary row so you
can see account balance, equity, P&L.
Those are these numbers here.
Account balance, equity, P&L.
If you don't want to see one of
these, perhaps you don't want to see equity
because it feels redundant to you, you can
uncheck it and it hides or not.
Account balance, you'll probably always want to see
profit and loss as well so that you
can get a feel for what your profit
and loss is at any point in your
account balance also.
Did you know you can also export your
data as well?
See the brokers list will bring you right
back to the brokers menu that we showed
you with real brokers.
Logout will log you out of paper trading
entirely and take this whole view away from
you.
So let's not click that yet.
More importantly is trading settings.
This is a really, really important thing to
grasp because on trading view, really you have
the freedom and capabilities to create a trading
environment that's best for you.
So we showed you how to right click
on the chart and place a trade, but
did you know if you go to your
chart settings, which can also be accessed here,
the setting wheel, or right clicked and settings,
there is a button that says trading.
We go ahead and we click that and
you'll see here it says buy and sell
buttons.
So if we click buy and sell buttons,
you'll notice, watch this section here, see that?
So we uncheck it.
They're gone.
Check it.
They're there.
You can have these buy and sell buttons,
market orders up at all times to place
instant trades as well in paper trading.
So if you're watching and practicing, watching and
practicing, let's go to a one minute chart.
If we really want to see some live
trades.
Okay.
Maybe it's below we're in the red.
Let's add some.
We click buy.
We get the order ticket up.
Let's add five more to our position.
Click buy executed.
Okay.
We're down again.
We're down $5.
Let's get these order tickets.
Let's try to double dip on the one
minute.
This time let's add 10.
You can do this as well to really
see what's possible.
Trying to buy a dip, trying to place
a better trade or improve your position.
You can do that with these buttons.
Let's right click and go to settings.
We have trading selected.
You've also got some other things to pay
attention to, which are instant order placements, as
well as play sound for execution.
So if you want to hear noises play
when you actually execute each trade.
And additionally, what's incredibly important is your appearance.
You may not want all of the data
on your chart.
So open this settings menu and get familiar
with all the things you can see.
So you can see here, we have positions
checked off.
There's positions, profit and loss.
That's gone.
Now we definitely want to see profit and
loss.
We can also do percentage profit and loss,
which is particularly helpful.
If you're just trying to base what your
profit and loss is in percentage terms, not
necessarily money, maybe you don't need the reverse
button because if you accidentally click reverse.
So watch what happens here.
It instantly closes the trade and then flips
it around into a short position.
So we quite literally had a trade on
long.
We clicked one button.
We closed that long trade out and instantly
went short.
So that's a pretty advanced tool.
You may not want to see that and
you can hide that from your chart as
needed.
And that's what all of these boxes are
going to do.
When you have the trading tab here, clicked
really tons of customizations, go dive in to
learn exactly what works best for you.
But of course we are now down $4.
Let's close this trade as well.
That's another way you can close a position
and pay attention to the fact that you
can partially close trades, which once again just
demonstrates how many trading capabilities you have when
the paper trading tool is open.
So we typed in 35.
So we're going to close, you know, a
little more than than half of this position.
Click partially close executed.
We're so far down $2 since we started
this tutorial, but you know what?
Let's close it out entirely and start over
because we want to keep walking you through
each tool.
We really are getting the basics across to
you.
We can feel that, but there's more to
do here because now we're on a one
minute chart.
We're zoomed in and we're going to try
this again.
Okay.
So here's a chart of Tesla on a
one minute chart.
We have got an interesting level here that
we are going to mark.
It's this low here.
So this would be the low of the
day.
Essentially since this, no, since this run up,
it would be the low since the run
up the retrace.
So this will be our stop loss.
We're going to open up our paper trading
tool.
And what we're going to do now is
we are going to place another trade.
This time, we're just going to click the
trade button right here and open up our
trade panel on the right side of the
chart.
Once again, so many different ways for you
to practice trading, whether it's the buttons, whether
it's right clicking and finding trade, getting that
floating ticket, or just clicking the trade button
here to open up this panel, the choice
is yours.
And hopefully you are still sticking around in
this video so that you can do this
exact same thing yourself and find the best
possible layout for you.
Now, when you do have the order ticket
open, you'll notice that there is a depth
of market.
This is especially helpful if you have a
brokerage on TradingView that provides this level of
data, or if you have access to a
data plan that gives you this level of
data.
There is a video on our YouTube channel
about the DOM or depth of market.
We're going to stick to the order panel
because this video is all about paper trading.
We are now going to set up a
trade from scratch, showing you an exact way
you could think about this.
So recall we drew this horizontal line because
we feel like this low is significant.
Everyone's analysis is different.
This is just our observation on a one
-minute chart.
One-minute charts are never all that easy
to trade, but this is just for an
example.
Now, what we're going to do is we
want to do a limit order.
A limit order, first of all, means we
only want to get filled at a specific
price.
It's not a market order, which just buys
at any price.
If you do market, it will literally just
get you filled at any price whatsoever.
Limit order is us being a little picky.
How about we only want to get filled
if it goes to $193?
So let's do $192.99. So we want
10 shares at $192.99, and we were
already filled just like that.
We're on a minute chart.
It happened quite fast, and that is how
you can place your limit order.
Now, remember we have not added a stop
loss or take profit, which as we mentioned
is really up to you.
You can drag and let go of those
stop losses and take profits, or when you
have this order panel open, you can check
to add a take profit, check to add
a stop loss.
In this case, you can see this horizontal
line says $192.55. That's our stop loss.
So it says $187 here, but let's add
a stop loss that says $192.
Let's do $192.50, round number.
There's our stop loss.
It has been placed and it's on the
chart.
So that is a very important component of
getting your stop loss on the chart using
the order ticket.
Now, the reason why we did place our
stop loss at that point is we wanted
to give our horizontal line here a little
bit of wiggle room.
We don't want to place it right at
the line because sometimes price has a tendency
to sort of break through, sort of fake
everyone out and then snap back up.
So hopefully this stop loss is playing into
that a little bit.
So look at this, we're up a dollar.
One more thing now is we want to
add our take profit.
So we check the box and we've got
our take profit here.
This is just like the floating ticket option
as well.
You'll recall, so let's actually right click to
shut that.
Remember, we could go here to trade and
create new order and it will pop up
and we can do the exact same process
as we did before.
Or of course, we can hover our mouse
over and drag our take profit.
In this case, our take profit target, and
pretty cool how this all works and automatically
updates from there.
In this case, our take profit target is
going to be a little bit better than
the last example we were showing you because
we're going to use these prior highs all
the way back here, which looks like it
was Friday morning.
We're recording this video on Friday the 9th.
So let's go ahead and draw our take
profit all the way up here to these
prior highs.
In fact, let's actually play a little more
bearish though.
Maybe it gets into this zone here.
So we've got this zone that we're kind
of playing off of for our take profit.
So now we've got our bracket trade set
up.
Let's watch it in real time.
And while we watch it in real time
on this one minute chart, let's also just
keep in mind the importance of the data
that we also have available.
Okay.
So right now we have positions open.
This is going to show us our live
positions.
So as you can see, we have a
Tesla trade on.
You just watched us place this trade from
start to finish.
Side means long.
That means we are long.
You'll recall, and if you go backward, when
we clicked this reverse button to suddenly close
out and go short, this changed to short.
Quantity shows how many shares we have.
Currently we have 20 shares.
If we buy more shares, this number will
go up.
Average fill price.
This is a wonderful stat for you to
get familiar with as a trader in paper
trading because average fill price is essentially telling
you what your average entry price is.
If you're picky, meaning you only use limit
orders.
If you're picky, and for example, maybe you
want to double dip down and lower your
average fill price.
Maybe you see here $192.50. You can
actually type that in because you want to
make a second purchase to lower that.
Let's do five more units.
Limit $192.50. Click buy.
Now we've got another buy order on the
chart as well in the hopes of lowering
this average fill price.
The point is that you can do things
just like this by paying attention to the
stats.
Take profit.
That's the exact thing you see here.
Remember, we drag this up to that level.
Stop loss.
That's what you see right here.
Remember, we drag this up to the level.
The last price is a real-time countdown
of the price right now and our profit
and loss.
Lastly, you're going to see this column set
up.
This really feeds into a key component about
the TradingView paper trading tool, which is what
we've been explaining almost since the start, and
all the customizations you have to make a
trading desktop look and feel that fits you
perfectly.
If you'd like to actually hide some of
these columns, maybe you find it to be
too noisy.
Maybe you literally only want to see quantity,
average fill price, and profit and loss.
You can simplify it to that degree.
Choice is yours.
Next up is orders.
Orders is going to be a very important
tool for those who are very meticulous in
tracking their trading history, everything that they've done
in the paper trading process.
This is where you can quickly see every
trade that you have placed.
Positions, these are live trades.
These are trades that are on.
They are positions that could be happening at
this moment.
Orders are every order that you've placed, whether
they've been filled, canceled, sold, anything of the
sort.
You can see here it says working.
That's because, remember, we just placed that limit
order to buy five more shares.
It's working.
It's waiting.
It's out there.
It's happening.
You can even sort all of these orders
by the specific category here to see how
many orders were filled, canceled, rejected.
This gives you more granular data into your
entire workflow as you get started.
History is especially powerful because history will track
your account all through time.
In fact, you'll see here we placed some
Apple trades, but you weren't watching the video
when we placed these.
But in the history section, we can go
that far back in time to see all
of these trades, the filled trades, canceled trades,
and rejected trades.
In addition, you have your account history.
This way you can get another look at
your account history, but not so much from
the positions that you have.
History, positions, orders are the orders you're placing,
positions are the positions you have on.
But account history more so in terms of
look at the balance.
You can actually track the balance of the
account and what trades played a role in
that balance and the details into that balance
change or the trade that moved the balance.
These are very, very important aspects to understand.
Lastly, we'll talk about the trading journal.
The trading journal is an especially detailed look
at your orders.
One common theme you'll notice about all of
this data that you can gather about your
paper trading journey is that most of them
feed into the positions that you have on,
the orders that have been executed, the history
throughout your account, your account's history and its
balance before and after.
The trading journal is a way for you
to actually look into the orders that were
successfully placed, canceled, modified, confirmed.
All of that good stuff is right here.
For many advanced traders, and the new traders
will find this interesting, sometimes this is some
of the most important information to gather because
you want to know what your entry was.
Did the trade go through?
Did it not go through?
Why did it not go through?
This is where you can really track that
process.
We've now given you the basics of paper
trading.
Our trade is still on at this very
moment and there are a final few key
details for you to pay attention to as
you watch this video.
That is the fact that you have your
account here, so TradingView USD account, and you
can create new accounts as needed.
This is key because not everyone has just
one brokerage account.
Some people have multiple brokerage accounts or multiple
portfolios.
This account is just called TradingView, but if
we wanted to start a fresh new account
and manage two different accounts at the same
time, we would call this paper trading account
number two.
We can set our starting balance.
Let's just start it at $100.
We don't want commission, actually, and let's click
create, and the account did not create.
Good reminder here, you can't have this number
in here, so let's delete that and click
create.
Oops, we still have the number.
Click create, and that's because of the, okay,
paper trading.
There we go, and now we're good to
go.
You just learned another important lesson there as
well, don't add the spaces, don't add the
numbers, just get it straight in there, one
straight shot.
Now we've got paper trading account and TradingView,
it's got $100.
Now we can bounce between our two accounts
as needed.
In addition, what's quite important here is the
account settings menu.
This, of course, is where you can choose
to include commission or reset the account.
We do not want to reset the account
at this point, but if you ever need
to start fresh, maybe your account's gotten a
little too messy, your account balance is messed
up, click reset account and start over from
scratch.
So ladies and gentlemen, that is paper trading.
It's a full walkthrough of the paper trading
process on TradingView.
You learned how to create bracket orders, how
to create market orders, you watched us place
a limit order, you saw us place stop
losses, you saw us place take profits and
stop losses at the same time, we even
reversed a trade and went from long to
short in a matter of seconds, we've been
watching this real-time trade the entire time,
and we walked you through the entire TradingView
panel here at the bottom of the chart
so that you know exactly what you're looking
at and all of the data that's before
you.
Now, as we wrap up this video, we
just want to make sure that you walk
away as well, especially for the new traders
out there, with some important details.
Paper trading is an effective way for you
to practice, practice, practice.
Right now, we've been placing trades on Tesla,
but you can do this across different asset
classes and place more than one practice trade
at a time.
For example, we have Bitcoin open here, let's
go ahead and place another order, and let's
actually do a market order, let's buy 10
Bitcoins.
Our take profit, this is still a one
-minute chart, so let's do our take profit
is right here at the high of this
green one-minute candle, looks like it's about
$47,800, let's do $47,800, and then
let's add a stop loss, which would be
the bottom of this wick here, which would
be $47,800.
Okay, so this is actually $47,800, let's
do $47,900, this is $47,800, and
now let's hit buy, let's make it happen,
the trade's been executed, we just placed another
bracket trade, and the reason for doing that
is as we were wrapping up our show,
we wanted to make sure you know, you
can manage multiple positions at once as well,
and as you click through each chart, it'll
load, our Bitcoin trade that we just placed
has already executed, looks like we lost money
on that, you can see here we had
that entry and we got stopped out rather
quickly, and even that took our whole account
into the red, we're now down 60 cents
just in this short period of time, but
we did demonstrate how you can manage multiple
positions at once, because if you think you
have what it takes to be an excellent
trader, this paper trading tool unlocks all of
that for you, you can place real trades,
practice your trades, work on bracket orders, and
do it across different asset classes, you saw
I went from Bitcoin to Tesla, we could
even go to Forex, here's EURUSD, we could
just place a market order, let's go ahead
and just buy 50, click buy, and now
we've got your USD as well, so you
can manage a portfolio as well, it does
not have to be just paper trading, so
before you risk your hard-earned money, before
you dive into markets, go see if you
have what it takes first to manage a
paper trading account into a profitable standpoint, that
is a great way to get started in
markets, as we mentioned, it's entirely free, and
we walked you through the entire journey here,
start to finish, from the most advanced concepts,
to the most basic concepts, and even the
settings process of making sure that you set
up a chart using this trading tab that
works for you, because as mentioned, we added
these buy buttons up here too, gives us
access to this order panel in a matter
of clicks, so thanks so much for watching,
we hope this video helps you get started.