People might wonder what does the work involve
once you have your algos?
Because you do for sure a lot of
testing, optimization and stuff, but what else do
you have to do on a daily basis
as a systems or algo trader?
Yeah, so I'm actually the guy who doesn't
do any optimization, doesn't do any backtesting.
I don't believe in any of it.
If backtests were great, how many guys do
you know who have beautiful backtests?
I know a million guys have shown me
beautiful backtests the moment they go.
If the backtests worked, we'd all be billionaires
because there's a billion backtests that all look
beautiful, and yet nobody has ever made money
on a backtest, because the market is, you
don't trade history, you trade the future.
So my view is what I want is
a general concept of a system.
And then it has to be obviously, don't
get me wrong, it's not that I don't
at all backtest, but in the backtest, what
I wanted to show me is that it's
not a complete failure.
It makes some sense.
It does have a small edge.
And generally, by the way, a 60-40
edge is about as good as you're ever
going to get, right?
So if I get a 60-40 edge,
I'm super happy, right?
One to one, or two to one?
Yeah, one to one.
And the other big myth is trading two
to one.
You trade three to one, markets do not
give you free dollar bills, and so you
do the odds of how well you're going
to do.
I mean, I actually do this little test.
You take just any daily chart on any
currency pair, and you say, okay, I'm going
to do a five pip stop and a
20 pip target, right?
And how many winning trades are you going
to get?
Pretty much zero, zero.
Now, do it the other way.
I'm going to do a five pip target
and a 20 pip stop, which is a
horrible risk-reward ratio.
I'm not advocating this.
It's just simply to show people how stupid
the ideas are.
And you do that, all of a sudden,
all your trades become winners.
Now, of course, you're going to hit losers
down the road.
They're going to give back all the money
if you have that risk-reward ratio.
But the point is, on an average day,
the one to four ratio is a much
better ratio than a four to one ratio.
So my view is that the best you
can do is even money bets with a
60-40 edge.
You can get anywhere close to that.
You are way ahead of almost everybody around.
So my process is actually, let's create something
that makes modest amount of sense.
Let's trade it live.
I always trade it live in live markets,
because the other thing is, backtests always lie.
Let me explain to you what I mean
by they lie.
They lie about where the prices are, where
the execution is possible.
You think you could have gotten like an
end-of-candle-perfect entry yesterday in dollar
-yen at whatever the backtest told you?
It would have been 200 pips.
So backtests always, always lie.
So I always like to trade it in
real market conditions, but with a small amount
of money.
I'm always trading small amounts of money.
Let's put the little reconnaissance soldiers out there.
See how well this trades.
You're going to learn so much more.
All your assumptions are going to be completely
upturned once the market goes live.
You begin to understand where's the volatility envelope.
We know what currency pairs are actually responsive
to your ideas, which are not.
And that's really where a lot of the
true work goes.
All my work is in front testing.
Not even front testing, but front trading.
I don't believe in the word testing.
I believe in the word trading.
So it's experience-based.
All of my strategies are experience-based.
And that's how, out of experience, you refine
the rules, increase size, and create something that's
tangible.
That's my personal process of how I do
it.
That's a really good process.
And how long is that front trading phase?
Does that last like a long time?
The rule of thumb is you got to
have at least, if you're day trading, you
got to have about 100 trades just to
have an idea of what the hell you're
doing.
Whatever your assumptions are, if you don't have
100 trades, it's not even a legitimate sample
size.
So it takes a couple of months to
babysit a strategy into a decent idea.
And remember, the whole point is, it's an
evolving organism.
So the three myths I hate is positive
risk-reward ratio, right?
Back testing is a must.
And the other big myth I hate is
set it and forget it.
If you're a systems trader, it's a set
it and forget it.
I don't do anything.
Nonsense.
You do a ton.
There's nothing ever is a set it and
forget it.
Do you think the NASA space probe is
a set it and forget it?
They just press a button, let the whole
thing go?
No, they're constantly monitoring the spaceship, and they're
constantly adjusting to market conditions.
Market conditions are just like weather conditions.
They change all the time.
There is no such thing as a static
life, right?
Yesterday is not tomorrow.
And tomorrow is not today.
You have to adjust and watch.
It's just a higher level of management.
But management is very much involved.
I don't believe in this whole let your
strategy go.
You want to evaluate your strategy.
And I evaluate my strategy almost every single
day on what's going on.
I don't necessarily change it every day.
Of course, I don't change it every day.
But I evaluate it every single day.
So you have to be involved just at
a higher level.
Yeah.
And I guess one of the temptation of
people when they have an alcohol, like when
they treat manually, is that they might say,
well, the alcohol is not working anymore.
It's like the results are bad.
Sometimes they stop it.
So how can you go back and review
the alcohol?
Is it like every month, every quarter or?
Just a question.
What does it mean when it's not working?
Right.
Like the people go, you're losing money.
That's that's that's.
So I'm losing money.
It's not working.
No, that's not the same thing.
Losing money and it not working is not
the same thing.
And that's where I think a lot of
people make the mistake.
That's a very, very common, I think, rookie
retail mistake.
Understand what's going on.
Maybe it's not working because the regime has
completely changed.
Like what is the algo supposed to do?
What is it?
What is it supposed to be working?
Right.
And also, I think a lot of times
people have to be much more nuanced about
what does it mean to be working?
Like, for example.
My algo doesn't work very well on dollar
Swiss.
Right.
But it works beautifully on euro dollar.
Why?
Well, because because the volatility signature of the
two pairs is quite different.
And also liquidity, you know, liquidity characters are
completely different.
So just because it's not working on one
thing doesn't mean it's a it's a it's
a not successful algo.
What your job is to find out where
it is working.
Right.
I guess that's kind of the key thing.
My constant process is to figure out as
many possible instruments on which this is working
as much as possible.
That's what I'm doing constantly.
I'm searching, you know, and and then when
you have that kind of attitude, it makes
a lot easier because you're not as you
know, you're not as deterministic, you know, like,
oh, you know, forget it.
I'm leaving it, you know, and I'm never
going to trade it again.
And then all the guys in my room
who are much more intelligent, much more patient
than I am, like keep on trading and
then come back to me.
I said, hey, you know what?
I made 2000 pips from that algo that
you gave me.
I'm like, what are you kidding me?
Are you kidding me?
And that was that was that was kind
of an eye opening lesson to me that
that it's not the strategy.
It's you.
You know, it's like, you know, it's not
it's not it's not you.
It's me.
Every trader should always look at themselves as
the point of failure, not at their strategy,
because usually that's always that's always the much
truthful point of view.
You have to be kind of much more
honest with what's going on over there.
And.