Renaissance Technologies is the most profitable hedge fund
in history.
This is probably the single most successful hedge
fund in the history of the industry in
terms of its performance record.
So you got to remember he charges a
lot, but before fees 66% on average
since 1988.
Behind the firm's wild success are a series
of mathematical models and powerful computers.
The quantitative models at Renaissance Technologies are constantly
being updated, but what's more important than those
models are the ways and methods that are
used to discover trading signals.
Jim Simons, the founder of Renaissance Technologies, is
a legendary mathematician.
He pioneered a unique way of research and
model building to the world of hedge funds.
He's worth $21 billion, making him the highest
earning hedge fund manager in the world.
Born and raised in Brookline, Massachusetts, Jim Simons
always knew that he wanted to be a
mathematician.
We used to go to a delicatessen late
at night when I was a student.
And one day I saw Ambrose and Singer
come in late at night and they were
obviously doing mathematics.
And I saw this on a number of
occasions and I thought, boy, that's the greatest
job in the world where you can just
hang out at a delicatessen and do mathematics.
Simons enrolled at MIT and even skipped the
first year of mathematics thanks to advanced placement
courses he took in high school.
Simons' academic career was very smooth and after
earning his PhD, he quickly became a professor
of math and also took a job as
a Cold War codebreaker.
But he yearns for more, particularly more money.
Growing up in a middle class family, Simons
always wanted to get rich.
Unlike other people in the academics who don't
really care about money, Simons, on the other
hand, knew exactly how to make money.
Start businesses.
While still at school, he started a business
with his South American classmates.
They decided to start a factory to produce
vinyl floor tile and PVC piping.
Well, I met some, I made friends at
MIT with two Colombian boys and they, at
a certain point, started a business.
And in fact, it was my encouragement that
they started that business.
And my father and I invested a small
amount in that business, which turned out eventually
to be a big success.
This is a story of Jim Simons that
a lot of people don't hear about.
So he took some time off to run
a business at first, but as soon as
the business takes off, he immediately delegated responsibilities
to other people.
And we saw that time and time again
with the story of Rentag.
But Simons had to focus on his academic
career.
In 1976, at the age of 37, Simons
was awarded the American Mathematical Society's Oswald Weibullin
Prize in Geometry.
This prize is the highest you can get
in mathematics.
It's the equivalence of Nobel Prize.
Conquering one summit, Simons was looking for a
new mountain to climb.
In 1974, the floor tile company Simons had
started with his friends, sold a 50%
stake, delivering profits to Simons and other owners.
Simons and his classmates made a lot of
money from this business.
He said, let's invest in the money.
So Simons knew a student of his who
was running a hedge fund by the name
of Charlie Fretfeld.
Superseding Simons' wildest expectations, he 10X'd their original
investment, making them $6 million total.
This is the moment Simons realizes the best
way to make money is with finance.
He was wondering, can I do the same?
In 1978, Simons left academia to start his
own investment firm with the money he saved
and from his friends.
He started MoneyMetrics.
For years after starting MoneyMetrics, Simons relied on
intuition and fundamentals to trade.
It was a great time to be in
finance.
The fund is doing so well, he didn't
really have to change his approach.
But in the beggar's mind, he was wondering,
can he use the mathematics to model asset
prices?
But Simons was getting tired of the fundamental
trading.
We did very well.
But it was a gut-wrenching experience.
You know, it's, you know, one day you
walk in and you think you're a genius.
Oh, my positions are my way.
Look, and the next day you walk in
and they're against you and you feel you're
a dope.
How could I have done what I did?
And so there was no rhyme or reason.
It was just, you know, you put your
finger in the air and you try to
sense which way the wind is blowing.
Simons quickly started working on his first model
with the help of his colleague, Lenny Baum.
They built a simple mean reversion model.
Buy currencies if they moved a certain level
below their recent trend line and sell if
they veer too far above it.
The idea of mean reversion is very simple.
Suppose you're a farmer and the average price
of corn is five dollars a bushel.
Now, some days it may be six dollars
a bushel, other days it may be three
dollars a bushel.
But in the long run, these prices will
revert back to the mean value.
This is what's called mean reversion.
Back in the 80s, many commodities were priced
like this.
Now, his model would not work today, but
back in the 80s, this was a revolutionary
idea.
They quickly expanded the strategy beyond currency trading.
By 1982, he changed the company's name to
Renaissance Technologies.
But soon enough, their simple mean reversion strategy
started to fail.
Simple mean reversion is not sufficient anymore as
other competitors started to build their models.
To stay ahead of the game, Simons had
to hire more talents.
This is what really separates Jim Simons apart
from other hedge fund managers.
When he sees a problem, he knows exactly
who will be able to solve it.
He immediately brought another renowned mathematician, Jim X,
to develop a new strategy.
When Jim X looked at those asset prices,
he noticed that it is a stochastic process,
which is also called a random process.
And he believed that using mathematical representation is
the best way to model those stochastic process.
When people hear about the word random, they
think that it's not predictable.
But that's not the case in mathematics.
Suppose you threw a dice, and you know
each side will come up with a probability,
and you can bet on those probabilities.
To model a stochastic process, they started using
machine learning.
Machine learning is such a buzzword today.
But in the 1980s, most of hedge fund
managers don't even know what that means.
And they still use their gut to trade.
But here's Renison Technologies, ahead of everybody else,
already started to use machine learning.
The style of machine learning that Renton used
was the kernel method.
The kernel used a class of algorithms to
do pattern analysis.
The main tool used in academic finance is
linear regression.
To this day, linear regression is used to
build forecasting models.
But the problem is the movement of asset
prices is non-linear.
So rather than use linear regression, Rentek decided
to build non-linear models to predict price
movements.
Simons at the time was proposing building an
early machine learning system.
This model would generate predictions for various commodity
prices based on complex patterns, clusters, and correlations
that would be very hard for the naked
eye to see.
Once again, they were so ahead of their
time.
This kernel was like a black box that
suggested trades that people couldn't even understand.
When the team started testing the model, they
quickly see great returns.
The firm began incorporating hard dimensional kernel regression
approaches.
Higher dimensional kernels work best for trending models.
They're great at predicting how long a trend
will last.
At this point, Simons had put up millions
to this automated trading system.
They call it the Medallion Fund.
But Simons sought more potential improvement.
He started investing heavily in bringing more mathematical
talents.
With the GEM-X model, Renaissance Technologies started
to combine trend following with mean reversion.
The model has generated about 20% annual
returns, which is a great performance considering most
of the hedge funds made less than 12%.
But Simons wanted better.
He brought on another brilliant mathematician, Alan Berlekamp.
Alan Berlekamp's specialty was game and information theory.
He immediately suggested to focus on shorter term
trades to reduce risk by going in and
out quickly.
Simons took his advice and started focusing on
shorter term approach.
They do a very different approach.
It's all patterns, it's all short term, it's
not high frequency, but it's something very distinct
from what everybody else is doing.
Now Berlekamp became fully in charge of the
Medallion Fund.
He started fully implementing his ideas.
He argued they should learn to handle trades
like casinos.
A casino doesn't care about any particular bet.
Even if you win like 10 times, a
casino is happy because it knows that in
the long run, the casino has the statistical
advantage.
This is what's called the law of large
numbers.
I think what Rentec adopted was the Kelly
Criterion.
This is what we call the scientific gambling
method.
To put it simply, your bet should be
proportional to how confident you are in your
bet.
The formula is your expected net winnings divided
by your net winnings if you win.
I think this is actually the secret sauce
for Renaissance Technologies.
They utilize massive compute power combined with the
scientific approach and to discover trading patterns and
validate them and trade based on them.
They keep collecting the patterns and anomalies and
that's how they stay ahead of the game.
Well, any one anomaly might be a random
thing.
However, if you have enough data, you can
tell that it's not.
So you can see an anomaly that's persisted
for a sufficiently long time.
So the probability of it being random is
not high.
But these things fade after a while.
Anomalies can get washed out.
So you have to keep on top of
this.
The firm implemented its new approach in late
1989 with a $27 million Simon's have put
up.
The results were almost immediate and startling.
They did more trading than ever, cutting Medallion's
average holding time to just a day and
a half and from a week and a
half scoring profits almost every day.
The Medallion scored a gain of 55.9
% in 1990.
The incredible streak has begun.
Simon's personal wealth soared.
He's never hesitant to pay his employee a
lot of money.
So Jim Simons bought a yacht and every
year he would bring his employees on his
yacht to all the luxurious places in the
world you can imagine.
Simon's wanted to have more money to make
real changes to the world.
He needed to expand his hedge fund business
even more.
The only way to do that was getting
into the equity business.
So far, the Medallion fund has been very
successful at trading commodities, but it was capped
at $10 billion till this day.
So when a hedge fund gets big, every
trade it makes, it gets bigger.
So when we have a big trade like
that, it takes a long time for it
to execute in the marketplace.
Suppose you're trying to buy 10 million shares
of Apple.
It's going to take a while for the
market to fill that order.
And by the time the orders are filled,
you might not actually get the price you
originally planned.
And Warren Buffett is having the same problem.
That's why he's saying that he's looking for
elephants now because the amount of stocks that
he can have are so few nowadays.
They created a similar model to trade equities,
but it fails to deliver great returns.
Simon's again knew exactly what to do.
He hired two top scientists from IBM and
started tasking them with creating equity models.
Peter Brown and Robert Mercer were experts in
natural language processing.
It took them more than two years to
solve this problem while their equity models kept
losing money.
They discovered the reason why the mean reversion
models don't perform as well is due to
the execution of the trade.
Their equity models were great at picking out
best correctly, but they were too unrealistic with
the execution of those trades, such as market
impact and slippage.
So if you trade any stocks, you immediately
realize that you do not get the market
price all the time.
This is the problem with the academia.
So whatever paper you read, they always assume
that you can get the market price.
But the market is a group of buyers
and sellers constantly negotiating prices.
And if you participate in that market, you
do not always get the market price.
Brown and Mercer realized that their strategy needs
to model this aspect as well.
And minimize the trading cost.
Once they solved the problem, Rentek has entered
into a new age.
Jim Simons went on a capital raise roadshow
and expanded its asset under management to the
next level.
By 2000, the firm was managing $6 billion
with 140 employees.
And the rest is history.
By 2020, Simons retired from Rentek.
That year he made over $1 billion.
What really separates Jim Simons apart is his
ability to hire talents and to create an
environment that the smartest people in the world
utilize the maximum potential.
And more importantly, Jim Simons insisted on using
the scientific method to discover patterns and anomalies,
instead of using the gut intuition.
It's an open atmosphere.
Everybody knows what everybody else is doing.
And every week there's a research meeting.
If you've had a good idea that you
think it's going to go somewhere, you present
it.
If it looks good, it goes to a
small meeting.
People vet it more carefully.
But there aren't little groups working in the
dark.
Oh, this is my little system, and I
want you to use it.
And that's the best way to do science,
I think.
Since Simons left the firm, Rentek has still
been beating the market consistently.
The fund is so successful, almost to a
mythical level.
But as we now see, there is no
mystery.
Behind the firm's success is Jim Simons' ability
to gather talents, and also his will to
succeed.
Don't give up.
Now, sometimes, discretion is the better part of
valor, and you can just say to hell
with it.
But, and go on to something else, and
that's a decision we've all made at one
time or another.
But persistence has a lot of value, and
something that's really worthwhile can take a lot
of time to come to fruition, and you
ought to have patience if you believe in
something.