There are so many different options strategies out
there that are available to you as an
options trader, but today's video is incredibly important
because we will be focusing on arguably the
four most powerful options trading strategies that you
can trade as an options trader.
And let me just tell you, if you
can master your understanding of these four vertical
spread strategies today, you will make a massive
leap forward in your options trading expertise and
knowledge.
And that's because if you understand these four
vertical spread strategies, you will essentially understand 80
% of the options strategies in existence.
Specifically, I'm going to teach you these four
strategies using numerous examples and trade performance illustrations
so that you can fully understand how these
strategies perform relative to changes in the stock
price and the passage of time.
Before we get started, I should note that
there are prerequisites for this video.
This is considered, at least in my opinion,
the second installment of my options trading for
beginners ultimate guide.
And I'm going to assume in this video
that you have an understanding of how buying
call options and put options works, how shorting
call options and put options works, and I
will also be assuming that you understand what
intrinsic and extrinsic value are.
Without further ado, let's get started.
So today's video is all about vertical spreads,
but what exactly is a vertical spread?
A vertical spread is the combination of two
options trades that are placed simultaneously.
The first trade is purchasing a call or
put option at a strike price, and then
the second component of a vertical spread is
shorting another call or put option at a
different strike price.
Now, you'll be using either calls or puts.
As a quick example of a vertical spread,
let's look at a vertical spread setup in
Apple.
In this image, we can see a call
vertical spread that I've queued up in Apple
by purchasing the $140 call option and shorting
the $150 call option.
This is an example of a vertical spread
because I am purchasing a call option at
one strike price and shorting another call option
at a higher strike price.
Now, this is called a vertical spread because
you're trading two different options at different strike
prices within the same expiration, and the strike
prices are listed vertically on the option chain,
so you're basically creating a spread vertically when
you're looking at it on the option chain.
At least that's how I interpret it.
But why would somebody want to trade this
vertical spread as opposed to simply purchasing that
$140 call all by itself?
Let me go through a real quick demonstration
by hopping over to my brokerage platform, which
is Tastyworks.
And by the way, if you are in
need of a brokerage account and you're interested
in Tastyworks, please check out the links down
in the description below, and you'll learn how
you can get my exclusive S&P 500
options trading course when you open and fund
your first Tastyworks account using the project option
referral code.
And look, I don't make money on this
channel by having you pay me out of
pocket, and by using that referral code and
opening a Tastyworks account, if you are interested,
it's a phenomenal way to support me and
the channel, and that's how I prefer to
make my money, through things that don't cost
you anything and that actually connect you with
things that are valuable to you.
So go ahead and check out those links
in the description if you are interested.
So let's check out this trade right now.
So I'm going to look at Apple, and
right now, Apple is down about $7 today,
with the stock price around $124.
So let's go ahead and look at a
$120 call purchase in the October expiration cycle.
If I wanted to buy the $120 call
option in Apple today, it's currently listed at
a price of about $11.60, and with
that, I would have to basically put up
$1,160 to enter this call option position.
But what if I didn't want to spend
so much money on this call option, but
I still wanted to have a trade that
would make money when the stock price increased?
And let's say I thought Apple might increase
to $130 over the next 43 days.
Instead of just purchasing this $120 call option,
I could also short the $130 call option,
and by doing so, I reduce the cost
of my trade from around $1,100 to
$435.
Now this not only reduces my risk, but
it reduces my breakeven price as well.
So the breakeven price for this vertical spread
here would be $124.35, which essentially means
I only need Apple to be at $124
.35 at expiration for this spread to not
make or lose any money.
But if I were to just purchase that
$120 call option for $11.40, then my
breakeven price would be $130.40. So by
doing a vertical spread trade, you can actually
reduce your risk, and you can make it
a higher probability trade that you can make
money on because your breakeven price will be
much more favorable as opposed to simply buying
that call or put outright.
So now that we've briefly touched on what
a vertical spread is and why somebody would
want to trade one as opposed to simply
trading an option by itself, let's look at
the four vertical spread strategies in depth so
that you can fully understand each of these
four strategies, and then we'll move on to
the more important and exciting topics, in my
opinion.
Now I will warn you, this is going
to be a fairly repetitive and lengthy section
of the video.
So by all means, if you want to
skip ahead because you're starting to grasp the
strategies very quickly, and you want to go
to the more unique and exciting topics near
the end of the video, please feel free
to do so.
And you can look at the playhead on
the video, which is sectioned out, or you
can go to the video description and click
on the timestamps to access various sections of
this video.
By the way, if you are enjoying this
video thus far and you like what you
see, please give this video a thumbs up
and hit that like button down below.
And if you're new to the channel and
you have no idea who I am, please
consider checking out some other videos on my
channel and consider subscribing.
The first of the four vertical spread strategies
we will cover today is called the bull
call spread.
Now as the name suggests, the bull call
spread is a bullish options trading strategy that
is constructed using call options.
The bull call spread is constructed by purchasing
a call option at one strike price and
simultaneously shorting another call option at a higher
strike price.
Sometimes the bull call spread is referred to
as simply buying a call spread or a
call debit spread.
So these vertical spreads have many different names
and it depends on the trader you're talking
to, so you'll just have to familiarize yourself
with the various names of these spreads with
experience.
So we're going to look at a real
historical bull call spread, and we're going to
see how the trade performed over time relative
to changes in the stock price.
So let's check out the characteristics of this
bull call spread example.
The stock price at entry is $142.28,
and to construct this call spread, we're going
to buy the $1.35 call for $9
.30, and we're going to short the $1
.50 call for $1.54. Both of these
call options are in the 46-day expiration
cycle.
The purchase price of this spread is $7
.76, which comes from the fact that I
bought the $1.35 call for $9.30
and shorted the $1.50 call for $1
.54, bringing my net payment for this spread
to $7.76. Now, this means I actually
need $776 to purchase this spread because we
need to multiply that spread's price by the
option contract multiplier of 100, and that's something
you will have learned in the options trading
for beginners video.
The breakeven price for this spread at expiration
is $142.76, and that comes from the
call strike price of $1.35 plus the
entry price of $7.76. Now, I just
did a video explaining breakeven prices in depth,
so if you are unfamiliar with how breakeven
prices are calculated or why they make sense,
be sure to check out that video in
the description on how to get any strategy's
breakeven price at expiration.
So before visualizing the performance of this trade
through time, let's actually look at the risk
profile for this position at expiration so we
can understand at expiration what the profits and
losses will be for this position based on
various stock price scenarios.
The first thing to know is that this
strategy has limited risk, and the most the
strategy can lose, as described earlier, is the
entry price or entry cost of $776.
So if I buy this spread for $7
.76 and it expires worthless, my loss will
be $776.
And that will occur if the stock price
is at or below $135 at expiration, because
if the stock price is at or below
$135, the $135 call and the $150 call
will both expire worthless, and therefore the spread
itself will be worthless.
The breakeven price of this call spread is
$142.76 at expiration, and that means if
the stock price is at $142.76 at
expiration, the $135 call option will have intrinsic
value of $7.76, but the short $150
call will have $0 of intrinsic value, and
therefore the net value of the spread would
be $7.76, which is the same as
the entry cost.
And therefore, the position will not have a
profit or loss if the stock price is
exactly at $142.76 at the time of
expiration.
And lastly, the maximum profit potential of $724
will occur if the stock price is at
or above the upper strike price of $150
at the time of expiration.
And that's because the maximum value of any
vertical spread at expiration is the width of
the strikes.
And in this case, the call spread has
strikes that are $15 apart, which means the
maximum value of this call spread at expiration
is $15, or an actual value of $1
,500.
So if I buy this call spread for
an entry cost of $776 and it appreciates
to its maximum value of $1,500, my
profit on the trade will be $724.
The reason that this call spread can only
be worth $15 at expiration is because if
the stock price is fully above the call
spread, meaning the stock price is at or
above $150, if we take the intrinsic value
of the call option that I own and
subtract the intrinsic value of the option that
I'm short, it will always come out to
$15 at expiration.
So for example, if the stock price is
at $155 at expiration, the $135 call that
I own will have $20 of intrinsic value,
but the $150 call that I am short
will have $5 of intrinsic value.
And basically what that means is that if
I want to close that spread at expiration,
I could sell the $135 call for $20,
collecting $2,000 in premium, and I would
have to buy back the short $150 call
for $5, therefore paying out $500 in premium,
and that would leave me with a net
premium collection of $1,500 at expiration.
So this is the expiration payoff graph, which
only really matters at expiration, but how did
this strategy actually perform as the stock price
changed over time?
Let's take a look.
On the top portion of this graph, we
have the changes in the stock price relative
to the strike prices of this call spread,
and on the bottom portion of the graph,
we're looking at the actual changes in the
spread's value as the stock price changed.
In the first few days of the trade,
the stock price drifted lower, which caused the
call spread to lose value.
If the spread price declines from the price
you pay for it, you'll have an unrealized
loss.
Fortunately, we can see that the stock price
rocketed higher in the subsequent weeks, leading to
an increase in the call spread's value.
You'll notice that there was a moment where
the stock price was above the entire call
spread, but why wasn't the spread's price $15?
Because I know I said that the maximum
value of this spread at expiration would be
$15 if the stock price was above $150.
Well, we will talk about that later in
the section titled Vertical Spread Profitability vs.
Time to Expiration.
At around 4 days to expiration, the spread's
price was very close to its maximum value
of $15.
It's worth mentioning here that you can close
a vertical spread whenever you want to, you
don't have to hold until expiration.
If the maximum potential value of the spread
is $15, and the spread's price gets close
to $15, then it makes sense to close
the trade because you have very little left
to gain from holding it, but you have
everything to lose.
At the very end of the trade, we
can see that the stock price did dip
lower and the call spread lost substantial value,
and that's exactly why a spread should be
closed when it approaches the maximum potential value.
It's really not worth holding.
At the time of expiration, the stock price
was at $148.06, leaving the trade with
a profit of $530.
But where does this profit come from?
If the stock price is at $148.06
at expiration, the 135 call will have intrinsic
value of $13.06, while the 150 call
will have no intrinsic value and expire worthless.
Therefore, the value of the spread at expiration
is limited to the intrinsic value of the
135 call, which is $13.06, meaning that
in actual dollar terms, the spread's value would
be $1306.
And if I buy a spread for $776
and it expires with a value of $1306,
my profit is $530.
So what we've learned with this example is
that when you buy a call spread, or
you trade a bull call spread, you want
the stock price to increase, and ideally you
want the stock price to be above the
upper strike price of the bull call spread
at the time of expiration, as that is
a scenario that will result in the spread
having its maximum potential value, which we also
learned is the distance between the strike prices.
So if I have a $20 wide vertical
spread, the most it can be worth is
$20.
If I have a $100 wide vertical spread,
the most that spread can be worth at
expiration is $100.
So keep that in mind.
We also saw that as the stock price
goes up and down, so does the value
of the call spread.
And this is important to understand because when
you enter any option position, it's not a
binary event where you only get the profit
or loss at the time of expiration.
The option prices, or the option spread in
this example, will change every minute of the
day as the stock price is changing, and
you can get out of that spread or
option position whenever you want to.
So just because it has an expiration date,
it doesn't mean you have to hold until
the expiration date.
So to close the call spread in this
example, since I bought the $135 call as
an opening trade, and I shorted the $150
call when I opened the trade, to close
this call spread, I just have to sell
the $135 call that I own and buy
back the $150 call that I am short.
And you can do this in one transaction
at one spread price, and effectively that will
realize whatever profit or loss you have on
that spread at that moment.
So you never have to hold a spread
until expiration.
You can close it whenever you want.
So I could buy a call spread and
sell it five seconds later if I wanted
to.
I can get out whenever I want to.
All right, let's move on to the second
bullish vertical spread, which is called the bull
put spread.
As the name suggests, a bull put spread
is a bullish vertical spread constructed with put
options as opposed to call options, which we
just discussed.
To set up a bull put spread, a
trader will short a put option at one
strike price and purchase another put option at
a lower strike price.
Now this is sometimes just referred to as
selling or shorting a put spread, but it
is also referred to as a put credit
spread because when you enter the trade, you
will collect a net credit, meaning the option
that you sell is more expensive than the
option you purchase, and therefore you will collect
premium when you enter the trade.
And that's why it's called a credit spread.
The goal when trading a bull put spread
is to see the stock price increase, but
at the very least, the trade can make
money so long as the stock price remains
above the short put strike price as time
passes.
So if the stock price is here and
you sell this put spread here, you can
make money so long as the stock price
remains above this put spread.
And that means it is a high probability
trading strategy, meaning that you have a greater
than 50% chance, in theory, of making
money on that trade.
So just like we did before, let's go
ahead and look at a real historical example.
In this example, the stock price is at
$146.92 at the time of entering the
trade.
To construct this bull put spread, we will
short the $145 put and collect $6.60
and simultaneously purchase the $135 put for $3
.07. Both options are in the 46-day
expiration cycle.
The entry price for this spread is $3
.53 that is received since I shorted the
$145 put and collected $6.60 and paid
$3.07 to buy the $135 put.
So a net premium is collected at entry.
The breakeven price for this particular position is
$141.47. And that means if the stock
price is at $141.47 at the time
of expiration, then this put spread will not
make or lose any money.
So remember earlier I said that the maximum
value of a vertical spread is the distance
between the strike prices, and in this case,
since the put strikes are $10 apart, the
maximum value of this put spread at expiration
is $10.
So let's look at the expiration payoff diagram
for this particular bull put spread position.
So as we can see here, the best
case scenario is that the stock price is
above the entire put spread at expiration.
If the stock price is above $145 at
expiration, the $145 put and the $135 put
will have no intrinsic value and therefore will
expire worthless, leaving the spread with a value
of $0.
If I collect $353 for this spread at
entry and the spread's price falls to $0,
I will effectively make 100% of the
profit potential, or $353.
And so when you short a put spread
like this, you want all of the options
to expire worthless, which will happen if the
stock price increases and is above both put
spread's strike prices at the time of expiration.
The expiration breakeven price of this position is
$141.47, which means if the stock price
is at $141.47 at expiration, the $145
put will be worth its intrinsic value of
$3.53, and the $135 put will be
worthless.
And lastly, the maximum loss potential of this
position is $647, which will occur if the
stock price is below both put spread's strike
prices at expiration.
If the stock price is below $135 at
expiration, then the put spread will be worth
its maximum value of $10, which again is
the distance between the two strike prices.
So if I shorted this spread initially and
collected $353 in premium and the value increased
to $1,000, which is its maximum value,
then I will lose $647.
So let's go ahead and take a look
and see exactly what happened to this bull
put spread in real life as the stock
price was changing up and down through the
trade's duration.
So again, the top portion of this graph
features the changes in the stock price relative
to the spread's strike prices.
As we can see early on in the
trade, the share price was falling, which actually
caused an increase in the put spread's value.
And since the bull put spread is a
bullish strategy, it will lose money when the
stock price falls, and it will make money
when the stock price rises.
Fortunately, the shares regained traction and headed higher
throughout the remainder of the trade.
And we can see that the further the
stock price increased, and as time passed, the
spread's value collapsed.
At around 17 days to expiration, the spread's
value was already very close to $0, which
means the trade essentially already had the maximum
profit potential.
And at that moment, a wise trader would
close the put spread to secure the near
-maximum profit.
Closing the put spread would entail buying back
the short $145 put and selling the long
$135 put.
The P&L on the trade would therefore
be the difference between the $353 in premium
collected at the time of entering the trade
and whatever they paid to close the spread.
So if they paid $20 to close the
spread, the profit on the trade would be
$333.
But as we can see, the spread continued
losing value and ended up with the maximum
profit at expiration.
Because with the stock price at $157.02
at expiration, the $145 put and the $135
put had no intrinsic value, and therefore the
spread's value was $0.
So thus far we've covered both of the
bullish vertical spread trading strategies, which are the
bull call spread, which is buying a call
spread, and the bull put spread, which is
shorting a put spread.
So one of those is referred to as
a debit spread, meaning you pay to enter
it, which is buying the call spread.
And one of those is referred to as
a credit spread, which means you collect premium
when you enter the trade, and that is
when you sell or short the put spread.
So you may be wondering, when would you
use the bull call spread and when would
you use the bull put spread?
And we'll talk about that later in the
section titled, How to Select the Right Strategy.
But for now we need to move on
to the bearish vertical spread trades, which are
the bear call spread and the bear put
spread.
So let's get started.
So the first of these bearish vertical spread
trades that we will cover is called the
bear call spread, which is basically when you
sell a call spread or short a call
spread.
So the bear call spread is sometimes referred
to as simply selling a call spread, a
call credit spread, and that's it.
The next strategy we will cover is called
the bear call spread, which is referred to
sometimes as selling a call spread or a
call credit spread.
And a bear call spread is constructed by
shorting a call option at one strike price
and purchasing another call option at a higher
strike price.
So it's basically the bull call spread from
earlier, except you do the opposite, and instead
of buying the call spread, you actually short
or sell the call spread as your opening
trade.
And a bear call spread will make money
as long as the stock price remains below
the call spread's strike prices.
So if you sell this call spread and
the stock price is here, it doesn't matter
if the stock price goes up a little
bit, as long as the stock price is
below the vertical spread's strike prices, the trade
will make money as time passes.
So let's look at an example.
In this example, the stock price is at
$141.46 at the time of entry, and
to construct this spread, I will short the
$142 call for $1.93 and buy the
$145 call for $0.87. Both options are
in the 32-day expiration cycle.
So the entry price for this spread is
$1.06 that is received, since the call
that I shorted, the $142 call, is more
expensive than the call that I purchased, and
this results in a net premium collection at
the time of entering the trade.
So let's look at the expiration payoff graph
for this position.
As we can see, the best case scenario
is that the stock price is below $142
at expiration, as that would lead to the
$142 and $145 calls expiring worthless, which means
the call spread's value is $0.
If I short the call spread for $106
and it expires worthless, I'll make the full
profit of $106.
The breakeven price is $143.06, which means
if the stock price is right at $143
.06 at expiration, the $142 call will have
intrinsic value of $1.06, and the $145
call will expire worthless, leaving the spread with
a value of $1.06. No profit, no
loss.
Now if the stock price is at or
above the upper strike of $145, the call
spread will be worth its maximum price of
$3, because the strike width is $3.
And again, we have to multiply these figures
by 100 to get their actual values.
So if I short the spread for $106
and it appreciates to a value of $300,
I will lose $194.
But this is just the expiration payoff graph,
and we know that this does not reflect
what will happen before expiration.
So let's go ahead and look at a
performance visualization for this position to see exactly
how the trade performed relative to changes in
the stock price as time was passing.
The first thing to note is the correlation
between the stock price and the spread price,
and since this is a bearish call spread
trade, I want the stock price to fall
and be below $142 at expiration.
About halfway through this trade, with 17 days
to expiration, we can see that the stock
price was approaching the $145 price level, and
we can see that the spread's value was
at $2, representing an unrealized loss of about
$94 at that time.
But as a few more weeks passed, we
can see that the stock price declined steadily,
and with two days to expiration, the stock
price was well below the call spread's strike
prices, and the spread price itself was almost
$0.
So with the best case scenario being that
the spread price falls to $0, it would
make sense at that moment to close that
spread if the price gets close to $0.
Now to close a short call spread, meaning
a call spread that you sold as an
opening trade, you just need to buy back
that same call spread to close it, which
would consist of buying back the short call
and selling the long call.
So in this trade, that would mean buying
back the short $142 call and selling the
long $145 call, and this can be done
in one transaction.
So if I paid $0.20 to buy
back the spread, my net profit would be
$86 because I initially shorted the spread for
$1.06. In terms of this spread's value
at expiration, the stock price was at $142
.26, which means the $142 call had intrinsic
value of $0.26, and the $145 call
expired worthless.
Therefore, the price of the $142-$145
bear call spread at expiration was $0.26,
or a real value of $26.
So if I shorted this spread for $106
and it had value of $26 at expiration,
my profit would be $80.
All right, so we've got one vertical spread
strategy left, and then we will get to
the fun stuff, at least in my opinion,
because the next sections are going to be
critical in your understanding of vertical spread profitability
and how you can make more and more
money on your vertical spread positions.
The final of the four vertical spread strategies
that we have to discuss is the bear
put spread, which is sometimes referred to as
simply buying a put spread or a put
debit spread, since you pay to enter the
put spread.
To enter a bear put spread position, a
trader will buy a put spread at one
strike price and short another put option at
a lower strike price.
And the goal is to see the stock
price fall below both of the put spread
strike prices, and that would lead to the
maximum profit at expiration.
And since the put that you purchase will
be more expensive than the put that you
short when you enter the trade, this position
will require that you pay to enter the
position, and for that reason, it is sometimes
called a put debit spread.
So let's take a look at an example
and then move on to the more important
and fun stuff.
At the time of entering this trade, the
stock price was at $780.22. To construct
this bear put spread, we'll buy the 800
put for $44.88 and short the 750
put for $22.63. Both options are in
the 59-day expiration cycle.
The entry price of this spread is therefore
$22.25. So let's go ahead and take
a look at the expiration profit and loss
diagram for this position and then visualize the
trade's actual performance.
The best case scenario is that the stock
price falls below $750 and remains there at
expiration, because in that scenario, the put spread
will be worth the distance between the strike
prices, which is $50.
So if I buy a put spread for
$22.25 and it depreciates to $50, I'll
have a gain of $27.75 from the
change in the spread's price, but as we
know, we have to multiply that by 100,
and we get an actual profit of $2
,775.
The breakeven price at expiration is $777.75,
and if the spread is right at $777
.75 at expiration, the 800 put that I
own will have intrinsic value equal to $22
.25, and the 750 put that I'm short
will be worthless, and therefore the spread's price
will be $22.25, and I'll have no
profit or loss at the time of expiration.
And of course, the worst case scenario is
that the stock price is above both put
strikes at expiration, in which case both options
will have no intrinsic value and simply expire
worthless.
In that scenario, I'd end up having a
worthless spread that I paid $2,225 for
in the beginning, leaving me with, unfortunately, a
100% loss on the position.
But this is just the expiration payoff diagram,
so let's look at how this trade actually
performed as the stock price changed.
Understanding that this is a bearish trading strategy,
it would make sense that the trade lost
money initially as the stock price was increasing.
In the first two weeks or so, the
stock price unfortunately went from $778 to almost
$850, and we can see that the 800,
750, bear put spread lost value, falling from
a price of $22.25 to a low
of $10.
The decrease to $10 represents an unrealized loss
of $1,225.
And that's because I initially paid $2,225
for the spread, and a reduction in its
price to $10 means the spread is worth
$1,000.
So we always have to multiply the spread's
price by 100 to get its dollar value.
I know it's confusing, but that's what we
have to do.
As luck would have it, the stock rally
did not last long, and the share price
plummeted over the remainder of the trade.
And we can see that at 14 days
to expiration, the stock price was just above
$750, meaning the 800, 750 put spread was
almost fully in the money.
The spread's price at that moment was around
$34, or a value of $3,400.
The stock price fell even further, reaching a
low price of $720 when the spread had
around 4 days left until expiration.
And at that moment, the spread's price was
around $47.50, or just $2.50 shy
of its maximum potential value of $50.
And so the trader could have sold the
spread at that moment for $4,750 and
secured a profit of $2,525.
So to close a put spread that you've
purchased, you simply sell that put spread.
In this example, that would be done by
selling the 800 put and buying back the
short 750 put.
If the trader held this position all the
way to expiration, the P&L would have
been $1,760.
But where does that profit come from?
With the stock price at $760.16 at
expiration, the 800 put had intrinsic value equal
to $39.84, and the 750 put had
no intrinsic value.
And therefore the price of the 800 750
put spread was $39.84 at expiration, or
a value of $3,984.
And so if I bought this put spread
initially for $2,225 and it was worth
$3,985 at expiration, my profit is $1
,759.
So we've covered the four vertical spread strategies,
and I know we've gone through a lot
of examples and a lot of numbers in
these past four examples, but it's important that
you understand the basic mechanics of these vertical
spread trades, and that's going to set you
up for the next sections that we're going
to talk about, which in my opinion are
much more exciting and I love talking about
them and explaining them.
And these next sections are going to talk
about vertical spread profitability versus the time left
until expiration, and also with changes in implied
volatility.
And then I'm going to talk to you
about how to select the right strategy for
your particular situation and stock price outlook, and
then we'll close out the video by talking
about what happens at expiration to a vertical
spread, and lastly, do you have early assignment
risk when you trade vertical spread positions.
So let's get started by talking about vertical
spread profitability versus the time left until expiration.
This is perhaps one of the most important
things to understand about vertical spread trading, as
the time left until expiration has a significant
impact on how profitable your vertical spread will
be, depending on where the stock price is.
The reason this is so important is that
you have to understand one law about vertical
spreads, and the law about vertical spreads is
that to achieve the maximum profit potential on
a vertical spread position, both of the options
in your vertical spread must have very little
extrinsic value.
And more specifically, to get to the absolute
maximum profit potential, the extrinsic value in your
options will need to be zero, which will
happen at expiration, or if the spread is
so far in the money that the options
have very little extrinsic value or no extrinsic
value.
So basically, the more time your spread has
left until it expires, the deeper in the
money that spread will have to be to
get close to the maximum profit potential.
But if your spread has very little time
left until expiration or is expiring this day,
then the spread can just be fully in
the money and it will be trading with
very close to the maximum profit potential and
subsequently expiring with the maximum profit potential, because
if the spread is fully in the money
at expiration, only intrinsic value will remain and
the spread's value will have 100% of
its maximum potential value, which will be the
width of the strike prices.
So in our earlier bull call spread example,
I had mentioned at one point in that
example that the stock price was well above
both call spread strike prices, meaning the call
spread was fully in the money.
But I had noted that the spread's price
was not $15, which is the width of
the strikes.
Instead, the spread's price was around $12, or
$3 shy of its maximum potential value, despite
being fully in the money.
And the reason for that is because the
spread was not close to expiration.
It still had multiple days left before expiration,
and because of that, the options in that
spread had lots of extrinsic value, and because
of the extrinsic value in those options, the
spread's price was not yet at its maximum
potential value of $15.
Take a look again at that example, and
at around 18 days to expiration, we can
see that the stock price is around $150
to $50, but the $135, $150 call spread
was not worth its maximum value of $15.
And as I mentioned, the reason is because
of extrinsic value.
If we just strip out the intrinsic value
of these options, we can calculate that at
a stock price of $150 to $50, the
long $135 call has $17.50 of intrinsic
value, while the short $150 call has $2
.50 of intrinsic value.
And therefore, the net intrinsic value of the
spread is $15, which is its maximum potential
value.
And by net intrinsic value, I mean the
intrinsic value that I own, and subtracting out
the intrinsic value that I don't own, or
of the option that I'm short.
So basically, if I need to sell that
$135 call, I can sell the $135 call
for its intrinsic value of $17.50, and
I have to pay $2.50 to buy
back the short $150 call, assuming that I'm
only paying and receiving intrinsic value.
And therefore, if I collect $17.50 from
selling the $135 call at its level of
intrinsic value, and I pay $2.50 to
buy back the short $150 call at its
intrinsic value of $2.50, then I will
collect $15, which is the width of the
strikes, or the maximum potential value of that
spread.
So why is it important to understand that
the more time left until expiration, the more
extrinsic value these options will have, which will
prevent the spread from getting to its maximum
potential value?
Well, the reason it's important is because if
you buy a call spread, or if you
buy a put spread, and you see a
favorable stock price movement that leaves your spread
fully in the money, you have to understand
that just because the spread is fully in
the money, it doesn't mean that you will
have the maximum profit potential.
And that's because if the spread is fully
in the money with lots of time left
until expiration, then there's going to be a
lot of extrinsic value in those options, and
therefore, the spread will not yet be trading
at its maximum potential value, or the width
of the strikes.
So basically, if you have a spread that
becomes fully in the money, you basically have
to wait for time to pass for the
extrinsic value to decay out of those options,
and therefore, the spread's price will gradually approach
its maximum value, or the distance between the
strike prices.
So I can prove this to you by
just looking at various vertical spreads and changing
the expiration date, or changing the vertical spread's
expiration cycle, so that we can basically simulate
the loss of extrinsic value, or the increase
in extrinsic value, and see how that affects
the spread's price.
So let's hop over to the Tastyworks trading
platform so I can show you some real
examples of this, and we can understand that
a fully in the money vertical spread will
be trading much closer to its maximum value
than that same vertical spread with more time
until expiration.
So let's hop over to the trading platform
right now and take a look.
So first thing I want to point out
is it's an absolute bloodbath today in the
market.
We have S&P down $125, or three
and a half percent.
NASDAQ is down 630 points, or over five
percent.
That's disgusting.
All right, anyways, let's go to Apple.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to queue up a vertical spread that
is fully in the money.
So for this I'm going to look at
a call spread.
So Apple's current price is $122.75. So
I'm going to look at the $100, $110
call spread.
And let's look at a long-dated expiration
cycle, such as November 2020.
So if I purchase, or queue up an
order to purchase the $100 call, and then
I queue up an order to short the
$110 call, we can see that this call
spread is fully in the money because this
is the $100, $110 bull call spread, and
Apple is currently at $123.
So this call spread is fully in the
money.
But we can see that the spread's price
itself is $6.95, and the most that
this spread could be worth at expiration is
$10.
So let's go ahead and look at the
$100, $110 call option in a much shorter
term expiration cycle and see if the spread
price is higher or lower than $7.
So right now it's jumping around a bit
because it's a volatile trading day, but we
can still gauge the increase in this spread's
price as time passes by simply looking at
the same spread in a shorter term expiration
cycle.
So let's go to September 2020.
If I queue up an order to purchase
the $100 call and short the $110 call,
we can see that the $100, $110 call
spread, with 15 days to expiration as opposed
to 78 days to expiration, this shorter term
call spread that is fully in the money
is trading for about $8.85. So basically
$2 more than the same exact call spread
with 60 days more until expiration.
And the reason for this is that 15
-day options have much less extrinsic value than
78-day options, and for that reason, if
you look at an in-the-money vertical
spread that has less time until expiration, its
price will be much closer to the maximum
potential value as compared to that same exact
vertical spread with much more time until expiration.
So the next thing we will talk about
is vertical spread profitability versus changes in implied
volatility, which relates directly to the extrinsic value
statements that I made earlier, because implied volatility
literally measures extrinsic value in options.
So if implied volatility increases, that's an indication
that the options have become more expensive extrinsically
relative to the amount of time they have
until expiration.
And on the other hand, if you see
a decrease in implied volatility, that means that
the options now have less extrinsic value than
they had before relative to the time left
until expiration.
So basically if we hold the stock price
constant and we have no passage of time,
a decrease in option extrinsic value results in
a lower level of implied volatility.
And on the other side of things, an
increase in extrinsic value, holding the stock price
and time constant, will lead to an increase
in implied volatility.
So here are two things that you need
to keep in mind and kind of internalize.
The first thing is that if you buy
a call spread or you buy a put
spread, you want the stock price to move
so that that spread becomes in-the-money.
And if you buy a call spread or
put spread and it becomes fully in-the
-money, you want implied volatility to decrease, meaning
that you want the options to have less
extrinsic value relative to the time left until
expiration, because with less extrinsic value in those
options through a decrease in implied volatility means
that the spread's price will actually expand towards
the width of the or its maximum value
potential.
So if you have a $20 wide call
spread and the stock price increases above both
call strike prices, you want implied volatility to
decrease because then that means that these options
have less extrinsic value, and because of that,
the spread's price that you have, which is
$20 wide, will appreciate towards $20 or its
maximum potential value.
The second thing that you should internalize is
that if you short a call spread or
you short a put spread and the spread
is out-of-the-money, which is a
good thing for you, then again, you want
implied volatility to decrease because that means that
there is less extrinsic value in your vertical
spread's options, and less extrinsic value means that
you will see a contraction in your out
-of-the-money vertical spread's price, because with
no intrinsic value, if your spread is out
-of-the-money and it loses extrinsic value,
which is all that it consists of, then
that spread's price will fall closer towards zero,
which is when you would realize the maximum
profit potential.
Now I don't like telling you things to
just memorize, so let me explain these things
that I've just said intuitively.
A broad decrease in the extrinsic value that
exists in a stock's options, meaning a decrease
in implied volatility, means that the option market
is expecting less volatility from that stock price
in the future, which means that there is
a higher probability that the stock price will
be somewhere around its current price in the
future as compared to before.
So if you own a call spread, meaning
you purchase a call spread, and the stock
price is fully above your call spread strike
prices, a decrease in implied volatility, meaning less
extrinsic value in those options, means that there
is a higher expected probability that the stock
price will be somewhere around its current price
in the future, which means that there is
a higher implied probability that your in-the
-money vertical spread will be in-the-money
at expiration.
And if the probability, or the implied probability,
of your vertical spread being in-the-money
at expiration increases, the spread's price will increase.
So basically, if your spread is fully in
-the-money and you own that vertical spread,
meaning you buy a call spread and the
stock price shoots higher, you want implied volatility
to decrease, because a decrease in implied volatility
means that there is a higher implied probability
that the stock price will still be above
your call spread strike price at expiration, and
because that means your spread has a higher
probability of being fully in-the-money at
expiration, the spread's price will increase towards its
maximum potential value.
And the same is true if you are
short a put spread or short a call
spread.
When you short a put spread, you want
the stock price to be above your put
spread strike prices, because then that means the
puts have only extrinsic value, which, if the
extrinsic value decreases, that means the spread's price
will fall towards $0.
So if you have a put spread that
you've shorted and the stock price is above
the put spread strike prices, a decrease in
implied volatility means that the extrinsic value has
decreased in those options, which will lead to
a contraction in the put spread's price towards
$0.
But the reason this makes sense is because
if you have a put spread that you've
shorted and the stock price is above your
put spread strike prices, a decrease in implied
volatility means that there is a lower expected
range for the stock price, and therefore the
probability that your put spread expires out-of
-the-money increases.
And if there is a higher probability of
your put spread expiring worthless, the price of
that put spread will fall.
So if you are short a put spread
and it is out-of-the-money and
implied volatility contracts, that means that there is
a higher probability that your put spread will
expire out-of-the-money or worthless because
there is a lower expected stock price range
than there was before when implied volatility was
higher.
You may have heard that when implied volatility
is low, it is good for debit spreads,
meaning when implied volatility is low, it's better
to buy call spreads and buy put spreads
because the increase in implied volatility will benefit
the position somehow because you are net long
options, meaning you've purchased options essentially.
And that's simply not true because if you
buy a call spread or you buy a
put spread, you want the stock price to
move through the strike prices, and when that
happens, and when your spread becomes in-the
-money, you want implied volatility to decrease because
that means there's less extrinsic value in the
options, and that means the spread's price will
increase towards its maximum potential value.
And intuitively, that's because if your spread that
you own is fully in-the-money and
a decrease in implied volatility occurs, that means
that there's a higher probability or higher implied
probability that your spread will expire in-the
-money, and if your spread expires in-the
-money, it will expire with its maximum potential
value or the width of the strikes.
So a favorable movement with a vertical spread
combined with a decrease in implied volatility is
always a good thing.
The only time an increase in implied volatility
is good is if the stock price is
not in a favorable situation, meaning if you
buy a call spread and the stock price
is below the call spread, meaning the call
spread is out-of-the-money, an increase
in implied volatility is good because it means
that there's a larger potential range for that
stock price or expected range for the stock
price, and that means that there is a
higher probability that your call spread will expire
in-the-money, and because of that increase
in the probability of the call spread expiring
in-the-money, the call spread's price will
increase.
But if the call spread is in-the
-money, you want implied volatility to decrease because
you want the implied probability of the call
spread expiring in-the-money to increase.
So I know this is a lot and
it's a little more complicated than the simple
examples that we talked about earlier, but it
is a critical thing to understand because it
doesn't matter if you are shorting a vertical
spread or if you are purchasing a vertical
spread.
If the stock price is moving in favor
of your vertical spread, meaning that your call
spread that you purchase is in-the-money
or the put spread that you've shorted is
out-of-the-money, you want implied volatility
to decrease 100% of the time.
The only time an increase in implied volatility
is good is if you own a call
or put spread that is out-of-the
-money or if you are short a call
spread or put spread that is in-the
-money.
All right, so let's move on to the
last sections of the video, which is first,
how to select the right strategy for your
given outlook, and then we'll talk about what
happens at expiration and early assignment risk.
So given that there are four different vertical
spread strategies you can choose from, which one
should you actually use depending on your particular
scenario or stock price outlook?
It's really a matter of preference, but here
are some guidelines to help you out.
First, if you are expecting a strong directional
movement from the stock, then in my opinion,
it would be better to buy a call
spread or buy a put spread since that
would be a trade that you could structure
in a way to have very favorable risk
-reward if you are right about your strong
outlook for that stock's potential movement in the
future.
And guideline number two is if you are
not expecting a super strong movement in either
direction, but you want directional exposure and you
want to place a higher probability trade to
profit if the stock price moves in favor
of whatever direction you want, but also could
move against you slightly, then in that scenario,
I think it would be better to go
with the credit spread strategies, which means you
short a call spread, in which case the
strategy will make money so long as the
stock price remains below the call spread, or
you short a put spread, which will give
you bullish exposure, but the strategy will make
money so long as the stock price remains
above the put spread strike prices.
So let's hop over to the Tastyworks trading
platform, and I will show you some example
trade setups with these four vertical spread strategies
so that you can understand kind of the
differences that you'll get with different strike price
selection methods and the risk-reward that you'll
get with those trade structures.
So let's check it out.
So right now I have Netflix pulled up
on the trading platform, and we can see
that Netflix is currently trading for $525 per
share.
So let's say I think that Netflix is
going to experience a very strong directional movement
to the downside, and I want to profit
from that assumption.
So I think Netflix will continue losing substantial
value in the share price.
Of my bearish vertical spread strategies, I could
either buy a put spread, and the other
option is to short a call spread.
So it's between the bear call spread and
the bear put spread.
So let's look at going to the October
expiration cycle with 43 days to go, and
with Netflix at $525, let's look at buying
the $525 put and then look at shorting
the $500 put.
So this would give me a put spread
with a cost of $11.45, and that
means my maximum loss potential is right around
that number.
Let me just lock this price.
So if the price of the put spread
is $11.65, my maximum loss potential is
$1,165.
But my maximum profit potential is $1,335.
So basically, the way I constructed this put
spread is to purchase the at-the-money
option and short a further out-of-the
-money option.
So this is just one way that you
could set this trade up.
But the reason I like this, and the
reason I would suggest buying a call spread
or put spread with a strategy or structure
similar to this one, is because it'll give
you favorable risk-reward, and that will be
beneficial to you if you are correct about
your strong directional outlook for the stock.
So in this case, my maximum profit potential
is slightly higher than the I can lose,
and because of that, if I'm wrong, I
will lose less than I will make if
I am actually right.
So if I'm right about my stock price
prediction that Netflix will fall, then my profit
potential is actually $1,335.
And if I'm wrong, then I will actually
lose less than that, and my potential is
$1,165.
So let's compare this risk profile with the
bear call spread.
So with Netflix at $526, let's look at—I
could even look at selling the $525 call
and then purchasing the $550 call.
So what we'll notice here is that if
I short the $525-$550 call spread,
which is $25 wide, just like the put
spread was that I just looked at, in
this case, I'll make money as long as
Netflix is below $525 at expiration in 43
days.
So since I can sell this spread right
now for $10.95, my maximum profit is
$1,090—well, let me just lock this.
If I sell this for $11, my maximum
profit is $1,100.
But if Netflix is above $550 at expiration,
then this spread will be worth $25, and
if I short it for $11 and it
goes to $25, I'll have a $14 loss,
which means my maximum loss on this is
actually $1,400.
So when we compare these two strategies of
either shorting the $525-$550 call spread
versus buying the $525-$500 put spread,
we can see that this has less favorable
risk-reward.
So I can lose more than I can
make, if I'm right.
But the benefit of using this call spread
strategy over the put spread strategy is that
it has a higher probability of making money,
because as long as Netflix is below $536
at expiration, which is this position's break-even
price, this position will make money.
Whereas if I buy the $525-$500
put spread for $10, then I actually need
Netflix to be below $515 at expiration.
So the reason that I said, if you
have a strong directional outlook for a stock,
then buying the spread is probably better, then
the reason I said that is because you'll
have more favorable risk-reward if you set
it up in this manner.
But I have to drop something on you
right now.
Call spreads and put spreads, buying them and
selling them, are effectively the exact same strategy,
just with calls and puts.
So buying a call spread is the same
exact thing as shorting a put spread with
the same strike prices.
So let me demonstrate that to you right
now.
So as opposed to shorting the $525-
$550 call spread, if I purchased the $550
-$525 put spread, which is essentially fully
in the money, we will see that the
risk profile is very similar.
So for the $525-$550 short call
spread, the max profit is around $10.50,
the max loss is around $14.50. If
I buy the $550-$525 put spread,
the max profit is $10.85, the max
loss is $14.15. Now keep in mind
that these prices are changing as the stock
price is changing, and it's a pretty volatile
day.
So they're not going to be exactly the
same, but if we roughly compare the risk
-to-reward of shorting a call spread or
buying a put spread using the same strike
prices, they will essentially have the exact same
risk profile.
So if we do that once more, go
back to...well, let's look at a different example.
If I short the $500-$475 put
spread, this has max profit of $9.25,
maximum loss potential of $15.75, but to
get this same exact position, I could look
at buying the $475-$500 call spread.
So let's see what the risk-reward profile
for that is.
So buy the $475, short the $500, max
profit $9.65, max loss $15.35. So
they are very similar in nature, and this
gets into the realm of option synthetics, which
is how you can construct the same option
positions in different ways.
But the reason that I'm bringing this up
is because I think it is awkward to
purchase an in-the-money vertical spread, much
like I think it is awkward to short
an in-the-money vertical spread.
So if you want to place a high
-probability trade, then I think it is better
to short an out-of-the-money vertical
spread, or if you want a very favorable
risk-to-reward trade based on a very
strong directional outlook, then I think it is
better to buy an at-the-money or
out-of-the-money vertical spread as compared
to buying a deep in-the-money vertical
spread, because if you buy an in-the
-money vertical spread, the profit potential will be
less than the risk, and if you buy
an out-of-the-money vertical spread, the
profit potential will be more than the risk.
So when you have a very strong directional
outlook for a stock, I think it is
more beneficial to give yourself better risk-reward
as compared to putting on a higher-probability
trade, where if you're right about that strong
directional outlook, you'll make a little bit of
money, but if you're wrong, you'll lose more
than you could have made.
So it's really a matter of preference, and
I would encourage you to go on the
trading platform and play around with the different
trade structures and see what the risk and
the reward profile is for those vertical spreads,
but in my opinion, if you have a
very strong directional outlook for a stock, then
I think it is better to buy a
call spread or put spread, namely one that
is at-the-money, meaning you buy an
at-the-money strike and short an out
-of-the-money option, or you even purchase
an out-of-the-money vertical spread, because
those will give you the most favorable risk
-to-reward profiles.
All right, so let's close out this video
by talking about what happens at expiration to
a vertical spread, and is there early assignment
risk when you are trading vertical spreads?
So understanding what happens to a vertical spread
is fairly simple, because at expiration, any option
that is in the money that is held
through expiration will automatically be exercised.
So for vertical spreads, what this means is
that if your vertical spread is out-of
-the-money, meaning the options have no intrinsic
value, then at expiration, those options will expire
worthless, and they will not convert into any
stock positions.
So those worthless options will simply disappear from
your trading account, and that'll be it.
Now, if your vertical spread is fully in
-the-money, which means both of the options
in the vertical spread have intrinsic value, and
you hold that position through expiration, then both
of the options will actually automatically be exercised
and convert into the corresponding stock positions associated
with whether that's a short or long call,
or a short or long put.
So for example, if I have a 125
-130 call spread that I've purchased, and the
stock price is at 135 at expiration, and
I hold the spread through expiration, the long
125 call that I own will automatically get
exercised, and I will buy 100 shares of
stock at $125 per share, but the 130
call that I am short will also automatically
be exercised, and since I'm short that option,
that means I will be assigned on the
short 130 call.
And that means I will sell 100 shares
of stock at $130 per share.
So basically what will happen if the 125
-130 call expires in-the-money, I'll buy
100 shares at $125, and I will simultaneously
sell those shares at $130, and basically I
will make $500 on that difference, because I
will buy 100 shares at $125, and I
will sell those 100 shares at $130, pocketing
the $500 gain on that transaction.
But if I paid $250 for the spread
when I entered the trade, my net profit
would be $250 in that particular example.
So if the vertical spread is fully in
-the-money, and you allow it to expire
in-the-money, then the exercise and assignments
will offset, and you will not end up
with any stock position after expiration.
Regardless of that though, you will pay exercise
and assignment fees based on whatever your brokerage
firm charges, and I actually would not recommend
holding a vertical spread through expiration, just because
you have the option to close it before
expiration, in which case you don't have to
worry about what's going to happen when those
options expire in-the-money.
So in general, I think it is a
good idea to always close option positions before
expiration, unless they are extremely deep out-of
-the-money, and they're just going to expire
worthless anyways.
But lastly, what happens if a vertical spread
is only partially in-the-money at expiration?
Let's say I buy the 100 put, and
I short the 90 put, and the stock
price is at $93 at expiration.
Well, the 100 put is in-the-money,
and the 90 put is out-of-the
-money.
So this means if I hold the position
through expiration, the 100 put that I own
will automatically be exercised, and I will therefore
short 100 shares of stock at the put
strike price of $100.
So I will end up with a stock
position which would be shorting 100 shares of
stock at the put strike price of $100.
But the 90 put that I shorted initially
will expire out-of-the-money, because it
doesn't have any intrinsic value if the stock
price is at $93.
And because of that, the 90 put will
expire worthless, but the 100 put that I
owned will be exercised automatically, and I will
effectively short 100 shares of stock at that
put strike price of $100.
So if your vertical spread is only partially
in-the-money, meaning the stock price is
in between the strike prices when it expires,
if you hold that spread through expiration, you
will end up with a stock position.
And again, as I mentioned earlier, I think
it is a good idea to close vertical
spreads before expiration, especially if they are partially
in-the-money, because in that scenario, you
will end up with a stock position.
And in most cases, you probably won't want
to be taking the stock position, because if
you're trading options, especially if you're trading in
a smaller account, that stock position is going
to represent a value that is significantly larger
than whatever option position you have.
And for that reason, if your spread is
partially in-the-money at expiration, I would
really recommend closing that spread before it expires
so that you don't end up with a
stock position, and especially if you don't want
the stock position.
And lastly, is there assignment risk when trading
vertical spreads?
And the answer is yes.
Since there is a short option component of
all of the four vertical spread strategies, when
you're trading a vertical spread, if the vertical
spread is in-the-money, meaning that the
short option is in-the-money, then theoretically
you do have risk of being assigned on
that short option, because the only time you'll
be assigned on a short option is if
it is in-the-money.
But at the same time, there really is
not a high risk of early assignment, because
if you're short an in-the-money option
and it has lots of extrinsic value in
its price, it is very unlikely to be
exercised by the person that owns it, because
whoever exercises the option with extrinsic value will
effectively burn the extrinsic value in that option
and give it up unnecessarily.
So for that reason, a rational trader would
never exercise an option that has lots of
extrinsic value, and if they did exercise an
option that had lots of extrinsic value, they
would essentially be forfeiting all of that extrinsic
value, and if you're short that option, that
means you will actually be benefiting by the
amount of that extrinsic value.
In the case of early assignment, there is
an early assignment risk when you're trading vertical
spreads, primarily if the short option is deep
in-the-money with very little extrinsic value.
But in the case of buying a call
spread or buying a put spread, if the
spread is so deep in-the-money that
the short option has very little extrinsic value,
that also means that the long option that
you own also has very little extrinsic value,
and for that reason, that means the spread
is probably trading for very close to its
maximum potential value, and you should be closing
it anyways.
If you own a call spread or you
own a put spread, there should never be
a scenario where you're worried about early assignment,
because in the case where you could be
assigned early on that short option because it
is in-the-money with very little extrinsic
value, that means your put spread or call
spread is already trading near the maximum profit
potential, and therefore, you should close that position.
Now on the other hand, if you are
short a call spread or you are short
a put spread and it is fully in
-the-money, then your short option is actually
going to have less extrinsic value than the
long option, and in this scenario, you are
much more likely to be assigned before expiration.
Since your short spread is actually fully in
-the-money, and that means you have a
losing position, it's a little harder to tell
you to close that spread because it is
illogical to close a vertical spread that is
close to the maximum loss potential, because you
have very little left to lose, but you
have everything left to gain.
So it's a little trickier when you're short
a call spread or put spread and it
is deep in-the-money with early assignment
risk, because in that scenario, the spread is
probably trading at a point that leaves you
with near the maximum loss potential, and in
general, if you have already lost almost all
you can lose on a trade, it doesn't
make sense to close it.
But in this case, it's tricky because if
you continue holding that position, there's a chance
that you'll get assigned early on that short
in-the-money option, but keep in mind
that that does not hand you a huge
loss, because you still have the long option
that is also in-the-money, and you
could just close the stock position and close
the long option to unwind that position, or
you could exercise the in-the-money option
that you own, which would effectively close out
that stock position that you were assigned into.
But again, I would not recommend exercising an
option if it has lots of extrinsic value.
So there's a lot to know there and
a lot to think about, but in general,
you should not worry about early assignment risk
with vertical spreads, because like I said, if
you're buying the spreads, so you're buying a
call spread or buying a put spread, by
the time you get to any situation where
you have early assignment risk, your trade's going
to have the max profit and it should
be closed.
But if you are shorting call spreads or
shorting put spreads, it's a little trickier because
by the time you get to an early
assignment risk scenario, then your position is going
to have close to the maximum loss potential,
and that means that you've already lost everything
you can lose on the trade, and in
those situations, it's illogical to close the trade.
But if you want to avoid the early
assignment risk, the only option you have is
to close that vertical spread.
All right, so that's going to do it
for today's ultimate guide to the vertical spread
option strategies.
I really hope you enjoyed this video and
learned a ton from it.
I covered not only the basics, but I
covered some more advanced material that I would
encourage you to study, namely the vertical spread
profitability versus time to expiration, the vertical spread
profitability versus changes in implied volatility, and both
of those things relate to extrinsic value.
So we not only covered the basics today,
but we covered some more heavy-hitting material.
But if you can master your understanding of
everything that I've described in this video, as
I said earlier, you will make a gigantic
leap forward in your options trading expertise.
If you enjoyed this video, I would really
appreciate if you gave it a like for
me down below, and if you left me
a comment letting me know what you liked
about this video or what you've learned, and
if you have anything else to add that
other people could benefit from, please leave that
down in the comment section below.
My name is Chris from Project Option, and
I will see you all in the next
video.