Most option traders start out buying options because
it's simplest to understand.
If you think Facebook stock will go up,
you could buy a call, and if you
think Facebook stock will go down, you could
buy a put.
This sounds great because you can trade the
options with much less capital than if you
were to simply trade the stock.
Let me show you an example.
First, let's look at an option chain on
stock XYZ, which is currently trading at $75
per share.
Let's say you are bullish on the stock
and you're looking to buy a call option,
so we're just going to go ahead and
ignore the put options for now.
If you were to buy the 70 strike
call option, for example, this would cost you
$750, and you're hoping that the price of
XYZ will rise so you can make money,
but this is not a very good trading
strategy because it puts time decay against you,
and not only does the price of XYZ
have to move up, it has to move
up a significant amount for you to even
break even.
In this case, your break even is at
$77.50, a full two and a half
points above the current stock price, and if
XYZ sits still and trades sideways, you're screwed
because your option you just bought will decay
each and every day.
And that's what options are, guys.
They are depreciating assets, and any smart investor
is not going to buy a depreciating asset
and call it an investment.
Let me show you a better way that
allows you to make a directional bet on
the stock, but without having to buy a
naked option or put up tons of capital
to trade the stock itself.
And we're actually going to eliminate time decay
altogether.
Instead of just buying the 70 strike call
option, we're going to do something a little
bit different.
We're going to buy this option, but we're
also going to simultaneously sell a cheaper out
-of-the-money option to reduce our cost.
So in this case, we're going to buy
the 70 strike call for $750, but we're
also going to sell the 80 strike call
for $250.
This knocks our cost down by a full
$250, and our net price is now just
$500.
This is called buying a vertical spread.
By trading a vertical spread rather than simply
buying a single option, we're able to significantly
reduce the cost of our trade, which improves
our breakeven on the trade and our probability
of success.
The net price we pay for this vertical
spread is $5, so our breakeven is at
$75 per share, which is where the current
stock price is.
If you're lost, hang with me.
I'm going to show you how this works.
Let's compare the two strategies in three different
scenarios.
Scenario number one.
XYZ stock price has moved up, and at
the expiration date, it's at $79.50 per
share.
First, let's look at the 70-80 vertical
spread.
The short 80 call that you sold for
$250 would now be worthless because it's out
-of-the-money.
So you made $250 on the short 80
call, and the long 70 call you bought
for $7.50 is now $9.50 in
the money, so it's worth $9.50. So
you made $200 on the long 70 call,
so your net profit is $450.
Now remember, the net price we paid for
the vertical spread was $500, so our return
on capital was 90%.
Our max risk was simply the net price
we bought the spread for, which was $500.
Now let's compare this to if we simply
bought the 70 call for $7.50. With
the stock at $79.50, our long call
would be at $9.50, providing us with
a profit of $200, so our return on
capital was only 26.67%. Our max risk
was $750 we paid to buy this option.
Let's look at scenario two.
XYZ has mostly traded sideways, and at the
expiration date, the price is still at $75
per share.
Looking at the vertical spread, our long 70
call will now be worth $5, resulting in
a loss of $250 on that leg of
the trade.
But our short 80 call will again be
worthless, resulting in a profit of $250 on
that leg.
So the two cancel out, and we would
actually just be at break-even on the
trade.
Now compare that to if we simply bought
the 70 call at $7.50. We would
now be sitting on a $250 loss.
So in the case of the vertical spread,
time decay was not an issue whatsoever.
However, if you just bought the 70 call
rather than trading the vertical spread, you're sitting
on a 33% loss due to time
decay.
Okay, scenario three.
We are completely wrong about the direction of
XYZ, and the stock tanks down to $50
per share.
Both of the options that make up our
vertical spread are out of the money and
are worthless.
So we lost $750 on the long 70
call, but we made $250 on the short
80 call.
So our net loss is $500, much less
than losing $750 like we would have if
we were to simply buy the 70 strike
call.
Buying the vertical was better than buying the
naked option in all three of these scenarios,
but there is one scenario where buying the
naked call would have worked out better.
Let's say the stock rips higher and is
now at $85 per share at the expiration
date.
For the vertical, the 70 call we bought
for $7.50 would now be worth $15,
providing us with a profit of $750 on
that leg.
And the short 80 call we sold at
$250 would now be worth $5, resulting in
a loss of $250 on this leg of
the trade.
So our net profit is only $500 as
opposed to $750 if we would have just
bought the call.
So that's the only downfall with the vertical
spread, is that it has limited profit potential.
Whereas buying the naked option allows us unlimited
profit potential.
But is the profit potential really unlimited?
Of course not.
That's just theoretical because theoretically a stock can
go to infinity.
But look, you still made a 100%
return on capital on the vertical spread, so
what is there to be upset about?
And trust me, these three scenarios are going
to happen way more often and the vertical
spread will pay you far more in the
long run than the few times you might
eventually hit a home run with buying the
naked option.
Now let me show you how to pull
up an order to buy a vertical spread
in the thinkorswim trading platform.
All you're going to do is go to
the option chain, right-click the option you
want to buy, then click buy vertical.
From there all you have to do is
adjust your strike selection.
I personally prefer to buy one strike in
the money and sell one strike out of
the money when trading this strategy.
Now we can click confirm and send and
view the pop-up box to see the
details of the trade, such as max profit,
max loss, capital required, and break-even stock
price.
And you can also do this on the
put side if you want to make a
bet that the stock will go down.
So alright guys, hope you enjoyed the video
and learned from it.
If so, be sure to click the like
and subscribe button below and also check out
our website and join our email list for
three exclusive free videos.
And I will see you in the next
video.