That's right, guys.
This video will change your life forever.
The easiest way to make money in crypto
is to automate your trades.
And in this video, and I will make
it a short video this time because I
talk a lot, because I have a lot
to say, but in this video, I'm going
to show you very quickly what you can
do right now to get ready for the
next bull market, for the next leg up
and how you can automate all of your
portfolio in just a couple of minutes.
Let's go, guys.
Am I hyped up?
Absolutely.
I'm hyped up.
I just came back from token 2049 and
I've met a massive amount of amazing people.
I've been able to get MM Crypto on
my channel, Austin from Altcoin Daily and Ran
from Crypto Banter, but you can watch all
of that later because this video is the
most important video you will watch in your
whole life.
Honestly, like if you don't watch this video
until the end, nobody can help you.
You will lose money forever.
Okay, I'm just kidding.
So this is not financial advice.
You can lose all of your money because
crypto is risky.
Okay.
That's why I'm doing this channel to give
you all the knowledge and strategies and automation
knowledge so you can outcompete yourself but also
other people who don't know about this stuff.
Okay, so having said all of that, smash
the freaking like button, subscribe to the channel,
hit the bell and let me change your
life with this video.
Let's be real, guys.
Most people lose money in crypto because they
don't know what they're doing, especially because they're
trading on smaller time frames, right?
They're trading on five minute, ten minute, one
hour, four hour, even four hour is a
problem and they don't know that on these
time frames, they have more enemies than on
the higher time frames.
You don't even see the enemy.
Okay, because it's somewhere on the other side
of the computer of the internet.
You don't even see that you're fighting a
massive gorilla that is playing with you.
However, this gorilla wants to play with you.
Okay, you don't see that because if you
go into a boxing match, at least you
see the enemy in front of you and
you see, okay, that's not good.
I'm going to lose this battle.
So let's fight something else, right?
But if you're fighting in the freaking small
time frames, you are getting absolutely massacred.
Okay, by the market maker, high-frequency traders,
you can't be fast enough because that is
just for bots.
Okay, these smaller time frames, that's where they
are good, right?
Because they're fast and they can run your
stops.
They can fake you in or they can
do whatever they want with you.
Okay, so that's the rule number one and
I have a video about this.
I will link it up top.
You do not trade on freaking below one
day.
Okay, just don't do it.
Not financial advice.
You can do whatever you want.
But if you made money on below one
day time frame consistently, you don't need me
go and watch other videos.
Okay, but most of you will still be
here because you are losing money and you
do regret your actions in the past now.
So with that out of the way, now,
let me show you how you can out
-compete yourself and 95% of other traders
who don't know what they're doing with a
very simple method.
Let me show you right now and I
will keep my promise of making this video
shorter than my other videos because I love
explaining everything.
That's why you subscribe to this channel.
But let's dive directly into the solution.
Okay, the solution is this.
Okay, you get a strategy that is good.
You automate the strategy and then you stick
to the strategy.
You don't change your plan every couple of
months, right?
You only change your plan every bear market.
You place your bets and then you let
it happen.
Okay, and next time you improve you improve
you improve but the chances of you making
more money than before are quite high because
you chose a good strategy.
Because your manual trading doesn't work.
Okay, so let's go through a couple of
strategies that you can actually use right now
after watching this video.
They are all free.
Okay, so listen, okay, listen, if you if
you didn't make this profit that I'm showing
you now on these strategies, then you should
consider using the strategies, right?
Because these strategies might be better than whatever
you've been doing before.
So if that's the case, why don't use
the strategies, right?
And because you don't have time to click
the button all the time, you automate it,
right?
That's the whole point.
Michael automates.
By the way, I changed the name of
the channel to Michael automates because that's what
I do, right?
Okay, this is the first strategy.
I want to show you it's called Gaussian
Channel Strategy.
Some of you might know it already from
my other videos.
It makes thousand seven hundred percent profit since
2018.
You can see here 2018 until when I
record this video with a max drawdown of
38.6%. That means that if you made
less money on Bitcoin than thousand seven hundred
percent, that's a 17x profit, then you should
consider using this strategy.
The next strategy is called Breakout Trend Follow
Strategy.
It made thousand four hundred percent profit a
bit less than the other one, but also
with a bit less max drawdown.
Well, not a lot less, but still and
what I really like is that it has
more profitable trades than the other one.
Now, you might ask yourself, listen, then I
take the other one, right, because it makes
more money, but yeah, sure.
It makes more money on Bitcoin.
But what if on Solana, this one is
better.
You have to just click around and play
with this, right?
And by the way, because I didn't tell
you before, this is all on the one
day chart.
Okay, the one day Bitcoin chart.
In this case, Bitcoin index chart.
I will zoom in and show you this
and that's where you get these numbers.
Okay, cool.
Now, let's look at another strategy and the
next strategy is called Halsoot Strategy.
Since 2018, it made 423% profit on
Bitcoin with a max drawdown of 70%.
Now, tell me if that's a good strategy
or not.
And you might ask yourself, why am I
showing you this stupid strategy?
Because it makes less money than the other
ones.
Well, because it might be better on other
assets.
Okay, so check this out.
I want to show you this exact same
strategy on Ethereum.
Now, on Ethereum, you can see it made
15x profit with 62% max drawdown.
Yes, it's high, but okay, Ethereum is also
quite volatile.
Now, the thing is, if I turn on
the Gaussian Channel Strategy, you will see the
Gaussian Channel actually made less profit on Ethereum
while the Halsoot Strategy made more.
Great!
No, because now you have more strategies you
can play with and you can pick the
best one.
The next strategy is one of my own
because it's actually very hard to find good
strategies on the Internet.
But the ones I showed you before will
definitely already change your game forever.
But let's check out this strategy.
Since 2018, like the other ones, it made
2400% profit on Bitcoin, 15% only
max drawdown and 63% profitable trades.
Let's go.
All right.
Now, the thing is that this strategy, yeah,
it's not free, whatever, but this is the
strategy I'm using.
Okay, I don't touch the trading interface.
Okay, I simply have automated the whole thing.
It's nice.
There are no emotions.
I don't waste my time checking the charts.
It's all awesome, right?
But honestly, if I did not have access
to this, it's fine.
I can just use the freaking Gaussian Channel
Strategy which already made a lot of money
because 17x, it's still awesome.
Now, how can you do pretty much the
same thing?
Well, you need to go to signum.money
and create an account.
Okay, click on try it now, create an
account and all of this stuff because then
you can take the trading signal from TradingView
and you can route it to your exchange
to buy and sell.
And that is what I do as well.
Now, let me show you in the Signum
interface where you can actually find these strategies
that I'm just showing you and more because
in the menu here on the top, we
have strategies for you.
You click on that and you arrive on
this page where you find the Gaussian Channel,
the breakout trend follower, the whole suit and
also the Ichimoku Cloud.
I didn't show you that but you can
use it yourself.
You click on it and it opens up.
You scroll all the way down and you
click on Add to Favorites, right?
After you added it to favorites, you will
find it here in your indicators and in
your favorite indicators and then you will have
it here.
How suit, Gaussian Channel, all of this stuff
will be there.
You click on it once to add it
to your chart and then you can see
the same as I do.
So it's very simple.
If you scroll down, you also find a
very short explanation on how to add this
strategy to your chart and as well to
auto trading, which is my own strategy, but
you don't need that.
Okay, because once you have access to these
strategies and to signum, you can start automating
and you can start changing your game today.
Okay, like right now and now what you
can do, you can go to my bots.
You can create a bot and you can
connect it to your exchange.
We're going to add Coinbase in a week
or so, not even a week two days
and so you can connect it and once
you have connected it, you can have all
you need here to copy paste into trading
view so you can automate it.
I don't want to explain this because we
already have video about this.
We have screenshots.
Everything is explained here, but really honestly guys,
the simplest thing to do is create a
freaking account on signum go to the strategies
page and pick a strategy and automate the
asset.
Okay, I mean like it's the easiest thing
ever and it will with high probability create
better results than anything else that you have
done before and listen, if that doesn't change
your game forever, then listen, I don't know.
Okay, you try you let me know, but
if you didn't make thousand seven hundred percent
profit like this strategy made here on Bitcoin
since 2018, then you need to do something
else with your life.
Okay, with your trading life.
Let me know down in the comments.
What do you think about this?
Try it out, but be patient.
Okay, because these strategies, they don't trade every
day, right?
That's the whole point.
That's why you're avoiding all the enemies on
the small time frame so you can make
money on the higher time frame.
Okay, so check the trades on the chart
and expect what the strategy has done in
the past, right?
So if it didn't trade every day, it
will not trade every day, right?
But if it made more money and protected
the portfolio better, then that's what you can
expect in the future as well.
With all of that in mind now, it's
your turn go and create your signum account
to start automating and if you have any
questions, we do have a telegram group where
we help people.
We already helped hundreds of people so we
can help you as well.
You'll be happy to hear that signum can
automate any strategy that you find on trading
view.
It can trade it with percentage numbers with
absolute numbers.
You will see what I mean once you
start using it and you can also automate
trades on trend lines that you draw yourself
on the chart.
Speaking of which, this is the next video
you should watch.