Hey traders, in this video I'll be showing
you 4 simple-to-learn trading strategies that's
able to generate $500 per day in profits.
And of course, these strategies are all backtested
to have a high win percentage, so you
can trust that they work.
And the best part is that I've laid
out specific instructions that you can easily follow,
so after watching this video, you can implement
these steps and start trading immediately.
So without further ado, let's move on with
the first strategy.
For this strategy, we're taking advantage of what's
called a stop-hunt in order to find
trade opportunities.
Now, for those of you who don't know
what a stop-hunt is, here's an example.
So, let's say you look at a chart
and you see the price rejecting an area
multiple times, so you draw a support level.
Next, as it approaches that level again, you
think to yourself, hmm, the price did reverse
from this support level in the past, so
maybe it could reverse from it once again.
Hoping for a reversal, you enter a buy
position.
Now, being the disciplined trader that you are,
you did forget your stop-loss, so you
placed it slightly below that support level.
However, instead of reversing from that level, price
instead went down hitting your stop-loss first
before reversing back up.
This is called a stop-hunt, and it
is purposely done by institutions to hunt the
stop-losses of retail traders.
Now, using the right technique, we can actually
use these stop-hunts to our advantage to
get high win-rate trade opportunities, and this
is how.
So, the first step is you want to
find an obvious key level.
This could either be a support or a
resistance level.
But remember, the key word here is obvious,
because you want to find a level where
many retail traders are also paying attention, which
is usually more susceptible to a stop-hunt.
Here, we can see the price went up
to this level and reversed from it, making
it an obvious resistance level.
The next step is to wait for the
price to approach that level again and break
out of it.
Once this happens, you take a closer look
at the price action that's happening at that
area.
So, you zoom in two timeframes below.
For example, currently we're on the 4-hour
chart, so let's zoom in into the 2
-hour chart.
Now, in the 2-hour chart, we can
actually see a large green candle breaking that
resistance area.
Now, a question arises.
How do we know if this will be
a stop-hunt or an actual breakout and
price did continue upwards?
So, the good thing about this strategy is
we could still make profits regardless of what's
going to happen.
So, what I do instead, as soon as
the price breaks this resistance area, I immediately
place a limit sell order below this key
level.
Now, for those of you who don't know
what a limit order is, it's simply just
an order to open a position at a
specific price.
So, only if price touches my limit order,
a sell position would open.
If it doesn't, then no position would open.
By doing this, if this breakout happens to
be a stop-hunt, then our sell order
would be triggered and we would make money
as the price reverses back down.
However, if this happens to be a real
breakout and price did continue upwards, our sell
order would not be triggered and we won't
lose any money.
Now, to add another layer to the strategy,
we can also place a limit buy order
above the breakout.
And the idea behind this is we're playing
both directions.
If this was a breakout, then our limit
buy order would get triggered and we would
make a profit as price continues to go
up.
However, if this was a stop-hunt, then
our limit sell order will be the one
that gets triggered and we would make profit
as price reverses back down.
Now, of course, there's still the risk that
price moves in the opposite direction after one
of our limit order is triggered.
That's why it's important to place a stop
-loss and profit target after one of them
is triggered.
Now, let's see which limit order would get
triggered.
As you can see, price moved downwards and
triggers our sell limit order which opens a
sell position.
After the sell position is opened, you place
a stop-loss in the middle of the
breakout candle and take profit at 4x stop
-loss.
And as you can see, price continued downwards
and hits our profit.
Let's move on to the second strategy.
So, for this next strategy, we're utilizing the
Fibonacci retracement tool but we'll be using it
slightly different from what is usually taught.
Now, for those of you who don't know
how the Fibonacci tool works, here's a quick
explanation.
So, it is simply a tool that is
used to identify where a pullback or a
retracement might end.
For example, if price moves upwards and forms
a slight retracement, we can apply the Fibonacci
retracement tool to know where this retracement might
end.
To do this, you drag the tool from
the swing low to the swing high.
Once applied, traders can observe these levels as
they often act as possible levels where the
retracement may end.
So, for this specific strategy, we're only using
the 0.618 and the 1.618 Fibonacci
level.
To do that, you go to the settings
of the Fibonacci tool and disable all the
other levels except the 0.618 and the
1.618. Once you've done that, your Fibonacci
tool should look like this.
Now, here's how you trade the strategy.
The first step is to look for a
price action where there's a trend and a
slight retracement like in this example.
Next, you apply the Fibonacci retracement tool on
that price action.
From here, we wait for the price to
pull back towards the 0.618 level and
try to see if the price shows some
type of rejection towards it.
To do that, we do a multi-timeframe
analysis by looking at lower timeframes to analyze
the price action further.
So, we're on the 4-hour timeframe, let's
zoom in into the 1-hour timeframe.
Now, in the 1-hour timeframe, we can
apply the MACD indicator for trend confirmation.
As you can see, the MACD indicator crossed
over upwards after price hits the 0.618
level which further confirms that the price will
likely bounce upwards from that level.
And so, we go back to the 4
-hour timeframe and enter a buy position.
The next step is we use the tool
once again, take the last highs of the
retracement, and drag it towards the lows of
the retracement.
And this is where the 1.618 level
comes into play.
We use it to set our target profit.
Once you've done that, you can let the
trade run.
And as you can see, price exactly hits
our profit target.
Now, let's move on to the third strategy.
So, unlike the other strategies on this list,
this one is a scalping strategy and we'll
trade it on the 1-minute timeframe using
an indicator called the CCI.
And so, based on backtesting results, the CCI
is particularly effective for identifying divergences.
But for those of you who don't know
how to spot divergences, here's a quick example.
So, usually, an indicator will display the same
signal as the price movement.
If the price forms higher highs, the indicator
will also display higher highs.
However, there are setups where it's the opposite.
For example, price forms higher lows but the
indicator displays lower lows instead.
And this is called a divergence.
Specifically, this is a bullish hidden divergence, presenting
a good opportunity to take a buy position.
There are multiple types of divergences and you
can use this graphic as a guide to
identify them.
Now, I'm going to prove that this strategy
works by doing a live trading session.
So first, you want to apply the CCI
indicator onto your charts.
And if you're using the SimpleFX platform like
I am, you can go to the indicator
section and select CCI.
After that, go to the 1-minute chart
and find a setup where the price forms
a divergence.
You can use the search menu here to
find different charts, whether it be crypto, forex,
stocks, or others.
So, after some searching, I came across this
setup on the Bitcoin USD 1-minute chart.
Price formed lower lows but the bullish divergence.
So you enter a buy position.
To do that, click the buy button here
and set your position size for this trade.
Next, for our take profit target, we can
set it at this minor resistance level at
64379.
So you insert that.
Now for our stop loss, we can set
it at slightly below the support area at
64209.
And insert that as well.
Here, you can see how much you'd make
if price hits our profit target and how
much we'd lose if the price hits our
stop loss.
Next, click submit to open the trade and
let the trade run.
And as you can see, price hits our
take profit and we made $90 profit in
a couple of minutes from this one setup.
You can keep repeating this strategy over and
over again as long as you spot a
divergence.
And by the way, if you're looking for
a broker to win more trades, I highly
recommend clicking the link in the description for
SimpleFX.
They're very simple to use, have all the
tools you need to make an analysis, and
you can trade multiple assets on one platform.
And if you use the link in my
description, you'll get a $40 deposit bonus if
you deposit at least $100 into your account.
Now let's move on to the fourth strategy.
So this one is one of my most
profitable strategy that has allowed me to scale
my trading account considerably.
And this is how.
So we know that markets are only trending
about 30% of the time, while remains
within a range about 70% of the
time.
This means that prices aren't always moving towards
a certain trend.
Most of the time, they move overall sideways
while deviate between certain levels.
Because of this, if you know a strategy
to trade range markets, you'll be able to
generate more profitable signals.
And here's how this strategy works.
The first step is to identify a range
market, which is simply a market that moves
overall sideways.
Now, during a range market, you should be
able to identify both support and resistance levels
within that range.
For example, if price rejects an upper level
multiple times, that's your resistance.
And if it rejects a lower level, that's
your support.
Now, here's how I trade range markets differently
from most traders.
Instead of only trading at these major key
levels, I also take advantage of the price
action that's happening in this middle area.
And to do that, I draw another line
in the exact middle of these major key
levels.
This is what I call the midline.
So, using the midline that we drew, we
can now see that the range is divided
between two zones.
The upper zone and the bottom zone.
So, we know that as long as price
stays within this range, only two things could
happen.
Either it stays on this upper zone or
switch to this bottom zone.
And it will keep doing this until eventually
price breaks out of the range.
But for this strategy, we only trade if
the price still remains within this range.
So, here's how it works.
The first step is to identify where the
current price is positioned.
In this example, it is currently in the
upper zone after it rejected this resistance level.
Next, you wait for the price to approach
the middle line.
Now, remember what I said earlier.
As long as the price is still inside
this range, it's either going to stay on
this upper zone and bounce upwards from this
middle line or switch to this bottom zone
and breaks this middle line downwards.
In order to know that, we need to
analyze the price action as it approaches this
middle line.
So, a rule of thumb to remember is
that price will likely move towards the bottom
level if it manages to break the middle
line decisively.
For example, if there's one giant momentum candle
crossing down or if there are multiple red
candles.
However, if we manage to see some type
of rejection in this middle line, there's a
high chance that the price will likely remain
above the middle line and retest the resistance
level.
So, let's see what happens to the price
next.
As you can see, it briefly broke through
the middle line but managed to bounce back
up, indicating that there's a slight rejection in
this middle area.
However, because this is only a slight rejection,
we still need more confirmation.
So, let's not rush to take a position
and observe what happens next.
Here, we can see that the price briefly
moved downwards all the way here, but buyers
pushed it back up before the candle manages
to close, which forms this long wick below
this candle.
So now, after multiple attempts of breaking below
the middle line, price failed to do so,
meaning there's a chance that the price will
actually remain above the upper level and retest
this resistance level.
So, this is a good opportunity to enter
a buy position.
As for your profit target, set it at
the resistance level and stop loss at slightly
below your entry.
And as you can see, price went upwards
towards the resistance level and hits our tick
profit.
So guys, for profitable strategies like this, you
would also need a good broker to execute
these trades, which is why I partnered with
SimpleFX to make your trading easier.
SimpleFX is a broker that lets you trade
any instrument, including stocks, forex, crypto, and more,
all in one platform.
They're very simple to use and they also
come with a built-in trading view chart
so you can analyze trades and execute them
within the same platform.
They have no minimum deposit, which means you
can start trading with as little as $1.
They also have some of the lowest fees
on the market.
And if you sign up using my link
below, you'll get a free $40 bonus in
trading capital if you deposit at least $100.
Of course, you'll get more rewards as you
deposit more.
So, big thanks to SimpleFX for helping me
make this video possible.
That's all for today.
Thank you so much for watching and I'll
see you in the next video.