So I turned $10 into over $1,300
in about a month to prove it's not
luck and that the only thing that matters
is your skill in trading.
You don't need a large amount of money
to make good returns.
So I want to show you the full
process I use to flip this small account
and I also just wanted to prove that
trading can be simpler than you think.
You just need one strategy, trade one pair
at one time and it's easy.
Like it doesn't have to be overly complicated.
Okay, first we're just going to cover risk
management.
So how much do I risk each trade?
What is the risk percentage, lot size, all
that sort of stuff.
Risk reward versus win rate, you have to
understand this.
You need to have a trading journal to
track everything to understand your win rate, your
risk reward, your average max drawdown of your
own unique system.
I have it all tracked down so I
know my win rate is 80% plus.
So I target around 1.5, I have
an 80% win rate so it's very
profitable.
But the thing is here, I focus mainly
on win rate.
A lot of people say to focus on
risk all that sort of stuff but I've
never found it helped me.
I'm more confident when I'm winning more often
and I trade better when I'm more confident.
So that's just what I focus on.
Smaller, more consistent moves, I trade in a
way that consistently gets more wins every single
day.
They're still having a positive risk to reward,
it's just focusing more on those probabilities.
Why is that?
A lot of people say to risk one
to two.
So have two times the reward of your
risk.
Yes, but likely everyone that I've coached and
mentored, they have around a 50% win
rate if they're succeeding really well with that.
But with a one to two, you have
a 97% chance of six losses in
a row.
Are you comfortable with taking six losses in
a row?
For a smaller risk to reward, a higher
win rate system like mine, higher probability scalping,
it's a 80 plus percent win rate.
I have a 86% chance of two
losses in a row.
I'm okay, really comfortable taking two losses in
a row.
So I just focus on small, consistent scalps
with a high win rate.
It's easier to execute on and it's easy
to be confident and trade well when it's
unlikely that I'll take more than three losses
in a row.
So understanding your win rate, it will help
you understand how many losing trades in a
you can expect.
And then once you know that, you can
then decide on how much to risk.
So my risk on a small account is
always going to be higher.
My leverage was one to 500.
So I had a good amount of leverage,
but I don't care if I blow $10.
So I can treat this small account like
a big account and risk 50% or
30% mainly.
So it was around 30 to 50%
risk.
Because I have a really high win rate,
I can risk a lot higher.
I can risk 30% pretty comfortably.
If you watch any of my Instagram reels,
you know I close my losses early.
So it's never actually that 50, 30%
loss.
It's a little bit less.
So I always close my losses early.
I always manage risk aggressively and I always
look to add to win.
If you have a lower win rate around
60, 50%, your percentage should decrease maybe around
10% or 20%, depending on your win
rate.
So the amount you risk should always be
based off your win rate.
You can only know your win rate if
you journal your trades.
So you better journal your trades.
I've never really cared about risk towards.
I think it's kind of overrated to target
one to twos, one to threes.
So my average risk reward is around one
to 1.5, but sometimes I take one
to one, sometimes negative.
But I focus on the probability of each
move and I always look to manage my
losses more aggressively, add to my winners.
So it still gives me a positive risk
reward.
It gives me a lot higher of a
win rate because I'm trading based on probabilities.
I'm not trying to force a risk to
reward on a market on conditions that actually
might not be the right way.
It's all about probabilities and it's consistent.
If you want to be consistently profitable, you
first need to be consistent.
That means doing the same actions every single
day.
If you're trading multiple different pairs at multiple
different times, using multiple different strategies, you're not
going to be consistent and you're probably not
going to make money.
Also embrace uncertainty.
Like this account flip, I've blown multiple accounts
before this.
And if you're going to do this as
well, accept the likelihood that you might blow
that account.
Nothing is certain in trading and you have
to accept that.
And so risk management is closely tied to
your technical analysis or strategy because if you
have a higher win rate, you can risk
more.
If it's lower, you can risk less.
It's all about understanding your approach, the pros
and cons of it, and then adjusting your
risk accordingly.
So I use pure price action, a three
-step approach, and always try to stack those
conferences to put probabilities in my favor.
So I trade at the same time every
single day on gold using the same strategy.
So that is the second hour of Asia.
That's 11 a.m. Australian Eastern Standard Time.
And I trade the exact same way every
single day and aim to take the same
type of trades.
So I trade live with my Discord every
single day at the exact same time, that
second hour of Asia, and catch the same
sort of moves.
So sales on gold using some DXY correlation,
which we'll go over as well.
Exact same trades, exact same time.
10.52, 11 a.m. It's always going
to be around 11 a.m. Because I
guarantee you, if you just trade at the
exact same time every single day and trade
on the same pair, you're going to see
the same things happening.
I'm going to go through some examples of
how the exact same thing happened every single
day for the past three days in a
row.
So I took the same trade pretty much
three days in a row, and it's really
easy to be consistent when you're just doing
the same things.
So this is how you get a really
high win rate.
You just niche down into one small thing,
and you get really good at that.
It's simply this.
It's a three-step approach.
You have your direction, you have an area
of interest, and then you have an entry
model.
This can be a shift, a type three,
or could be like a break-in retest,
volume shifting in your direction, could be like
a break of a low, volume shifting in
direction.
I just use that simple three-step approach,
direction, area of interest, entry model, stacking probabilities,
stacking confidences in my favor.
So I break price action down into counter
behavior and market structure.
So counter behavior is how an individual candle
moves throughout the life cycle of a candle.
So this is a good example here.
When we're moving bullish, and we have a
bullish candle close above a recent high and
low, I'm expecting that to continue moving bullish,
but I first expect it to create a
bottom wick in that first half of that
candle.
So if this is a day, I expect
it to be bearish first to create a
wick, fill in this body, and then push
bullish.
If it's bearish, I expect it to create
a top wick and then flip and push
bearish.
So in this scenario here, since it's bullish,
it should open, create a bottom wick first,
and then push bullish.
That's just because price tends to fill its
moves.
It's a push and pull between buyers and
sellers.
So I'm trading at that second hour here,
that second hour of Asia.
So at that new 4-hour candle, that's
what I'm trading.
So we had this 4-hour close bearish.
So I was expecting it to create a
top wick first on that 4-hour candle,
and then drive down to create that bottom
wick on that daily candle.
So using that counter behavior on different time
frames to find direction.
So the first step finding direction, I'm using
counter behavior, bit of market structure, because when
we're over bullish on high time frame, especially
for Asia session, will be bearish first to
create a bottom wick, and then push bullish.
If I'm looking for a sell, I'm looking
for the 4-hour to first create a
top wick, a reaction to some highs, maybe
after it takes out a high, looking for
a reversal off that.
So low time frame bearish, high time frame
bullish, something like this.
This is what to my Discord when I
was trading with them live this morning.
And then I use DXY correlation as well.
This is what it was looking like.
You had a break of a low, a
break of a high, the reaction to an
area of interest, but this would be a
type 3.
So type 3 is just a shift in
market structure where you're breaking a low, then
breaking a high, one coming in.
So just looking for a continuation of that
there.
So we're currently pulling back, reaction to this
high.
So I was just waiting for that there.
So I'm not taking a trade in these
conditions because it's kind of low time frame
range bound.
I'm waiting for it to create a top
wick on that 4-hour candle first.
Creating a top wick on that 4-hour
candle.
You had a break of a high, a
strong reaction to that area there.
Really strong reaction.
And what was DXY looking like here?
You're having a bit of a reaction to
around this area of interest.
And then as soon as we broke this
high here, this little high there, then the
next one, you have a break of that
high there.
That's looking pretty bullish for continuation of this
overall shift.
So you had a break of a low,
break of a high, a type 3 continuation
with gold looking bearish.
You had volume coming in.
This is looking pretty nice.
You also had the 4-hour looking like
it was going to flip bearish.
So this is the 4-hour candle flipping
bearish there.
So really nice quick little scalp.
Stop behind the high, targeting previous low of
the range for a nice pretty clear clean
trade there.
And so that was the 2nd hour of
Asia using that direction area of interest, using
market structure, using candle behaviour.
Then an entry model such as volume coming
in for a reversal and a DXY type
3 pushing bullish.
So you can look at entry models on
DXY and use them to take trades on
gold.
This is why I love trading correlation.
So at the exact same time or around
the exact same time, the day before this,
you had pretty much the exact same thing
happen.
You had the 4-hour open, immediately go
bullish.
It took a little buy before it created
that top wick, react to this previous area
of interest.
And then we had a pullback, a type
3 shift here.
Type 3 shift, entering on that pullback, a
reaction for a nice little scalp that continued
further on.
And that looks like that.
And then the day before that, at the
exact same time as well, that 2nd hour
of Asia, around that 4-hour open, took
the exact same type of trade.
You first opened, immediately created a top wick
there.
Then it flipped, took a sell on that
candle flip for a nice little scalp.
So 3 days in a row, I took
the exact same win.
And this is what consistency means.
This is what I say when if you
want to make money from trading, you shouldn't
focus on trying to win.
You should just focus on doing the exact
same thing every single day.
It's really easy, simple.
This is what trading is.
I see what's happening and then I trade
it.
Just going back to technical analysis, it's that
purely price action, candle behavior, market structure, that
3-step approach, direction, area of interest, entry
model, and then looking to stack, align different
confluences in your favor.
Really simple, easy.
And then using that gold and DXY correlation.
I love trading that gold and DXY correlation.
It has a really big increase to my
win rate, around 16%.
And it has an inverse relationship.
It's really nice for confirming as well.
If you actually want to be able to
do this for yourself, you need to be
journaling your trades.
So as I said recently, the easiest way
to improve your system, to improve your strategy
is just to journal your trades, do more
of what works and less of what doesn't.
So I've journaled around 300 trades.
This is the most recent iteration of that.
If I just go to using DXY correlation,
that 56% win rate goes into a
73% win rate.
Such a simple way to improve my system,
just using DXY correlation, using to stack that
confluence.
And then if I just look to take
a 1 minute type 3, a shift, that
73% win rate goes into an 83
% win rate.
So this is how you get a high
win rate.
You journal your trades, you focus on what
works, taking a trade with DXY correlation, 1
minute type 3, shift of structure, that gives
me an 83% win rate.
And you can keep refining this, focusing on
what works.
If you want to be profitable, you need
to be doing this, having a journal, that's
having objective data, also tracking the trades as
well, taking screenshots to trade your subjective data,
to be able to review those trades, look
at what works.
So this is a nice type 3 shift.
You make a high, break a low, enter
on the pullback, pretty much the exact same
trade as yesterday.
And then this is how you do the
exact same thing, get consistent, make consistent money
from trading.
You can get really high win rates just
through refining this.
Like I have a setup here, so I
have a setup here that has a 93
% win rate just on two little small
variables.
So it's really important that you refine your
approach, refine your system, using a journal.
There's a link to this journal in the
description below as well, that you can check
out.
So if you take anything from this, I
focus on probabilities, a small risk-to-reward,
using that 3-step approach, stacking confluences, and
trading at the same time every single day.
So I could only flip this account using
this trading journal, like I wouldn't have understood
my win rate, my risk-to-reward, what
confluences actually resulted in a high win rate,
such as the DXY, the type 3 shift.
So this is why you need to be
journaling your trades.
Record it, analyze the confluences, see how they
affect the outcome of a trading journal, see
how they affect the outcome of each individual
trade, track the outcomes, view and then reflect
that, refine.
And this is how you become profitable.
This exact process here is how you become
profitable.
No strategy really is going to get around
this.
You're not just going to pick up a
strategy straight away and make it profitable.
You have to put in the work, you
have to journal the trades, you have to
understand and slowly improve that win rate through
taking hundreds of trades, refining it slowly, all
that sort of stuff.
So keep it consistent, keep it simple.
The biggest learning I found in my trading,
the biggest aha moment was just to keep
it simple.
Define what your approach is, it can be
how do you define direction, how do you
define an area of interest, make it as
simple and as easy to replicate as possible.
And then test them using your journal and
see just what works, see what works.
Not everything is going to work.
And then the main basis of my approach
is just to, I've identified all the factors
that result in a positive expectancy.
So always looking to take a trade with
correlation, with a market structure shift, all that
sort of stuff.
I can assign weights to those and I
can just look to stack as many of
those probabilities, those confluences in my favor.
Stacking time frames, using timing, trading at the
same time, using the same pair, using the
same strategy, keeping it as simple and as
easy as possible to execute.
That is the key.
If you just do that, I guarantee you,
when you put in the work, you will
be profitable.
And then focusing on embracing a probabilistic mindset,
that means acknowledging that no trade is 100
% certain.
You can take the best trade set up
in the world and it can still lose
and that's okay.
Just focusing on your process.
I didn't focus on trying to flip $10
into $1,000 as quickly as possible.
I just focused on taking the best trades
and that was a happy accident that I
made money.
Because I could have easily blown the account
if I got unlucky or if just taking
off the conditions weren't great.
But the conditions on gold have been amazing
in the past month.
I've been trading the exact same way the
whole month and it's been paying off.
So I'm still managing risk aggressively.
I'm closing my losing trades before they hit
stop loss because I know if it's going
to hit stop loss, the bottom's moving against
you.
I'm always looking to manage risk and lose
less than I initially risked.
So what do 95% of traders do?
Well, they fail.
But they also lose more than they initially
risk through adding two loses, through moving their
stop loss.
I just simply do the opposite to be
a winning trader.
It's really that simple.
And then always focusing on continuous learning.
Learning from each loss you take because I
did take losses.
I didn't let them affect me.
I see value in them, if not more
than wins, because I learn more from losing
trades.
And learning is more valuable than a couple
of dollars.
So if you just use a simple approach,
it can be parts of my strategy.
It can be this psychology.
It can be the journal, which I think
is the most important.
It's actually possible to then have these big
flips, taking a small amount of money into
a bigger amount of money and be profitable.
It could be using this to pass prop
firms, using it to grow or compound your
personal account.
You don't have to go for big percentage
gains because it is high risk.
But yeah, hopefully this helped.
If you liked this video, like the video.
And if you want to see more, subscribe
because I will be posting more content in
the future as well.
And if you want to trade with us
every single day, every single morning, there's a
link in the description below to join the
discord where we trade at the exact same
time every single day, take wins.
I'm kind of on a win streak at
the moment.
We'll see how long it lasts.
But we all catch wins, lots of nice
profits around there as well.
So yeah.
See ya.