I wanna share with you the 3 high
win rate scalping strategies that will get you
to making your first 10k per month.
And if you have a small trading account,
these strategies will be perfect for you.
The first step is to identify your supply
and demand zones.
And you can do that by identifying any
one of these 4 types of supply and
demand zones.
So as you can see, there is reversal
and continuation zones.
Let's go from left to right.
So the first reversal supply demand zone is
your rally base drop.
It's basically when price goes up, consolidate and
reverse and head back down.
And then for a continuation supply zone, that
means price will be going down, starts consolidating
and then eventually it breaks out of the
consolidation and continue going down in the downtrend.
And then for your demand zones, this is
what a reversal will look like.
Your drop base rally.
So it's basically when price drops, starts consolidating
and starts reversing and heading back up.
And then for your continuation, it's basically your
rally base rally.
It's basically when price goes up, consolidate and
then continue going up even further.
Now, these are the 4 supply and demand
zones, namely your rally base drop, drop base
drop, drop base rally and rally base rally.
Now, if you want to learn more about
supply and demand, check out this video next.
So in this strategy, we will combine both
price action and supply and demand because these
two concepts have been proven to have the
highest win rate and they are also my
favorite trading strategies.
Now, the first strategy is the momentum candlestick
strategy.
So as you can see, like I said,
the first thing you want to do is
to mark up your supply and demand zones.
And we can see right here, price is
approaching a supply zone that we have drawn
earlier.
So at supply zone, we know that there
will be sellers waiting to shut the price
down.
So what we want to do is to
wait for some sort of bearish price action,
some sort of signs that tell us that
the sellers are entering the market and the
bullish buyers are going away.
So what I want you to look out
for is this long wick doji candlestick.
So in a supply zone, you want to
look out for a candlestick with a long
upper wick.
And then in a demand zone, you want
to look out for a candlestick with a
long lower wick.
So what does this candlestick mean?
This means that at some point of time,
the buyers try to push the price all
the way up to this level right here
before the sellers come in and say, hell
no and push the price all the way
back down here so that candlestick actually ended
up closing somewhere right around here.
This signifies that the sellers are entering the
market right now or if not, they have
already entered the market and that is exactly
why price is getting rejected at this key
supply zone right here.
Right now, the selling momentum is about to
come in and overtake the whole buyer's momentum.
Now, this is the first sign of sellers
entering the market, the first sign of selling
pressure and selling momentum.
So if you want to play it safe,
what you can even do is to evaluate
the next few candlesticks that's going to form
because you might not be confident enough to
enter immediately on this trade.
It's okay, you want to play it the
safe way, play it the low risk way.
So what I'll recommend you to do is
to actually evaluate the next few candlesticks.
So these next few candlesticks have just been
formed.
Let's just look at what it's trying to
tell us, right?
It's all about understanding candlesticks, understanding candlesticks momentum
and pressure.
Over here, we see a doji candlestick that's
being formed after this long upper wick candle
is formed.
This tells us that there is a lot
of indecision, right?
Right now, the sellers and the buyers, they
are fighting a war right now.
They are fighting a tug of war and
they have no idea which one will win.
Which brings me to the next candlestick.
Next candlestick gave us another red candlestick and
another red candlestick.
This just clear as day tells us that
the sellers have managed to enter the market.
So over here, that is when you can
potentially enter for a sell position.
Basically, you want to enter for the trade
when you see some sort of bearish price
action at a supply zone.
So entering here will be the safe way.
But if you want to get a sniper
entry, what you could have done earlier is
to enter where price has formed this long
upper wick candle.
And then this is when you can place
your stock loss above this key supply zone.
And I'll recommend you to place your take
profit at the next opposite zone, which will
be some sort of demand zone that is
like somewhere right around here.
That is where I personally place my take
profit.
So once again, make sure that you have
at least a 1 is to 3 risk
to reward ratio.
This means that you can be wrong three
times and just win one trade and you
will be able to break even.
So let's look at how this trade play
out.
You can see price eventually goes down and
smash our take profit.
Now let's look at an example in an
uptrend.
So over here, what is this demand zone?
This is your rally base and potentially, it
could be making a rally somewhere right around
here.
So what we can do is to mark
up our demand zone somewhere right around here.
And you can see price has managed to
come back down to this demand zone.
And like I said, what we want to
do is to wait for some sort of
bullish price action at this demand zone.
And that is when we can enter the
trade.
So even though price has managed to come
back down to this demand zone, I'm not
going to be entering yet.
I want to wait for some sort of
candlestick confirmation, which brings me to this candlestick
right here.
Now this is your long lower week candle,
right?
This is what we call a pin buy
if I'm not wrong.
So what this candlestick means is that the
sellers try to push the price all the
way down here.
They tried, right?
They tried to break past this demand zone,
but that's all they did.
They tried.
They did not manage to succeed because the
buyers have came into the market and pushed
the price all the way up.
The bulls are winning.
Clap for the bulls.
ChicagoPulls96, Mike Jordan.
But back to trading.
Basically, right now, buyers have entered the market.
That is the first sign of buying momentum
and buying pressure.
So what you can do is to enter
for a buy right here.
And like I said, if you want to
play it safe, by all means, go ahead.
Wait for the next few candles.
You can see the next candle.
It gives us this huge candle.
Not really huge actually.
A medium-sized green bullish candlestick with a
nice, nice body.
Not as nice as mine, but basically, this
is when you can enter for a buy
if you want to play it the safe
way.
For me, I personally have entered immediately after
price gave me this long low-weight candle
at this demand zone.
And then that is when you can place
a stop loss below this demand zone and
place a take profit at the next key
supply zone, which could be right here.
This little demand zone, supply zone right here.
Let me just change the color because I
have OCD.
So there you have it, guys.
So you can see price went up, go
up, hit our take profit, and we call
it a day.
I go home, go to the bank, take
some money out, treat my family to some
nice dinner.
Now, don't worry if you still don't get
it yet.
If you have been watching my videos, you
will know that I will always give you
guys more examples and explain it in a
clearer and more simple way so that you
can gain a better understanding.
So over here, you can see we have
a demand zone right here and price has
just did its drop.
So right now, we know that this is
a demand zone.
So we are waiting for your drop base
ready, right?
So that is when we can continue to
wait, wait out for some sort of bullish
price action.
You can see that is exactly what we
had, right?
Our beautiful long-legged candlestick right here.
Long legs.
So over here, when price gave us this
long low candle, we know that the buyers
have entered the market.
So we can enter for a buy right
here, place a stop loss below this demand
zone and place a take profit at the
next key level, the next key supply zone
even.
One to two, let's get it.
You can see price eventually goes up, smash
or take profit as simple as that.
So the example was more risky because we
entered immediately when price gave us the long
weak candle.
But let's try the more played safe, the
more less risky way, the less the more
pushy way.
So right here, price is making your rally
base drop at this supply zone.
So this is our first step, right?
We identify your supply zone somewhere right around
here.
See supply zone right here.
So what we can do next is to
wait for price to get this supply zone
and show us some sort of bearish price
action.
And then that is when you can enter
for the trade.
So you still wait and wait and you
can see right here, price managed to go
up and it actually got rejected by the
supply zone.
How do we know you got rejected?
Because that is your long upper weak, right?
Like I said, they tried, the bulls tried
to overtake the bears but the bears are
just way too strong, right?
Now, since we are doing the played safe
way, I won't necessarily enter for the trade
right here after price gave me this long
weak candle.
Let's evaluate the next few candlesticks.
So you can see this is another doji,
like some sort of doji candlestick and then
followed by another weak candlestick and you can
see there is one, two, two red candlesticks
so far, right?
Some sort of seller's momentum is coming in.
There's a momentum shift somewhere right around here
and boom, there we have it guys.
Immediately after this few candlesticks have been formed,
right?
And after the long candlestick has been formed,
the bears have came in and overtake the
whole market and just push the price all
the way down but make no mistake because
if you look at this candlestick, there is
actually a long upper weak.
So what happened here?
Basically, price got pushed all the way up
because the bulls wanted to make a second
attempt at breaking past this key level and
then once again, the bears decided to come
in, the sellers come in and say hell
no once again and push the price all
the way down and it ended up closing
right here.
Now ladies and gentlemen, if you still don't
know that this is a sell trade, I
don't know what to say to you.
You must be an absolutely idiot.
So as you can see, if you enter
for a sell right here and you place
your take profit like at this demand zone
that we have right here, this green little
demand zone, right?
It could be a little bit too late.
It could be a little bit too late
because now if you enter for a trade
right here, your stop loss must be all
the way up here and your take profit
will only be like right here.
So it's like not really worth it, right?
It's not really worth it to enter for
this trade.
That is why if you want to enter
for this trade, you have entered somewhere right
around here.
Somewhere right around here when these next few
candlesticks have gave you the confirmation that sellers
have been entering into the market or like
I said, sniper entry will be right here.
Now you don't necessarily need to find long
weak candlesticks because they can be quite hard
to spot.
Sometimes.
So the first step will always be the
same and that is to identify your supply
and demand zones.
So right here, we can see that there
is a supply zone right here because there
is obviously there's a lot of sellers at
this area here, right?
Now this could be your rally base drop.
So over here, we can see that price
is consolidating at this area here and you
can see that there is a lot of
candlestick wicks.
You can see all these are candlestick wicks.
All these are a lot of candlestick wicks.
So what does this tell us?
When you see multiple wicks, this tell us
that there is a lot, a lot of
uncertainty.
There is a lot of indecision.
And when you notice all these candlesticks right
here, they all have a long upper wick
candle and they have a small candlestick body.
And just now I've already explained to you
what this long upper wick candlesticks mean, right?
So obviously this tell us that there's a
lot of selling pressure, a lot of selling
momentum and price could potentially collapse right now.
When you're looking for multiple wick rejections, make
sure that you look for at least three
multiple wicks.
At least three candlestick wicks.
One, two, three.
Three wicks, good to go.
But basically the reason why that it was
even multiple wicks is because price has tried
to challenge this key supply zone multiple times,
right?
The buyers tried.
The buyers tried to push the price up
but they failed one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight.
Eight times, right?
Eight times they failed miserably.
And since they failed so many times, you
will know that this is a very strong
supply zone, right?
The sellers are waiting to literally shoot the
whole shit and get it all the way
to the floor.
I don't even have any idea what I'm
talking about here.
But basically when you see multiple wick rejections
at a supply zone, enter for a sell.
So this is where I'll potentially enter for
a sell, place a stop loss above this
multiple wicks here or you can even place
it above this key supply zone.
And then same thing, take profit at the
next key zone, right?
The next key demand zone or basically the
next key level.
And you can see price immediately just collapse
all the way down.
Here's another example.
Right here we can draw a key demand
zone because there was a drop base rally.
And right now we could be expecting to
see price do the same thing because price
has just been dropping and dropping and you
can start to see like the momentum starts
fading away, right?
The candlesticks are getting smaller and wicks are
starting to form.
So we could be expecting price to come
down to this area here.
The sellers will start to show some sort
of weakness and then that is when we
can potentially enter for a buy.
So right here we are waiting to see
what price does at this key demand zone.
And you can see, okay, doji candlestick, another
wick candlestick and another candlestick wick.
Guys, like I said, it must look for
at least three candlestick wicks, right?
This signifies there is multiple wick rejections at
this key demand zone.
So very, very strong demand zone.
And that is when we can potentially enter
for a buy right here, when price has
shown us multiple wick rejections at this key
demand zone.
Place a stop loss below this demand zone,
take profit all the way up at the
next key supply zone, somewhere right around here.
Now, obviously if you place a take profit
all the way up here, it's gonna take
quite long to reach there.
It could be taking up to an hour
or so.
So what I can even do is to
place at this key level right here, this
key level here, that price has broken past
this support level and now it could potentially
be a resistance level.
So that is when you can place your
take profit right here.
And then look at what happened next.
You can see price starts to go up,
go up and go somewhere now around our
take profit area right here and it starts
to consolidate, right?
Starts to consolidate.
Once again, observe the price action.
What does this tell us?
This tell us that this buying momentum could
be fading away, right?
Because price doesn't have the strength to reach
this area here.
So what I can even do is to
manually take profit somewhere right around this area
here because now you can start to see
like, oh, the candlesticks are getting smaller and
smaller.
There's not much momentum left, right?
So manually go close the trade.
Now for this strategy, we will be using
the eight exponential moving average.
These are the settings.
You can copy them if you want.
Now, same thing.
First step is to identify your supply and
demand zone and I can identify a demand
zone being formed right here because price has
just did its drop base and it could
potentially be doing a rally soon.
So right now, what we want to do
is to wait for the moving average to
cross over the candlesticks and then that is
when we can potentially enter for a buy.
So right now we are still waiting and
you can see somewhere right around here, the
candlesticks has crossed over the moving average.
What does it mean?
This means that a reversal is prone to
happen.
A reversal is about to happen.
You can see before that, the candlesticks are
all below the white line, which is the
moving average.
And now the candlesticks have crossed over the
white line and they are now above the
moving average.
So easily enter for a buy somewhere right
around here where there was a moving average
crossover, stop loss below this key demand zone.
And if I take profit, I like to
place it at the next supply zone.
Like I said, there's a supply zone right
here, right?
E clear as day.
This is the supply zone because there was
a rally base drop.
Yeah, very strong demand zone right here.
So that is when we can place our
take profit all the way up here.
And let's not waste my time.
So just go up there and smash our
take profit.
Obviously, this is actually a little bit longer.
Yeah, this is actually a little bit longer
for your take profit to hit because understand
that it's gonna take you a few hours
for this trade to play out.
So instead of placing your take profit here,
what you could have done is that you
can place your take profit somewhere right around
here where there was another little supply zone
right here.
Yeah, so this will be a much more
faster trade.
But for me, when I'm scalping, I'm more
of a mix between a scalper and an
intraday trader.
So I'm perfectly fine with moving my take
profit up here and having like a 40,
30 to 40 pips take profit.
And you can see price eventually went up
there, break past the supply zone.
So after you have taken profit from this
trade, guess what?
You should be looking for the next opportunity.
So over here, what we can see is
that price is forming your supply zone right
here, right?
There is a supply zone being formed right
here.
You can see super long upper wick right
And then there is multiple rejections at this
key zone that we have right here.
So what we can do is that knowing
that this is a supply zone, we have
to wait for the moving average to cross
over.
And that is exactly what price gave us.
Previously, the candlesticks are above the moving average.
And then over here, that is when the
candlesticks start to cross below the moving average.
Now that's the first confluence.
The second confluence is that if you observe
closely, there is your multiple wick rejections right
here.
So multiple wick rejections.
And then there is also your long upper
wick right here.
Now we have all the confluences in the
world for us to enter for a sell
right here.
Moving average cross over, long upper wick candle,
multiple wick rejections, clear as day that price
is about to collapse.
So that is when you can enter for
the trade right here based on stop loss
above this supply zone, take profit all the
way down at this next demand zone that
I have right here.
Now, like I said, understand that this will
be more of an intraday trade already if
you do decide to trade this way.
But if you are more of a scalper,
feel free to take profit like somewhere right
around here, right at the next key zone.
And as you can see, price goes down,
smash your take profit and you can call
it a day.
But for me, I'll most likely like to
have the take profit all the way down
here.
And you can see price eventually went down
and smashed out my take profit.
Now this is more of like a sniper
entry type shit, right?
This is really how I really get like
my low risk, high reward ratios where people
are always asking me, oh my God, why
are you entering on like such small time
frame when you are intraday trading or when
you are swing trading?
It's because you can get nice sniper entries
like this with very, very high precision.
Now over here, price has came down to
our demand zone.
What do we do next?
We look for the next opportunity once we
get out of this one, right?
So right now, once again, I'm waiting for
some sort of moving average crossover, right?
Some sort of moving average crossover like this,
right?
Clear as day.
Moving average crossover right here.
You can enter for a buy right here.
Stop loss below this key demand zone.
And once again, guys, look for other confluences
as well.
You can see there is a multiple weak
candlestick rejections right here at a demand zone
and also a moving average crossover.
Easily three confluence.
Easily enter for a buy right here.
Take profit at this next supply zone that
we have right here.
See price hit our take profit right here
and I can see potentially go up up
to the next key supply zone that we
have right here, right?
What you could have even done for this
trade is that you can take partial profits.
So when price reach this first supply zone,
close half the trade.
And then when price reach this second supply
zone, close the other half of that trade.
Now for me, I don't personally like to
take partial profits anymore.
What I like to do instead is to
scale in because when I'm winning, I want
to get that position bigger and make more
money.
So what I could have done in this
trade is that when price form another demand
zone somewhere right around here.
Somewhere right around here, there was another demand
zone, right?
So this is when I will be looking
to enter for the trade.
Enter my second trade.
Scale into this position.
Remember, my first position could be somewhere right
around here, right?
Remember, my first position is where I entered
somewhere right around here where the moving average
has crossed over.
And let's say my overall take profit is
all the way up at this second supply
zone.
Now over here, when price has formed a
new demand zone, where price is really base
and it's about to rally to continue this
uptrend, I'll potentially be looking for another long
trade, right?
So that is when I will enter for
another buy somewhere right around here.
When the moving average has crossed over and
this candlestick has also shown me that it
has a very long, not really long, but
like an average low week which show us
that this demand zone is gonna hold and
I can place my second take profit like
somewhere right around here.
So easily, place a stop loss below this
new demand zone.
And what you can even do is to
move your stop loss for this first trade
into like somewhere right around here, somewhere right
around here.
So basically you can move your stop loss
somewhere to right around here.
Now both your trades, right?
The stop loss will be somewhere right around
this area here.
When you do that, you are literally limiting
your risk.
Now, even if you lose this trade, even
if you get stopped out, guess what?
You are walking away risk-free.
You have not lost a single bit of
money because you have managed to think clearly.
So now I have two trades running to
my overall take profit and I make not
just one profit but double the profit now.
I really thought about whether to share this
scalping strategy with you guys or not because
these three scalping strategies have been so valuable
to me throughout my past few years of
trading and I've never really shared this with
anyone but I really wanted to just share
this video with you guys.
So I'm not gonna ask you to hit
on the like button because I know that
you will definitely hit on the like button
because this video has been so valuable and
just look at the quality of our videos.
It has been increasing and I'm spending more
and more money investing in better equipments, better
editing.
So automatically, hit that like button, hit that
subscribe button, make more money for the channel
so that more money can be going back
into improving the quality of our videos and
when the quality of our videos increase, guess
what?
You get more educational, more valuable and more
higher quality 4k videos just like this.
Now in order for this scalping strategy to
work, you need a very deep understanding of
supply and demand zone which you can learn
in this video right here and remember, you're
just one trade away.