We would never have cash around just to
have cash.
I mean, we would never think that we
should have a cash position of X percent.
And, frankly, I think these asset allocation things
that tacticians in Wall Street put out, you
know, about 60 percent stocks and 30 percent
– we think that's total nonsense.
So we want to have all our money
working in decent businesses, but sometimes we can't
find them or sometimes cash comes in unexpectedly
or sometimes we sell something and we have
more cash around than we would like.
And more cash around than we would like
means that we'd have 10 or 15 cents
around because we want money employed, but we'll
never employ it, just employ it.
And you will find us quite unhappy over
time if cash just keeps building up.
And I think one way or another we'll
find ways to use it.
You may have trouble believing this, but Charlie
and I never have an opinion about the
market because it wouldn't be any good and
it might interfere with the opinions we have
that are good.
If we're right about a business, if we
think a business is attractive, it would be
very foolish for us to not take action
on that because we thought something about what
the market was going to do or anything
of that sort because we just don't know.
And to give up something that you do
know and that is profitable for something that
you don't know and won't know because of
that, it just doesn't make any sense to
us and it doesn't really make any difference
to us.
There's nothing magic.
We like to put a lot of money
in things that we feel strongly about.
And that gets back to the diversification question.
We think diversification, as practiced generally, makes very
little sense for anyone that knows what they're
doing.
Diversification is a protection against ignorance.
I mean, if you want to make sure
that nothing bad happens to you relative to
the market, you own everything.
There's nothing wrong with that.
I mean, that is a perfectly sound approach
for somebody who does not feel they know
how to analyze businesses.
If you know how to analyze businesses and
value businesses, it's crazy to own 50 stocks
or 40 stocks or 30 stocks probably because
there aren't that many wonderful businesses that are
understandable to a single human being in all
likelihood.
And to have some super wonderful business and
then put money in number 30 or 35
on your list of attractiveness and forego putting
more money into number one just strikes Charlie
and me as madness.
It's conventional practice and if all you have
to achieve is average, it's a confession in
our view that you don't really understand the
businesses that you own.
On a personal portfolio basis, I own one
stock, but it's a business I know.
And it leaves me very comfortable.
Do I need to own 28 stocks in
order to have proper diversification?
It would be nonsense.
Three wonderful businesses.
It's more than you need in this life
to do very well.
The average person isn't going to run into
that.
I mean, if you look at how the
fortunes were built in this country, they weren't
built out of a portfolio of 50 companies.
They were built by someone who identified with
a wonderful business.
Much of what is taught in modern corporate
finance courses is twaddle.
Volatility does not measure risk.
And the problem is that the people who
have written and taught about risk do not
know how to measure risk.
And the nice thing about data, which is
a measure of volatility, is that it's nice
and mathematical and wrong in terms of measuring
risk.
It's a measure of volatility, but past volatility
does not determine the risk of investing.
I mean, actually take it with farmland here.
In the early 1980s, farms that sold for
$2,000 an acre went to $600 an
acre.
I bought one of them when the banking
and farm crash took place.
And the beta of farms shot way up.
And according to standard economic theory, market theory,
I was buying a much more risky asset
at $600 an acre than the same farm
was at $2,000 an acre.
Now, people, because farmland doesn't trade often and
prices don't get recorded, you know, they would
regard that as nonsense, that my purchase at
$600 an acre of the same farm that
sold for $2,000 an acre a few
years ago was riskier.
But in SOX, because the prices jiggle around
every minute, and because it lets the people
who teach finance use the mathematics they've learned,
they have, in effect, they would explain this
away a little more technically, but they have,
in effect, translated past volatility in terms of
all kinds of measures of risk.
And it's nonsense.
Risk comes from the nature of certain kinds
of businesses.
It can be risky to be in some
businesses just by the simple economics of the
type of business you're in.
And it comes from not knowing what you're
doing.
And, you know, if you understand the economics
of the business in which you are engaged
and you know the people with whom you're
doing business and you know the price you
pay is sensible, you don't run any real
risk.
And I don't think Charlie and I, certainly
at Berkshire, I don't think we've ever had
a permanent loss in marketable securities that was,
what, 1 percent maybe?
Half a percent of net worth?
I made a terrible mistake in buying Dexter
Shoe, which cost us significantly more than 1
percent of net worth where I bought an
entire business then.
But I was wrong about the business.
It had nothing to do with the volatility
of shoe prices or leather or anything else.
It just was wrong.
But in terms of marketable securities, I cannot
recall a case where we've lost.
I mean, we've done a lot of things
in securities that had a very high beta.
We've done a lot of things in securities
that had a low beta.
It's just the whole development of volatility as
a measure of risk, we've never found a
way for it to be useful to us.
Both corporate finance and investment management courses, as
taught in the major universities, we would argue
it's at least 50 percent twaddle.
Yet these people have very high IQs.
One of the reasons we've been able to
do pretty well is that we early recognized
that very smart people do very dumb things,
and we tried to figure out why.
And we also wanted to know who so
we could avoid them.
It's a temperamental quality, not an intellectual quality.
You don't need tons of IQ in this
business.
I mean, you have to have enough IQ
to get from here to downtown Omaha.
But you do not have to be able
to play three-dimensional chess or be in
the top leagues in terms of bridge playing
or something of the sort.
You need a stable personality.
You need a temperament that neither derives great
pleasure from being with the crowd or against
the crowd because this is not a business
where you take polls.
It's a business where you think.
And Ben Graham would say that you're not
right or wrong because 1,000 people agree
with you, and you're not right or wrong
because 1,000 people disagree with you.
You're right because your facts and your reasoning
are right.
By far the best investment you can make
is in yourself.
For example, communication skills.
I tell those students that come that they're
going to graduate schools and business, and they're
learning all these complicated formulas and all that.
If they just learn to communicate better, both
in writing and in person, they increase their
value at least 50%.
If you can't communicate, somebody says, you know,
it's like winking at a girl in the
dark.
Nothing happens, you know, basically.
And you have to be able to get
forth your ideas.
And that's relatively easy.
I did it myself with the Dale Carnegie
course.
Some people wish I'd taken a shorter course
now in terms of my talking later on.
But it's just hugely important.
And if you invest in yourself, nobody can
take it away from you.
If I gave you a car, and it'd
be the only car you'd get the rest
of your life, you'd take care of it
like you can't believe it.
Any scratch, you'd fix that moment.
You'd read the owner's manual.
You'd keep a garage and do all these
things.
And you get exactly one mind and one
body in this world.
And you can't start taking care of it
when you're 50.
By that time, you'll have rusted out if
you haven't done anything.
So you should really make sure that you
just remember that you've just got one mind
and body to get through life with and
to do the most with it.
We think the best way to minimize risk
is to think.
And the idea that you have, you know,
you'll say, I've got 60% in stocks
and 40% in bonds and then have
a big announcement, now we're moving it to
65-35 as some strategist or whatever they
call them in Wall Street.
I mean, that has to be pure nonsense.
I mean, 60-40 or 65, it just
doesn't make any sense.
What you ought to do is have your
default position is always short-term instruments.
And whenever you see anything intelligent to do,
you should do it.
And you shouldn't be trying to match up
with some goal like that.
I found it entertaining.
I was just reading yesterday an article, I
think it was, about the two fellows at
Google and all of the problems they're going
to have because they're each going to get
a few billion dollars.
I mean, I wanted to send a sympathy
card.
I almost went down a Hallmark store because
this article went on, they've got this terrible
problem and that terrible problem and they're going
to need lawyers and they're going to need
financial aid.
They don't need anybody.
Those guys are smarter than the people that
are coming to them.
And they do not have a big problem.
And they're very capable of thinking it through
themselves.
The people that have the problem are the
people who want to sell their services to
them and are going to have to convince
them that they have a problem.
But so much of what you see when
you talk about asset allocations, it's just merchandising.
It's a way to make you think that
if you don't know how to determine whether
it should be 60-40 or 65-35,
that you need these people.
And you don't need them at all in
investing.
Most of the professionals that tell you you're
going to get in great trouble unless you
listen to them and sign up for their
services, they're good at selling.
But it's what my brother-in-law, former
brother-in-law that worked at the stockyards
used to say, was that people would bring
in cattle or something and I'd say to
them, how do you get the farmer to
employ you to sell the swift or armor
or cut a hay instead of the guy
right next to you.
It's a cow is a cow and armor
is going to buy it the same way.
He gave me this disgusted look and he
said, Warren, it's not how you sell them,
it's how you tell them.
Well, there's a lot of that in Wall
Street.
People have always had this craving to know
the future.
The king used to hire the magician or
the forecaster and he'd look in sheep guts
or something for an answer as to how
to handle the next war.
There's always been a market for people who
reported to know the future based on their
expertise and there's a lot of that still
going on.
It's just as crazy as when the king
was hiring the forecaster who looked at the
sheep guts.
People have an economic incentive to sell some
nostrum.
It can be sold over and over and
over again.
The really interesting figures are when you combine
the underperformance of the market, say by the
mutual fund industry, which is probably a couple
of points per annum, that that understates it.
Now if you take all of the investors
in the mutual funds who are constantly whipsawing
from one fund to another by a bunch
of brokers who want commissions, now you take
a subnormal performance and it goes down another
three or four percentage points due to the
shuffling of the mutual fund investments.
So the poor guy in the general public
is getting a terrible result from contacting the
experts and these guys are hitting the scout
troop and the community chest drive and are
locally reputable people.
I think it's disgusting.
It's much better to make a living by
being part of a system that delivers value
to the people who are buying the product.
But nobody refrains from creating gambling casinos or
something on my theory.
If it'll work to make money, we tend
to do it in this country.
Desire of people to gamble, and they gamble
in stocks incidentally too.
Day trading I would say very often came
very close to gambling as defined.
But people like to gamble.
I mean if the Super Bowl is on
or even better yet if a terribly boring
football game is on, but you don't have
anything to do and you're sitting there with
somebody else, you're probably going to enjoy the
game more if you bet a few bucks
on it one way or the other.
The human propensity to gamble is huge.
Now when it was legalized only in pretty
much in Nevada, you had to go to
some distance or break some laws to do
any serious gambling.
But as the states learned what a great
source of revenue it was, they gradually made
it easier and easier and easier for people
to gamble.
And believe me, the easier it's made, the
more people will gamble.
I mean when I was, my children are
here and 40 years ago, I bought a
slot machine and I put it up on
our third floor.
And I could give my kids any allowance
they wanted as long as it was in
dimes.
I mean I had it all back by
nightfall.
I thought it would be a good lesson
for them.
And now they weren't going to Las Vegas
to do it, but believe me when it
was on the third floor they could find
it.
My payout ratio was terrible too, but that's
the kind of father I was.
But gambling, people are always going to want
to do it.
And for that reason I particularly think that
to quite an extent gambling is a tax
on ignorance.
I mean if you want to tax the
ignorant, people who will do things with the
odds against them, you just put it in
and guys like me don't have to pay
taxes.
And I really don't.
I find that, I find it kind of
socially revolving when a government preys on the
weaknesses of its citizenry rather than acts to
serve them.
And believe me, when a government...
I've really said that growth and value, they're
indistinguishable.
They're part of the same equation.
Or really growth is part of the value
equation.
So our position is that there is no
such thing as growth stocks or value stocks
the way Wall Street generally portrays them as
being contrasting asset classes.
Growth usually is a positive for value, but
only when it means that by adding capital
now you add more cash availability later on
at a rate that's considerably higher than the
current rate of interest.
So we calculate into any business we buy
what we expect to have happen in terms
of the cash that's going to come out
of it or the cash that's going to
go into it.
So if you tell me that you own
a business that's going to grow to the
sky and isn't that wonderful, I don't know
whether it's wonderful or not until I know
what the economics are of that growth, how
much you have to put in today and
how much you will reap from putting that
in today later on.
And the classic case again is the airline
business.
The airline business has been a growth business
ever since Orville took off, but the growth
has been the worst thing that happened to
it.
It's been great for the American public, but
growth has been a curse in the airline
business because more and more capital has been
put into the business at inadequate returns.
Now growth is wonderful, it sees candy, because
it requires relatively little incremental investment to sell
more pounds of candy.
So it's growth, and I've discussed this in
some of the annual reports, but it's growth
is part of the equation.
But anybody that tells you you ought to
have your money in growth stocks or value
stocks really does not understand investing.
Other than that, they're terrific people.
The real point is that we're trying to
put out capital now to get more capital.
We're trying to put out cash now to
get more cash back later on.
And if you do that, the business grows,
obviously, and you can call that value or
you can call it growth, but they're not
two different categories.
And I just cringe when I hear people
talk about now it's time to move from
growth stocks to value stocks or something like
that because it just doesn't make any sense.
In general terms, unless you find the prices
of a great company really offensive, if you
feel you've identified it, and by definition a
great company is one that's going to remain
great for 30 years.
If it's going to be a great company
for three years, it ain't a great company.
So you really want to go along with
the idea of something that if you were
going to take a trip for 20 years,
you wouldn't feel bad leaving the money in
with no orders with your broker and no
power of attorney or anything, and you just
go on the trip, and you know you
come back and it's going to be a
terribly strong company.
I think it's better just to own them.
I mean, you know, we could attempt to
buy and sell some of the things that
we own that we think are fine businesses,
but they're too hard to find.
We found See's Candy in 1972 where we
find here and there we get the opportunity
to do something, but they're too hard to
find.
So to sit there and hope that you
buy them in the throes of some panic,
you know, that you sort of take the
attitude of a mortician, you know, waiting for
a flu epidemic or something.
I mean, I'm not sure that will be
a great technique.
That's a lot to count on, and, you
know, if you start with the Dow at
X and you think it's too high, you
know, when it goes to 90% of
X, do you buy?
Well, if it doesn't, it goes to 50
% of X.
It gets, you know, you never get the
benefit of those extremes anyway unless you just
come into some accidental sum of money at
some time.
So I think the main thing to do
is find wonderful businesses.
So we've had our share of flu epidemics,
but you don't want to spend your life
waiting around for them.
When people said cash is king a year
ago, I mean, that's crazy.
I mean, cash wasn't producing anything, and it
was sure to go down in value over
time.
And then you always want to be sure
you have enough.
I mean, it's like oxygen.
You want to be sure it's around, you
know, but you don't need to have excessive
amounts of it around.