Have you ever seen those mobile game ads
in GORN?
This game looks so shi- I bet
I could make this in like, one hour.
Well, uh, I have.
Let's do it!
The rules of this challenge are simple.
I have exactly 60 minutes to get as
close as possible to the game.
I've found three different mobile games, and I'm
gonna see how close I can get to
each of them within an hour.
Alright, the first game is this piece of
shi- It's called Countmasters.
And if you already knew that, then that's
really sad.
This is the poster boy for shi-ty
mobile games.
It's a classic.
I'm sure you've seen it around.
Alright, new Unity scene.
New timer.
Let's do this.
Okay, ah, I forgot it starts right away.
Alright, let's start with a platform to run
on.
Okay, great.
And now we need a character to do
the- to run.
To be the runner.
Oh, shi- She's zooming!
Me when your ma- Me when your
mom is- Okay.
Boom.
Yes, okay, we've got a running guy.
Oh, excellent.
Now we need to set up a navmesh,
which is Unity's pathfinding shi- That just
helps our guys move together and follow like
a central point.
Okay, please.
Yes!
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
And then if I move the sphere around,
it should run towards the sphere.
Yes, it's all covered together.
Now we just have to move the sphere
down the thingy, and they should follow.
Okay.
We got a game going.
Hell yeah.
Easy, easy.
Okay, uh, it's gate time.
It's fucking gate time, boys.
Alright, let's run this bitch.
Uh, times- Okay, that was a fucking
useless test.
Okay, times two should spawn another guy-
Ah, okay.
Nope, sad.
I think you- Alright, alright.
That's fair.
That's fair enough.
Times ten?
Uh, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes!
Okay, let's add some more gates, and we
got a game, baby!
Plus one?
Boom.
Fourteen?
Just- just fourteen?
Uh, times two, double it and give it
to the next guy.
Double it again- I'm so goaded.
Holy shit.
Now let's go minus six.
I think times zero might break the whole
game, and I don't want to deal with
that right now.
If you don't test for it, the bug
doesn't exist.
Write that down.
Okay, let's like clump them together a little
more.
They're a little too spaced out.
Okay, divided by one?
Nice.
Times ten?
Uh, I should have done plus forty-five.
I'm bad at this.
I'm the guy in the ad.
Plus seventeen, times four.
Oh, hell yeah.
Plus seventeen.
This game's so easy.
This looks great.
Actually, it looks so good.
Next, I cranked up the saturation of the
players to appeal to your stupid monkey brains.
Plus forty-three?
Excellent.
Beautiful, beautiful.
Okay, I have twenty-three minutes left.
That's a while.
That's not bad, actually.
Okay, with the time left, I decided to
make some of the obstacles.
Uh, so there's, I added the spinny c***s,
which kill players if you touch it.
Uh-oh.
Come on, speed up.
Why did I put it right at the
end?
I don't have time for this.
Oh, yes.
Okay, yes, great.
Okay, now let's just add some more of
them, and I'll add some basic obstacles as
well.
And finally, we need a finish line, which
should stop the sphere from moving, and just
do something pretty to celebrate.
So in the actual game, they do this.
But that's a lot of whack, so instead
they do this.
Which is pretty good, I think.
That's something.
With my last minute, I basically had no
time to do anything.
Uh, so I just decided to set the
background to an obnoxious color.
Let's make it f***ing vibrant green or some
s***.
No, that looks terrible.
Red.
No, pink.
There you go.
That's a mobile game.
Okay.
Done.
Done!
Oh!
Wow.
That was f***.
I'm actually pretty happy with this one.
Okay, let's test this.
But before I do, I do have a
confession.
After completing each of these games, I did
go through and make some changes.
But, but, but.
All I did was sound effects and music.
I did not touch the functionality of the
game whatsoever.
If you count that as cheating, then, uh,
keep it to yourself.
I don't care.
Okay, let's see how I did.
Okay, let's go.
Oh, it's right into it.
Times three.
Oh, my guy's already gone.
Okay, that's a rough start.
I'm ready this time.
I'm ready.
Um, okay.
Bad start.
Okay, once again, terrible start.
I am so bad at this.
All right, let's close everything and reopen it.
I really should have added a restart function,
but you know, that's okay.
We do not have time.
Minus 48.
Okay.
But I still have one guy alive.
That's pretty good.
Okay, I'm ready.
I'm ready.
One of the spikes is white.
That's okay.
That's, that was an aesthetic choice.
Okay, plus 55.
Nice.
Oh, can we get that plus 53?
Yes.
Okay, we lost a few, but that's okay.
Plus 48.
We're getting big numbers here.
I like it.
Nope, never mind.
Yeah, I'll go to times one.
What's this expert piloting?
I call this the weave.
Oh, baby.
Oh, my God.
The footsteps get so loud.
That's so annoying.
Oh, we did it.
Yeah, I guess.
I mean, you can't really lose this game.
This goes on for a while, huh?
Whoa, that's gaming.
It should be possible to get an absurd
amount of boys.
I'm seeing a time seven at the end.
Baby, that's going to be huge.
Oh, what's this?
The wave is back, baby.
Woo.
This time seven is going to be brutal
on performance.
You ready?
Oh, the music stopped.
Oh, no.
I have no idea how many lads we've
got, but it's a lot.
This is not as satisfying as I expected.
Okay, we got there.
Finally.
Oh, my God.
I still think we can go more.
Code bullet on a horse.
He's on a horse.
Plus, I think you have like two seconds
to make the first decision.
Oh, this one's looking good.
I think I'm seeing a lot of big
multiplications.
We got a time six, a plus 47,
and then a time seven.
Ready?
Music's gone again.
Oh, we got a times 10 at the
end.
This is going to absolutely destroy my computer.
You ready?
Oh, it's trying.
Oh, Jesus.
Okay, let's see how long we're here for.
Oh, we did it.
Let's go.
It's only, what, 24 minutes.
Hell yeah, that's quality gameplay, baby.
That's what it's all about.
I love it when games break my computer
for 24 minutes.
Okay, next game.
Okay, for the next game, we're going to...
Oh, my God.
What?
What the fuck is even that?
What am I looking at?
Is it dangerous?
It's looking at me.
Security.
Can we get security in here, please?
No, it's looking at the camera.
Oh, fuck.
Is he going to take the camera?
You can have the camera.
It's fine.
It's theoretical anyway.
Bye, GamersOps.
What?
Is this an ad?
Okay, game two is attack hole.
Okay, so basically, you're a hole.
You pick up bullets.
Very nice.
Then you get bigger, and then you can
pick up shotgun shells.
Look at this.
Oh, baby.
Then when the time runs out, you shoot
everything at this robot guy.
I don't know what he did.
I don't know what his story is.
But apparently, we don't like him.
Anyway, you know the drill.
New project, new timer.
Let's send it.
All right, first, we need to figure out
how to make a hole, because I don't
know how to do that.
First off, we also want to override the
stencil settings.
Select one for both objects to be on
the same stencil layer.
For the compare function, we don't want to
- No, fuck that.
That sounds so complicated.
All right, I have a plan.
Hold my beer.
Boom.
Hole.
Fuck you.
Did they fall in the hole?
They fell in the hole!
Okay, okay.
Yeah.
Okay, let's make the hole look more hole
-like, and let's add some basic controls.
And also, I made it a bit prettier.
Wow, that looks like shit.
Perfect.
Okay, let's add some scripts.
One that keeps track of the bullets that
fall in the hole, one that moves the
hole and increases its size, and one little
guy that just holds how many points each
bullet type is worth.
All right, let's fucking grip it and ship
it.
See what happens.
It might even work.
Anything is possible.
Okay, it didn't crash immediately.
That's better than usual.
Oh wow, the hole did get bigger.
It was not the most graceful animation I've
ever seen, but it works.
All right, here's what's happening.
At the moment, the hole is increasing in
size like this, which does make it bigger,
but it shifts the center of the hole
over, and essentially just makes it look like
shit.
I want to increase the size of the
hole relative to the center of the hole.
And to mark the center, I made this
little guy.
Isn't he cute?
His name is, uh, Sphere.
It's, it's European.
That looks like it worked.
Yes!
All right, no, no, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no.
I am so good at things.
Yes!
All right, I added some shit.
We got bullet, long bullet, square bullet, pointy
bullet, bullet holder, and long bullet holder.
I don't know about guns.
I'm Australian.
All right, hole is done.
Now we just need to make a robot,
give it a health bar, have it move
towards us, store all the bullets we eat,
then shoot them at the robot and deal
the appropriate damage, and have the robot kill
us when it touches us, and have the
robot die when its health runs out, and
add a bunch more bullets to eat, and
add a timer for how long we can
eat stuff, and change the camera to see
the robot, all in 23 minutes.
Fuck.
Okay, I'm gonna have to lock in, so
it's montage time.
Okay, we're done.
We're done.
Woo!
That was fucked.
That one was so much harder.
Oh my god.
All right, whole game.
Let's see.
Let's see how we did.
I've not tested any of this.
Oh right, we got, I forgot we had
a timer.
All right, go, go, go.
All right, let's grab these boys first.
Nom, nom, nom, nom, nom, nom, nom.
Oh, that guy does go.
Oh, they're all falling over.
Don't worry about that.
Why is that?
Why did they fall over?
Whatever, whatever.
That's okay, that happens.
All right, let's get some bigger bullets.
Pretty good, oh.
That's okay, that's fine.
That's fine, everything's fine.
This is normal.
He's still there, he's still stuck.
Let's get some pointy bullets.
Fuck yes.
This game's actually fun.
I'm actually, like, enjoying this.
That's crazy.
All right, can we get the big ones?
Oh my god.
Oh no.
Oh, that's not ideal.
You gotta, guys, you missed him.
You missed him.
Let's go again for the sake of the
video, not because I'm having fun.
Happens to the best.
What did three men they say?
I think they do damage when it runs
into him.
Perfect, no notes.
No notes.
Welcome to game three.
We got a knife, it spins.
That's pretty much it.
That's the whole game, you cut shit.
Yeah, what you see is what you get.
Yeah, I don't know what else to say.
That's all this is.
Okay, let's get to work.
Okay, we got a brand new unity scene.
And let's start a timer for 60 minutes.
Ah, okay, we're going, we're going, we're going.
All right, so first up, we need a
way of splitting shit in half.
I think that's going to be the hardest
thing.
So we could cut it ourselves, but we
do not have time for that shit.
So let's steal someone else's work.
I'm sure that's what the creators of this
did anyway.
Come on, come on, come on, come on,
come on.
All right, dynamic mesh slicer, that'll do.
It's free, let's go.
Boom, all right, what does this do?
Oh, okay.
Excellent, excellent.
That's exactly what we want.
Okay, okay.
Let's adjust the code so it splits it
in half perfectly.
Whoa, yeah, making progress.
Okay, okay, let's add some rotation to the
split so it looks a bit nicer.
Okay, now it should cut and then like
split nicely.
I mean, I guess that was a touch
more forceful than I was hoping.
Three.
Okay, yeah, whatever, that'll do.
We gotta move on.
Now, what do we need?
We need some shit to cut.
This is sought by cheap.
Food, yeah, sure, you cut food, that works.
There's no way this works, right?
Get rid of the cube, grip it and
ship it.
What happens?
P?
Oh, it's gone.
Not allowed to access triangles.
Not allowed to act.
Oh, you know what?
I don't have time for this.
Let's bring in the big guns.
What is this?
Okay, project view, import settings.
Yes, okay.
Okay, it's kind of shit.
You know what?
We take those.
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
We got a splitting apple.
What do we need?
We need a knife, obviously, duh.
Just give me the knife.
It's fucking pink every time.
Boom.
Yes, gaming, okay.
Here, we run it, slice.
Yes, okay, okay.
Let's fucking go.
Now, that might have looked like the knife
was cutting the thing, but I actually just
pressed P at the right time to make
it look like that.
So we gotta actually make the knife cut
the thing.
This should cut it without me pressing P.
That's the dream.
Please, please.
Fuck.
Oh, here it is.
This needs a collider.
Yeah, that should fix it.
Fucking piece of shit game engine.
Goddamn.
Yes, okay.
It cut it a billion times.
Who cares?
Move on, move on, move on.
Yes, okay, okay.
Gaming.
All right, now we need the actual movement
of the knife.
How does the knife actually move?
It spins.
Oh, I forgot what I was doing.
I just started actually playing the game.
So it spins.
How much time do we have left?
40 minutes.
Okay, okay.
We're doing all right.
We're doing all right with 20 minutes.
Okay, okay.
We're crazy.
So as I said earlier, with such grace
and articulation, we need to spin the knife,
but also we need to apply an upward
force and a forward force.
So it's sort of like hops forward.
If that makes sense, you get it.
Let's let it rip.
All right, that's interesting.
Yeah, that's better.
That's what I wanted.
Okay, great.
Now we just need the camera to follow
the knife and we're looking solid.
Oh, that's pretty good.
That's pretty good, actually.
Okay, 20 minutes.
Um, okay.
Ah, fuck.
I lost it again.
Um, what are we, what are we doing?
Where am I?
Um, I need to, I need more shit
to cut.
See, I added cans.
Whoa.
Wow.
At this point, I thought it was a
good idea to get a skybox, which games
use to make the sky look like a
sky.
But Unity was less of a fan of
this idea.
Oh, this is taking so long.
Don't worry about the edge fix ups.
Just go, go.
I should have just set it to orange.
Go.
Oh my God.
Unity, please, please, please.
Okay.
You can't be busy for 60.
That's over a minute.
I'm sorry.
That was a ridiculous thing to ask for.
I shouldn't have tried to skybox.
That was dumb.
I'm sorry.
Unity, I'm sorry.
I'm free.
Hi, I'm sorry about shit.
Fuck you.
Let's go.
Skybox.
Oh, I forgot I added the ground.
It's perfect.
No notes.
Ah, fuck.
The ground doesn't even ground.
Ah, I should have that.
I should make that do that.
Okay, fuck.
I think I did it.
We got like 10 minutes left, but I'm
feeling good about this.
That's rough.
That's rough to watch.
Oh my God.
What the fuck is happening?
I just wanted to make the ground ground.
You know what?
Fuck this.
You've lost collider privileges.
It'll be our little secret that you can
just go through the ground.
Don't tell anyone.
Eight minutes.
I added some more stuff to cut, like
doughnuts.
Oh, don't look at that.
I also added the score, which I apparently
put in the middle of the screen.
It's a bold choice.
And I added a finish line and...
Oh, okay.
All right, let's cut some shit.
I think visually this one's the worst.
I think it looks like shit.
Okay, it's pretty good.
Oh, huge lag spike there.
That's okay.
Eggplant splits into 4,000 parts.
Whoa, did you see that?
Whoa, what the fuck?
What is going on?
Oh, wait a second.
Oh, oh, I see what's happening.
I left some scripts that when you click
on something, it splits it apart.
Okay, until I was clicking on the ground.
Oh my god.
Okay, that makes sense.
I was clicking on the ground and because
of that, it was splitting the ground.
So this should reset it.
It does!
Huge!
That actually worked.
So if I don't click on the ground...
It looks pretty good.
Do you like if I click on that
can?
Click on that can.
This is not really how you're supposed to
play the game.
I can just click on this.
Yeah, I can just click on them.
Makes it a lot easier.
Let me get that guy.
Can I...
What happens if I click on the finish
line?
What happened?
Nothing.
Oh, wait.
I think I split it in half and
then I can go through this finish line.
Oh my god, I'm free.
Okay, let's run it back one more time.
I want to see what score I get.
Oh wait, is that...
Is that Brilliant.org cutting through the competition?
What?
So dumb.
Oh my god, I think that was the
worst segue I've done in my life.
Okay, Brilliant.org.
People often ask me how I got this
good at making games.
Well, the trick to achieving this level of
mastery is breaking the journey up into small
steps and learning something every day.
Brilliant is the epitome of this philosophy by
helping you build real knowledge in just minutes
a day.
It's like the opposite of mindless doomscrolling.
Instead of watching this...
On the left side, the internet won't let
him in the right side.
Are you serious right now?
You could be doing an interactive course learning
about how large language models like Chachapiti work,
or you could take one of the many
courses on programming, which are a good way
to build foundations and learn real world applications.
Brilliant's courses are also available right on your
phone, so you can do them whenever you
have a spare minute.
Whether that's when you're on the toilet or
driving on a particularly straight road, you can
level up on the go in just minutes.
So to support this channel and try everything
Brilliant has to offer for free for a
full 30 days, visit brilliant.org code bullet
or scan the QR code on screen, or
you can click the link in the description.
You'll also get 20% off an annual
premium subscription.
Thank you, Brilliant.
Hey, it's Patreon battle time.
Okay, thanks for watching.
This one is fun to make.
Kind of crazy how close I got to
the games within an hour.
Of course, they're not as good as the
originals.
The originals had a lot more like polish
and stuff.
And like honestly, like a lot of the
originals had just like a lot more level
design, I guess.
Like a lot more, they had a lot
more levels to play through, which probably would
have taken a bit more time.
It was kind of crazy.
Like all the functionality was kind of essentially
there.
Which is nuts.
Yeah, I was pretty happy with that one.
Especially the first game, the Countmasters one.
That was actually like, I thought that was
really cool.
The knife one was kind of shit.
If for some reason you want to play
them, I don't know why you would.
But if for some reason you do, they
are on my Patreon.
So you can go check that out.
Maybe you want to see if you can
beat my score on how long it took
the Countmasters thing to end or something.
Yeah, I mean, obviously they're buggy.
They are not fun, but they're there.
I hope you like this sort of like
lower effort content.
It's still like a lot of editing and
all that.
But like the actual project themselves obviously took
me three hours, which is way less than
my usual project.
Because I kind of get stuck in scope
creep hell of like, oh, I should add
this.
I should add this.
So then it ends up taking like six
months.
So giving it like an hour or 24
hours or whatever, some sort of time limit
or challenge or whatever makes it a set
scope of how much time I can spend
on it.
Okay.
Anyway, congrats to Report Turret.
You win some free merch.
I'll be in contact.
Okay, bye.