Understanding technical analysis can mean the difference between
buying here and buying here.
And that's why I've decided to create the
Best Darn Beginners Guide to Technical Analysis on
the Internet.
Starting with some very important terminology.
above due to previous demand or price action.
That is, predicting the asset will go up
in value.
Short position, the opposite of a long position.
Entering a trade position, betting the asset will
go down in value.
Don't worry if you're feeling lost already, we
will break everything down even more.
A market order.
In order to buy an asset or security
immediately at the current market rate.
Limit order.
In order to buy an asset or security
at a specified price or better.
If you set a limit order to buy
an asset at $5, your trade will not
be initiated unless the price hits $5 or
less.
These terms will help you with the learning
process for the remainder of this video.
Now, let's go ahead and get you set
up.
The first thing you need to do is
select your trading platform.
It's important to take your time on this
because there's a lot of scam exchanges and
exchanges that simply charge way too much in
fees.
For trading cryptos, I'm personally a fan of
KuCoin.
If you're looking to trade stocks, I'm a
big fan of Webull, as they have a
really easy to use interface and some free
stocks for signing up.
I'll have all the options linked in the
description of this video.
After you've created your account, you'll need to
understand what you're getting yourself into before entering
any trades and risking your life savings.
Please don't risk your life savings.
I don't understand.
Why would you buy a policy?
It's just the cost of a cup of
coffee an hour.
I've seen people make millions trading, but I've
also seen people lose everything.
So trade responsibly because no one can predict
the future.
Technical analysis is just an additional tool in
your tool belt that you can use to
become a more well-rounded investor.
It is by no means a fortune teller,
and none of this video should be interpreted
as financial advice.
So what are we doing when we talk
about our own technical analysis?
Picture this.
You're planning a vacation to Italy with your
family, but you need to get a hotel.
Before you go, you could manually call some
hotels in Milan and ask about their services,
their schedule, and how close they are to
a wine and cheese shop.
It takes you about two weeks to complete
this exercise.
And at that point, you have about 10
hotels on a spreadsheet with all this data
that you've collected.
You have great information, but most won't go
through all of this effort.
Instead, you probably would look at an aggregator
website that allows you to compare customer feedback,
average booking prices, and of course, the distance
to your local cheese shop for the most
popular hotels.
This allows you to get a pretty good
idea of what you're getting yourself into without
ever having to crack open the operations manual
of 10 different hotels.
Technical analysis works a bit like the second
situation.
Well, it's important that we have a good
understanding of a crypto or stock's fundamentals before
considering it.
You have to ensure it's not a scam
anyways.
Past a certain point, we need to learn
about how investors are trading that asset.
What's the price action, and what can it
tell us?
Can this help us invest?
This will help us determine if the trends
we see happening right now will continue or
if they're more likely to change in the
future.
Technical analysis measures price movements, uses indicators, and
offers suggestions as to potential opportunities to buy
or sell cryptos and stocks.
This usually is more useful for short-term
traders, but it can be valuable to long
-term holders as well who want to ensure
that they find the best possible entry prices
for the assets that they're looking to invest
in.
Now, to keep things simple, this is a
beginner's guide.
Now, I've selected a few of the most
accessible ways that you can start doing your
own technical analysis and learn to create a
more proactive strategy for crypto and stock trading.
And before we dive deep, I also need
to let you know about my Patreon, linked
in the description.
There you'll find a massive private investor community,
daily crypto trade signals, free coaching, and alerts
whenever I buy or sell assets, all for
as little as $10 a month.
And there's a reason that we have nearly
10,000 satisfied members.
The first indicator that I want to talk
about is the candlestick graph.
It's one of the most popular ways of
looking at how prices change.
This tells us a lot more about the
supply and demand for an asset than a
simple line graph ever could.
Candles can be set to show price changes
per minute, per hour, or per day, and
this is beneficial depending on how frequently you
trade.
So let's look at the colors first.
A red candle tells us for that day,
the asset closed at a loss.
And you guessed it, a green candle tells
us that the price went up.
What's more important to look at here is
the opening and closing prices.
If the candle is red, then the closing
price is the bottom end of the candle
with the opening price at the top.
The opposite is true for green candles.
The bottom is the opening price and the
top is the closing price.
But that's not all.
Many new traders will forget to look at
the wicks, and this is important.
Don't forget the wick.
That sounds dirty for some reason.
That's what she said.
The wicks tell us what the highest and
lowest prices were for the day or whatever
time interval your candles are set to.
Very often, the wick extends past what a
candle's opening and closing prices are.
So as a rule of thumb, we say
the larger the wicks, the more volatile the
market.
But we can dig deeper still, because short
and long wicks have different meanings between red
and green candles.
First, the red candles.
A long wick at the bottom of a
red candle can tell us that within the
day or whatever time period you're looking at,
prices fell to what many investors consider to
be the cheapest price.
And so they bought back in at that
price, driving the price back up.
Some investors see this as an indication that
the price will begin to move up in
the next day or the next trading period.
But remember that a long wick means high
volatility, and that trend could easily reverse.
Now, if you see a short wick at
the bottom of a red candle, proceed with
caution.
This tends to mean that traders will continue
to sell the asset.
But again, this is not always certain.
Now, for green candles, a green candle means
that during the set time period, the asset's
price went up.
A long wick at the top of a
green candle tells us that at some point
within the day, the price significantly exceeded the
closing price, meaning that traders might have considered
that to be the top and then decided
to take profits at that top price.
That is, sell their crypto or stock.
Long wicks show us that the market is
volatile and could indicate that the price may
fall from there.
A short wick at the top of a
green candle, on the other hand, is common
when the price is at all-time highs.
Now, some say this is a good time
to sell if you're looking for an exit
in that position.
If you're looking for an opportunity to buy
and you only had the candlestick chart to
look at, a good time to do so,
according to technical analysis, would be on a
red candlestick with a long wick at the
bottom and a short one at the top.
Now, let's pump the brakes here for a
second because you'll notice on this chart for
ADA price movements, there are some red candles
that fit the description of a buying opportunity,
only for the price to fall well past
that just a few days later.
And spoiler alert, the tools that we're going
to discuss today can't account for which way
investor sentiment is going to go in the
response to headlines and other global events.
There isn't a candlestick that can predict a
global pandemic or election results, And if you
find a fortune-telling candlestick, keep it to
yourself, but DM it to me, but keep
it to yourself.
Now, investing, especially in crypto, can be very
volatile.
And one way of making an informed decision
despite that volatility is by using trend lines.
This is the practice of finding the overarching
movement in price, the trend.
Many exchanges will have charts that automatically show
you trend lines generated by AI.
But if you want to DIY a trend
line, you basically just draw a trend line
yourself by choosing a period of time starting
at the bottom of the candlestick for that
day, week, or hour, and then drawing a
line connecting it to the bottom of other
candlesticks.
Once you have enough points, you can project
your trend line into the future to help
you determine if the price will move upwards
or downwards if that trend continues.
Trend lines can help us take a step
back and look at how much an asset's
price rises or falls over a defined period.
If we look at that same price chart
for Cardano ADA except zoomed out, where each
candle represents one week, we can see the
trend now tells a completely different story.
If we were looking at the performance of
Cardano just in the last few days, our
trend line would be clearly pointing downwards.
However, looking at the last few months, the
bottoms of most of the severe candles have
been showing a general uptrend.
This indicates that ADA could be a good
long-hold crypto.
However, with this, you may have to sit
through some heart-wrenching price swings on your
way up.
And again, none of this is science.
Because of this, it's good to compare multiple
trend lines.
Looking at long-term trend lines covering about
six months to a year, and then compare
that with short-term trend lines.
This will help you find better entry and
exit points in the assets that you're interested
in.
So far, I've talked about ways that you
can interpret common price charts for your own
technical analysis.
So next, let's talk about support and resistance
lines and how to derive and interpret them
for your very own strategy.
Well, support and resistant lines are horizontal lines
that you can draw onto your price chart.
Support shows the lowest price at which investors
are willing to buy that asset.
This signals when buyers show the most demand
for an asset.
When you see an asset continually bouncing off
a specific price, this is support.
Let's say you're trying to forecast prices for
the next month.
You might look at the lowest price point
from the previous month and label this your
support level.
This way, if and when your stock or
crypto dips to below that price point the
following month, you can anticipate that an upwards
trend may be coming.
Resistance, on the other hand, shows the highest
price at which investors will usually stop buying
and instead begin selling that asset.
This can signal that there are more buyers
than sellers in the market at that specific
price, meaning that the asset will have a
harder time passing through this price point.
In your analysis, you might see that support
and resistance lines don't really change from period
to period.
This happens when the majority of buyers and
sellers tend to group around the prevailing support
and resistance lines.
And this could lead to what we call
trading sideways, where the price doesn't change a
whole lot over a period of time.
Now, what you want to look out for
are price movements that break away from support
and resistance lines.
Take, for example, our ADA chart from last
month.
Notice how from September 15th through October 18th,
there was a steady decline in the resistance
line, meaning that investors were finding lower and
lower prices too expensive to buy.
We saw the resistance line drop from $2
.6 down to $2.3 and then continue
to dip around $2.1. So at least
for this short period that we're measuring, the
price at which there was an oversupply of
ADA kept getting lower and lower.
This might lead an analyst to believe that
there would be a steep correction coming in
this asset.
Next, we need to talk about formations.
Formations are patterns in the price movement of
an asset on its chart.
Formations are amazing because this is what allow
us to identify the most likely direction an
asset is headed to, as well as the
most likely price it will stop at after
breaking through that formation.
In the same image, you will see a
yellow circle and a green circle.
The yellow circle is the moment this asset
broke out of the formation.
Most traders, get a listen here, most traders
will make the mistake of entering a long
or buy position at the moment of breakout.
This is a huge but very common mistake
new traders make.
They assume that since it broke out of
the formation, this verifies the formation that they
drew, it verifies that it's accurate, and verifies
that the asset will go directly to their
price target.
But it's an extremely important practice to be
patient here and wait for the confirmation bounce.
An example of this is the green circle.
The price bounces off of our previous resistance
line, confirming that this resistance no longer has
the same effect.
The confirmation bounce should be the best moment
to enter in your trade.
If it bounces to the upside, you would
enter a long position.
If it breaks through to the downside, you
would enter a short position.
Breaking through a pattern just like the trend
lines we just discussed is called a continuation
pattern.
So let's briefly cover a few popular patterns
that you may see referenced.
The pattern that we just looked at could
be referred to as a wedge pattern.
If trend lines had connected in that pattern,
it would be called a pennant pattern.
Flag patterns are two parallel trend lines that
can head upwards, downwards, or sideways.
A cup and handle pattern is when the
price increase has paused.
The bowl shape is then followed by what
looks like a pennant chart pattern, and this
may indicate a further breakout in price.
A head and shoulders trend following an increase
in price may indicate the price will decrease.
A reverse head and shoulders trend following a
decrease in price may indicate that the price
will increase.
Now, it's important to note that humans love
finding patterns in literally anything, and there are
a million chart patterns that can mean different
things.
But this doesn't mean you should expect the
result to always come true.
Again, this just helps paint a more clear
picture, but does not absolutely tell us the
future.
Now that you know when to enter a
trade, let's talk about when you should exit
a trade because this may be even more
important than when you enter a trade.
And this answer may vary because it depends
on whether or not you are trading futures
with leverage or trading spot without leverage.
Leverage is simply borrowing money to use in
a trade to help increase your potential return.
Let's say you've entered a trade When trading
with leverage, you may borrow funds against that
$100.
With 10x leverage, your $100 acts as if
it's $1,000.
So mathematically, when the asset you're trading goes
up 1%, you will actually be 10%
in profit.
However, it's not all good and rosy because
if the trade goes down 1%, you will
be at a 10% loss.
If you lose too much, you will be
liquidated completely, meaning you lose all the funds
that you entered into the trade and you
don't want to be in that position.
So this, of course, is very high risk
and not for beginners.
Now, trading spot is just regular trading with
your own money and no borrowing.
Here you still have the risk of losing
money, but liquidation is not a concern like
it is with leverage.
When trading with leverage, typically you want to
close your trade the moment you hit your
target or just before.
This will prevent you from being hit with
recurring leverage fees.
When you're trading with spot, you don't have
to worry so much about rushing out of
the trade.
So if a trade has surpassed your target,
you can simply hold longer and set up
a trailing stop loss.
Now, a trailing stop loss is a stop
loss tool you can use that will follow
the price of an asset by a dollar
amount of your choice and then close your
trade at the maximum amount of profits possible
completely on autopilot.
Typically, you wouldn't set up a trailing stop
loss until your price target is already hit
and you just want to try and make
a little bit more profit.
Now, speaking of hit, if you appreciate my
efforts in putting together this free course, just
please consider hitting the subscribe button.
It's totally free and you can always change
your mind later.
Now, spotting trends isn't enough on its own.
You also need to evaluate the strength of
a trend because not all trends are created
equally.
So one indicator that we can look at
is trading volume.
This is the total dollar amount traded of
an asset.
Now, it's pretty simple to do this, so
it should be a regular part of your
technical analysis.
The higher the trading volume, the stronger the
trend.
And this makes sense if you think about
it because a trend with 10 million in
volume behind it means much more than a
trend with 1 million in volume behind it.
So it's always good to take a look
at the 24-hour trading volume on days
where the price moved downwards and then compare
this to the trading volume on days where
the price moves upwards.
If you see higher volumes on positive days,
this can tell us that there's a long
-term potential for the asset to continue trending
upwards.
This also helps us evaluate how the market
will react to a sharp drop in price.
If the trading volume during one dip is
larger than another more severe dip later on,
we might determine that the drop in price
does not signify a stronger downwards trend.
Something else to take into consideration is market
cap, which you get by multiplying the current
price of your crypto or stock with the
total supply of the crypto or stock.
Big cap coins and stocks tend to be
more stable because large volume trades have less
of an impact on their prices.
It's hard to move a big ship.
Now, let's move on to a more technical
indicator of price movement.
And one that I use quite regularly.
This is the Relative Strength Index, or RSI
indicator for short.
The RSI of a certain crypto or stock
usually is pretty easy to access.
It's usually displayed just underneath price charts for
the purpose of directly comparing price trends with
the RSI.
It's displayed as a number between 0 and
100, and this number changes continuously based on
trading activity, typically relative to the average gains
in losses over a 14-day period.
This kind of graph is called an oscillator
because the readings always show a number between
0 and 100.
So let's break down how this works.
In basic situations without drastic market moving events,
RSI indicates whether a crypto or any kind
of security is overbought or oversold.
A reading above 70 would tell us that
it's overbought and can signal that a price
correction may happen.
A prolonged RSI above 70 can be interpreted
as some kind of bubble and that the
coming correction could create dramatic losses to the
people who are invested in that asset.
Now, readings under 30 indicate that the security
is oversold.
In other words, the asset may be undervalued,
meaning it could be a good opportunity.
You've probably seen videos where certain cryptos or
stocks are proclaimed to be undervalued.
The RSI indicator was likely one of the
tools used to come to that conclusion, and
now you can use that.
At the water cooler, at work, you can
be like, Hey, you know what?
I think that this stock is undervalued.
You know, you just check the RSI.
It can be that easy.
So there's actually a whole book written about
the Relative Strength Index.
If you want to fully understand it, I
will have this book linked in the description
of this video.
Now we need to talk about the moving
average.
You can calculate this by taking the price
readings of your crypto or stock from the
last X number of days.
The standard is 20, but you can reduce
it to about 5 if your trading strategy
requires it.
So this works by adding up the prices
each day of your stock or asset or
crypto and then dividing that sum by the
total number of days in the period.
It's just the average price.
What this gives you is a price figure
that's less impacted by wild market swings, allowing
you to focus on price performance as it
changes over longer periods of time.
If you want to use a shorter window
for your average, like five days, just know
that your moving average could be far more
affected by temporary price swings than longer averages
are affected.
So just make sure your investing strategy takes
this into account.
I like using moving averages to forecast price
changes in a similar way to how the
RSI indicator triggers buy and sell alerts.
When the price of an asset falls below
your moving average, some investors take this to
mean a downward trend is imminent.
And you can interpret crypto or stock prices
above your moving average to mean an upwards
trend is more likely to happen.
Now, understanding when to take profits can sometimes
be tricky, but there's a solid rule you
can remember, and I think everyone should follow
this.
It's never wrong to take profits, even if
it's 1%, even if it's half a percent.
Don't let greed take over and tell you,
you know, it could just keep on going
up.
Trust your plan, not your emotions.
Please, you will make more money in the
long run.
So far, we have gone over trend lines.
Now let's cover how we can use these
formations to find a price target so then
we know when to safely exit a trade.
In this example, I will show you a
double bottom formation or a W formation.
We'll call it a booty formation.
I don't know.
In this formation, you wait until we break
the resistance called the neckline.
We then wait for the confirmation bounce.
This is revealed to us after the breakout.
The price action uses the neckline as support.
We measure the target by measuring the bottom
of the W formation to the neckline, then
dragging the measurement to the top of the
neckline.
We can also use indicators to tell us
if we're unlikely to hit the exact target.
Indicators I like to use are EMAs, which
stands for Exponential Moving Average.
My settings are at 21, 90, 200, and
600.
This indicator will tell you when the price
is likely to hit short-term support or
resistance levels.
And there you have it.
Some of the useful tools that you can
use to get started in your own technical
analysis of your favorite stocks and cryptos.
I would recommend setting a reminder on your
calendar to rewatch this video in about a
month from now, just to ensure that everything
locks in.
And again, if you'd like even more content
and buy alerts, daily crypto trade signals, and
weekly coaching, make sure to check out my
Patreon, linked in the description below.
You will not regret it.
Also from here, I highly recommend you watch
my free Crypto for Beginners or free Stocks
for Beginners courses.
I will have these clickable on screen here.
And with that, I want to thank you
so much for watching, and I hope you
have a profitable day.