Heads is the bull and tails is the
bear.
And tails is the bear.
Tails, you're going to show us your trading
desk.
Let's go.
Peter Tuchman is one of the most famous
traders on the floor of the New York
Stock Exchange.
He's known as the Einstein of Wall Street.
And not just because of his looks.
The excitement, the adrenaline, we are the last
human marketplace in the world.
So what's important is...
He showed us why coming to the floor
still gives traders like him an edge over
people trading from home.
How you doing?
Good.
So this is me.
This is my spot.
So I'll give you a little breakdown of
what we do here.
This character was done to me back about
seven years ago.
It's become my brand.
Your first time that you came on this
floor and you stood here.
Do you remember the emotion that you felt?
And what was it?
100%.
I came on the floor.
I had gotten a summer job.
I was working under the podium there.
It was a bit of fear and excitement,
but the adrenaline came out and it was
roaring.
And I just said, I found where I
want to spend the rest of my life.
Not a bit more clear.
You guys all right?
I've been doing this for 40 years.
In 1985, when I started here, I was
a teletypist.
I went on to be a clerk.
And my goal was to become a broker,
basically a trader.
I still get butterflies in my stomach every
morning when I come into work.
It's like being in the Super Bowl.
We are more relevant now than ever as
brokers on the floor of the stock exchange
because the more technology you use, people tend
to get detached from the reality of the
human part of the market.
But the human element here is what made
this place.
I have a trading strategy, which I trade
on the close around the imbalances that only
come to the floor of the stock exchange.
That's one of the reasons I'm here every
day, because what we do and I do
down here cannot be done off floor.
And so I take that information, I analyze
it and I convey it to the customers
in a compliant way so that they're able
to have some kind of an edge to
trade the marketplace.
There came a wave of selling that sent
the 2,000 men on the floor of
the New York Stock Exchange scurrying.
In the old days, during open outcry on
the floor of the stock exchange, when there
were thousands of people down here trading and
screaming and yelling, if there was ever a
discrepancy or an argument around a trade, you
called in a governor and a governor had
what's called a flipping coin.
Whether it was a $10 problem, a million
dollar problem or whatever it was, you have
to flip the coin and you have to
live by the solution.
So I've had this in my pocket for
a long time, for 37 years.
Is it reversing?
No, market's getting smacked.
How did you survive it for decades?
How did you last?
I've had to reinvent myself many times.
I've had to sort of bob and weave.
I had to be flexible.
A lot of the people who I started
out here with are no longer here.
Either they retired or they were not able
to reinvent themselves.
There's been a huge transition over the years
of what a floor trader does.
We're standing, you know, in a place that
in 1650, you know, they were trading stocks
outside under the Buttonwood tree.
In 1903, they built this building.
We need to acknowledge that every industry has
been outsourced a little bit by technology.
We still have a plethora of human beings
here.
What is the most problematic emotion that you
deal with when you are trading?
Obviously fear, right?
The greatest emotion of all.
One of the biggest problems that day traders
have is they get emotional about money.
They get emotional about a trade, but it's
money.
You make it, you lose it.
What was the biggest failure that you learned
the most from?
In 2006, I literally spent two years not
making any money.
The market was going into a rough time.
And so for me, it was really a
struggle to find customers, to find business.
We were also going into a bit of
a transition with technology entering into the marketplace.
You really have to go out there and
fight for the business.
And yet I got up every morning.
I knew opportunity was not going to find
me, you know, cowering at home in bed,
feeling sorry for myself.
I figured one day things are going to
turn.
And in fact, they did.
Did you ever have doubt that you weren't
going to make it?
Oh, absolutely.
My parents are Holocaust survivors.
They found each other, fell in love and
came to America and got their American dream.
So they were two people that really woke
up with gratitude.
You know, you can live in fear or
you can live in faith and you can
live in victim mode or you can live
in gratitude.
What is your favorite indicator or indicators on
a chart?
Well, first of all, I'll tell you that
the S&P 500 for me is the
most exciting indices.
It is a basket of 500 stocks.
It really sort of tracks the movement of
the market and the economy in the globe.
And so I love that.
There are multiple indices that are super important,
whether it's exponential moving averages, whether it's pivot
points, whether it's the RSI, Relative Strength Index.
You have to look at all of them
together.
I would say moving averages and the RSI
are the most important because they basically are
the market.
They represent support and resistance.
They represent oversold and overbought conditions.
So as a day trader, for those who
day trade, that is the necessity to identify
that to really get your most out of
a trade.
My advice to day traders is don't make
decisions based on economic data and earnings.
Don't trade on FOMO and hype.
Who's Peter Tuchman outside of the trading floor?
I used to run a record store in
1980.
Jazz was a big part of my world.
I was also in the food business.
I had a hot sauce company back in
the 90s.
Art is a big passion.
I love to inspire and mentor young artists
as well.
You know, I don't sleep that much.
I am the ambassador of the stock exchange
in so many ways.
This is my home.
I eat, drink, sleep, the stock market.
And so I'm glad we could let you
in.