This video is sponsored by Squarespace.
Go to squarespace.com slash ThePlainBagel to save
10% off your first purchase of a
website or domain using code ThePlainBagel.
If I were to ask you about stock
trading, this would probably be the image that
comes to mind, the New York Stock Exchange
trading floor, a scene synonymous with stock investing
itself.
This is where traders meet in person to
buy and sell stocks, finding deals for their
clients and employers and yelling tickers and prices
across the trading floor.
While this used to be how most trading
was done, these days, you can do most
of the work online.
And advancements in technology have even allowed everyday
individuals to take up trading at home to
try and make money.
But despite the fact that trading involves stocks
and other investments, it is often seen as
a very different practice from investing, what you
or I probably do when we buy or
sell stocks.
You see, being a trader, whether professionally or
as a hobby, is different from being an
investor.
And while you've probably heard of people making
quite a bit of money off trading, it's
an area that most people are best served
avoiding.
Why?
We'll answer that question and more on today's
PlainBagel.
If you look at the literal definitions of
the terms investing and trading, you probably won't
grasp the difference between the two.
After all, investing is the act of spending
money with the hope of generating some larger
benefit or return in the future, while trading
is the act of buying or selling investments.
It's not very clear how the two differ.
In fact, there is no technical distinction dictating
what counts as trading and what counts as
investing.
But the terms are often used to refer
to two very different approaches to making money
from investments.
An investor is someone who places their money
in something and looks to profit from that
asset growing over time.
Whereas a trader is someone who makes money
in the short term by buying and selling
stocks frequently.
In other words, while one relies on gradual
appreciation, the other focuses on market volatility.
Now, being a trader can mean a number
of different things.
Many companies actually hire traders to help them
carry out their investment decisions.
For example, an investment firm may decide they
want to own shares of PlainBagel Co.
So they'll hire a trader to help them
get the best price for the shares.
In this video, however, we'll be focusing on
traders who operate with the sole objective of
making themselves money.
And there are two main areas wherein this
practice differs from investing.
The timing of trades and the analysis of
stocks.
For timing, as we mentioned, investing is typically
a long-term strategy, whereas trading is more
short-term.
When you invest in a stock, you're betting
that over time the company will grow, either
by expanding its asset base or its profits.
You can invest in a company for as
little time as you want, but generally speaking,
you'll be aiming to sell the stock two,
five, 10, even 30 years from now.
On a day-to-day basis, the price
of a stock may fluctuate.
And indeed, some investors try to take advantage
of that by buying when the stock's price
is abnormally low.
But once the purchase is made, the focus
tends to shift to the long-term movement
rather than the short-term volatility.
Trading, on the other hand, is the fast
and furious approach.
It involves buying and selling investments to take
advantage of short-term price swings.
Day trading, for example, involves individuals buying and
selling stocks same day.
While swing trading expands the process to a
few weeks, months, or sometimes years, there are
other styles of trading as well, but they
all tend to fall under fairly short timeframes,
sometimes even making buys and sells within a
matter of seconds.
Because of this, traders submit many more trades
than investors and often cycle through many more
positions.
But selling something shortly after buying it doesn't
alone make you a trader.
So let's move on to the second point
of distinction, the analysis.
To understand how the analysis of a company
and its stock price varies between traders and
investors, we first need to explain the difference
between a stock's price and its intrinsic value.
Theoretically, the price of a stock only reflects
the number of buyers and sellers trading that
stock at that given point in time.
And past this stock price, there is some
intrinsic value, a true worth of that stock
that only an omniscient being would know.
Over time, the price of the stock should
track closely to this intrinsic value as buys
and sells factor in company information known by
the investors.
But human factors like fear or greed might
lead a stock's price to deviate from its
actual worth from time to time.
Within the world of investing, people take two
approaches to this information.
Passive investors ignore short-term fluctuations in stock
prices and look only to benefit from the
rising intrinsic value, knowing that even if they
do buy an overpriced stock, they should benefit
in the longterm as the aggregate market grows.
Active investors instead try to estimate a stock's
intrinsic value so that they can buy the
stock for less than its worth, allowing them
to benefit not only from the rising intrinsic
value, but also from the return of the
price to its intrinsic level.
While these two approaches vary from one another,
they both generally depend on the intrinsic value
of a stock increasing.
Traders, on the other hand, only care about
the stock's price.
There is no attempt to estimate the intrinsic
value of their stocks.
And indeed, many traders buy and sell stocks
without even knowing what the company does, looking
only to take advantage of the short-term
swings or trends in its stock price.
For this reason, it's common for traders to
focus their analysis on technical indicators.
These are measures and gauges that only take
into account historical pricing information to help the
trader determine whether there's a developing trend or
pattern that they can quickly exploit.
It's the graphs and charts you imagine when
you think of a professional trader sitting in
front of their four screens buying and selling
stocks.
Now, some traders do incorporate qualitative information into
their research as well, but it is usually
only to take advantage of a short-term
shift that they're expecting in the stock's price.
For example, if a trader finds out that
a company is announcing news tomorrow, they may
decide to buy the stock with the belief
that the company's announcement will be positive, leading
to a jump in the stock's price.
In either case, traders generally only focus on
snippets of a company's information rather than trying
to develop a broader understanding of the firm's
operations.
So, those are the two primary ways trading
differs from investing.
It requires a very different mindset and operates
in a very fast-paced competitive environment.
Some would even argue that it requires a
fair amount of bluffing.
This was more so the case when traders
used to talk in person about the stocks
they wanted to buy and sell, but even
today, traders often try to hide their true
intentions when they submit an order.
After all, if you can convince other traders
that you don't want to buy something, you
may be able to get it for a
lower price, just like with anything else.
All of this can make trading a very
alluring practice for young investors.
I mean, competition, fast trades, quick payoffs, it's
got it all.
And with all the ads that we see
online of millionaires and their private jets explaining
how they went from zero to hero with
their $300 trading strategy, it probably seems like
a fairly easy field to enter.
But trading is a high-risk practice.
Most traders put a lot of money behind
their individual trades, sometimes even borrowing to leverage
their returns, which exposes them quite heavily to
short-term volatility of individual positions.
It also requires a lot of effort and
time.
Many trades only end up yielding a fraction
of a percentage point, meaning traders are continually
rolling their money into new positions.
And honestly, when it comes to amateur traders,
the truth is there just isn't that much
working in your favor.
With such a narrow timeframe, you're often forced
to make decisions on fragmented information.
And when you consider that you're competing with
industry professionals with copious amounts of money, cutting
-edge research, and even industry-best algorithms that
can trade faster than you can say the
word stock, it's just not a fair fight.
Now, I'm not saying you can't make money
trading.
There are people who make a full-time
living from their home with trading activities.
And some companies even offer salaried positions for
traders, like we mentioned earlier.
So there are some merits to the field,
but trading is a lot like playing poker.
You can be very good at it, and
indeed, some people do make a living from
it, but there's a lot of chance involved.
And with other great players at your table,
the odds are often not in your favor.
So any advisor will probably tell you that
investing is the better way to go for
the average person.
By carrying out more comprehensive research and holding
over the long-term, you're more likely to
benefit from the broad growth of the economy
and the stock market as a whole.
Sure, you won't get that same rush as
a tripled-levered buy on an out-of
-the-money put option, but that's probably for
the best.
After all, if you're looking for the rush
of high stakes and not-so-great odds,
you may as well go to the casino.
At least there, you'll get free drinks.
Thanks for watching.
If you like this video, make sure to
hit the like button.
If you like what we're doing here, make
sure to subscribe.
Hit the bell icon if you want notifications
about future videos.
If you have any feedback or topics you
want me to cover in a future video,
leave a comment down below.
For The Plain Bagel, my name's Richard Coffin.
Thanks for joining me today.
So perhaps your trading venture isn't going to
bring you the success and fortune you were
hoping for, but maybe you have your own
business you're trying to gain traction with, or
maybe you're looking to get your name or
your work out there for people to discover.
While there's no surefire way to achieve success,
there's no denying that having a website can
help you with whatever you're working on.
And today's sponsor has a great all-in
-one tool to help you build your online
presence.
Squarespace is a website builder with one of
the best structured editors in the space.
You can pick from one of over 70
themes and just drop your own content in,
so you don't need a graphic designer to
end up with a professional-looking website.
They've also got a bunch of features, including
email campaigns, appointment scheduling, and e-commerce capabilities
that allow you to sell products through your
page.
I use Squarespace for my own website, and
I find it really easy to use, but
don't just take my word for it.
You can try their page builder yourself for
free.
And if you do decide to launch, consider
using coupon code ThePlainBagel.
It'll save you 10% off your first
purchase of a website or domain, and it'll
support the channel.
So if you're looking to share something with
the virtual world, do it with Squarespace.