Hey, it's Clay at ClayTrader.com.
I am gonna be your guide here through
futures trading at a very beginner level and
a very basic level.
So I wanna quickly just tell you who
this is for because I don't wanna waste
your time.
If you are looking for the mathematical theory
of things, if you're looking for all the
different nooks and crannies of how the futures
markets work from the mathematical standpoint, you're probably
gonna be disappointed.
If you're looking for just, listen, I wanna
trade futures, I wanna know how do I
make money from futures.
Sure, I wanna know some broad aspects of
how the futures market works, what actually it
is.
From a broad sense, yeah, I wanna know
that.
But I'm more here for the practical, real
-world type applications, not a bunch of theory,
not a bunch of just mathematical equations that
I'd learn in some sort of textbook.
I wanna just know futures, sure, but I
wanna know how do you make money in
the market?
How do they work?
How will they put profit in my pocket?
If that's more of your mindset, then this
will be for you.
But again, if you're somebody that's looking for
the mathematical theory of it all, then you're
probably gonna be disappointed.
So keep that in mind.
And maybe you're on the fence, do I
even wanna learn futures?
One of the biggest benefits futures do allow
for people is that it is a way
around the pattern day trading rule.
So perhaps you're kinda stumbling around with that,
you're a little bit frustrated with it.
Futures trading does not have to, it doesn't
fall under those regulations.
So that's one thing that I would just
kinda throw out there that may get you
interested into the markets and wanna learn more
about them.
So with that being said, let's go to
my desktop and let's get this course and
class started.
Welcome to my desktop.
Before anything else, we need to take a
very wise approach to all this.
And the wise approach would be, well, let's
just figure out what the futures market even
is.
What's the purpose of it?
What is going on?
How is it interacting with the general markets
as a whole?
And once we know that, well, let's start
to make money from it.
But like I said, if we're gonna make
money from the futures market, it would probably
be wise to at least know what the
futures market is in the first place.
So that's what we're gonna do here with
this first class, establish a good solid framework
and foundation from which we can build upon
and then eventually start to make money from.
But let's just start, like I said, at
the ground floor and let's look at some
definitions here.
So let's grab our trusty Merriam-Webster dictionary
and look at each of these words.
So the first being future.
What does future actually mean?
Well, it's something that will exist or happen
at a later time.
The two key components there being something.
So, okay, something is what?
Happening at a later time.
And we'll get to more of that as
we go.
And then the next part is just a
market.
And a market is a meeting together of
people for the purpose of trade.
What we're concerned about and what we're gonna
look at is a meeting together of people.
So future market, just something.
And this something's happening at a later time.
And this is all being based within a
market and a market, a meeting together of
people.
So meeting together of people.
The logical question then becomes, okay, well, who
are these people?
Who are these people that are meeting together?
You know, what are they doing?
But who, right?
Very, very logical question.
So with that, you gotta keep in mind
that there are two main people that must
be involved for a market to exist.
Once again, very, you know, basic economics here.
You can't have a market if there's not
two people involved, right?
One person does not make up a market.
So who are these people that must be
involved?
Who are these people that make up the
market?
Well, you're gonna have a buyer and you're
gonna have a seller or just in general,
buyers and sellers.
And that brings up the next question.
Okay, well, what is the purpose of their
meeting?
And that is to negotiate a deal or
a trade, right?
That's what a marketplace does.
If you're going to the grocery store and
you wanna buy an apple, you are negotiating
a deal.
You're saying, okay, I will trade this piece
of money for that.
And you have to try to negotiate.
If you think it's priced too high, if
you think the seller is trying to rip
you off, well, then guess what?
As a buyer, there's no deal, right?
No deal, nothing's happening.
So again, we're keeping a very basic right
now and just economics 101.
That's what a marketplace is made up of.
Two people and these two people are buyers
and sellers.
Let's look at the next part here.
Something, and then this is happening at a
later time.
Now, at this point, the deal has been
made.
So that leads us to, all right, well,
what is the something of a deal?
I get it, a deal has been made,
but the something.
So what is this something?
And that is an agreement for a transaction
to take place at a later time in
the future.
There we go.
Are you seeing how everything's kind of coming
together here?
So a deal has been made.
And then the details of the deal, the
something of this deal, is just an agreement
for some kind of transaction.
So what kind of transaction?
Or in other words, what are the details
of this agreement?
So a little bit of context here.
Let's just say that when this particular agreement
is made, that the current date is August
15th.
So again, to reiterate, who is this happening?
Who is making, or who's this happening between?
Who's making up the marketplace?
Well, we have, again, the buyer.
And in our situation, in our little story
here that we're going through, let's say the
buyer in this story, they manufacture, they produce,
they sell, one of my all-time favorites,
Sour Patch Kids, all right?
So if you're not aware, Sour Patch Kids
aren't exactly healthy.
That's why I eat them in moderation.
But the buyer, one of their main ingredients
in Sour Patch Kids that they need to
buy is sugar, right?
So they're saying, you know what?
I would like to buy 100 pounds of
sugar for $1.50 per pound.
And then the other part of this market,
who would they be talking to?
Well, hopefully you have, the common sense would
say, well, if they're looking to buy sugar,
they're probably talking to somebody that sells sugar.
Very good job, exactly.
So they're talking to a seller that is
going to offer up, they produce sugar, right?
They have the big sugar cane fields, and
they are a producer of sugar.
So the seller looks at their proposal, the
buyer, and saying, all right, well, the buyer's
offering us $1.50 per pound, and they
wanna buy 100 pounds of sugar.
Well, you know what?
Yeah, I will produce that 100 pounds of
sugar for you.
And then the final part of this agreement,
the last little bit of detail, which is
very important for the futures market, is that
they are saying this transaction will take place
on October 15th.
Not to insult your intelligence, but again, as
far as our story is concerned, the current
date is August 15th.
So this deal, this transaction, will not actually
take place until two months later, right?
Two months into the future.
So that's what's going on here.
They are making an agreement for this transaction
to take place in the future, and that's
why this would be called a futures contract.
All a futures contract is, is an agreement
to buy or sell a commodity on a
given date for a given price.
So the agreement, again, in our situation right
there, and to buy, so what's going on
here?
Well, they wanna buy the 100 pounds of
sugar, or sell, so in this situation, the
seller is going to sell 100 pounds of
sugar for some commodity.
What is the commodity in this case?
Well, the commodity is actually the sugar itself.
What is a commodity in general, though?
Well, that's just a raw material or agricultural
product, and that can be bought and sold.
So it's a physical product.
It's something that you can pick up with
your hands.
You can smell, you can throw at somebody,
I guess, if you want.
So what are some other examples out there
of commodities?
Well, there's coffee beans, and these are all
things that can be traded in the futures
market.
There's oil, there's gold, corn, cotton, wheat, and
there are many others, but here's just kind
of a few of the more common ones,
but again, that's what a commodity is, just
a raw material, and then getting back into
the definition, this agreement, this futures contract is
all what?
It's going to happen on a given date,
so in this situation, October 15th, and then
for a given price, which we've established is
$1.50 per pound, but why in the
future?
Why agree to buy or sell something in
the future when you can just simply buy
it and sell it right now?
To understand, we got to go back to
kind of the foundations of business.
Even if you've never taken a business class,
that's okay.
This is very straightforward, but a principle in
business 101 that if, assuming, of course, you
want to be a successful company, assuming you
want to have a successful business, you need
to, at the very, very core, the forefront
of any decision you make, of any pathway
that you choose to take, you need to
always be attempting to do one thing, and
all companies, once more, assuming they want to
be successful, assuming they want to be profitable,
they are attempting to do this, and what
is this?
Well, that is try to manage risk.
Nobody knows the future.
There is no such thing as a crystal
ball.
Nobody can know for sure.
Nobody can be certain what's going to happen,
so you need to be able to do
your best to forecast what you believe is
going to happen, what you think is most
likely to happen, and that way, you can
manage risk the best part, so that's really,
and that's why I love that image.
That's what companies are trying to do.
They're trying to go from uncertainty to certainty.
No guarantees, no crystal balls.
Nobody can tell the future, but the better
a company is at managing the risk, the
better a company is at trying to erase
that uncertainty, or erase the un from uncertainty,
that's a good thing.
That's going to give them a leg up
on their competition.
That's how companies get so big is they're
just so good at managing the unknown.
They're just so good at making decisions based
off of what they think is gonna be
in their best favor from a risk management
perspective, so risk management, the other word for
this would just be hedging, so hedging.
That's what is going on in the futures
market at the foundational core is risk management,
and in futures market terminology, that would be
known as hedging, so let's look at each
person in the agreements perspective, and we'll start
with the buyer's perspective.
Now, a buyer from a business point of
view, a huge focus for that buyer is
what?
They wanna make money, of course, and they're
gonna make money, and their goal is gonna
be, well, they wanna keep their cost of
production as controlled and predictable as possible.
Not guaranteed, but let's just try to keep
our costs as controlled, and just keep it
as predictable as possible because that's gonna make
our life easier to do forward-looking projections
and all that, so from the buyer's perspective,
when they say, all right, well, we need
sugar to make those Sour Patch Kids, so
they're thinking, you know what?
In the future, I believe a pound of
sugar might actually rise up above $1.50
per pound, so if that's what the buyer's
thinking, that's why they're thinking, you know what?
If we think, now, why do they think
that?
I mean, they have, for some reason, they
believe that sugar prices are gonna be going
up, so that's why they're saying, you know
what?
Let's just lock in the price.
Let's get the price of $1.50 locked
in, so that's what we're gonna do that,
so they got it locked in per that
agreement.
Let's now say, as part of this story,
a tornado comes, and sugar crops are destroyed
just all over the place, and because of
that, all of a sudden, there's less sugar,
and when there's less supply, right, supply and
demand, less supply of something, but the demand
stays the same, well, that's gonna shift prices
up, so let's say that the new market
price is $2.25 per pound.
Now, here's a quiz for you that I
want you to answer.
What does the buyer pay?
What price per pound are they paying, okay?
Hopefully, I gave you enough time.
If you said, you know what?
They're paying $2.25 per pound, because that's
the new market price, that would be wrong.
They are paying $1.50 per pound.
Why?
Because, well, that's what they agreed to.
Remember that agreement.
In the future, we're buying it at $1
.50 per pound, so sure, that's, I mean,
for the sugar company, that's not a very
good deal, because had they not entered into
that agreement, they could be selling that 100
pounds for $2.25 per pound, but because
they did enter into it, ah, now they
gotta sell it for $1.50 per pound.
Of course, from the buyer's perspective, hey, all
right, we made a good decision.
No, good job, they're all high-fiving each
other.
We're only paying $1.50 per pound, great.
Yeah, our competitors, ha, too bad they're not
as smart as us.
They're over there paying $2.25 per pound,
but us, yeah, we're gonna be able to
make those Sour Patch kids for $1.50
per pound.
Now let's take a look at the other
side, the seller's perspective.
A huge focus now for the seller.
Of course, they wanna make money, too.
This is just business, but how are they
gonna make money?
How is the seller gonna make money?
Well, they're gonna make money by just selling
their product for as high as the market,
you know, the buyers are willing to pay,
right?
That's just basic stuff there.
If you're looking to sell something to make
money, yeah, the higher you can sell that,
that would be the goal because that's gonna
be the more profit.
So from the seller's perspective, they're gonna be
thinking something like this when they enter into
the agreement.
You know what?
In the future, I believe that a pound
of sugar might drop below $1.50. That's
the thing.
Now, why do they believe that?
I mean, they're gonna have their reasonings, they're
gonna have their economic models, but for whatever
reason, they believe that in the future, yeah,
you know what?
I think $1.50 is getting pretty high.
I don't think this price is gonna last
very long.
So that's why they're saying, you know what?
Yeah, yes, producer of Sour Patch Kids, we
will sell, we agree to produce to you
100 pounds of sugar in the future for
$1.50 per pound because in the back
of their mind, they're thinking, yeah, because I
mean, if you would just wait, you can
probably get it for cheaper, but I mean,
if you're willing to pay us $1.50
now, okay, we'll take it.
So to carry on with the story, they
get that approved, and then all of a
sudden, the supply of sugar just increases all
over the place.
You have a bunch of new people getting
into the business of selling sugar.
You have sugar cane crops popping up all
over the place.
So once again, Economics 101, when all of
a sudden supply of something increases, well, that's
going to cause prices to what?
To go down.
So the new market price all of a
sudden is $1.15. So let's go through
the quiz again.
The question this time being, so what does
the seller receive?
How much does the seller get?
Are they getting $1.15 or $1.50?
If you're saying, well, they're getting $1.50
per pound, you would be right, because that's
what the agreement was.
So who's kind of getting the short end
of the stick here?
Who's feeling some pain?
Oh man, the buyer, because the buyer's saying,
oh, I mean, we signed that contract.
We made that agreement.
We have to buy it at $1.50?
Oh, oh, that's not going to be very
pleasant.
Now the seller's thinking, yes, we were right.
They're all high-fiving because, oh yeah, other
people are having to sell their sugar for
a dollar.
All those other competitors out there, they're having
to sell their sugar at $1.15 per
pound.
But because we made this agreement with the
Sour Patch Company, we're able to sell it
for $1.50 per pound.
And they're feeling very, very good about themselves.
I mean, it would have been a good
transaction on their part.
But this is all theory.
This is all just the basics of how
it works.
But let's move into getting a little bit
more practical here.
And this will be kind of the launch
point for you and I to be able
to start to make money from the futures
market itself.
Unless, of course, you are a maker of
some sort of product, then yeah, maybe you
would want to have more of this approach.
But I would assume that probably 99%
of people watching this are going to be
wanting to get a little bit more practical
with all this.
But it's good to know what actually is
going on, like I said, behind the scenes
here.
So the strategy of hedging are the pillars
of the futures market.
Like I said, that's the foundation.
Those are the pillars that we want to
build upon.
And this is also what is known as
a physical settlement.
However, for us, I mean, like I said,
the vast majority of people here and the
vast majority of people in the market itself,
I mean, they're not producers, they're not manufacturers,
all right?
So majority of the people, I want to
say that in the, because I'll make this
thing, so I already made the comment about,
yeah, I'm assuming most of you watching, which
is true also.
But please also understand that as far as
the futures market as a whole, the vast
majority of people participating in it, they're not,
they're like you and I, right?
They're not producers, they're not manufacturers of any
sort of commodity that what they would need
ingredients for or anything like that.
So this is what would be known as
the speculators.
You have hedging with the physical settlement, and
then you have speculators, and this is the
investors, this is the traders.
So you and I can get involved through
what is known as the cash settlement.
Because we're not interested in, I'm assuming nobody
here wants 100 pounds of sugar to show
up at their door.
So assuming that is correct, then yeah, you
would want to be getting involved through the
cash settlement.
But the point here is that we can
indeed get involved in the futures market through
speculation, by being an investor, by being a
trader.
And yeah, that's definitely exciting, that's good.
I'm glad we can get involved.
So what are the types of futures markets?
Pretty much, there are two broad markets speculators
can choose from.
So if you're saying, you know what?
Yeah, I want to get in the futures
market, I want to get involved, let's go.
There are two types of markets you can
choose from, two types of futures.
So the first type is commodity futures, which
we've already talked about.
These are the raw materials.
They can be metals, they can be agriculture,
they can be energy, I mean, they can
be livestock.
Like I said, anything that you could pick
up, grab, smell, like I said, throw at
somebody.
You might have a hard time throwing a
cattle at somebody, but you get the point
here, right?
Like they are items that you can see,
you can pick up with your hand.
And then the other type is financial futures.
And these are literally just pieces of paper.
These are just, you know, they're some sort
of paper that says, hey, this represents some
other sort of abstract object, like a currency.
Have you ever thought of like the money
that you hold in your hand?
Why does that mean anything?
Well, because there's this abstract idea, there's this
belief that, well, there's value in there.
But is there actually value in that piece
of paper?
I mean, I guess maybe if you're looking
to try to start a fire, there'd be
some real life practical value.
But other than that, no, I mean, it's
not like you're gonna be able to, you
know, a hammer and Allen with a piece
of paper in your hand.
So these are just objects that represent abstract
ideas.
So you'd have indices.
And the most popular for these would be
the S&P 500.
You have futures contracts attached to those.
And we'll actually be talking about those in
future classes.
But you can do it in regards to,
you know, currency exchange rates, and then just
even interest rates and treasuries themselves.
And these are all the contracts revolving around
debt.
And, you know, you can do either people.
Some people trade commodity futures.
Some people just wanna focus on financial futures.
But the point here being is that these
are the two broad types of, you know,
futures markets that exist and the types of
futures that would be out there.
You have commodity futures and then financial futures.
So how do speculators make money?
Well, let's look at our example here.
And remember, we had that $1.50 price.
And that is going to be what we
would consider and call, in our example here,
the spot price.
And spot price is something you'll see out
there.
But just understand that a spot price, all
that means is that's the current price.
Right now, at this very moment, if you
wanted to buy sugar, it would be $1
.50 per pound at this very moment.
The current price, that is the spot price.
But spot prices don't stay the same.
So as time moves forward, things are gonna
start to change around.
Spot prices are gonna change.
Spot prices could rise up to the 2
.25 mark.
Spot prices could go down to, let's call
it that $1.15 mark.
All right, so why?
Why are spot prices changing?
Well, I mean, you could have weather.
You could have government decisions.
You could have just world events.
You know, just stuff happens in the world.
Interest rates, maybe interest rates change something.
Speculation itself, that's always the entertaining and crazy
part, not necessarily just about the futures market,
but really all financials markets as a whole
is, well, why is the price changing?
I don't know, because you got a bunch
of traders.
You got a bunch of investors making different
decisions.
So it's not like, from an economic standpoint,
supply and demand has changed at all.
I mean, supply and demand could be the
exact same thing, but prices could be changing.
Spot prices could be changing just simply because
of speculation, investors, traders, acting, and that's it.
So that's always the crazy part about the
market is sometimes nothing happens at all.
Supply and demand remains the exact same, but
spot prices are still fluctuating.
Well, because you have a bunch of traders
and investors that make up the market.
So let's think about the value of the
contract.
Because of this change in spot price, what
is the value of this contract gonna be
doing?
And again, the contract between the buyers and
the sellers.
Well, when spot prices change, the value of
the contract changes.
I wanna say that again, if you're taking
notes, definitely write that down because this is
how you make money.
This is how the futures market opens up
the door to you and I to make
money.
When spot prices change, again, the whole why,
we just talked about, could be for a
variety of reasons, but when the spot prices
change, the value of the contract changes.
The value of that futures contract itself is
going to change.
It's gonna go up and down and all
over.
And right here, the change in the value
of the contract itself is what allows speculators,
again, traders, us investors, to make, or of
course, lose money from the contract.
And who are these traders?
Well, the traders are anybody you can imagine.
They can be people down on Wall Street.
They can be people in the retirement home
if they have the internet access.
They could be, you know, whoever wants to
get involved in that is the power of
this day and age of technology and the
internet and software and brokerages and platforms is
anybody can be participating.
Anybody can be making money from this fluctuation,
from this change in the value of a
futures contract.
So you don't need any requirements.
You don't need to go to college.
You don't need to have a college degree.
I mean, theoretically, it wouldn't necessarily be wise,
but you could just open up in the
next five minutes a futures account and be
trading, you know, the value of contracts.
I mean, in theory, if you wanted to.
That's just the day and age of technology
we live in, but that is how we
are gonna be making money.
That is how the opportunity to make money
actually arises is because spot prices change, the
value of contracts change.
And because the value of contracts change, there
is an opportunity in there for traders, speculators
to make money.
So where does all this actually happen though?
Well, this all happens on what is called
the futures exchange.
Let's once more quickly get out our dictionary.
So what does exchange mean?
Well, that is the act of giving or
taking one thing in return for another, but
we can boil this down a little bit
more.
So in our case, as far as the
futures exchange is concerned, it's the act of
giving or taking contracts in return for, well,
in our case, money.
We're giving money, we're getting contracts, and so
on and so forth.
Now, these markets can be found all over
the world.
The most famous of them all is where
it all actually started, and that would be
the Chicago Mercantile Exchange, the CME.
If you maybe you've already done some research
on the futures and maybe you've seen CME
places, that's what that's standing for.
But as far as, because I wanna make
this timeless presentation.
So if you're watching this several years from
now, as far as, because things change, right?
Now, the Chicago Mercantile Exchange has been around
for decades upon decades, but you never know.
So in order to keep this timeless, just
get out a bit of technology.
If Google doesn't exist, maybe 10 years from
now when you're watching this, there's some little
robot butler that will come down from the
ceiling and you can just ask them.
But what you're gonna wanna be asking or
just typing into the search engine is just
type in futures exchange, insert whatever country you
live in, and then insert the year and
it'll do its thing.
It'll spit out all the information about the
current futures exchanges that exist out there.
And you can then keep up to date
on everything from that point of view.
So that's what I have here.
Let's go back to me at my desk
and we'll wrap this up.
Well, hopefully now you have a much better
understanding of what the futures market is, how
it works, what the purpose of it actually
is, and then who these players are.
And then from that, that'll give us a
good foundation that we can build from in
future classes, no pun intended.
Before I go though, a few things.
First off, if you enjoyed this, just let
me know, hit that like button.
And then also leave a comment down below
in terms of what you would like to
see in the next classes I put together.
Maybe you actually had a question on this
class in and of itself, so you can
ask those.
Or like I said, if you wanna give
me some suggestions for future videos, again, sorry,
no pun intended, then leave those down in
the comment section.
But if nothing else and you're just, hey,
I enjoyed it, then hit that like button.
And over time, I'll try to do some
more series and classes like that.
So just like I said, the easiest way
to communicate, hit that like button.
Also check out the channel.
The entire channel is not necessarily just about
futures trading.
It's more about just kind of money in
general, growing wealth, taking control of your finances.
So there's stock market stuff, options market stuff,
personal finance, some real estate stuff.
So check out the channel as a whole
and hopefully you decide to ultimately subscribe to
the channel also.
But if nothing else, like I said, hit
that like button, leave a comment down below,
and I'll see you back for class number
two.
First off, thanks so much for watching the
entire video.
Real quick, before you go, I wanna invite
you to a live webinar, web class, training,
workshop, online event, whatever you wanna call it,
but it will be me live revealing to
you what I've discovered that has allowed me
to transform myself from being an employee to
being my own boss, including how I had
only one losing day out of 73 days
in total.
I'm gonna cover three keys that have helped
me unlock profitable consistency within the markets.
The first key is super weird, but in
a productive type of way.
The second key is super awesome because it
quite literally is wired into our DNA as
humans, making it very easy to use.
But in a cruel way, this becomes a
pitfall for many traders.
I'll explain it all though, including how to
avoid the pitfall that it creates for some.
And yeah, the third key, when you hear
it, sounds way too good to be true,
but it's not.
And I'll show you how it all works.
Then at the end, I open it up
for a question and answer session that is
again, totally live.
Even if you can't make the live session,
please still sign up as it will be
recorded and you can go back and watch
the replay that I will send you.
Click the image on the screen or click
the link down in the description box so
you can get the date and time and
claim your spot, which I should note is
limited due to the fact that this truly
is a live event.
If you have any questions, let me know.
If not, I'll be seeing you soon.