So in this video, we are going to
make a game in 10 minutes.
So at the end of the video, you
will have something like this.
And we are going to use something called
code.
This is powered by Unreal Engine 4.
So this is quite powerful and way beyond
Roblox and other tools.
So if you want to start making games,
but you don't know all the aspects of
game development, this video is perfect for you.
So first I'll leave a link down in
the description.
You can click that link and you can
go to this website.
So you need to make an account here.
So just sign up and after signing up,
you can download code.
After installing it, you can open it.
So we can create a new project either
by selecting the empty project or we can
create a project using a gameplay framework.
So we are going to select a gameplay
framework.
And as you can see, code gives us
a lot of gameplay frameworks to work with.
So we have a battle royale, we have
a deathmatch.
So you can really make full-fledged multiplayer
games and you don't need to worry about
any networking and stuff.
So I'm going to do a multiplayer video
later.
But in this video, we are going to
use the dungeon crawler framework.
So you can name your project whatever you
like and you can just create this project.
And this is the interface of code.
Now, what we are going to do is
we are going to select the maps folder
in the hierarchy and the map folder contains
all the objects that are in the scene.
So you can select the map folder and
you can delete it because I'm going to
start from scratch.
After that, you can go under the core
content.
And in this core content panel, you have
all kinds of objects.
You have 3D objects, animated meshes, audio decals,
particle systems, materials.
So you have all kinds of objects here.
So we are going to search for sky
and we are going to pick the night
sky.
So this is just a skybox.
Actually, this is a skysphere.
After you have created the sky, you can
go in the terrain editor and you can
generate a new terrain.
I'm going to generate a flat terrain and
you can click the generate button.
After that, we are going to search for
something called as a spawn point.
And this spawn point object decides the position
of the player in the beginning of the
game.
So you can drag the spawn point object
in your scene.
And if you test it out, the player
spawns at that position.
So let's give our terrain a material.
So you can go under the material section.
So I'm going to use this triplanar landscape
material.
After you have selected your material, you can
sculpt the terrain and by default, you have
the surface tool selected.
So there are a lot of brushes that
you can use to sculpt your terrain.
After you have done sculpting, you can select
the smooth tool and you can just smooth
this out and this will give your terrain
a very natural look.
So just smooth this out and I will
recommend you that you play with all these
brushes.
You can really make some interesting things with
this.
So after we are done sculpting, we are
going to add some foliage.
So under the foliage panel, so you can
search for grass and you can add the
grass.
You can change the distance between each grass.
So if you decrease the distance, you get
a very dense looking grass.
So now our grass is looking good.
You can stop here, but I'm going to
add one more grass.
So I'm going to add the tall grass.
Variation is the key thing while you are
creating natural looking scenes.
We are going to add some trees now
and this is quite similar to how we
added our grass meshes.
So our forest scene looks pretty good.
So now we are going to select the
spawn point and I'm going to add a
mesh on our spawn point.
So this will sort of define the starting
position of our player.
So this is just for visual purposes.
So you can search for an arch and
I'm going to add the arch mesh in
my scene.
After that, you can go in your hierarchy
and you can search for fog and you
can select the environment fog.
So you can move the fog on the
z-axis.
So after you have changed the height of
your fog, you can change the color of
this fog.
You can also turn on the volumetric fog
if you like, and the volumetric fog is
quite powerful.
It gives your scene a very realistic and
atmospheric look.
Now let's make things interesting.
At the moment, we don't have any enemies
in our scene.
So let's add some enemies.
Under the project content, you can search for
a skeleton.
I'm going to add a skeleton swordsman.
So let's test it out.
So the player can damage the skeleton and
the skeleton can also damage the player.
So the combat system is working really well.
So this looks pretty good.
Now the default dagger that the player has
is really quite boring weapon.
So I'm going to search for a fire
sword and I'm going to add this fire
sword in my scene.
So we can equip the fire sword and
this fire sword has a very anime-like
moveset.
And I really like this, like it has
some particles for the trail effects.
Cool stuff.
After we have added the fire sword, we
are going to give our character the ability
to roll and to heal.
So you can go in the community content
and you can search for basic abilities.
So this will give you some basic abilities,
such as a healing ability and a rolling
ability.
So you can just import this package.
Just import this.
After you have imported this, you can see
the basic abilities package under the imported content.
So just add this abilities object in your
scene.
So you can select the roll object and
the roll object is currently bound to the
ability feet.
So the action binding is the ability feet.
So you can change that by going under
settings.
So as you can see, here are all
the abilities and the abilities are bound to
a certain key.
So the ability feet is bound to spacebar.
So the spacebar key will be used for
the roll ability.
After that, let's move our UI to the
left-hand side.
You could also disable this UI if you
like.
So back in our abilities, we are going
to select the heal ability.
Here are all the settings that you can
change.
So for instance, you can change whether the
character can move while he is healing.
You can set the execution time.
You can set the recovery rate.
You can also set the cooldown of this
ability.
So just to show you how much variety
there is, I'm going to add this ice
elemental.
The ice elemental has a very cool move
set.
So from here on, you can create more
interesting levels and you can add more enemies
and you can really pretty much make your
own game.
So after you have made your own game,
I'm going to show you how you can
publish the game.
So go under the file and you can
select the publish option.
And here you can define the name of
your game.
You can write a short summary about your
game and you can also add tags.
And these tags are going to help other
players find your game.
So after you have decided the name of
your game, you have written a short summary
and you have added your tags.
It's time to add some screenshots.
So you can upload your own screenshots, but
there is also option to take screenshots in
engine.
So let's take a screenshot of this.
Let's take the screenshot of the skeleton.
And finally, let's take the screenshot of this
ice guy.
Make sure that the game is set to
public.
Now you can pretty much publish your game.
And as you can see, we have successfully
published our game.
So your game now has a link on
the core store.
So let's visit the game page.
So here you can see our game page
looks pretty similar to steam.
So at the end, I modified some things
and I changed some things.
So it took me around 40 to 45
minutes to make this.
So you can watch the full gameplay here.
But first, if you like this video, leave
a like down below.
It helps a lot.
Subscribe to the channel.
Enjoy the gameplay.
I'm going to see you in the next
video.
Bye.