So the trick to Android development is to
choose the right tools for the job and
to learn only the skills you really need
to build the kind of app that you
want to make.
I believe that the best tool for Android
game development is Unity.
It makes the whole process so much quicker
and simpler, so much so that in this
video I'm going to show you how you
can get something up and running in just
seven minutes.
So Unity is a game engine, that means
it handles things like the physics and controls,
it provides certain assets for you ready-made,
it basically makes the whole process of creating
a game much simpler, so you can focus
on what makes the game unique and on
the assets and on the design and let
Unity handle a lot of the more advanced
code.
You only need very little code to get
started with Unity and what you do use
you can find tons of guides and references
online to help you through.
That said, Unity is still very powerful, very
flexible and it's used by a lot of
professional developers.
In fact many of your favorite games from
the Play Store were probably built using Unity.
Were you to try and make a game
in Android Studio you'd need to learn Java,
you need to understand classes and libraries, you
need to create the physics engine yourself, so
you're handling things like gravity and collision, whereas
Unity does all that for you and makes
it so much easier, while still being as
powerful as you could need even as a
professional developer.
If you're someone who'd like to create an
Android game but you think maybe it's too
difficult, it involves too much code, then I
hope this video is going to demonstrate just
how quick and simple and easy the whole
process can be.
I'm going to really run through it though,
so if you want to slow things down
and understand what each step does, then follow
the link in the description down below.
As you'll see though, the process really is
very simple.
You don't need any prior knowledge and as
long as you've got Unity and the Android
SDK installed on your computer already, then you'll
be good to go.
Okay so seven minutes, let's go!
So the first thing you want in any
game is probably player character, so you're going
to open up Paint or whatever, I mean
obviously there's better tools to use for this,
but this is all about the gravity.
And the easiest and quickest player character to
make is a square with a face, full
of attitude this guy.
You're going to take Squarey and you're going
to drop him into your game like that,
so he's a sprite.
We also need some platforms for him to
walk on, so drag your platform into your
game in the exact same way.
Cool thing is, look, you can drag and
reshape this, so if you copy that and
then paste it, you can make as many
as you want.
Select your player character, Squarey, and then you're
going to open up here on the right,
the Inspector.
In the Inspector, you're going to say Add
Component, Physics 2D, Rigid Body 2D.
So this is basically 2D physics for your
character.
What we're going to do is we're going
to drag the camera onto Squarey like so
in the hierarchy.
These along the top here are controls that
you can use to decide what you want
to do with your game objects, and that
one's used for moving stuff around.
If we place it right on top of
Squarey, then it kind of makes more sense
because you can click play and now he's
in the center of the screen.
So anything that's a child of anything else
will follow that thing around.
Anyways, enough talk.
Work.
Okay, so select Squarey.
The problem you can obviously see here is
he's falling through the ground, so we want
to add another component, and this time we're
going to add Physics 2D, Box Collider 2D,
and we're going to do the same thing
with the platform here.
Add Component, Physics 2D, Box Collider 2D.
Once more, and if we copy these now,
then we'll also be copying over that new
collider and the new physics.
Okay, so now click play, and hey, that's
starting to look more promising.
Okay, now the next thing we're going to
do is create our first script so that
we can actually start controlling what happens in
this game.
But don't worry, it's very easy.
So first of all, go down to your
assets folder in the project window here, and
you're going to right-click anywhere and say
Create Folder Script.
Now, with that open, right-click and say
Create C Sharp Script, and we're going to
call this Player Controls.
Okay, so double-click on that, and it
should open up Visual Studio for you here.
All right, and this is your first script.
You'll see there's already some code here.
I'm referring to a reference here because I'm
not, you know, Mr. Remember.
However, I did write the reference, so it
doesn't feel like cheating.
All right, so what we're doing up here
is we're going to create a new object
of the type Rigidbody 2D.
Like I say, don't worry too much about
this.
You can learn as you go.
It's going to be that same Rigidbody that
is attached to our player character.
So in order to move our character, all
we need to do is say RB, which
is the new Rigidbody, which refers to the
Rigidbody attached to our player.
Velocity equals new Vector2, and that's a point
that has two axes, and we're going to
say 1.
That seems like a decent speed to start
off with, and then RB Velocity Y.
Okay, so now open back up Unity.
Click on your player like that, and then
go to Add Component just as you did
before.
This time we're going to say Scripts, and
then there you have it.
You have your player control script that you
made.
Click Play.
We should speed along.
Well, speed along is a strong word, but
yeah, he's certainly moving.
I think that's three.
He's going to move three times as quickly.
Yeah, that's challenging.
We want to open up our script again.
Okay, and then we're going to say during
our method, if input getMouseButtonDown, index
zero, then we're going to say RB Velocity
Y.
RB Velocity equals new Vector2.
RB Velocity X, and then we'll make that
three.
So if the player clicks the mouse whilst
the game is running, then he should move
upwards now.
I know what you're thinking.
You're saying, Adam, there isn't a mouse click
on Android, but that's the cool thing because
a mouse click is equivalent to tapping anywhere
on the screen.
Bear with me.
We're just going to type out some variables,
and you don't need to worry about what
these mean.
I will explain it all as we go.
On ground, so our Boolean, our true or
false statement equals physics2D overlap circle ground check
dot position ground check radius.
What is ground?
I'm going to add one more thing here,
which is and on ground.
Now we're going to create a new empty
game object, and we're going to call that
check ground, and this is an invisible object
that we're going to use to see if
there's an overlap to see whether or not
we're hovering over the ground.
Of course, we want it to move as
Squarey moves, so just like the camera, I'm
going to drop it underneath Squarey so that
it becomes a child.
Now if you click Squarey, you should see
that in the script we have some new
options, and the ground check is a transform.
Then take check ground and drop it in
to ground check.
I'm going to set the radius to 0
.1. We want it to be nice and
small, and then now we're going to create
our new layer mask.
So select your platform, and up here in
the inspector, you can see it has the
option for layer, and you're going to go
add layer.
Then you're going to make this layer called
ground.
If you click back to the inspector, you
can now select ground as your layer.
Okay, so now go back to your player,
and then the last public variable, what is
ground, you're going to set that to your
new layer, as ground.
Now, fingers crossed it should work, unless we've
forgotten something.
So when he's on the ground, you can
click click, and he'll jump.
When he's not on the ground, he doesn't
jump.
There you go, and that is the basis
of a fun little game.
And yeah, if you followed my advice at
the start of this video, and you went
through the installation process, and set up Unity
and the Android SDK, you should now be
able to test your game on your Android
phone.
And it's quite a great feeling when you
see it come to life on your device.
Okay, so it's something pretty basic, but it's
a great foundation to build upon.
And there's not that much more code necessary
for handling things like enemies, collectibles, next levels,
and tilt controls.
Once you've done that, you can just focus
on designing your different graphics and dragging them,
dropping them into the scene.
So I hope you found this video useful
and interesting, guys.
If you did, then please leave a like.
Subscribe to the channel if you'd like to
see more like this.
Hit the bell button if you want notifications.
Comment down below if you have any questions.
And of course, check out AndroidAuthority.com, for
we are your source for all things Android.