So, you want to make a game.
You got a perfect dream game idea, with
everything already planned in your head, but you
don't know how to code, let alone how
to make a game?
Well, you have come to the right place.
I am going to share with you a
few tips and tricks to help you get
started on your very own dream game.
You're ready?
Alright, here we go.
Tip number one, don't.
Okay, alright, well, what I mean by that
is, you can't just run straight to the
final boss right away, you know?
You gotta play the tutorial first.
It's the same for game development.
Every single time I've tried to learn a
new game engine, just so I could make
a single game idea I had in mind,
I failed miserably.
Instead, the only times I was able to
make a game was when either A.
I was just messing around with the engine
and adding random stuff for fun, or B.
I already knew how to use the engine
and had a game idea that would work
well on it.
You see, game development has a steep learning
curve, and when you know nothing, it can
all seem extremely daunting.
Not only do you need to learn how
to use a game engine, you need to
learn some sort of programming language and basic
game making concepts.
And if you're one of those people who
give up immediately after trying something new, just
because you're not super good at it right
away, you're gonna have a hard time.
If that's the case, my first real tip
for you is, do not try to learn
Unity or Unreal.
These are for the big boys only, alright?
You should start really really small, and lower
your expectations on yourself.
In fact, you'll have to start from Scratch.
Literally.
So, Scratch is a game engine that uses
its very own programming language, and you can
both play and make Scratch games directly on
the website.
Instead of writing code, you use little blocks
of pseudocode and put them together to create
logic.
And in my opinion, this is the best
way to learn programming and basic game logic.
Unlike with say, Unity, here you don't have
to worry about learning the engine.
Everything is super straightforward and neatly organized, so
you can focus on learning.
Scratch also comes with a sprite editor that
uses vector graphics, which means that instead of
drawing with pixels, you draw using shapes, which
means they can be scaled and moved as
much as you want without ever losing quality.
As you may have seen in the background,
I made a very simple little game as
a demonstration.
You have red balls coming at you from
both sides of the screen, and you avoid
them by moving the cat with the arrow
keys.
Once you get hit three times, it's game
over.
I made all of that in just under
20 minutes.
It's pretty simple, but it just goes to
show how easy to use Scratch is.
Now, don't get me wrong, you can make
really impressive things on Scratch.
People have made 3D games with it in
the past, but that's more for the kind
of people who do it just for the
challenge.
You know, the kind of people who port
Doom on any electronic device just for fun.
But that's not what we're here for today.
Now, some of you might be thinking, why
should I learn how to use Scratch when
I could be learning how to code instead?
And to that I say, coding, and by
extension, learning how to code, is much, much
easier when you already understand programming logic.
Once you know how to program, you basically
already know how to code, and all you
need to learn is the structure and syntax
of the language.
Alright, so, you've used Scratch for a little
while now, and made a couple little games,
and you're starting to get a feel for
programming.
You're now probably ready for the next step.
Unless you think you can make your dream
game on Scratch, in which case, I will
not stop you.
But if that's not the case, you'll be
asking yourself the question that every single new
game developer will ask themselves.
What engine should I use?
And that's a really good question, so let's
go over some popular game engines.
I'll start with some simpler ones, and then
we can work our way up in difficulty.
Assuming you don't want to learn how to
code, there are codeless engines out there that
you can use, like GDevelop and Construct.
I've never actually used them, but I'm sure
they're great for beginners.
Also, they're both free to use.
Next up is GameMaker Studio 2.
I've only ever used the OG GameMaker, but
it's probably about the same.
You can use both visual programming and code,
so I guess it's got a little something
for everyone.
It's responsible for popular indie games like Deltarune
and Pizza Tower, so you can absolutely make
some pretty good games with it.
It's also free to use, but if you
want to publish your game, you need to
pay for a subscription.
RPG Maker is a little more niche.
I'm not going to go into too much
detail because I plan to make a video
on it eventually, but if you want to
make a simple top-down story-focused game
with no major unique gameplay mechanics, then yeah,
RPG Maker is great.
It's mostly codeless, but you are allowed to
fully customize the game if you do know
how to code.
Otherwise, the engine is pretty limited.
It does cost money, but there's a 30
-day free trial you can use to see
if you like it first.
Click Team Fusion, the engine that brought us
both Five Nights at Freddy's and Baba is
You.
It's completely codeless and can be surprisingly powerful,
and I really like how it lets you
easily access and modify data from every object
from anywhere in the code.
Oh, but it's also the engine with the
highest price that I know of.
I mean like, okay look at this.
Base engine is $100, add-on with extra
features $60, 3D game tools $80.
What's this?
You want to port your game to something
that's not a Windows computer?
Well, better pay up, pal.
Mac exporter $50, web page exporter $70, Android
and iOS exporter $100 each.
Developer upgrade $300.
If you want the full complete Click Team
experience, it'll cost you $860.
There is a free version you can use
forever, but it's very limited.
Alright, now all of the engines I've looked
at so far have been primarily 2D focused,
but if you want something that can do
3D, you'll have to use one of the
big three.
Unity, Unreal, and Godot.
Now I absolutely don't recommend using any of
these as your first game engine, but if
you really need to, then Godot engine is
by far the most beginner-friendly out of
the three.
However, it's also by far the least popular,
which means it's a lot harder to find
help and support.
In contrast, Unity has like a bajillion tutorials
out there.
Oh, but Godot is 100% free, so
you can publish and monetize your game with
no subscriptions or royalties whatsoever.
No pro version with extra features.
You have access to the whole thing for
free.
So, now that you've chosen your engine, you
can start working on your dream game, right?
Wrong.
Don't start working on that dream game of
yours unless you know for sure you know
the engine well enough that it seems doable.
Otherwise, you'll just quit halfway when you realize
it's harder than you expected.
Try to remember this quote.
Don't learn the engine to make a game.
Make a game to learn the engine.
That's a quote from me.
I made it up.
But essentially, the best way to learn any
engine is by making very small and simple
games and slowly increasing in complexity.
You can't just watch a tutorial and expect
to understand everything about the engine right away.
Oh yeah, speaking of which, let's talk about
tutor- Tutorials won't make the game for
you, and you shouldn't use tutorials to make
your entire game.
If you're using a new engine for the
first time, or really, any new program, then
yes, you should probably watch a tutorial just
to know the very basics and see where
everything is and see what each button does.
But beyond that, you should try to learn
on your own as much as possible.
The fun of gamedev is experimenting and trying
things out for yourself, seeing what works and
what doesn't.
Because personally, I learn much better from first
-hand experience.
But I didn't always knew that.
When I was a kid, I wanted to
learn Game Maker, and so I watched a
tutorial on how to make a full game
from start to finish, and I followed it
every step of the way.
But as soon as something didn't work, I
had no idea what to do.
That's because I learned nothing, and I remembered
nothing.
All I was doing was copying the video.
So, don't do that.
In short, when learning a new game engine,
don't go into it with any goals in
mind.
Just try things out and experiment.
Start by making extremely simple and basic games,
and if there is one mechanic in particular
that you're not able to implement, and you
really tried, then yeah, you should go look
up a tutorial.
Before I finish this video, I'd like to
touch on one last subject, and that's why
should you make games?
Now, we all have our own reasons for
making games.
Maybe you want to make a shitty mobile
game for ad money, or maybe you're just
trying out a new hobby and making games
just for yourself.
And that's good enough of a reason, but
at the end of the day, games are
made to be played.
Undoubtedly, my favorite part of making games is
seeing people play them.
There is genuinely no better feeling in the
world than to see a loved one play
and enjoy something that you made.
It makes all the pain and suffering you
went through while making your game feel completely
worth it in the end.
Really, it's...
it's the best.
So, what are you waiting for?
Go out there and go make some games.
And make sure you have fun, alright?