I've spent the last year making free games
for itch.io, and I'm starting to realize
this isn't sustainable.
I can't survive off game jams and nice
comments.
It's time to start making some serious money
out of this.
I wish I was one of the cool
indie developers on Steam, but for that you
need a unique and cool looking game, and
I don't have one.
I also need the money before Christmas to
be able to buy gifts for my friends
and family, so I guess my only option
left is a free-to-play casual mobile
game.
Yeah, this is where the real top dogs
operate.
Fast development cycles, no nonsense game lore, just
a raw, simple game loop.
After that, you sprinkle your game with some
ads and you can now buy all the
things your parents wished for Christmas.
If you do a little bit of googling,
you can see that the mobile game markets
make billions of dollars each year.
Okay, but we still need a game, and
I happen to have one in the making
as you who watched the last devlog know
about.
The game is a simple endless runner with
a one-touch-and-hold control for the
player to make turns, and the only thing
to worry about is to not crash into
obstacles or going down the slope edge.
And since mobile free-to-play games are
fairly simple, I think this kind of gameplay
can be a perfect fit.
The game is a mashup of all my
favorite aspects with casual free-to-play games,
a little bit of chill-vibe from Alto's
Adventure, and short game sessions like Jetpack Your
Ride or Subway Surfers.
Something you can pick up when waiting for
the bus, or just give your life a
little bit of silver lining when doing your
business.
A good visual style is important and leads
to more downloads on the app stores, and
as some of you pointed out in the
comments, the colors right now is too bright
and a bit hurtful for your eyes.
So I made a quick mockup for a
new background and visual design.
I also modeled some new segments for the
slope and removed the skiers and replaced them
with a ball to save some time.
Let me know if you think I should
bring back the skiers as skins in future
update of the game.
The game was lacking good sound effects and
music, so I went to the best place
on the internet for that purpose, freesounds.org,
and picked some sounds.
I also added relaxing music to get that
nice zen atmosphere I was aiming for, and
created a Respawn ability to use after a
crash.
The whole point here is to make money,
so we need ads.
And to not go full on evil I
will integrate the ads in a way that
they are optional for the player.
For this purpose I will only use rewarded
ads.
Rewarded ads are used to give something in
return to the player, like a chance to
respawn and keep playing after death or get
a new skin or character to play with.
And this was pretty easily integrated into the
game loop with the Unity Ads tool.
In this game, since it is an endless
runner with a quite steep difficulty curve, the
most obvious place for the rewarded ads option
are after a crash, and this is where
the respawn ability comes into play.
So far I have only tested the game
on my computer, and since it is supposed
to be a mobile game I ported it
to Android.
Luckily this is a very straightforward process in
Unity, as surprisingly it worked on my Samsung
phone right away.
And for all of you poor people with
iPhones, sorry, too expensive for my budget.
Maybe when the money starts rolling in, I
don't know.
When the complete game loop started to feel
somewhat solid, I tweaked the difficulty curve on
the obstacle spawning.
I may have made the difficulty curve a
little bit too steep, cause none of my
friends have beaten the 100 meter mark yet,
but they are kinda bad at games, and
I'm pretty sure that some of you here
can beat my personal best at 891 meters.
If any one of you do, I will
salute you in the next devlog.
Put your score in the comments and let
me know.
Alright, everything worked, sort of.
Let's upload the game to Google Play Store
and start making some money.
After setting up the developers account on Google
Play Store, creating an app icon, gameplay screenshots,
feature graphics, I could finally start uploading my
game.
Or so I thought.
What are all those questions?
Swastikas or Nazi symbols?
Ah wait, I hope I didn't by mistake.
Sexuality?
No, not this time.
Terrorists?
To have any chance to get some visibility
on Google Play Store, I deep dive into
the wonderful world of ASO.
Just kidding.
Let's publish and hope for the best.
Okay guys, I did my part here.
Start downloading the game.
It's free, and there's a link down below.
Leave a nice review for the game on
the Google Play Store, and watch some ads.
I will share the revenue and the statistics
for the app in the next devlog.
Until then, bye.