Before we get into option trading strategies and
all the technicals, let's talk about the basic
definition of options and why they even exist
in the first place.
So what is an option?
An option is a contract that you can
purchase that gives you the right to buy
or sell stock at an agreed price on
or before a particular date.
Now you can also sell an option contract
where you would be selling this right to
someone and collecting a premium for it.
Okay, I'm sure that sounded very confusing, especially
if this is new to you, but just
bear with me as we get through a
few more definitions.
Once we get through these definitions, we'll be
able to show you some examples and it
will all start to make sense.
But go ahead and take notes and write
down these definitions so you can refer back
to them during the rest of this course
if you need to.
Okay, there are two types of options, calls
and puts.
A call option gives the option holder the
right, but not the obligation, to buy shares
of stock at an agreed-upon price on
or before a particular date.
And a put option is the same thing,
except it gives the option holder the right
to sell shares of stock at an agreed
-upon price on or before a particular date.
And the agreed-upon price is what we
refer to as the strike price, and the
particular date is what we refer to as
the option's expiration date.
Now, we got those out of the way,
but in layman's terms, let's say you bought
a call option, so you're the option holder,
and the strike price of this call option
is $120 and it expires in 30 days.
Owning this call option will allow you to
purchase the stock at $120 anytime during the
next 30 days, no matter where the stock
goes.
So, if the stock goes up to $135
within the next 30 days, then fortunately for
you, you own a call option that allows
you to buy stock at $120 even though
the stock is currently trading at $135.
Now, instead of a call, let's say you
bought a put option with a strike price
of $120 that expires in 30 days.
This will allow you to sell the stock
at $120 anytime during the next 30 days,
no matter where the stock goes.
This is cool because what if the stock
tanks down to $100 per share?
Well, you own a put option that gives
you the right to sell stock at $120
even though the current market value is $100.
So, you have a much better sale price
than if you were to just sell stock
at the current market value.
Okay, simple enough, but why might someone actually
want to purchase an option?
First, we're going to explain to you why
you might want to buy a put option,
which if you remember, would give you the
right to sell stock at a certain price
on or before a particular date.
And let's put this in terms anyone can
understand.
Let's say you just bought your dream car.
You just bought a new Ferrari, and to
protect this Ferrari, you're going to need insurance.
So, you go to Flow from Progressive, and
you purchase insurance.
This financially protects your new Ferrari in case
you get into a crash.
And this is the exact same concept as
options.
Now, instead of a car enthusiast, let's say
you were an investor, and you just bought
100 shares of XYZ stock at $125 per
share.
So, the total cost of this investment is
$12,500.
We all know that stock prices fluctuate, and
stocks can even go to zero if something
catastrophic happens.
So, your total risk on this investment is
technically $12,500.
Now, just like we purchased insurance on the
Ferrari, we can also purchase insurance on this
investment.
We would do this by purchasing an option
contract.
Specifically, in this example, we would purchase what
is called a put option.
By definition, buying a put option gives us
the right, but not the obligation, to sell
stock at an agreed upon price on or
before a particular date.
Now, let's recap.
You own stock, and you want to buy
insurance on that stock investment.
So, you buy a put option.
Simple enough, right?
Now, if you bought an option, someone had
to have sold it to you.
But who?
The answer is any other trader who is
willing to be paid to take on your
risk, just like an insurance provider.
That's the basic idea of options.
An investor has risk, but he's willing to
pay someone to take away his risk, and
the person who gets paid now assumes that
investor's risk.
Now, let's look at a real example.
You bought $12,500 worth of XYZ stock,
and you also purchased a put option as
insurance.
The price of this insurance is going to
be determined by several factors, and you're going
to learn about these factors in Chapter 3.
For now, let's just say you had to
pay $500 for this put option, and this
gives you full coverage insurance for the next
30 days.
Now, let's look at two different scenarios.
In the first scenario, after you buy the
stock and the put option, the stock price
goes from $125 per share up to $132
per share.
So you made $7 per share on 100
shares of stock.
That totals to a profit of $700 on
the stock that you own.
But remember, you also paid $500 for an
option contract that now has no value to
you.
So your net profit is only $200.
At this point, you're probably saying, what a
rip-off, and the person who sold you
the option is saying, thanks for the easy
money, because they got to keep the $500
that you paid them.
But let's look at another scenario.
Now, in this scenario, rather than the stock
price going up, let's say the stock price
goes down to $113 per share.
So the stock's share price is now $12
cheaper than where you initially bought it.
And since you own 100 shares, that means
you've lost $1,200.
But thankfully, you bought a put option as
insurance.
Now, you go to the person who sold
you the option and say, hey, remember our
contract?
Now, even though the stock is at $113,
you are able to exercise your option to
sell your shares at $125 per share.
So you lost nothing on the stock.
Your only loss in this scenario is the
$500 you paid for the put option, much
better than the $1,200 that you would
have lost if you did not purchase this
option contract.
Now, remember, the person who sold you the
option had an agreement with you.
They were obligated to purchase your shares from
you at $125 per share.
So they got to keep the $500 that
you paid them for the put option, but
they are now sitting on a $1,200
loss on the stock that they own.
Now, they can hold the stock and hope
it goes back up, or they can sell
it at the current market price of $113
for a total net loss of $700.
So that's all options are, guys.
They're simply insurance for an investor.
That's why they even exist in the first
place.
So a few thoughts may be running through
your head at this point.
You might be saying, but I don't want
to buy insurance on my stock portfolio.
Or maybe you don't even own any stocks
and you were hoping to just learn option
strategies that you can trade with very little
capital without ever even touching the stock.
And you can.
That's the cool thing about options.
You don't have to own stock to trade
them.
You can actually just trade the fluctuating option
prices with your brokerage account, just like you
can trade stock.
But we just had to lay the framework
because understanding how options relate to insurance is
crucial for you to understand how options are
priced, which we're going to cover in chapter
three.
Okay, you get it by now.
Buying a put option is like buying insurance
on a stock investment and selling a put
option is like selling insurance on a stock
investment.
But let's look at another reason one might
want to buy an option.
And this time we're going to explain to
you why you might want to buy a
call option.
This time, let's say you don't own any
shares of stock yet, but you have your
eye on a stock that you really like.
There's just one problem.
That stock is expensive.
So if you were to buy shares, it
would require a lot of capital.
What you could do instead is you could
buy a call option.
This would allow you to pay a small
premium for the right to buy shares at
a later date, if perhaps you are correct
about the stock and the price goes higher.
So let's look at a real example.
Stock XYZ is currently trading at $125 per
share.
To buy 100 shares of the stock, it
would cost us $12,500.
So instead of putting up $12,500 to
buy the stock, let's instead buy the 125
strike call option that has 30 days until
it expires.
This gives us the right to purchase 100
shares of stock at $125 per share anytime
during the next 30 days.
Now again, the price we have to pay
for this call option will be determined by
several factors that you're going to learn about
soon.
But for now, let's just say we had
to pay $500 for this call option.
Let's look at two scenarios.
In the first scenario, after you buy the
call option, the stock goes from $125 up
to let's say $137.
Now you own the 125 strike call option.
What you could do now at this point
is exercise your call option.
Exercising your option just simply means that you
have decided to take advantage of your right
to buy stock at a lower price.
So in this case, you exercise your 125
strike call option, so you now own 100
shares of stock at $125.
You are up 12 points on this stock.
And since you own 100 shares of stock,
this means you're up $1,200.
But remember, you paid $500 for the call
option, so your net profit is really only
$700.
Now you might be thinking, well if I
would have just bought the stock to begin
with, I would have made more money.
Yes, this is true, but let's quickly look
at one more scenario.
In this scenario, the stock goes down.
It moves down to let's say $100 per
share.
Now remember, you own the 125 strike call
option that you bought for $500, and this
call option gives you the right to buy
stock at $125 per share.
But why on earth would anyone want to
purchase stock at $125 if the stock is
currently at $100?
The answer is you wouldn't, and thankfully you
don't have to.
Let's think back to the definition of a
call option.
It gives you the right, but not the
obligation to buy stock.
So owning this call option doesn't require you
to buy stock if you don't want to.
And of course, you aren't going to exercise
your right to buy stock at $125 if
the current market price is cheaper than that.
So in this case, you simply lost the
premium you paid for the option, which was
$500.
If you would have bought stock at $125
instead, you would currently be down $2,500.
So that's the benefit of buying an option
rather than just buying the stock.
You can put up much less capital, and
therefore have much less risk.
But in exchange for that, you will have
to pay a premium for it.
And by the way, you can also trade
put options in this way as well.
If you buy a put option without already
owning shares of stock, then you are simply
betting that the stock will go down.
Because if you exercise your right to sell
stock that you don't own, then you will
just end up with a short stock position.
So again, if you buy a call, you
are betting that the stock is going to
go up.
And if you buy a put, you are
betting that the stock is going to go
down.
Now before you go out and start buying
calls on every stock you think is going
to go up, and puts on every stock
you think is going to go down, keep
watching because there are big negatives to buying
options like this.
And of course, we are going to show
you much better ways to trade options.
One last note before moving on, you don't
actually have to exercise your option contracts when
you trade them like we showed you in
the examples.
You can simply buy an option and then
sell the option, hopefully at a higher price
than you bought it for.
And we're going to cover that more in
the next two chapters.
So alright guys, hope you enjoyed the video
and are staying safe out there.
Be sure to click the like and subscribe
button below.
And also be sure to check out our
three free video series by clicking the link
in the video description below.
These videos will help your trading tremendously, and
they are completely free.
All you have to do is click the
link, input your email, and we will send
you the three videos.
So I will see you there.