Algorithms, they're written by a programmer and they
have to be written to go somewhere, okay?
Where are they written to go?
These technical areas that we're putting out, those
algorithms are going to that as sure as
we're having this conversation, there's no doubt.
They want to shake out the longs and
they want to get people short and what
do the smart people do that are on
the bottom of these algorithms that are scooping
this stuff up?
They're feeding into these people, that's what algorithms
do.
I'm able to take advantage of what they've
given me, printing the money, man.
That's what we do and we do it
every day, hundreds of times.
In terms of market makers and hunting stops,
there's a big thing in the retail space
of like price hitting your stop loss and
going completely the other way, people feeling very
targeted.
I've heard you say that that is a
case, that is something that does take place.
Yes, you're 100% right.
I started focusing on the algorithms a very
long time ago.
It wasn't my will, I was an agent.
Algorithms are there to create volatility and liquidity.
They want to trap one of the trades
that lose money 85-90% of the
time is when you sell, fail, break down.
Those algorithms know that.
You just know it and I know that
those algorithms are going to make that print
and they're programmed in to go to those
strike places.
A lot of retail traders, they all make
the same mistake.
The important thing is for retail traders is
- The
number one podcast in the trading space, the
fastest growing and that's thanks to every single
one of you.
Welcome back everyone to the Words of Wisdom
podcast.
We are back once again and still the
number one podcast in the trading space and
the fastest growing thanks to all of you
and our incredible guests, talking of which we
have a true veteran with us today.
He first set foot on the New York
Stock Exchange in 1965, so in one year's
time that will make 60 years.
Absolutely incredible the amount of knowledge that is
going to be shared here with us today.
At one point he was responsible for 90
% of the volume trade in IBM, which
was almost 20% at one point of
the S&P.
And I am proud and honored to announce
that we have Richie Nasser with us today.
Thank you so much for that.
I appreciate it.
I'm trying to work on my intros.
Richie, it's an absolute honor, like I said.
Where we like to just start off with
is sort of how you got into trading,
like what were the mindset going into trading,
especially at that time, you know, the New
York Stock Exchange as well.
Where was your mindset?
Why trading in the first place?
It's pretty amazing.
You know, first of all, I thank the
good Lord, because I couldn't have carved out
a better situation for myself without really knowing
what I was doing.
You know, I started out in a typical,
my family is a typical Italian family growing
up in Queens, New York.
But I grew up in a very tough
neighborhood.
And although I was a very big sports
fanatic in everything I did, at sometimes in
high levels, like getting a scholarship to high
school for basketball.
And, and so, you know, I formed many
baseball teams and many softball teams and traveled
around the tri-state area playing for money.
Okay, my family had bingo games going on
at the end of Sunday dinners at my
grandmother's house.
You always, the kids always wanted to use
their real money to play bingo with the
older people.
Okay.
I grew up in, again, in a Queens
neighborhood, a very tough Queens neighborhood, and pitched
quarters against the wall, pitched, traded picture cards
and flipped picture cards for money, played poker
for money, played, played anything for money, played
anything.
I once sat in my basement at 15
years old, and I'm prefacing this on a
reason on purpose.
I once sat in my basement and had
four decks of cards faced upside down backwards.
So I couldn't see what I was doing.
I placed a baseball hat against the wall,
okay, against the wall.
And I stood there for hours, days and
hours and hours at a time, flipping those
cards against the wall, and counting up what
suit, what suit just fell into the hat.
Didn't know what I was flipping.
At the end of the day, no matter
what I did, the club suit always came
out on top.
Gave me an edge.
I'm playing poker.
If I'm playing contact poker, and I played
with bookmakers, and I played with the best
wise guys, I played with everybody.
But always clubs came out.
So if there were three clubs on the
board in contact poker, and there was one
card in the deck that had to be
pulled out, and I had three, four clubs,
three clubs and one on the board, and
I needed a club, I know what I
was doing.
If I needed a diamond, I probably would
have folded.
So that's the level.
And, you know, I had no real idea
of what my future would be.
And so it was unbelievable.
You know, the experience of winning and losing,
you cannot replicate.
You know, I tell people on my sessions
to this day, well, I'm going to go
on a simp account.
I'm going to go on a simp account.
I said, do yourself a favor.
You're not going to learn anything on a
simp account.
The reason you're not because you're not risking
anything.
You've got to feel the emotions of risking.
You've got to feel what it is to
lose.
You can't.
Everything is not fun and games.
So anyway, it just meant it was a
tremendous preparation for me to walk in there.
You know, graduating high school, they all started
in with the yearbooks and they all wrote
the salutations of what they're going to be
in life.
How they knew that at 17, I don't
know, but they all knew it.
They all knew it.
I had one line.
I put one, one, one word and that
was business.
Did I know what business was that was,
where it was, what kind of business it
was?
No, I didn't.
I just wrote business.
I mean, I sold encyclopedias door to door.
I mean, I was a, a, a manager
trainee for John's bargain store.
People in this part of the country will
know what that was.
You know, soup to nuts across the court,
you know, delivering newspapers at five 30 in
the morning, you know, stuffing groceries at the
supermarket for a quarter a day or whatever
the hell it was, you know, stuff like
that.
But it all, I'm saying this for a
reason.
Nothing is an accident, folks.
Really nothing.
It's all predetermined.
Nothing is an accident.
And so when did trading come into your
sort of path?
Yeah.
So I never traded a stock in my
life.
I didn't have the money.
I saw an ad in New York times
that said, you know, wall street runner or
whatever they called it.
I said, Oh, New York stock exchange.
That's impressive to me.
Yeah.
I'm going to go and apply for this
job.
So I put on my Easter suit, the
only suit I owned, and only came out
once or twice a year and, and walked
into the stock exchange, filled out an application,
got hired.
I want to say one other thing.
And I want to say one other thing,
because it's important the way things are supposed
to work out.
My first job interview was for an assistant
accountant at a bookkeeping firm.
Okay.
And I didn't get the job, but the
woman, I didn't get the job because I
tested worse than the kid who was looking
for the same job.
And, but the HR person or whatever they
were called in that day, came up to
me and said, I'm sorry, but I have
to hire the other.
He got higher on a test, but she
said, I know I'm making a mistake.
And that was the end of that.
Then I went to wall street.
Then I got this clerk, a job as
a runner on the floor of the New
York stock exchange.
That simple.
But I remember one thing and one thing
that no, I found the home when they
suited me up, you had a special jacket,
blah, blah, blah.
And then you walked into that trading room.
They escorted you into that room.
It was like, it was like you got
hit with a boulder.
I mean, the energy that came out of
that room that I felt went through my
bones from the toe to top of my
head, down to my top of my bottom
of my toes, man, it was stupid.
It was like, Oh my God, I had
no idea.
No idea.
And that was it.
I was hooked after that.
I just did what I did.
I did my, I did my study and
I did my due diligence.
I passed whatever I had to pass.
I was not a great student in school.
I didn't care.
I didn't think they would teach me anything,
quite frankly.
And, you know, I, I rose through the
ranks in New York stock exchange as a
runner.
And then as a reporter, somebody who recorded
all the sales that took place.
And after nine months, they offered me a
job as a clerk, as a clerk.
What is a clerk?
A clerk is a trainee, but they work
for a firm.
And that was a big step because that
puts you on a level where you could
start to advance if you were good enough
to advance.
Nobody gave you anything.
And I had a hard time.
I can tell you, honestly, I had a
really hard time because I couldn't understand what
a quote was.
I didn't understand what a bid and offer
was.
I really didn't.
I mean, I was a workaholic, but I
did not.
I couldn't, I couldn't get it through.
Okay.
So my boss at the time sent me
up to the over-the-counter desk.
Over-the-counter.
Over-the-counter was rock and roll.
There was no Nasdaq.
This was a thousand people making markets in
every stock on a planet that wasn't listed
on the New York Stock Exchange.
And it was, this was, this was Dodge
City.
Check your pockets.
I'll tell you that.
It was Dodge City.
But when you were making markets, it was
the best education I ever got because after
that, it just all came together.
Down to the trading floor again.
And just kept moving up on a trading
floor, you know, where I was got the
confidence of many, many different companies that called
me, you know, to represent them, to be
their clerk and to stuff like that.
One thing you really, you said there, which
really stood out to me was nothing was
ever handed to anyone on the floor.
Can you just speak on that a bit
more?
Yeah.
I mean, look, I was never handed anything.
And, but the good news is that I
didn't want to be handed anything.
You know, I have a sibling that was
handed everything, but I never wanted to be
handed everything.
I always wanted to earn it.
And so it fit my personality real well.
Because when you're competing against other people, the
best comes out.
And if you, and if you know the
job that you could do, and if you
know what you're capable of doing, and you
have confidence in what you're doing, you are
going to beat these other people.
And you know, I mean, that's the way
it is.
That's capitalism.
That's it.
You want to get a job, you want
to do better than somebody else, you just
do the best you can.
And you automatically better than somebody else, as
long as you don't cheat along the way,
as long as you put in the time.
That's where the confidence comes from, putting in
the time, you need to be a student
of the game.
How important is that mindset going into something
like the floor where, whether even at that
time, people who would be entitled and think
they deserved something, think they have done enough
time, and therefore they should get something?
Oh, sure.
I love though, I love to compete against
those people, because that was easy stuff.
It was just easy.
And especially on the floor, the New York
Stock Exchange floor has a very high tradition
in heritage, okay?
The specialist system had lines of heritage.
Grandfathers, grandfathers, to sons, to sons, all right?
And many of the specialist firms had heritage
like that running through them.
So conversely speaking, to answer your question, a
lot of the offsprings of these senior people,
if you will, they thought that this was
easy life for them.
They already had money, they knew they were
getting money.
And so it's good to compete against those
people.
That's all I could say.
When you're a kid that comes from a
rough neighborhood, and you're able to work your
way up through it, and you find yourself
in an arena where people think they deserve
something, you stand out.
Going back to what you said about your
sort of upbringing into the trading journey, you
mentioned about essentially everything was winning and losing.
Everything was trying to play those odds.
How important was that when you're coming into
the New York Stock Exchange?
Was it simply just some like almost familiar
to you?
Was it something that you just thought, this
is just a larger game of what I've
played before?
Intellectually, at that point, no.
But somehow, some way, my system knew it.
I did not recognize it at first.
I really did not.
It was, I don't know, a couple of
years, two, three years where I started realizing,
forget it.
And I started moving up quicker than a
lot of people were moving up.
And then I figured out, and the answer
to your question is at one point, but
not from the beginning.
Not from the beginning.
I knew I belonged there because of the
energy.
And I knew that's what drives me.
And that's what's always driven me, no matter
what I did.
So from that perspective, the energy was just,
oh my God, this is my home.
This is where I belong.
And I remember, I said, wow, when I
got my first job and I was making
$60 a week, that was the pay in
1960, $65.
$60 a week, I cleared $48.12. And
that's what I remember.
And I remember also, I said to myself,
wow, if I can make, my goal was
to make $40,000 a year.
That was my goal.
And now I'm dead serious.
That was my goal to make $40,000
a year, which was a lot of money
at that time.
In terms of, as you said, in terms
of the energy, I'm sure there would have
been people who would have gone there.
And rather than energy, they would have said
chaos, would have said something maybe more of
a negative feeling because they couldn't handle it.
And what was it about you that felt
that energy instead?
What was it about the energy on the
floor that really resonated with you and wanted
you to be there?
The gambling instincts, the gambling instincts.
There were two times I had that feeling
in my life.
Once, I was in a Marine Corps and
stationed in 29 Palms, California, which is only
two or three hours away from Las Vegas.
I'd never been to Las Vegas.
I'd never been anywhere.
And the same feeling is when I walked
into a Las Vegas casino.
But that was second to the New York
Stock Exchange.
The gambling mecca of Las Vegas is second
to the gambling that goes on every day
and to what I did.
Nothing comes close to that.
Nothing.
What would you say is the separation then
between the gambling and the trading?
I'm sure there were traders on the floor
who were so emotional that you could call
it gambling.
Then what would separate those from the traders
to the gamblers?
Profitable trading really boils down to two things,
opportunity and volatility.
And that is why the podcast has partnered
with Market Journal.
Because between the years 2016 and 2020, the
amount of opportunity that was available, as well
as volatility to take advantage of, was at
the highest it's ever been.
And all of that really pointed towards one
man, President Donald Trump.
During his period in office, all it took
was one tweet, and that would present so
much volatility and the right traders would take
advantage of that and would create their record
P&Ls.
And that is why those same traders are
so excited for this new period between 2025
to 2029 when we have President Donald Trump
back in office.
Now, Market Journal is going to give you
the weekly insights you need across crypto, forex,
futures and the stock market.
So regardless of what happens, whether it's a
tweet, a particular stock running up hundreds of
percent, whatever volatility and opportunity that Market Journal
can identify, it is going to share with
you every single week.
So you can purely focus on taking advantage
of those opportunities and taking advantage of that
volatility to create your record P&L.
Now, Market Journal is absolutely free.
All you do is click the link in
the description below, put in your email, and
you will receive key updates on the markets
every single week.
So you are always up to date with
what's going on and ready to execute when
the time is right.
Links in description below.
Thank you for enjoying this episode.
Let's take a break for a minute there,
guys, because I want to let you know
about one of our sponsors.
Alpha Futures is offering the best one step
evaluations in the industry.
And in the month of December, they have
no activation fees.
They have the largest end of day based
drawdowns in the entire industry with up to
90% profit split and lightning fast payout
speeds and offering advanced and standard accounts to
fit your needs.
Alpha Futures is truly offering the most elite
plans for the lowest total cost to entry
in the industry.
You can start as low as $79.
And thanks to the podcast using code RIZ,
R I Z, you can get 20%
off any of those challenges.
Go to the link in the description below.
And let's get back to the episode.
Gamblers take risk.
I say it to my in my sessions
all the time.
Folks, we're not here to gamble, okay?
We're not here to gamble.
If you're in a Las Vegas casino, they
don't want you in there if you win
58.9% of the time, okay?
They don't want you in there, all right?
I take pride in figuring out the nuances
that lead to a trading decision, and there
are a lot of them, and they change
rapidly.
They don't stay the same.
You can go in and gamble in a
Las Vegas casino, and you know what the
odds are.
You know what you're doing.
You know you have a disadvantage.
You're every bet except one in a whole
casino where the house does not have an
advantage.
But I say it all the time.
I say, look, I'm not here to gamble.
I said, don't laugh because I'm dead serious.
I'm not here to gamble.
I am here to make a bet, and
I'm here to be on the right side
of the percentages of that bet.
I said, that's what I do, folks.
That's what you're paying me for.
That's why you're in these sessions, and that's
what I do.
So what's the difference?
I'm not a gambler.
I'm a technical player that slices and dices
everything that goes on a daily basis, on
a second-to-second basis.
Slices and dices, they can come up with
an advantage, at least what I feel is
an advantage, and then make the play.
In terms of that, though, the differences between
when you started your career and you're starting
your career as a trader in the pits
and within that energy in the room and
the other traders in the room, you're able
to read the order flow in the room
because it's happening there and then in the
room, versus today where you're trading from screens
remotely.
If you want to read the order flow,
you're using level two charts, for example.
You're not really getting that emotion, direct emotion.
But as someone with your experience, potentially you're
getting that from the actual candlesticks and the
way that the moves are printing within the
technicals versus what it used to be in
the pits.
Is there similarities that bridge the two?
Well, yeah, there is.
There is.
Again, the specialist system was prominent.
They dictated the flow.
They had the buy and sell orders that
were above and below the market on what's
called a specialist book.
And depending on the level of player you
were, i.e. the size of order flow
you used to have, when you went into
a specific trading crowd, you want to know
where the supply and demand is.
Now, that wasn't public knowledge.
But if you were a sizable player and
had sizable order flow and you went into
a trading stock, they know you meant business.
And so they would help you and speak
to you about where the order flow was,
where was the supply, where was the demand.
If you had a large buy order, you
wanted to know where the supply was and
vice versa.
So in this day and age, there are
different ways to navigate that.
And one of them is there's a superdome
that we have and display every day on
our sessions.
And it's a superdome.
And a lot of the firms offer these
domes, but these domes are not.
This is a superdome.
And it shows the size of the order
imbalances, depends what bar you're in.
But if you're on a NASDAQ bar, it's
3,000 ticks I have set up.
And 3,000 ticks will show in a
3,000 tick bar, it will show you
the order imbalances with the size, with the
sizes.
So you see.
And you see the NASDAQ size coming in
and blue imbalance orders in size.
And it gives you a little bit of
an edge.
Why?
If I see the market shooting up, I
mean, I left early today.
But if you see the market shooting up,
it's at a high, an intraday cycle high,
high, high.
And you see the superdome light up with
blue imbalance orders.
I'm watching that very closely because I know
these buy orders, these buyers here, they're long
at the top.
So number one, I know that it's going
to be a difficult world to really break
out if you want to get short.
I know that.
And I do know also that I'm going
to be covering my short when these people
start to puke if they're wrong.
And so that's an edge.
And we have a superdome.
It's expensive.
It's not proprietary to us, but we own
it.
And I don't know anybody else that has
this superdome.
I really don't.
So that's relative to the specialist book.
And not everybody in my era or eras
well before me and after me, for that
matter, the specialist book was the Bible.
Because you don't want to look like an
idiot by buying into a large seller that's
just slightly above the market and vice versa
on the downside.
You don't want to sell into a huge
buyer.
So edges like that, it comes from the
experience level.
And so I think very interesting what you
said there in terms of that, like, depending
on you and the size that you're sort
of fulfilling and essentially your track record, if
you will.
There's a lot of talk about track record
nowadays about traders, you know, trying to acquire
them, whether it's to get capital, to prove
themselves as traders.
But the same happened back in the pit.
If you didn't have the performance behind you
to be able to handle that size, no
one was going to give you that size.
So for you to be able to get
the size that you got, you showed the
skill set, the track record to be able
to handle it and then continue to perform
to this day.
100 percent.
I mean, that's just the fact of the
matter.
And, you know, I speak to my I
speak to my subscribers all the time about
the volume weighted average and, you know, the
80 percent of the order flow that comes
down today, the volume weighted average is a
huge factor.
Why?
Because the size of the positions today with
the amount of money on the management, you
can't have a million share position if you're
managing 10 billion dollars or 20 billion.
Your positions are 20 million shares, 30 million
shares.
OK.
And 80 percent, 80 percent, give or take,
it's probably more 80 percent.
A portfolio manager says, all right, I own
XYZ.
It's up substantially and they own 20 million
shares.
I want to take off, you know, 5
percent of that.
OK, so sell an order, take an order
to sell a half a million shares, two
million shares, a million shares.
And they give it to the trader on
a desk and they sell to the trader.
Just, you know, go along, beat the volume
weighted average.
80 percent of the orders on these deep
pocketed investors and funds have orders that are
that are following an algorithm that allows them
to stay close to the volume weighted average.
Why?
The trader doesn't want to be embarrassed.
The portfolio manager doesn't really care.
He's banking money.
So he doesn't want he doesn't want anybody
playing the market on his dime.
He'd rather just know that he's about around
the mid price of the stock that it
trades for the day.
But it's a very important factor when you're
doing what I do, because where the volume
weighted average is, you know, if a new
bar comes up on a super superdome, for
instance, and the bar is above the volume
weighted average, those those orders that are in
there following an algorithm on a volume weighted
average are buyers.
And when it's below the bar, they're sellers.
And that's how they keep up.
It's a balancing act.
So.
So the VWAP is really, really important.
My clients, like you, what you just said,
which prompted me to speak about this is
my clients.
I mean, you know, I represented Vanguard and
I represented their index funds.
So every time a stock went from one
S&P to 400 to 500, they, you
know, they restricted and they balanced, they had
to balance the mathematics out to reflect what
their index was.
And so so my customers, to your point,
they didn't give me the order.
I could put on an algorithm, too.
No, they they they wanted me to trade
the order and use my expertise.
So to your point, that's exactly what took
place.
And you want to know what?
I destroyed the volume weighted average.
I destroyed it almost every time.
Never really got hurt.
Played in the market without any algorithms, without
any machines, without anything.
I mean, I can't tell you the amount
of money I made for that index fund.
A lot of a lot of those people
owe me a lot of money.
They really do.
Their subscribers owe me a lot of money.
I would tell you that.
What was it like, though, going from obviously
being a runner to being a clerk to
then obviously starting to manage these positions yourself
on behalf of your clients as well?
But as the size was incrementally getting larger,
did you face any sort of psychological issues,
any barriers at all?
Interesting question.
The answer is no.
Never fazed me one bit.
It was all the same to me, whether
it was a thousand shares or a million
shares.
Yeah, I put up so many million share
blocks in IBM, you know, they counted on
me to price it and to trade out
of it.
So the size never intimidated me at all.
It's all relative.
I, you know, just ambivalent to it.
It doesn't mean anything.
It's just numbers.
And so I just increase the numbers.
And no, the answer is no to your
question.
It never affects me at all.
I never was intimidated by it.
And it never affected me.
Where do you think that came from?
My upbringing in a very tough neighborhood and
in a lot of different ways.
Drugs, wise guys, a lot of stuff.
It was a good, nice middle, middle class
neighborhood in Queens.
But there was a lot of stuff going
on, a lot of stuff.
And so where did it come from?
I, you know, I just my personality, I
guess.
I can't tell you where it came from.
Well, what do you think when you see
people going through psychological problems when it comes
to trading, you know, even if they're handling
much lesser size than what you were, for
example?
Yeah.
What do you say to people when you
see them or speak to them in that
regard?
Yeah, I say to them that, number one,
they have to know their personality.
If you have to, you need to know
your personality.
I said, and I say all the time,
don't laugh.
Don't laugh when I say that.
You have to know your personality because your
personality dictates the level of tolerance and level
of controlling your emotions.
And so it's extremely important to be able
to manage your emotions in this game.
And the way you do that best is
to understand your personality.
Everybody's personality is different.
Everybody can risk a certain amount without being
not effective any longer.
It's extremely important to know your personality.
It really is.
And you have to stay focused, all right?
You have to stay focused.
What do I do?
I give them an example all the time.
A horse races on a racetrack and a
horse does, you know, it's getting beat, getting
beat again, getting beat again.
A horse, you know, on a warm-up
track sets huge numbers and does great.
Gets in a race, horse can't do anything.
And the trainer finally figures out that, wait
a minute, the horse is getting distracted by
looking peripherally.
So what do they do?
They put what they call blinders on them.
And so the blinders make the horse look
straight ahead.
And that's an example I give my people
all the time.
Stay focused, man.
Because that is an interesting point.
A lot of people are so focused on
the wrong things rather than what actually will
make them into a better trader.
Correct.
Like, obviously trading in the pits is far
different than, say, trading on your own, especially
as a retail trader.
And as part of that, a lot of
traders will need, like, trading plans, right?
They'll need their systems that they follow in
order to create their edge in the market.
What have you, what can you speak on
in terms of, like, trading plans, maybe outside
of the trading floor era, I guess?
Yeah.
Well, I had to go through that.
I really had to go through that because
I had no experience trading, you know, in
front of screens until after I left.
And so what can I speak to that?
You know, people have to understand that what's
good for one trader is not good for
another trader.
What one trader looks at, another trader looks
at something different.
So you have to understand that this game
is wide in scope.
It is wide in scope.
And so, you know, manage your trades, protect
your money, protect your investment with stop orders.
But know what your limitations are with that.
Know what your limitations are.
I don't think I answered your question.
No, you did in terms of your trading
plan.
As you said, every trader is different, so
it's not going to be fixed, of course.
I think the benefit of trading is that
there are so many options of how to
do it successfully.
Equally, I feel like a lot of people
think of that and then they start trying
everything and therefore they find themselves very scattered
as a trader versus, as you said earlier,
focus on and know your personality.
So if you combine those two, that's where
you can start to probably really build that
trading plan out.
No, it's true.
It's true.
And, you know, simplicity is best.
And I refer to this a lot.
And, you know, and I say, keep it
simple.
You don't need all these things.
You don't need all these.
Don't get carried away.
When you start flipping around from one way
to trade to another way to trade, one
chart, another chart, one, you know, one technical
area, another technical area, you know, one Keltner
channel.
I said, whoa, you know, it's too much.
You're confusing yourself.
And, you know, I can delineate that, but
you can't.
You can't.
And that's going to retard your growth by
exposing yourself to too much.
It's OK to get to an area.
You know, I had only two monitors, but
I got to an area.
You get to the area, but you need
to conquer simplicity first or you're going to
retard your growth, like I just said.
And you're going to it's going to it's
going to stall your journey.
This is a journey.
Well, that's where a lot of people find
themselves, I think, is that they find themselves
in this boom and bust cycle where they're
just they're not losing.
They're not winning.
They're just going along sideways for a long
chunk of their time.
And a lot of the time they're not
really trying to learn or to be fair,
on the flip side, they're learning too much
and trying to overcomplicate things.
Correct.
Because they think that's a quicker way to
get to where they want to be.
And they're wrong.
What would you say in terms of people
trying to manage larger capital?
What is it that you've noticed?
You know, because obviously you were handling large
size, but I'm sure there are other players
around you who you also recognize were handling
large size, too.
What were the common traits among those people?
That's an interesting question.
The common traits were keeping you cool, keeping
you focused, not getting flustered, holding, controlling your
emotions.
Do your best not to get swept away
in an emotional situation.
And there were many, many, many, many.
And those people were able to keep their
cool, keep their focus.
All right.
You know, baseball player Andy Pennant, New York
Yankees.
It always stuck me even when I was
a kid watching this.
His hat was bent downwards and bent in
a way where he could only look forward.
It's the same example.
It's a simple example.
But that's the kind of focus that you
need.
And so the people that were competent people
knew were not intimidated by the size of
the order flow, were straightforward, honest people who
stated their case.
All right.
Listen, man, I'm going to buy a million
shares of stock here, OK?
Tell me where the supply is.
Tell me now.
I'm putting up a block of a million,
a million one eight IBM right now.
Don't anybody leave the crowd.
Stay here.
Tell me what your interest is now.
All right.
Customer A, customer B, customer B, this guy
represent that.
But the people were straightforward and stated their
case at the time.
You put the block together and you slapped
it on a tape.
All right.
And those are the people that impressed me
growing up.
And those are the people that I learned
from as well.
Growing up, people like that.
Is there ever any sense of like missing
those times?
Because obviously that energy must have been so
contagious, so almost addictive to some degree, no
doubt.
And to not be in that environment anymore,
even after even if it's been some time,
do you ever miss those days and that
sort of flow?
Let's take a break for a minute there,
guys.
I want to tell you about one of
our sponsors, Alpha Capital.
Now, without our sponsors, it's not possible for
us to host such incredible podcasts around the
world and get the level of guests that
we are getting.
So again, thanks to Alpha Capital for sponsoring
the podcast.
Now, Alpha Capital is one of the best
prop firms in the industry.
So far this year alone, they have done
over $50 million in payouts, which is absolutely
incredible.
They have the very best infrastructure in place
for longevity from an in-house broker so
they can offer the very best trading conditions
and platforms that all traders love to use.
They're still able to offer services to the
U.S. as well, so the U.S.
traders can still trade with them on particular
platforms.
They have institutional experience, so they know how
to manage a prop firm correctly and have
such an incredible team on hand, on top
of which they have both a pro and
swing plan.
So depending on your style and strategy, you
can choose which one is best for you.
Now you can use and get the highest
discount available at anywhere using RIS25.
So that's R-I-S-25 for 25
% off all challenges.
The link's in the description below.
So let's get back to the episode.
You know, I mean, it was the greatest
education one could ever get.
You know, I consider myself blessed and very
lucky that I found my way there.
I had no idea, trust me, none whatsoever.
But looking back at it now, you know,
been there, fine, another aspect of my life.
I didn't expect to start LPQ trades.
I did not expect it.
I was trading my own money, like I
said earlier.
I did not expect to start a trading
room.
I did not expect to probably start a
hedge fund by the end of the year.
I did not expect any of it.
I'm not the retiring type.
I'm just not.
So I'm occupied, is the answer to your
question.
Do I miss that?
No.
Do I treasure it?
Oh my God, do I ever treasure it?
Again, I will tell you, you can bundle
together all the great colleges of the world
and you could not get the education of
growing up in those times that I grew
up.
You could not.
Experience is king, as they say, because even
just when I look at, you know, footage
nowadays, it's really just footage or stock photos
of those times.
And you see it, and a lot of
the time, maybe slightly dramatized with some music
or whatever it may be, but you still
see it and you think, wow, that must
have been like chaos.
That must have been crazy to trade.
And then when you speak to the traders
like yourselves, you learn a whole nother level
of, of perception that's actually going on in
those moments.
It is chaos, but it's very organized chaos.
It's very, as you say, educational to be
in those moments because you're learning and picking
up on so much that today's traders, they
don't get that same sense, right?
They're learning and it's not a negative thing
necessarily, but they're learning just from the charts
normally by themselves in their, in their office
or at home, wherever it may be, but
they very rarely know other traders.
But in that environment, the only way to
really know a trader is to then actually
be in the room with all the traders.
Bingo.
I mean, you just hit it on a
head.
That's exactly right.
And again, and a reason why I started
this room is because I replicated a Wall
Street trading room.
You know, when I sold my broker dealers,
I went to a hedge fund friend that
were customers of mine, pretty big name, by
the way.
And they said, you know, come on in,
you know, blah, blah, blah.
I went in and they offered me and
they say, Richard, we don't understand.
You don't need to give us 30 or
40% of your P&L because we're
giving you extra money to trade.
But we know you don't need that.
I said, that's correct.
Why are you doing it?
The chairman of the company.
Why do you want to sit in this
hedge fund?
Because I want to be in a trading
room environment.
So there you go.
And that is a freaking letter of the
law.
All right.
I never went there, but I started doing
what I'm doing.
And now I hate to keep repeating myself,
but I, you know, you, you hit on
a head.
What I can bring to people with the
experience level is unparalleled.
So I tell my people, I said, this
room is a replication of a Wall Street
trading room.
There are three master traders here comparing ideas
during the whole session.
So that's what we're giving you.
And that is head and shoulders above anything
out there.
And nowadays you are trading futures, right?
Trading futures.
I can trade anything, man.
Doesn't matter.
I choose to trade futures.
What is it about the futures market that
got you sort of focused on it?
The future markets are liquidity and volatility.
All right.
The liquidity is paramount.
The volatility is paramount.
The other thing is that the market, the
stock market is based on hope.
Everything is based on hope.
Hope.
You know, Apple's getting killed.
Apple doesn't have any growth.
Where's the growth coming from, Apple?
China's shutting them out there.
China's like, you're not selling your phones here
anymore or whatever, blah, blah, blah.
They come out with their earnings.
Now everybody knows, I know, that their earnings
were going to be bad.
Okay.
They're not good.
They were not going to be good.
So what, what, what do they do?
They give their investors hope on a conference
call.
What's the hope?
We're going to, we authorize a buyback of
$110 billion.
That's the hope.
Hope.
Elon Musk.
Earnings bad.
You know, two, three year earnings ago.
Stock is $150.
What did he do?
He gave them hope.
What was the hope?
His robotics game.
Robotics.
Stock is $250 now.
I mean, $290.
I don't know where.
It's $290 yesterday.
Gave them hope.
So the future market gives you hope.
It also helps you stay focused on the
stock market.
How does it stay focused?
I have, one of my monitors has three
one-minute charts up.
The ES, the NQ, and the YM.
And they all have micro and mini contracts.
So 10 to 1 usually.
All right.
10 to 1.
So these, nothing, nothing.
They're one-minute charts overlaid by technical areas,
9 EMA, and the volume weighted average.
Nothing can take place in a marketplace without
those three, rather than being reflected in those
three charts.
Because it's a bet on hope and it's
a bet on a future.
And when you can get into a contract
like that and turn 20, 30, 40 handles
in a NASDAQ by picking off a divergence
from one to the other, future markets are
the place to be.
I mean, I, and the other thing is,
the other thing is, how much money are
you going to invest to make $0.50
on Microsoft at $350 a share?
How much do you have to invest?
You know, LPQ stands for limited exposure, L.
Limited exposure.
I mean it.
I put on three trades yesterday.
I put on three trades this morning before
I left.
One was $450 at 23 seconds.
One was $300 at six seconds, because I'm
able to take advantage of what they've given
me and keep printing the money, man.
That's what we do.
And you can, the liquidity, I'm sorry, but
the liquidity in the future market allows you
to do that.
You want to pay up a nickel for
to buy Microsoft at $350 a share, or
any of these other wild names?
How long are you going to stick around
if you're a day trader?
You don't have the capital to do it.
You mentioned earlier in terms of algorithms, and
you gave a good description in terms of
your medium, your low, your high.
You're looking at the orders at these points
as well.
And I've heard you previously, you've had a
very viral video that went around.
I remember on Twitter, like millions of views
in regards to algorithms, talking about discounted prices,
premium levels, and then the algorithms hunting these
buy stops, sell stops.
Can you speak more in terms of the
intricacies and sort of where the knowledge comes
from?
Again, IBM was 19.78% of the
S&P.
So that ES contract, my eyes were peeled
on it.
It also touched off buy and sell programs.
So I started focusing on the algorithms a
very long time ago as my order flow
was touching off buy and sell programs at
will.
It wasn't my will.
I was an agent.
I had to do with the order.
Listen, I had complete discretion over my order
flow at 90% of the time.
That's what my customers paid me for, as
I mentioned earlier, regarding clients.
So the order flow just came and the
focus on the ES contract just came.
And therefore, with that being said, the algorithms
come into play.
Algorithms fuel the high frequency traders.
Algorithms, and there's a video out there on
this, and this is really, everybody should just
go find that one because it really does
describe.
Algorithms are there to create volatility and liquidity.
They want volatility.
They want volatility to create liquidity.
How does that work?
Market's coming down to a major technical area.
We put out technical areas every day, six
o'clock in the morning.
Major technical areas that one should be aware
of.
Technical areas are borders.
They're borders.
Nothing is the end all or be all.
When an algorithm, a perfect example of algorithms,
what they do.
All right, technical area here.
Markets are getting killed.
Boom, boom, boom, boom.
Looks like it's resting here.
Not going to rest there.
The algorithms are going to come in here
and touch that technical area, which is usually
a discount area.
And they're going to come and touch that
off.
Two reasons.
Number one, they want to trap one of
the trades that lose money 85, 90%
of the time is when you sell a
failed breakdown.
Sell a failed breakdown.
Those algorithms know that.
And by the way, what broke me through
on the algorithms to make that video was
discovering that, listen, ladies and gentlemen, algorithms may
be mathematical equations generated by a code.
Yeah.
But they're written by a programmer and they
have to be written to go somewhere.
OK, where are they written to go?
These technical areas that we're putting out, that's
a good example of where they're going to
go if the situation arises.
So what happens?
Let's go back.
Market comes down.
Stops here.
Market looks like it's firming up.
Those algorithms are going to that as sure
as we're having this conversation.
There's no doubt why they want to do
it again.
They want to shake out the longs and
they want to get people short because at
that point, it looks like the market's going
to fall out of bed.
What happens?
Market stops.
Market starts going up.
The shorts have to cover and the longs
are so, they knew, they realized they've been
had and they were right on the long
side.
And what do they do?
They jump on a bear wagon too.
And what do the smart people do that
are on the bottom of these algorithms that
are scooping this stuff up?
They're feeding into these people that missed the
market and have made bad sales.
That's what algorithms do.
And there's a way to look at these
and it's a way to track them.
And we do it every day, hundreds of
times.
I'm not sure.
Are you aware that in the retail space
is a very large community of traders who
follow, say, a mentor, if you will, who
describes himself as someone who has like coded
the algorithm or coded a algorithm and therefore
teaches concepts that are supposed to help you
decipher this algorithm.
And, you know, they get very fixated on
essentially having concepts that literally can allow them
to sort of decipher the algorithm in the
markets.
My answer to that, my question to that
is, do they trade their own money based
on their methodology?
That's my answer.
That's my question to them.
If they don't, I don't trust it because
what we do, I can, I don't want
to say guarantee, I don't like the word,
but I know our methodology and there's nobody,
there's nobody better on picking it off because
I helped define it.
And it's that simple.
All right.
Everybody know what a bar chart comes down
and one bar charts right in front of
the other and there's a little space between
them.
It's because the algorithms are piling in, are
piling in that area and it's wherever the
direction that bar is going, it's going down
lower.
Those are algorithms.
But it's the mentality.
It is really the mentality.
It's known where the premium area is.
It's known where the discount area is.
It's known where the gaps are.
Algorithms will always come back and fill gaps.
That was one of my trades this morning.
All right.
I bought, I bought the, what did I
buy?
I don't know what.
I bought the Nasdaq.
I bought Nasdaq.
I bought NQ this morning because at 9
.26 or whatever it was, the, the, there
was, I like to call it a pre
-market mini puke.
And I look for an opportunity there when
it, when it does that.
But what I, what I saw was I
saw a gap here and you know, gap,
what is a gap?
A gap is a market comes up, market
comes up, all of a sudden it shoots
up.
There's a gap.
Algorithms love to come back to those gaps.
Same scenario, same, same instance I just gave.
They'll come down here, down here.
The gap is here, down here, down here.
Most of the time, you know, 50%
of that gap is filled, if not all
of it.
And you know, that's it.
I took a long one.
It hit that gap.
And you know, I mean, it was about
an eight second trade and I don't care
where it goes after that, folks.
I really don't.
Take what the market gives you.
Don't turn your nose up at what the
market gives you, especially if you can turn
over that kind of money in six seconds.
So more so for you, it's following the
algorithm, but just taking what the algorithm, you
know, no matter even if it's a few
seconds, a few minutes, wherever that play may
be, that's the edge.
Would you say the algorithm is designed for
efficiency?
Is that what it's designed for?
Let's take a break for a minute there,
guys, because I want to tell you about
our sponsor, TradeZella.
TradeZella is the number one trading tool for
all traders.
It doesn't matter whether you're a crypto trader,
a futures trader, or a forex trader, whatever
trader you are, all you do is connect
your trading platform directly with TradeZella.
It automates and makes your trading journaling so
easy.
If you want to be a profitable trader,
you need Trading Edge, and that is exactly
what TradeZella does.
It allows you to identify edge, maintain your
edge, and optimize your edge by automating your
trade journaling, in-depth analytics, backtesting, bar replay,
and so much more.
Now, WOR gets you 20% off your
yearly subscription with TradeZella, so use WOR for
20% off your yearly subscription, or RISC
-10 for 10% off your monthly subscription.
The link is in the description below.
Now, let's get back to this episode.
The algorithms are designed to create volatility and
liquidity.
They want the fractions moving, and high-frequency
traders live for this.
They live for that because they can get
in the middle of all trades, especially for
the retailers, especially if you're with a broker
that says you're not paying any commissions, you
know, free brokerage, check your pockets with that
one, because, you know, your order flow is
being sold.
Because where would they make their capital then?
Where would they?
The brokers, if they're doing free commissions, they
won't be making anything unless, as you say,
the order flow or the data, whoever it
may be.
Correct.
What would you say in terms of common
pitfalls that you see amongst retail traders of
today?
Yeah.
You know, as we discussed that a lot
of the time, they are just by themselves.
At most, they have a community or some
sort of trader room that they're part of.
But at the end of the day, they
still are by themselves for the majority of
the time.
What pitfalls do you recognize within these traders?
They don't know how to protect themselves.
You need to know what you're willing to
risk on a trade.
If you're lucky enough to be green on
a day, you don't want to be in
a position to give it back.
And so you want to set a limit
to what you're willing to give up of
those profits on a given day.
And in certain situations, you know, they ask
me all the time, they ask me, you
know, where would you put your stop on
this particular trade?
And I say, I don't have any specific
area.
It's relative to where I am on a
particular day and where I am relative to
where the market is on that particular day.
For instance, for instance, if I'm going to,
if I'm buying, if I see strong, strong,
strong, and I see a divergence with the
Nasdaq trail in the YM, which is another
trade I made this morning, Nasdaq trail in
the YM.
And I know the Nasdaq is coming up
and I know the Nasdaq is coming up.
And I know I'm long.
All right.
And I make my profit.
And then I see the Nasdaq continue to
go up.
And I also see the technical area, a
huge resistance area, a major resistance area right
here on a market that's up pretty good
during the day.
All right.
If I want to short this here, I
know that if it goes higher from there,
it's going much higher.
But if I want to play in case
it's the top of the market, intraday, intracycle,
whatever, I know I can protect that down
three or four handles.
Because, yeah, I can protect that three or
four handles down.
If I'm long, it means they're taking it
right up.
And if I'm right, I'm covered.
So, you know, and I put that the
opposite way.
But if I'm short here and I want
to protect it going to a level, I'm
going to protect it up four handles.
All right.
You know, 100 bucks, 200 bucks, whatever it
is, I know I'm protected because I know
that if it's going through this area here,
it's going through.
But I have a chance to hit a
double and maybe even more than that, because
I know that this technical area is major
resistance.
So just accepting the fact that, OK, at
this level, the risk to reward makes sense.
Right.
Because if the price does break through there
and it hits my stop loss, whatever I've
set, it's going to go anyway.
But if not, the reward of this trade
could be huge.
100 percent.
That's the kind of situation.
So the question is relative about where to
place your stops.
There is no one place to place a
stop, ladies and gentlemen.
The important thing is for retail traders is
to place a stop.
Whatever your tolerance is relative to the size
of your account.
That's the important thing.
Place a stop.
Always do not leave yourself naked.
Do not.
You know, you must protect your money and
you must P as in L P Q
prevent blow ups.
Why?
I just made up these names.
I made up the names.
P prevent blow ups.
Master trader, any master trader, all your experience
in the world, in life or whatever it
is, they will tell you prevent blow ups.
Prevent blow ups.
You know, once you blow up, you blow
up your account, you blow yourself up.
You know, we help people pass apex accounts
and people don't know how to do it.
They roll the dice.
Yeah, I'm going all in.
I'm going all in.
Yeah.
Pay another whatever it is.
Pay another fee.
You don't do that.
You know, you you build up small with
those people and you build up small and
you build up small and stay under the
radar until you're getting ready to get paid.
OK, what are your thoughts in terms of
that?
Like these prop firms or they're not the
traditional prop firms that were truly around, but
the new evaluation firms have entered the futures
market.
We're seeing a lot more into the futures
market now.
I just said, you know, people who trade
them.
Yeah.
Now, what are your thoughts on them being?
It's such a wild different sort of product
that has been around previously.
But yet there is huge benefits to undercapitalized
traders, too.
So what are your thoughts on them?
Yeah, I mean, you're referring to funded broker
dealers that fund accounts.
Yeah.
Pay a fee and you get a quarter
million dollars or whatever it is.
Yeah.
Check your pockets.
That's my feeling.
If you really want to know, check your
pockets.
There's been a number of situations.
I trade three different accounts and there's a
number.
And I always keep that one around, too,
because I'm trading anyway.
What's the difference?
If it costs me 40 dollars to have
a third or fourth account, I'm going to
spend 40 dollars.
You know, I'm wheeling around hundreds, hundreds of
thousands of dollars.
I want to give myself the best chance.
So I've been in a couple of situations
where I was about to hurt these people,
hurt them, pass the test.
All right.
Last week alone, it was an eighteen thousand
dollar swing in an account where I had
them.
All right.
I bet against an earnings report.
I was short the Nasdaq based on based
on whatever Magnificent Seven stock reported.
I don't remember.
Maybe Meta or maybe Amazon.
I don't know.
I think it was Meta.
Soon I was up.
The Nasdaq puked.
I was short 10 NQ contracts.
10 in a funded in a funding account.
And the profit went to, I don't know
what, 15, 18 thousand dollars.
OK, certainly way past the amount of money
you need to pass an account and get
paid.
What happened?
My system froze.
They wouldn't allow me to take the trade
off.
I said, what?
What are you talking about?
And then what happened was the trade went
the other way.
And blew up my account.
Well, I went crazy.
I just went crazy.
And I said, oh, well, we're sorry.
We can't do anything.
I said, oh, yeah.
I said, listen, the SEC is going to
be very happy to hear about this.
I said in the timing of this, this
happened to two of my friends.
And the timing of this does not sit
well with me.
So I would suggest and they reinstated my
account.
But I don't like those firms.
I don't trust them.
That's the answer to your question.
In terms of the changes we see within
the industry, we see a lot of traders
stepping in, especially since Covid.
We've seen so many people become traders.
What are your thoughts in general around trading?
Do you feel like anyone should give trading
a try if they're interested?
Or do you think that trading is really
for those who have the personality traits and
I would say passion for the actual markets
rather than just making money?
Yeah.
You know, it comes down to who you're
going to listen to, who is going to
be your mentor.
I know what I bring to the table.
I know I want to help people, my
group.
We want to help people.
The money is good and all that stuff.
But first and foremost, I want to help
people.
Well, listen, a drug company could come up
with a drug to to, you know, help
sick people with a certain disease.
And that's good.
But it's only a small percentage of the
population, relatively speaking.
But what we're talking about here, you know,
the potential of how many people you could
add and help.
But in this day and age where people
are paying a lot of money for groceries
and gas and rent and insurance and so
on and so forth, and people are living
paycheck to paycheck and people are paying 23
percent juice to credit card companies that maintain
their standard of living.
OK, that's worse than you would pay a
bookmaker in a neighborhood.
I grew up to borrow money.
Shylock, as you would call them.
I mean, it's unbelievable.
So people are getting hurt.
And I'm really my group.
One of the main reasons I started this
company is to help people augment their incomes,
show them how to make two or three
hundred dollars a week.
That's nothing.
It's nothing.
So I think if you're with the right
person and with the right group.
Yes.
Who can cut out reading a novel and,
you know, go to the library.
I'm going to really, you know, nice to
be able to have that sense.
Go to the library and read every book
you can on economics and and trading and
this and that.
But man, it's the that means everything, because
what I could say to these people at
one specific time and one particular instance could
help them for the rest of their lives.
And that's what gets my juices going.
And the people that are with me.
A big debate that seems you mentioned time,
that's actually very interesting.
A big debate that's been happening at the
moment is between time and price are both
important is one more significant than the other.
I've had ex-institutional traders saying that time
is irrelevant.
It's all about price and when price meets
certain levels, that's all that matters.
Where I've had other people on the podcast
where they say time is the most crucial
factor and that when you trade specific time
windows, that's when that's the optimal time to
trade and anything outside of that is not
optimal and shouldn't be traded.
What are your thoughts from your experience is
time and price just as important as each
other?
Is anything that more prevalent than the other?
Yeah, I mean, the market has a different
personality every day.
OK, I've seen it all.
All right.
I don't I hear people say that all
the time.
I only trade between the hours of nine
and eleven or I trade.
I don't trade in the afternoon anymore.
I don't do that.
So I don't trade on news or I
don't trade at the opening or I don't.
I wait to 945.
I don't get any of that myself.
I don't get it.
You want to if you consider yourself a
trader, you should you don't give in to
not trading.
You give you do not.
You apprise the situation and look at the
opportunity.
Now, you may have a pension.
It may be mental.
I don't know.
And that may be suit suit some people.
But I don't close out any time frame
when or when not to trade.
All right.
If I looked at my trades over the
course of a couple of years, I'm sure
there'll be pockets of times when I was
more successful.
But it doesn't deter me from trading the
market from 8 a.m. or even 6
a.m. sometimes until until the market close
closes.
So, you know, and the timing of anything
is always about the entry.
It's always about the entry is always about
the timing of the entry.
All right.
And, you know, I talk about scalp trading
with these things that these trades that take
that took me six seconds, 20 seconds, 18
seconds.
This is all fact.
Constantly, constantly, because I'm able to pick out
this info, this divergence in a market where
I know I can print money.
All right.
And it may still go up after I
sell it.
I don't care about that.
But it's a timing of the execute.
It's a timing of the entry.
And when you're trading with this mindset.
I say it all the time when you're
trading with this mindset, you can you know,
it's a difference between it's a difference in
your P&L, because if you if you
if you're paying up and by the way,
retail traders don't chase.
If you miss the entry level where you
want to purchase, don't chase a lot of
a lot of retail traders.
They may they all make the same mistake.
You know, they say, oh, man, I didn't
buy it.
I didn't buy it.
Meanwhile, it's up, whatever.
And they're buying it here.
They're chasing.
Well, you know, you just made this thing
quadruple difficult for you to make money.
But if your entry, the time of your
entry is where it's supposed to be, man,
that is the difference between you making four
handles or five handles or seven handles or
eight handles.
That's the difference.
That pays the bills that pays the commissions
and so on and so forth.
So, you know, the timing, the timing of
the entry is really is really everything.
Yeah.
So that making sure that you are there
to strike and how important is it, though,
to be prepared for that?
You know, so like a lot of people,
they don't have a strict routine for their
trading, for example, one day they'll turn up
one day they won't.
Of course, a lot of these people are
in that boom and bust or not profitable
stage, unfortunately.
So that's why, you know, as part of
the podcast, we're just trying to educate and
show showcase, you know, profitable traders and what
they do.
Is that something that is important to a
profitable trader to making sure that they're consistently
turning up so that if the time does
arise, they're there to strike and not just
essentially miss an opportunity just because of laziness
or just not being prepared?
Yeah.
I mean, you have to be prepared.
I mean, you this is no this is
no sprint this game.
It is a marathon.
And you need to give you if you
really want to do this and try to
make a living or augment your income by
by trading, you need to put in the
time.
OK, and it's OK.
And, you know, putting in the time helps
your confidence and confidence is the whole thing.
You've got to feel loose that you could
do this and you can do this.
But there's no easy way to do it.
Anybody can roll the dice and get lucky.
But we're not talking about that.
We're talking about consistently making money.
So what are your thoughts about journaling trades?
I know I've seen the pits journaling trades
as an individual, as the trader themselves would
be difficult because you're managing the flow all
that day.
But you have, I believe, clerks and people
who would track them for you and afterwards
you would evaluate what trades have been processed,
etc.
Then you find your carry trades.
And as you said, like days later, you'd
find out about those.
But now, like as you've stepped away from
there, how important has it been to journal
your trades and keep track of your personal?
A hundred percent.
OK, a hundred percent.
You need to look at your trades.
You need to learn from your trades.
You know, it's one thing to see a
profit and a loss, but it's another thing
to see how you got there.
And you will remember your trades as you're
going over them.
You will remember.
You will remember the prices.
You will remember the circumstances.
You will remember.
OK, you when you're journaling your trades, you
don't want, you know, I hear people say,
well, I'm 90 percent accurate.
I'm not 90 percent accurate.
OK, great.
That's that's great.
But that doesn't mean anything.
I'd rather be 65, 70 percent accurate, because
when you look at your journal, you know,
some of the best trades you will make,
some of the best trades your retailers will
make, retail traders will make will be losing
trades.
They will be losing trades.
OK, why?
OK, you see something, you know, everything clicks
in your head.
You whatever reason you get long here, you're
wrong.
And you and the earlier you see that
you're wrong and you're willing to pull the
trigger and take that trade off, you want
to see that in your journal.
And that kind of stuff is not going
to promote 90 percent.
If you're at 90 percent, you're not seeing
that.
And you're at 90 percent.
You're never going to be able to do
that consistently.
You want to be at 65, 70 percent.
What does it mean?
It means that you cut losses on trades
and it means that your road win is
longer.
That's what you want to see in your
journal.
In terms of I've heard you talk on
before, instead of having a single entry that
you should be averaging into your entries instead.
And is that more so in terms of
if the market is going against you or
do you mean once the market is showing
you its hand and it's working in your
favor, then you should be scaling in?
Both.
So what you don't want to do is
you don't want to use up all your
ammunition when you're initiating a trade.
I never do it.
That puts pressure on yourself to be right
immediately.
You know, sometimes you are right immediately.
Sometimes you feel no pain in a trade.
That's wonderful.
It doesn't happen like that all the time.
So, you know, you don't want to bunch
together positions if you're going to average.
Of course, you're not doing yourself a favor.
If you buy something at 50, you don't
want to buy it at 49 because that's
bringing your average down a half, two ticks.
You don't want to do that.
You're not accomplishing anything.
Why?
Because you just used up another 50 percent
or whatever you used up.
You doubled your money.
You may have more buying power, but you're
clumped together.
Okay.
You want to stretch that out.
You want to bring that down to 45.
So now you're talking 47 and a half.
You don't want to bunch together, but you
don't want single entries because single entries will
burn you every time.
It will burn you every time.
But don't clump together.
When you average it down and you want
to average down to your initial position, don't
clump it together.
Let it spread out, especially in a NASDAQ.
You know, I don't maybe 10 to 20
handles.
I don't average down in a NASDAQ.
This morning, it was much more than that
during some of these sessions where I was
long 20 or 30 NQ futures.
Okay.
Because, man, they kept coming down.
And if you have the bank to do
it, as it comes down lower and lower,
you want to increase your size.
You don't want to buy one.
If you're long four, you want to buy
four to eight.
And that brings your price way down.
And that helps you feed in when the
market turns.
And the market always turns for day trading
purposes.
It may not trade for, you know, to
ride off into the sunset, but it will
turn around and it will allow you to
feed into a rally.
But if you're only buying one or two
down, you're not bringing your price down enough.
It's going to make it too difficult.
So you have to close your eyes and
buy them if you want to do it
right.
What are your thoughts on market cycles?
Because you've been through your fair few, you
know, you've got your 87, you've got your
dot com, you've got your 2008.
You had obviously your COVID crash recently as
well.
Then last on Monday of this week, sorry,
not even last Monday, August 5th is August
9th as of today.
And yeah, like on August 5th, we saw
the market open up.
We saw markets across the board red and
selling off very aggressively, emotions extremely high.
And yet we bounced back and actually, you
know, printed new highs from those lows.
Amazing.
You know, what can you speak on in
terms of like recognizing the emotions, any sort
of common traits amongst these volatile market conditions
that come in from time to time?
And any of the biggest mistakes that traders
make when these moments happen?
Yeah.
Well, if the volatility is on a downside,
as I mentioned earlier, one of the biggest
failed trades is and sometimes you could do
it.
But but vast majority of times, you know,
you can't get away with it.
And that's selling failed breakdowns or buying failed
breakouts.
OK, markets going crazy, going crazy, going crazy.
I mean, sometimes I will go crazy when
I recognize that they're out of control by
the various components that I look at and
I realize they're out of control and I'll
just hit that buy button and I'll just
keep riding it.
All right.
And I'll just start flipping out as they
as they come up.
But, you know, you can just recognize the
emotions.
You can recognize the emotions by the way
the tape is moving.
You can recognize the emotions, you know, you
know, you know, by the technical areas that
are being invaded by algorithms.
You could recognize it.
And and, you know, when, you know, the
market is out of control, I have a
couple hundred, one hundred and fifty two hundred
names.
That's a watch list.
It's a customized watch list.
It's a watch list, whatever the banks, the
oil stocks, you know, the semis on and
on and on.
And I got a really good sense when
all these things are puking in the same
time at the same time and the volume
picking up as such.
Of course, I always monitor the volume bars.
I mean, you just know that the emotions
are running high and that gets my juices
going, because the emotions running high, you know,
people make mistakes and all the folks out
there, retail traders are probably in that group
that makes mistakes.
And, you know, for instance, you know, up,
up, up, up market, everybody's having a grand
old time by the by the market goes
up, make money.
Oh, this is great.
You know, a cab driver is talking about
it up, up, up, up, up, up.
OK, but they don't know how to handle
down, down, down, down, down.
And there's less sophistication and down, down, down.
And they make more mistakes and down, down,
down.
All right.
They'll sell at the bottom.
And that's what they do.
And that's the emotions.
How interesting has it been to recognize that
over the last 60 years or coming up
to 60 years of your career, the mistakes
that traders make and the things that make
traders be unprofitable are still the same?
A hundred percent.
That's no true statement was ever made.
You can beat their head against the wall.
You can do anything they want.
And they'll still make the same mistakes over
and over again.
And part of it is because new traders
come into the fray and they're at a
different stage and make mistakes.
Maybe the people that started this two or
three years ago have advanced somewhat, but they'll
still make the same mistakes.
But collectively, as new traders come in and
everybody wants to be a trader, the new
traders come in, you know, as an average,
they still make the same freaking mistakes.
It's amazing.
Has trading always been sort of this allure,
this this thing that people have always been
interested in?
Yeah, I absolutely, absolutely.
You know, you know, I mean, I don't
live in New York anymore, but everything I
do is in New York.
And, you know, people ask me, I just
came over from a, doesn't matter, from a
doctor and just normal stuff.
And, oh, man, give me, give me, give
me a thing.
I'm a, you know, a cardiologist nurse, a
nurse practitioner.
Oh, really?
Give me, I want you to give me,
give me, give me your, give me your
email address.
Give me the, you know.
So, yeah, the answer is, yeah, it's true.
It's true.
People feel like they're missing a boat, number
one.
Number two, people are looking to augment their
income because of the reasons we stated earlier.
So one thing that did come out after
August 5th as well, around that same time,
earlier this week, was that Warren Buffett, Berkshire
Hathaway, sitting on the most cash and they
sold a huge portion, billions of dollars worth
of Apple shares.
You know, these sort of traits that you've
recognized previously when, you know, things are all
time highs, you start to see these huge
funds start to liquidate their shares and start
to sit on cash.
I know there's a lot of talk of
potential recession and market downturn.
We're currently in election years across multiple, not
just the US, but UK just had an
election.
France just had an election.
When these things have happened in the past,
what are the common occurrences that usually take
place?
Yeah.
Well, you know, usually in election years, they'll
buy the market in the last two months
of the year.
You have tax selling at the end of
the year as well.
That's another famous play that I always made.
I always specialized in, you know, stocks that
have gotten beaten up, gotten beaten up during
the year, down 30, 40 percent in an
up year.
All right.
Those stocks are going to be sold and
replaced in a new year.
So, I mean, that's a play.
To be fair, it's been a play or
been in talk, should I say, and whispers
of it for many years now since before
COVID.
COVID, we had that crash, which sort of
instigated it being that the COVID and coronavirus
instigated the crash.
They turned the money printer on.
Interest rates were down at pretty much near
zero.
Everything turned back up, all new time highs.
And now it seems like we're starting to
stagnate again.
You know, we've got interest rates risen, inflation,
all time highs.
We've got a lot of wars across the
world.
We've got a lot of political distress as
well.
And it seems like there's something on the
horizon.
There's a lot of talks of the US
dollar collapsing and the end of that empire.
What are your thoughts after being in the
markets for so long and seeing different rises
and falls from different stocks, for example, and
different sectors of stocks?
Like right now, we're in AI tech sector
and the boom there.
Is anything worrying to you when you look
at these markets?
I mean, yeah, absolutely.
That's why you saw the last three or
four days doing what it did after it
made a high.
A couple of weeks ago, it made an
all-time high.
You're not talking a long time here.
Warren Buffett, that's what smart people, deep pocketed
investors do.
They're sitting there with cash, they buy at
bottom, and then they start peeling off millions
of shares in a questionable environment, which is
what he does.
And no, I assumed he was doing that.
I didn't have to read it to tell
you the truth.
And it doesn't really mean anything that he's
doing it because I assumed he was doing
it because that's what smart people do.
When they're throwing it out the window, smart
people are there to catch it.
And when they're coming up the other way,
smart people are there to let it happen.
So when was he doing this?
At the height, near the height of the
market.
Does it matter to him?
Is the market going up another 20%, 10
% in his face?
Probably not.
Was it going up another 5%?
Maybe.
But it doesn't matter to him.
He's printing money by liquidating these positions.
One of the smartest investors on the planet
is Stanley Druckenmiller, who sold all his high
-tech names and bought the IWM.
The IWM, lesser names, less growth names, potentially
more growth names, that's why he bought it.
The IWM lists companies that are 30%, 7
% of them do not make money.
But what they do do is have research
and development.
And if you buy a basket of stocks
in an ETF like that, one or two
of them can hit.
And that's what he did.
Very smart dude.
But as far as the concept of going
wall street, it will never change.
We talked about a number of times during
this conversation about selling bottoms, selling bottoms, selling
bottoms.
Well, in essence, or buying tops, buying tops.
Well, the smart people of the world, they
know this.
So when people are puking and the market
is puking, they have to place their bets.
And they have to stay in power just
to hang on until it turns around.
And when they're selling up here, he's printing
money.
So this goes on over and over.
It'll never change.
Do you feel like once, when everyone's talking
about recession, that's obviously not when it's going
to take place.
It's normally when it catches everyone off guard,
when peak euphoria, essentially.
So like, every time we make a new
all time high, everyone expects us to then
suddenly crash.
It keeps doing it over and over again.
Correct.
Until the point where no one questions it
anymore.
This is going to keep happening.
Perfect.
That's when it's going to take place.
I stood up and watched the dot com
era the same way.
OK, you shook your head.
None of those companies ever made money.
They didn't make money at the time.
It didn't matter.
And every day, I shook my head.
I said, you've got to stop this.
My customers shook their head.
They couldn't believe it.
They were getting running all over the place.
What's this?
The impetus on the money is capable of
this.
Until, as you just eloquently said, until it's
not.
OK, and then it gets ugly.
OK, and I firmly believe in the last
three weeks, OK, what were they talking about?
What word did you hear?
Bubble.
It's a bubble.
Want to know why the market made new
highs, all time highs, two weeks ago?
Because everybody was talking about a bubble.
Exactly what you said.
That's the way it goes.
Simple common sense, man.
What are your thoughts in terms of, I
know that you were part of history with
the New York Stock Exchange.
You placed the first trade, if I'm not
mistaken.
Was it executed via, I don't know if
it was electronically, something you.
Buyback, the program trade orders.
Program trade orders, that's right.
First ever, first ever on a New York
Stock Exchange.
First ever.
I had six million shares, give or take,
of 60 S&P names to buy, market
on close, when there was no supply.
No supply.
Stacker orders like this, no supply.
Buy 100,000 mobile, market on close.
Buy 20,000 IBM, market on close.
20,000 IBM, right.
20,000.
500 shares of IBM in those days to
buy market on close could take the stock
up a buck and a half or two
bucks.
20,000.
60 S&P names.
I had 25 brokers, seven of which worked
for me, 25 of which were just my
friends that were representing.
I'm staying in a separate location handling every
freaking order.
I said, wait a minute, this is not
going to work.
It's not working.
There was no supply.
The place was in a panic.
The chairman of the stock exchange, the directors,
the board coming down.
Are these real orders?
I said, fellas, what do you mean are
these real orders?
Yes, they're real orders.
Oh, yes, they are.
Oh, my God.
What are we going to do?
We're going to do nothing.
Get away from me.
I'll take care of this.
25 brokers running all over the place.
Finally, I realized that the traditional way to
do this is not the way to do
it.
So what did I do?
I called the largest, the biggest firm on
Wall Street who were clients of mine and
will pay me to trade IBM for them.
$15,000 a month in 1980, 1981, a
lot of money, just as a retainer, just
as a retainer.
But they had the most successful person that
headed a trading desk and the most powerful
person on Wall Street, excuse me, named Stanley
Shopkorn.
Stanley Shopkorn was the head trader of Salomon
Brothers.
Salomon Brothers was noted as a bond house,
but they had a huge equity desk.
Every piece of merchandise that came down the
pike to get placed, called Stanley, called Salomon
Brothers.
I said, I need somebody with strength here.
I go to the phone.
I say, give me Stanley.
Stanley, Richie, what's happening?
Stanley, listen to me.
I have debt.
I have about to buy.
Okay.
So, you know, call me back.
He says, well, call me back and we'll
wipe somebody's debt.
I said, no, no, no.
There's no way.
Cannot do that.
There's none of that.
He says, give me my clerk.
It's his clerk.
He says, give Richie sell orders up to
the amount of shares that he has to
buy at his discretion to fill every one
of those buy orders.
And that was an incredible day.
And we just went up, talk about the
specialist book, find out where supply was, you
know, and then we filled it in with
Salomon Brothers proprietary sell paper and priced every
damn one of them.
Wow.
Crazy.
So that being part of that history, so
that you being part of the history of
being one of the first people to instigate
a sell, a program, a trade.
And how does that make you feel though,
like knowing that you're part of that history?
It was just, I wish I had those
original papers.
I wish I really did.
They'd be worth millions of dollars, but I
don't.
But how did it feel?
It feels very satisfying.
Here's a kid growing up in Queens with
nothing.
I mean, I wasn't, I didn't grow up
with a poor family, middle income people worked
hard all their lives, you know, lived in
a 10, $12,000 house.
You know, I had everything that I wanted,
which was really not much.
And, and, and here I am dictating flow,
which the top firm on Wall Street and
the top, top, top trader on Wall Street,
basically, not basically you go look them up.
Top guy.
I mean, he's controlled everything.
And here I am, you know, one-on
-one with this person and he's given me
discretion over millions of shares.
So how does it make me feel?
It makes me feel great, man.
It really does.
As it should, as it should.
And, you know, as part of this whole
interview, there's so many gems that we've taken
away.
That's for sure.
And to speak from the experience and wealth
of knowledge that you've had, you know, I
know it's going to have a huge impact
on traders out there.
As we discussed, like people of, you know,
this audience, the retail audience of today, you
know, we've talked about like their issues being
more so of rushing, their greed, their lack
of focus.
But when it comes to, we talked about
sizing trades, right?
We talked about handling size for yourself, but
what would you advise to traders out there
who are going through that scaling process themselves?
You know, they're going from, I would say
trading a few thousand dollars into the tens
of thousands, the six figures, the seven figures,
you know, and a lot of them have
these barriers when it comes to that psychology
of being able to handle, you know, new
size, whether it's new stop loss amounts, new
take profits amounts or new contract sizes.
Is there anything that you can sort of
advise them to help them overcome those barriers?
I would say something in a very profound
manner here.
If you find yourself in that position, stop
and manage what you can manage because it's
not for you.
You will make mistakes and it's going to
cost you money.
If you think you can fight through it,
it's your prerogative to try it.
But if you have a roadblock and you
sense a roadblock because the chips on a
table have changed, you know, you may have
to look in a mirror and say, maybe
this is not for me.
Or you may have to just stand in
one place, you know.
I think it's very fair.
I think it's very, very fair.
And it's interesting you mentioned about chips on
a table.
How close of the relationship between, say, poker
and trading is there?
Because as you mentioned earlier, actually, the similar
thing where you need to know the personalities,
obviously, that was more so for the pits.
But do you treat the markets even now
in a similar fashion of trying to recognize
the emotion within the charts, if that makes
sense?
Like, if you're seeing a lot of a
down movement, a lot of emotion just within
the chart itself, when you're looking at the
charts, you're seeing this huge red candles.
Is that how you're operating?
Are you looking at, OK, this is how
the average trader is probably feeling right now,
or the traders are out there.
This is what the flow may be telling
me and therefore acting accordingly.
Yeah.
I mean, listen, I made my living and
as of today, have learned under very stringent
conditions how to control emotions and how to
manage emotions.
Again, the size doesn't really matter to me.
It means nothing.
It doesn't mean anything.
Trading that kind of volume under those circumstances,
what the stock meant in the overall picture
of the market, every trade, most of the
trades during the day, I can recount and
look at the percentages of every one of
those trades and the decision process that takes
place to pull the trigger on a specific
trade.
Yes, it does.
And I believe that those decisions really are
the decisions that control the decisions we make
in our everyday life, whether it's to stand
on a curve, whether it's to take a
step this way, whether it's to yell at
somebody, whatever it is, there's a percentage in
everything.
So you talk about a poker game, there's
a percentage in a game.
It plays.
Do I want to play?
Do I want to go all in?
Do I want to fold?
Am I going to make a bet?
Am I going to make a raise?
Blah, blah, blah.
But the stock market boils all that down.
And the difference is there is no time.
You have to make a split decision and
you make a split decision based on the
time you put in.
And being a student of the game, as
I say that word again, you need to
get to a point where your gut spits
this out.
And you can.
You are capable of doing that, providing you
have the right mentor.
That'll tell you.
Providing you have the right mentor, you're all
capable of doing it.
But the decisions that I make to this
day are based on that gut feeling.
I tell everybody, look at the rhythm of
the numbers.
What do you mean?
I said, watch the quote and watch the
size that trades.
Watch it.
That'll spit out scalp trades to you without
looking at another thing.
Yes, it will.
You'll see the momentum go.
You'll see it.
So, you know, those decisions are based wholly
on mathematics.
And I say, if you're a student of
the game, your gut will start spitting out,
spitting out these moves.
You will see it.
And learning from the way I learned it
and lived it, to this day, it holds
up.
It just does.
So it's all about mathematics, man.
To finish up on the algorithm side of
things, what would be your advice for people
to start trying to observe these algorithmic plays
within the markets?
I know you've described really well previously in
terms of having sort of your range, knowing
where your premium, your discount is, understanding your
buy and sell stops within those ranges and
acting accordingly.
Is there anything that we can elaborate on
that at all?
You need to remember that algorithms are there
to create liquidity and volatility.
They have no mind.
They have to go to an area.
They don't just go to an area.
They're programmed by, no matter what you say,
it comes down to a programmer programming them,
programming whatever technicals they put in, whatever the
mathematics is that make up this algorithm.
So it's not only the premium and discount
areas, but when you see the NASDAQ go
into a full number, coming up 20 or
30 handles, 19,200, all right, 200, 230,
240, 250, 270, 275, 280, market's rallying, 275,
280.
You know it's printing at the main number.
You just know it.
And I know that those algorithms are going
to make that print.
But it's the same example could be made
by any firm even number.
Where is that?
10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 70, 80,
especially 50.
You know, they sit and they sit and
they want to go to those numbers.
Why?
We should spend a little time talking about
algorithms going to option strike price areas.
We specialize in that as well because this
market and this enormity, we gave the example,
the positions in this market this day and
age are multimillion share positions.
It's not easy to put that kind of
money to work.
And they have to put it to work.
It's their mandate to put it to work.
Why am I giving you my money if
you're not putting it to work?
So they have to.
So their positions are huge.
Does anybody out there think that they just
sit back and they buy and hold and
smile and go home and have dinner with
their wives?
No, that's not the way this works.
They hedge their positions as well.
Where do they hedge their positions?
For the most part, all right, options.
So these strike prices become huge and the
amount of puts and calls that sit at
these strike prices, the algorithms know where they're
sitting and they're programmed then to go to
those strike places.
Why?
To create liquidity and volatility.
That's all their mandate is.
They're not human.
They don't care about P&L.
Understand that.
Interesting to finish up on because I know
it's a topic I've discussed previously on the
podcast, but I haven't for some time.
In terms of market makers and hunting stops,
there's a big thing in the retail space
of like the market makers, like your price
hitting your stop loss, then going completely the
other way, people feeling very targeted.
Correct.
And I've heard you say that that is
a case, so that is something that does
take place.
Oh, 100 percent.
One of the lock trades, as a member
of the New York Stock Exchange, that a
specialist made or if you were an agent
and had size flow is to be on
the other side of stop orders.
OK, so conversely speaking, here's another little gimme
for you folks out there.
Retail traders, especially if you're going down to
a number and the market is coming down
and down and down and it's you know,
the algorithms are going to print a number.
Put an order in two ticks underneath the
number, because why?
Because you wind up being on the assumption
is that there are stop orders at those
prices.
And the assumption is that you will be
on the other side of a bad sale.
The market is a buy and sell.
There's a buyer and seller in every transaction.
Somebody's going to be right.
Somebody's going to be wrong.
You want to be on the other side
of stop orders.
Yes, you're 100 percent right.
You want to be on the other side
of stop order.
But it's not easy to identify where those
stop orders lie.
If you're going to put a stop order
to protect yourself again, don't put it at
50, because they're going to get hit.
You know, put it at 48.
Give yourself a chance.
Give yourself a chance to breathe and for
the position to be right.
Don't put it at 50.
You're going to get swept away by some
intelligent buy like myself who wants to who
wants to get long or if you're a
mistake.
Richie, I love that.
I love that.
And I'm sure we could keep going.
But thank you for being with us today
and sharing so much with us.
My pleasure.
And everyone at home, drop a comment of
your biggest takeaway from this episode.
There was so much, as always, and the
links for Richie will be in the description
below.
So make sure you check those out as
well.
There'll be other episodes on screen.
So check those out.
Hit subscribe.
And until next time, take care.