Hello traders!
I'm Joanne from Binary Trader.
The YouTube channel focusing exclusively on binary options
trading.
Today I will make a $1 challenge using
parabolic and CCI indicators.
Before diving in, let me kindly ask you
to like the video, and consider subscribing to
my channel, so you won't miss upcoming content.
Thank you for your support.
Let's start!
I am trading at Pocket Option.
Platform link is in the video description as
usual.
I will use 1 minute candles.
I will use 1 minute for trade duration.
Among indicators, I choose parabolic, and CCI indicators.
For parabolic I use the default settings.
For CCI I set the period to 13.
I choose some trading pairs with a decent
payout.
And let's look for setups.
Strategy is simple.
When parabolic flips to below candles, and CCI
is around 100, a trade should be placed
in the upward direction.
Likewise when parabolic flips above candles, and CCI
is around minus 100, a trade in the
downward direction should be placed.
Though as this is a $1 challenge, so
I only risk $1 throughout the whole session,
I won't spend too much time on market
analysis, especially in the beginning.
Here parabolic flips down, CCI is close to
100, so I place trade in the upward
direction.
$1 challenge means you start with $1 and
risk all you win on subsequent trades.
With a 92% payout level you can
get above $1,000 with 11 winning trades
in a row.
That's not as unlikely to happen as you
would think.
Of course do not expect to have a
long winning streak for the first time.
If you deposit like $100, that means you
have 100 chances to start a $1 challenge
again if you fail.
If you use the promo code also found
in the video description, you can boost that
up by 50%, so you will have 150
chances.
People with an attitude of taking more risks
can start from 10 or more dollars obviously.
If you can't bear staring at the shots,
feel free to take a break.
The trade will play out in your absence.
You can perform your analysis afterwards based on
the outcome.
Here I place a trade in the downward
direction as parabolic flipped up, CCI is close
to minus 100.
It's not too close and the candle is
already open, but we are at the beginning.
Risk is small, so we can be a
bit more loose on the rules.
Similar situation as previous.
I am trading at pocket option.
Platform link is in the video description as
usual.
If you haven't done yet, follow the link
in the video description to join pocket option
and start trading today.
You can use the fully functional demo mode
before investing your money.
The trade won, so look for next setup.
This is not the best setup either, and
it's a bit late here too, but we
are still at low risk.
This is a perfect time to press the
like button and subscribing to my channel.
Do not forget to select all notifications, so
you won't miss any upcoming content.
It's just a few clicks for you, but
means and helps a lot to me.
Great, look for next setup.
If you can't bear staring at the charts,
feel free to take a break.
The trade will play out in your absence.
You can perform your analysis afterwards based on
the outcome.
I am trading at pocket option.
Platform link is in the video description as
usual.
The trade won, so look for next setup.
Feel free to ask any further question in
the comment section.
Remember, you should practice on demo balance first
without any risk.
And deposit real money to trade with once
you become comfortable with the strategy of your
choice.
Check out my other videos for different strategies
to find the one that best suits your
style of trading.
Follow the link in the video description to
join pocket option and start practicing today.
Great, look for next setup.
Don't forget to check payout levels regularly as
they might fall for some pairs.
Rise for others.
I recommend to only keep pairs on your
watchlist with a payout level of at least
80%.
Remove pairs with low payout and add back
other ones with higher payout.
The trade won, so look for next setup.
This is a perfect time to press the
like button.
And subscribing to my channel.
Do not forget to select all notifications, so
you won't miss any upcoming content.
It's just a few clicks for you, but
means and helps a lot to me.
If you haven't done yet, follow the link
in the video description to join pocket option
and start trading today.
You can use the fully functional demo mode
before investing real money.
Great, look for next setup.
Feel free to ask any further question in
the comment section.
I especially like to see when you talk
to each other, that can build a community
here.
Great, look for next setup.
If you can't bear staring at the shots,
feel free to take a break.
The trade will play out in your absence.
You can perform your analysis afterwards based on
the outcome.
The trade won, so look for next setup.
I am trading at pocket option.
Platform link is in the video description as
usual.
This is a perfect time to press the
like button.
And subscribing to my channel.
Do not forget to select all notifications, so
you won't miss any upcoming content.
It's just a few clicks for you, but
means and helps a lot to me.
Great, the trade won and I reached the
$1,000 milestone.
But I won't stop just yet.
I'm trading for almost an hour.
Feel free to take breaks during your session
to avoid losing focus.
And keep your trading sessions short in general.
Remember, you should practice on demo balance first
without any risk.
And deposit real money to trade with once
you become comfortable with the strategy of your
choice.
Check out my other videos for different strategies
to find the one that best suits your
style of trading.
Follow the link in the video description to
join pocket option and start practicing today.
Great, look for next setup.
I am trading at pocket option.
Platform link is in the video description as
usual.
Don't forget to check payout levels regularly as
they might fall for some pairs and rise
for others.
I recommend to only keep pairs on your
watch list with a payout level of at
least 80%.
Remove pairs with low payout.
And add back other ones with higher payout.
As the
risk got high, accept good signals only.
You might need to wait a lot for
those.
Patience is the most important skill in trading.
This is a perfect time to press the
like button.
And subscribing to my channel.
Do not forget to select all notifications, so
you won't miss any upcoming content.
It's just a few clicks for you, but
means and helps a lot to me.
Great, look for next setup.
I stopped
risking everything from now on, as I'm trading
for almost an hour and I want to
keep a portion of the gain even if
things go bad.
If you haven't done yet, follow the link
in the video description to join pocket option
and start trading today.
You can use the fully functional demo mode
before investing your money.
Great, but before looking for next setup, I
will take a longer break, as I am
trading for like an hour.
Always keep breaks during long sessions.
As the account balance got quite high, so
even if the recent bullish engulfer and the
huge bullish candle makes the signal strong, I
don't risk all of the balance this time.
So I keep some of it if things
go bad.
Don't worry when price falls back after a
nice move during an open trade.
Only the price at the end matters.
This is a perfect time to press the
like button.
And subscribing to my channel.
Do not forget to select all notifications, so
you won't miss any upcoming content.
It's just a few clicks for you, but
means and helps a lot to me.
Cool, the trade won.
Look for one more setup.
I am trading for an hour and a
half already.
So next will be my last trade, whatever
happens.
The signal is clear and market analysis tells
the downtrend is forming, which confirms the signal,
though I won't risk more than half of
the capital, for safety.
Of course I was risking technically $1 only
throughout the whole session, but it was a
long one, and I want to keep some
profit even if things go bad.
If you haven't done yet, follow the link
in the video description to join Pocket Option
and start trading today.
You can use the fully functional demo mode
before investing real money.
And deposit real money to trade with once
you become comfortable with the strategy of your
choice.
Check out my other videos for different strategies
to find the one that best suits your
style of trading.
Great, that was my last trade today.
It's an amazing gain.
And I was risking technically only $1.
Hope you enjoyed today's video.
If you did, please press the like button.
And if you like my content in general,
consider subscribing to my channel as well.
Don't forget to select all notifications.
If you haven't done yet, use the link
in the video description below to join Pocket
Option and start trading today.
Use the promo code also found in the
description for 50% extra on your first
deposit.
Ask any further question in the comment section.
Or feel free to leave your thought or
idea there or whatever else is on your
mind.
Thank you very much for watching my video.
I wish you successful trading.
See you next time.