You can do some crazy stuff with options,
like $10K to $90K.
Zero days to expiration options, or Zero DTE,
have exploded in popularity in the last year.
They allow investors to bet on stock market
moves within the same day, which can result
in big wins and big losses.
This is one of the biggest shifts I've
seen in markets of the past decade.
Here's why Zero DTE options have taken off,
despite being some of the riskiest in the
entire market.
So I got into Zero DTE in 2020,
during the whole lockdown.
Drayson Little graduated from college in 2021 and
has been trading options full-time for about
a year.
He lives in Las Vegas, so his day
typically starts around 5.30am, an hour before
the market opens on the East Coast.
First things first is I'll head over to
Twitter, that's where I get all my news.
On big news days, like when inflation data
is released, he says it's easier to spot
a trend in the market.
You can see a massive move into and
from that PCE number.
Which he says is the best time to
trade Zero DTE.
In one minute, I had made $100.
He says he usually bets a few thousand
dollars per trade.
One of his biggest one-day profits was
about $14,000, and biggest loss was about
$12,000.
It's like euphoria, it's like winning a lottery.
But then you also have your crazy lows.
Zero DTE options expire the same day they're
purchased, which is why...
They are some of the most sensitive to
changes in the stock's price.
So that's why you can see them zip
higher or crash incredibly quickly.
But that's also part of the reason they're
so appealing to traders.
Your upside potential is infinite.
It can be 500%, it can be 1
,000%.
Traders are also drawn to Zero DTE options
because they're cheaper than longer-dated contracts.
But...
Often the odds are stacked against you.
A lot of these retail traders do end
up losing a lot of money.
Drayson says some of his biggest losses occurred
in his first year of trading.
I think I probably lost at the time
during 2020 upwards of like $65,000.
And this was when I was a full
-time student, I was an entrepreneur before, I
had made some money from e-commerce.
I lost 20-30% of it.
And it just feels really bad, to be
honest with you.
But he says the possibility of big wins
enticed him to keep trading.
The thing is, with a 9-to-5,
it's not scalable.
You only make so much during these hours
compared to trading, where you take one crazy
trade, like just one trade, and you make
a million dollars.
This type of options trading has long been
reserved for professionals with sophisticated technology and tools.
But in the last few years, retail traders
have played a big role in driving Zero
DTE trading volumes to record highs.
It's really become a viral phenomenon.
You know, when I was looking at hashtags
for Zero DTE online, there are tens of
thousands of mentions of Zero DTE just this
year alone.
A few years ago, there were no such
mentions.
Part of the reason is that options exchanges
expanded Zero DTE contracts to every day of
the week last year to capitalize on this
boom.
And that just unleashed a frenzy of activity.
And traders I was talking to were saying,
we've never seen something take off the way
Zero DTE trading has.
Many of these retail traders started with meme
stocks.
This is really the continuation of a trend
the past few years, as more people have
entered markets, where they want to bet on
sports, they want to bet at the casino,
and they also want to bet on stocks.
But some experts think all this betting could
mean trouble for the market.
There's a lot of concern from a lot
of industry analysts and pundits that suggest that
Zero DTE could kind of bring about an
end of day scenario in markets.
That's because when professional traders buy or sell
options, they also buy or sell stocks to
hedge their positions.
That creates worries that if there is a
big move in the market, and all of
a sudden someone's doing a ton of buying
and selling of options, that could ripple over
into the stock market.
For example, during the meme stock mania, there
were concerns that options activity was exacerbating the
volatility.
I think a lot of the fear now
is that Zero DTE volumes will put the
market in the same position.
The odds of that happening is a lot
lower than in a situation like GameStop or
meme mania.
While this concern is hotly debated on Wall
Street, Kochuba says Zero DTE options have become
such a large part of trading that when
there's an unexplainable move in the market...
You can look at the Zero DTE volumes
and movement in Zero DTE and understand that
this could be driving those strange behaviors.
I wouldn't regret anything.
I honestly find it has taught me a
lot more things and has leveled me up
as a person rather than pull me down.
With the money he made from trading, he
says he was able to buy...
One of my dream cars, the AMG GTR.
Get back to my family, travel around the
world.
And then I bought a Rolex, so that
was pretty cool.
He says his goal for next year is
to make six figures every month and launch
an options trading course.
You're going to have your lows, you're going
to have your highs, but as long as
you just keep moving forward, you'll eventually get
to your end goal.