You will never need to use an indicator
again if you learn all the price action
methods in this video, because naked price action
tells you everything you need to know.
Now if you want more trading videos, make
sure to hit the like button, subscribe, but
most importantly, turn on the notifications bell as
this goes a long way in supporting our
team.
First, what is price action exactly?
Price action is you making trading decisions based
on price formations you see materializing in the
market in real time.
Indicators are lagging, whereas price action is a
leading indicator.
So let's dive right into it, starting with
market structure and key levels.
What are key levels exactly?
This is the uber stock.
Price moves up before reversing drastically, making this
a key resistance level.
Resistance levels are areas where price can possibly
reverse downwards from.
So as price came back up, you had
a great short trade setup right at the
resistance level that produced a winning short trade.
Now from a price action standpoint, when price
comes up to a recently formed resistance level,
it is deemed expensive within that particular moment
in time, meaning less buying occurs, triggering the
reversal downwards.
Now going in the opposite direction, this is
the general electric or GE stock.
Price moves down before reversing drastically, making this
a key support level.
Support levels are areas where price can possibly
reverse upwards from.
So as price came back down, you had
a great long trade setup right at the
support level that produced a winning long trade.
Now from a price action standpoint, when price
comes down to a recently formed support level,
it is deemed cheap within that particular moment
in time, meaning value buyers will take advantage
and load up on long positions, triggering the
reversal upwards.
So moving on.
Supply and demand and multiple reversals of price.
When you have an area above where price
reverses off of multiple times, this is known
as a supply zone.
Supply zones are areas where price has failed
to push through on multiple separate occasions.
From a price action standpoint, the market is
deeming this area of as expensive, which results
in buyers consistently deciding to close their long
positions at this area and sellers choosing to
hold this area strong and open new short
positions.
The double action of buyers closing long positions
and sellers opening new short positions is what
creates downwards momentum for your short trade entries
off of these key areas.
Now in the opposite direction, when you have
an area below where price reverses off of
multiple times, this is known as a demand
zone.
Demand zones are areas where price has failed
to push through on multiple separate occasions.
From a price action standpoint, the market is
deeming this area of price as cheap, which
results in sellers consistently deciding to close their
short positions at this area and buyers choosing
to hold this area strong and open new
long positions.
The double action of sellers closing short positions
and buyers opening new long positions is what
creates upwards momentum for your long trade entries
off of these key areas.
Let's show this again.
This is the Funco stock.
Notice how on multiple separate occasions, price tried
to push through this area and failed, making
it a supply zone and presented a ton
of great short trade opportunities.
So moving on.
Extreme swing highs and lows.
These reversal points in between the swing highs
and lows are your traditional key levels.
The absolute highest resistance level here is your
swing high key level.
Short trade setups off of swing highs are
of higher quality because there is a higher
percentage chance of price reversing off of the
level as price is deemed very expensive within
that timeframe.
The absolute lowest support level here is your
swing low key level.
Long trade setups off of swing lows are
of higher quality because there is a higher
percentage chance of price reversing off the level
as price is deemed very cheap within that
timeframe.
So moving on.
Higher timeframe key levels.
When you are using the weekly timeframe or
monthly timeframe, many of the key levels you
find on the lower timeframes aren't visible.
But then, the levels that are visible and
visually obvious on the weekly and monthly are
known as major key levels, which are levels
where there is a higher probability of price
reversing off of them, but not just a
slight bounce, but a true reversal that will
often move a greater distance.
So this is the monthly timeframe.
These levels here that are visible are known
as your major key levels.
Because these levels are slower to form, they
become very key levels because these are the
ones where slower moving large institutions look to
unload positions or take on new positions.
Notice how this level here formed in 2008
but was still valid in 2010, still valid
in 2012, and again, still valid in 2018.
Now you don't trade on the higher timeframes,
but here's a technique on how to use
them.
Label the levels as monthly levels.
So this is price right now moving up
towards that key monthly resistance level.
But again, you aren't spending most of your
time on the monthly timeframe.
So let's jump to a lower intraday timeframe
of this same asset.
So you're doing your usual day-to-day
trading on these lower intraday timeframes, but then
you notice price approaching a level, but this
isn't just any regular level.
This is a monthly level.
By having this level labeled as a monthly
level, you are reminded that this will be
a killer short trade opportunity once price gets
to the level.
So moving on.
Long wick candles.
In an uptrend, when price is approaching a
key level, how do you know whether price
will break through a level or react to
it?
Look for candles with the wicks sticking out
above like this.
From a price action standpoint, it shows buyers
tried to push through the level, but failed
and price swung back down, causing the wick
to stick out above.
If buyers successfully pushed through the level, you
would have a full rectangle body momentum candle
like this closing through the level.
These long wick candles show a reaction to
the key level within that moment in time
and present short trade opportunities.
Now going in the opposite direction.
In the downtrend, when price is approaching a
key level, look for candles with wicks sticking
out below like this, which shows price reacting
to the key level and presenting long trade
opportunities.
From a price action standpoint, it shows sellers
tried to push through the level, but failed
and price swung back up, causing the wick
to stick out below.
If sellers successfully pushed through the key level,
you would have a full rectangle body momentum
candle like this closing through the level.
After you had the long wick candles, look
for an intraday trend change confirmation before taking
long entries.
So moving on.
Trends, reversals, and ranges.
Now before we continue, we need to hear
from you.
What kind of videos do you want us
to make next?
Do you want more trading videos?
And if so, which topics should we cover?
Or do you want more investing related videos?
Let us know in the comments below right
now.
As always, please hit the like button, as
it goes a long way in supporting our
team.
So here are the traits of identifying an
uptrend.
You have your runs here, and your pullbacks
here, which means an uptrend makes higher highs
and higher lows.
From a price action standpoint, a moving uptrend
shows bullish momentum and that the buyers are
in control.
So you lean towards taking long entries to
trade with the moving upwards herd momentum.
There are many ways to enter trades with
a moving uptrend, but a simple way is
to take pullback long trades at resistance turn
to new support levels.
So now how do you identify a trend
change from an uptrend to a downtrend?
Type one, you have your moving uptrend through
the higher highs and higher lows before a
lower low forms signaling a trend change from
an uptrend to a downtrend.
Type two, you have your moving uptrend through
the higher highs and higher lows before you
have a lower low form followed by a
lower high pullback before the full trend change
breakout and lower low.
Type three, you have your uptrend through the
higher highs and higher lows before you have
a lower high that forms followed by a
trend change breakout and lower low.
Now going in the opposite direction in a
downtrend, you have your runs here and your
pullbacks here, which means a downtrend makes lower
highs and lower lows.
From a price action standpoint, a moving downtrend
shows bearish momentum and that the sellers are
in control.
So you lean towards taking short entries to
trade with the moving downwards herd momentum.
There are many ways to enter trades with
a moving downtrend, but a simple way is
to take pullback short trades at the support
turned to new resistance levels.
So now how do you identify a trend
change from a downtrend to an uptrend?
Type one, you have your moving downtrend to
the lower highs and lower lows before a
higher high forms signaling a trend change from
a downtrend to an uptrend.
Type two, you have your moving downtrend to
the lower highs and lower lows before you
have a higher high form followed by a
higher low pullback before the full trend change
breakout and higher high.
Type three, you have your moving downtrend to
the lower highs and lower lows before you
have a higher low that forms first, followed
by a trend change breakout and higher high.
Now let's take this up a notch.
Combining key levels with trend change price action.
This is the GE stock daily timeframe.
This reversal point here gives you your key
support level.
You have your downtrend here through the lower
highs and lower lows.
Once price got to the key level, you
had a trend change pattern through the higher
low and higher high that formed, which presented
a great long trade setup.
Now that we've covered uptrends and downtrends, here
are sideways and ranging markets.
Prices making same highs and same lows and
moving in a sideways direction.
In markets like this, look to take trades
in both directions with confidence.
So moving on.
Fresh trends versus trend exhaustion.
You had your long trade setup here followed
by a higher high and trendline break confirmation.
When you get into a trade close to
the start of a move, this is known
as a fresh trend, which is where price
has legs and room to move because traders
just got into the trade and haven't made
their money yet.
So they most likely aren't closing out those
positions just yet.
Fresh trends or fresh reversals are higher quality
trade entries because you can capture a larger
portion of the move as you are getting
in early.
Now, in contrast, if you get into a
long trade up here, after price has already
moved significantly, price might suffer from what we
call trend exhaustion.
During trend exhaustion, if not enough new buyers
enter the market, price will lose momentum and
chop sideways.
Also during trend exhaustion, if traders have made
their money and see potential risks coming up,
they will decide to start locking in profits
and closing out their long positions.
If enough traders take profit, the trend will
reverse.
Now, does trend exhaustion mean that trend will
reverse a hundred percent?
No, it does not.
Price can go on and on, but in
terms of trade quality, the higher quality trade
would be one that is closer to the
start of a trend and fresh trend change.
So next momentum gain versus momentum
loss.
Starting with how to identify momentum gain.
First, look for tight price movement without large
swings.
In an uptrend, notice how price is very
tight together without wide swings, which shows buyers
are in full control and that not enough
sellers are in the market to cause swings
in the opposite direction.
You want to trade with this upwards gain
of momentum and not against it.
In the opposite direction, in a downtrend, notice
again how price is very tight together without
wide swings, which shows that sellers are in
full control and that there are not enough
buyers in the market to cause swings in
the opposite direction.
You want to trade with this downwards gain
of momentum and not against it.
So the second way to identify momentum gain
is candles growing in size.
In an uptrend, notice how each candle is
getting larger and larger and moving a greater
distance per candle, which shows a gain in
bullish momentum.
You want to trade with this gain of
momentum and not against it.
And in a downtrend, notice again how each
candle is getting larger and larger and moving
a greater distance per candle, which shows a
gain in bearish momentum.
You want to trade with this gain of
bearish momentum and not against it.
Now moving on to identifying momentum loss.
First look for wide swings of price.
So this uptrend here is tight price movement,
which means the buyers are in full control.
You had wide swings occurring, which shows momentum
loss and that the buyers are no longer
in complete control and can lead to a
possible reversal of price.
If paired with trend change price action going
in the opposite direction, this downtrend, here is
tight price movement, which means the sellers are
in full control.
You then had wide swings occurring, which shows
momentum loss and that the sellers are no
longer in complete control and can lead to
a possible reversal of price if paired with
trend change price action.
So the second momentum loss type to look
for is sideways price movement.
So this uptrend here is tight price movement,
which means the buyers are in full control.
You then had sideways price movement occur, which
shows momentum loss and that the buyers are
no longer in complete control and can lead
to a possible reversal of price if paired
with trend change price action going in the
opposite direction.
This downtrend here is tight price movement, which
means the sellers are in full control.
You then had sideways price movement occur, which
shows momentum loss and that the sellers are
no longer in complete control and can lead
to a possible reversal of price if paired
with trend change price action.
So the third momentum loss type is shrinking
candles.
You have your key level here.
As price approaches the level, you had shrinking
candles, which shows momentum loss and that the
sellers are losing speed as the distance traveled
per candle is shorter.
This presents long trade opportunities.
So the fourth momentum loss type is a
candle color change.
You had your key level here.
As price approaches the level, all red candles
before a green candle appears, which means this
is the first candle that closed higher than
the previous candle showing a loss of bearish
momentum and sellers losing steam.
This presents long trade opportunities.
Now moving on.
Deep pullbacks versus shallow pullbacks.
When trading pullbacks during a trend, the best
kinds are what we call deep pullbacks, which
are pullback trades to roughly 50% or
more of the current leg of the trend.
These work best when paired with a key
level.
From a price action perspective, you're getting in
at a great area of value within a
moving trend.
In contrast, a shallow pullback would be roughly
25% to 30% of the current
leg of the trend, which is still a
great trade setup.
But when deciding between a shallow pullback and
a deep pullback, a deep pullback is the
better trade option.
So next chart patterns, we
use chart patterns or what we call consolidation
patterns to help identify trend continuations versus trend
reversals.
So you have removing uptrend followed by your
pattern formation.
This could have been any pattern from this
list, but in this case, you would a
descending triangle pattern.
Once the pattern breaks above and in the
same direction as a larger trend, this signals
a trend continuation upwards and presents long trade
opportunities.
Now, in contrast, you have removing uptrend again,
followed by your pattern formation.
Again, this could have been any pattern from
this list, but in this case, you had
a descending triangle pattern form.
Now price breaks below and in the opposite
direction of the larger uptrend, which signals a
trend reversal downwards and presents short trade opportunities.
So going in the opposite direction in a
downtrend, you have removing downtrend followed by your
pattern formation.
Again, this could have been any pattern from
this list, but in this case, you had
a descending triangle pattern form.
Once the pattern breaks below and in the
same direction as a larger trend, this signals
a trend continuation downwards and presents short trade
opportunities.
One more downtrend, but an ascending triangle pattern,
this time break below trend continuation downwards.
Now in contrast, you have removing downtrend followed
by your pattern formation.
Again, this could have been any pattern from
this list, but in this case, you had
a channel pattern form.
Once price breaks above and in the opposite
direction of the larger downtrend, this signals a
trend reversal upwards and presents long trade opportunities.
From a price action standpoint, chart patterns represent
indecision and infighting between buyers and sellers.
And the side that wins is the side
that the pattern breaks on.
So moving on, looking at where price is
coming from.
So you notice this long with candle at
the key resistance level, and you think yourself,
this is a great short trade setup.
But now if you had looked to the
left and to where price is coming from,
you would think otherwise.
You had a clear recent long trade set
up here through the long with candle at
a very key support level, creating heavy bullish
upwards momentum.
So if you entered this short trade here,
you were going against where true momentum is
headed, which is upwards.
This is why all you got was a
slight bounce downwards before price continued in the
true market direction, which is bullish and upwards.
Let's show this again.
You notice this long with candle at the
key support level, and you think to yourself,
this is a great long trade setup.
But now if you had looked to the
left and to where price is coming from,
you would think otherwise, you had a clear
short trade setup here and a lower high
that formed creating bearish downwards momentum.
So if you entered on this long trade
setup here, you were going against where true
momentum is headed, which is downwards.
Now moving on stacking high quality trades.
Now, before we continue, we need to hear
from you.
What kind of videos do you want us
to make next?
Let us know in the comments below right
now, as always, please hit the like button
as it goes a long way in supporting
our team.
So the best trade setups are the ones
where you have a lot of high quality
traits baked into them.
The higher the trade quality, the higher the
probability of the trade going in your favor,
but more importantly, moving a greater distance so
that you can make a good return on
the trade.
This here is where the high quality short
trade setup occurred.
So let's break down the high quality traits
that this trade had going for it.
First, you have a clear moving downtrend through
the lower highs and lower lows.
So you would be trading with the downtrend.
This is a positive factor.
Second, you had a descending triangle pattern followed
by a break below seemingly a trend reversal
from an uptrend to a downtrend.
Third, you're at a key level with multiple
recent reactions.
Another great factor.
Fourth, you're at a trend line with multiple
recent reactions.
Another great factor.
Fifth, you had shrinking candles as price approached
the level showing momentum loss.
Another great factor.
Sixth, you had a long candle form right
at the area of confluence showing prices reacting
to the area.
Seventh, you had a bearish momentum confirmation candle
right off of the level that is also
a candle color change.
Another great factor.
Look at this list of all the great
factors going in your favor for this short
trade setup.
This is a high quality A plus short
trade opportunity.
So let's show this again.
This here is where the high quality long
trade setup occurred.
Let's break down the high quality traits that
this trade setup had going for it.
First, you have a fresh trend change through
the break of the short-term trend line
and break of the longer term trend line.
This means the new uptrend has legs and
room to move further.
Second, you have a clear moving uptrend through
the higher highs and higher lows.
So you would be trading with the uptrend.
Third, you're at a key level with multiple
recent reactions.
Another great factor.
Fourth, you're at a trend line with multiple
recent reactions.
Another great factor.
Fifth, you had shrinking candles as price approached
the level showing momentum loss.
Another great factor.
Sixth, you had a long candle form right
at the area of confluence showing prices reacting
to the area.
Seventh, you had a bullish momentum confirmation candle
right off of the level that is also
a candle color change.
Again, look at this list of all the
great factors going in your favor for this
long trade setup.
This is a high quality, a plus long
trade opportunity.
So moving on.
A trigger event and continuation entry.
You first need to identify a trade setup
or what we call a trigger event to
give you a confirmed directional bias to trade
in and momentum for the trade.
This double bottom here and long with candle
at support followed by a bullish momentum candle
acts as your trigger event.
This long trade setup and trigger event gives
you an upwards directional bias and bullish momentum.
So you want to take long continuation trades
exclusively to ride the upwards bullish momentum.
Now to get into a long continuation trade
after the trigger event, you have two options.
Option one, look inside of the moving uptrend
for any continuation pattern to form.
Followed by a break in the momentum direction.
So in this case, when you look inside,
you had a falling wedge pattern followed by
a break above, which is then when you
would take a continuation trade long to ride
the upwards momentum option to look inside of
the moving uptrend for an intraday long trade
setup.
So once you look inside of the moving
trend, you had an intraday long trade set
up here where price pulled back to the
trend line and intraday support level, which is
then when you would take a long continuation
trade to ride the upwards momentum.
So moving on.
Timeframe Confluence.
Timeframe Confluence is having the three core timeframes
you trade on all with price action that
tells you to trade in the same direction,
which gives you super accurate trades.
The three core timeframes you choose to use
will be based on your speed of trade.
If you trade lower timeframes, then your three
timeframes will be adjusted for that, which we
cover with our members.
So the top left chart is the weekly
timeframe.
The top right chart is the daily timeframe
of the same asset.
And the bottom chart is the intraday timeframe
Starting with the weekly, you have a clear
moving downtrend to the lower highs and lower
lows.
So you want to trade with the downtrend
and you have a bearish bias.
This year is your short trade setup to
the long with Kendall at the key weekly
resistance level.
Now you look inside of the trade setup
area here on the daily timeframe on the
right to see if there is also bearish
price action, which you had through the double
top reversal pattern, giving you a bearish bias
again on the daily timeframe at this point,
the weekly timeframe and daily timeframe are both
bearish and conflict.
So when you look inside of the trade
setup area here, but on the lower intraday
timeframe below, you had a trend change pattern
through the neckline break and lower low that
formed, which again is bearish price action and
gives you another bearish bias, the weekly downtrend
daily double top reversal pattern and intraday trend
change pattern all give you bearish price section
and all tell you to take short trades,
meaning all three timeframes are confluent.
You would then go to the very low
timeframes and take a hyper accurate short entry
using our entry and exit strategy.
Now we applied the same method to a
great Tesla short trade.
This is the Tesla stock.
The top left is the Tesla weekly timeframe.
The top right is the Tesla daily timeframe.
And the bottom chart is the Tesla four
hour timeframe.
Starting with the weekly, you had a clear
moving downtrend through the lower highs and lower
lows.
So you want to trade with the downtrend
and you have a bearish bias.
This here is where the short trade setup
occurred through the long week candle at the
key weekly resistance level and trendline that crossed
giving you an area of confluence.
Now you look inside of the trade setup
area here, but on the daily timeframe on
the right to see if there is also
bearish price action, which you had through the
multiple long week candles reacting to the But
also the two recent reactions to the left
made this an imperfect triple top pattern.
At this point, the weekly timeframe and daily
timeframe are both bearish and confluent.
So when you look inside of the trade
setup area here, but on the four hour
timeframe below, you had a rising wedge pattern.
Once the pattern breaks below, this confirms the
reversal from an uptrend to a downtrend.
And again is bearish price action and gives
you another bearish bias.
The weekly downtrend daily triple top and multiple
long with candles and four hour reversal wedge
pattern and break all give you bearish price
action.
And I'll tell you to take short trades,
meaning all three timeframes are confluent.
You would then go to the very low
timeframes and take a hyper accurate short entry
using our entry and exit strategy.
So moving on trade
exits and stop loss management.
So you entered the short trade set up
here at key resistance and you target this
next support level here.
Price gets there and your position automatically closes
for a profit.
Great.
You then enter a long trade set up
again at key support, and your target is
this next key resistance level up here.
Price gets there and your position automatically closes
for a profit.
Awesome.
But now this is what occurs in the
best case scenario, but as a trader, you
should know that it doesn't always play out
as picture perfect as this.
Alternatively, these scenarios can occur instead after you
enter scenario.
Number one, you enter on this long trade
set up here and are targeting this next
key level.
But before price gets there, it reverses all
the way back down and you would end
up with a loss.
Without knowing how to manage a position correctly,
you would have taken a loss on this
trade instead of knowing where to lock in
profits.
Scenario number two, you enter on this long
trade set up here and are targeting this
next key level.
Price starts to pull back and you think
it will come all the way back down.
So you let your emotions take over and
you manually close out the position.
Then what happens?
Price takes off upwards, hits your target, and
even continues on further for a massive profit
you missed out on.
Again, not knowing how to properly manage a
trade means you're at a huge disadvantage and
leaving a lot of money on the table
scenario.
Number three, you enter on this long trade
set up here and price hits your profit
target, so you close out the position, but
closing it out was premature because price continued
on even further for even larger gains.
Again, you need to know what to do
to lock in gains, but also still be
able to take advantage if price continues on.
In all of these scenarios, where do you
initially place your stop loss?
Where do you move your stop loss if
there is a trend change before price reaches
your target?
To not only protect your position and lock
in gains, but also to not have it
hit by accident.
In case price swings before continuing on, how
do you know how to correctly manage your
position to maximize gains, to not miss those
big profitable trades, but also protect yourself from
losses?
We answer all these questions in depth on
our site at wisetrade.com.
Everything we've covered in this video is only
the foundational concepts, but we go in depth
into a lot of advanced strategies and methods
only available on our site at wisetrade.com.
So go check that out now as we
have some limited time special things available for
you.
As always, we want to hear from you.
What topics do you want us to cover
next?
Let us know exactly in the comments below
right now.
As always, please hit the like button, subscribe,
but most importantly, turn on the notifications bell.
And lastly, make sure to go subscribe to
our Instagram account at wisetrade.
So thanks for watching and I'll see you
in the next episode.
I'm right here.