What's up everyone?
Welcome back to this channel.
In this video I'm gonna change your life.
I'm gonna show you three strategies that are
freely available on TradingView which are way better
than what most people are doing in crypto.
Actually it's better than 95% of all
retail investors making more money and having less
drawdown, less risk.
I'm gonna show you exactly which strategies those
are, I'm gonna analyze them, I'm gonna show
you the trades they're doing and then you
can decide for yourself if those strategies made
better decisions than you or worse and also
let me know down in the comments.
And the best thing of all you could
actually if you choose to automate these strategies
there is another video that I have about
that.
So you can take any of these strategies
you can automate them to actually buy and
sell on your exchange.
That is not part of this video but
part of this video.
But if you know me I'm all about
automation that's why all the strategies that I'm
talking about are automatable because I think that's
the highest success rate that you will have
when you automate things.
Alright let's get started.
Eyes on the screen, coffee in your hand
so you have enough energy to watch the
whole video through.
I mean how would you miss a second
of it when it is about making more
money than before?
And as always don't like the video, don't
subscribe to the channel unless you hear something
interesting, you learn something new, I'm inspiring you
and then it makes sense and then click
the button.
Not now, later.
So watch the full video so you know
if it helped you or not.
Let's go.
As you know 95% of crypto investors
lose money and I think that is horrendous
and they could do much better than that.
Let's look at three strategies that I found
on TradingView.
They are fully free and how they perform
and if they perform better than what most
people are doing.
So keep in mind what you were doing
in the last bull and bear market and
compare to the outcome of these strategies.
If these strategies are better then you have
to ask yourself what are you doing?
Alright let's get into it.
In the background I have a strategy called
the Supertrend strategy.
Now how do I get there?
I go to TradingView, I click on indicators
and here I search for strategy and then
I scroll down a bit and I find
the Supertrend strategy.
You click on it and when you click
on it it will be added to your
strategies and immediately it will pop up like
this.
You might see it actually in this particular
way where you have all the text on
the chart.
You can turn this off by unchecking signal
labels and quantity, click OK and now the
chart looks much cleaner.
Now let's look at the performance of this
strategy.
It made 6,266% profit since the
beginning of Bitcoin.
This strategy is now applied on the chart
since the beginning and it had a drawdown
of only 15% which is quite good
actually if you think about how volatile the
asset is and also was.
That means if you put money into the
strategy and let it play out you would
have lost maximum 15% on a particular
trade.
Alright and then we also have this number
which is quite important.
How often did the strategy win when it
invested?
It won 47.9% of the time.
When it lost it lost a little amount.
When it won it won a higher amount
of course otherwise it wouldn't be profitable.
But let's zoom in into the last bull
market and check what the strategy did.
When did it buy?
When did it sell?
And you should always compare with what you
did.
Is it better or worse than what you
did?
Let's go.
First of all I'm closing the strategy tester
to get rid of it and then let's
check out when it invested before the bull
run started.
Trading view shows buys and sells with arrows
so the blue one is buy and the
red one is sell of course.
So here you can see it bought in
at 11,500 and then it sold here
with 166% profit at 30,700.
That's not bad.
What did it do afterwards?
It waited it out and then bought and
sold here with no profit at all.
Bought and sold here lost 11% and
what happened afterwards?
Afterwards it protected people from losing money meaning
that it prevented a 44.6% drawdown.
That is nice.
People can do other things with the money
other than losing it here.
Then it invested back in here made another
27% then invested back in here made
another 15% and again protected people from
losing here 38% of their money but
still made a losing trade here 12%
and so on.
Now you can compare with what you did
in the last bull and bear market right?
Did you buy early enough or not?
If not then consider using a strategy like
this one it's free and if it is
better than you then use it right?
Makes sense.
Then when did you sell?
Did you forget to sell here before the
crash came or did you sell only later
on and lost like 50% 70%
of your money?
If that is the case then again this
strategy would be way better for you than
what you have done manually.
Now let's see what it does right now
in the current state of affairs.
We can see that it bought here on
the bottom at 27,900 made a profit
of 41% and currently it is invested
again and is in profit 14%.
Now did you miss this buy signal for
example here at 27.9?
Are you not invested in Bitcoin or did
you buy much later?
Again this strategy would be much better for
you.
So what I'm trying to explain here is
that you need a strategy but then which
strategy to use right?
Because usually good strategies cost money that is
correct but if you can find strategies that
are free which is why I'm making this
video and they are better than what most
people are doing especially than what you are
doing then why not use a strategy that
actually has a proper back test like this
one and you can actually see how it
performs right?
So it's more mathematics, it's more logic behind
it, it's more thinking behind it than emotionally
deciding every day what to do with your
investment right?
This is the first strategy I wanted to
show you and it's already much better than
what most people are doing out there with
their money.
But there's more let's go to the second
strategy.
Alright the second one is hull suit strategy
and again you can find it by going
to indicators and you type in hull suit
strategy you can copy that also from the
bottom of this video description and then you
click on the one from dash trader and
once you've done that the strategy will appear
on your screen on your chart and then
you can see the performance metrics in the
back test.
Now this strategy made more profit it is
at 9322% and that looks awesome on
paper but it also had a much higher
drawdown a max drawdown of 70% but
what does it mean that this drawdown is
so high?
Well it means that you have to emotionally
survive that one of your trades during the
time of trading might be minus 70%
not realized loss but in between the trades
so it might rebound it might go back
up it might make a profit it might
make a loss but in between it was
minus 70 and that's usually very hard for
people to sustain and that's why I'm showing
you this so you understand when you look
at such a strategy yes it makes more
money but also you have to mentally prepare
for the drawdown.
If you really want to know what the
largest losing trade was then simply click on
the performance summary and then scroll down and
at some point you find these two line
items here largest losing trade was 24.6
% and largest winning trade was 132%
on one trade that means that it didn't
lose 70% but the max drawdown is
an indicator that is important because it is
psychologically problematic if you have a trade that
is potentially 70% in minus because you
might sell manually instead of letting it play
out and rebound right so a strategy like
that it's quite risky and I would never
use such a strategy because it has a
higher drawdown than 50% and 50%
is also hardcore to sustain you can choose
if you can stomach 70% because you
trust the overall outcome well then perfect then
use it and then you can see here
that it had a 49% chance of
winning trades which is quite good as well
so as you can see on the chart
if we zoom in a little bit and
see how it performed in the last bull
market what did it do there you can
see it was buying here at ten thousand
seven hundred sixty six which is even earlier
than the other one and then it sold
here with the profit of 67% then
it went back in here made another profit
of 55% by the way in the
bull market almost any strategy makes money the
magic is to sell before it falls off
a cliff now let's see how it performed
in that case so as you can see
here it made another trade that was profitable
27% and then it started actually losing
a little bit of money 8% here
and then here like 0% basically 5
% and why is that because it started
to be a sideways market and let's see
so it protected from a downside of 40
% that's quite nice then it made some
well not so smart trades here losing 13
% not really necessary and then it made
another profit here that's nice 30% and
let's see what it did in the massive
bear market it sold here that's fine but
then it bought here lost bought here lost
lost yeah so it's a bit more risky
as you can see that's why the drawdown
is higher as well so yeah it protected
but it's not as easy to use I
think as the super trend strategy still better
than what most people did because most people
actually lost money even this strategy if it
buys and sells and loses a little bit
it made a lot of profit beforehand to
compensate for a few losses let's see how
it's performing right now on the current price
and the current market we can see here
that it bought in at 28,000 that's
good and then it sold over here with
48% profit that is nice then somehow
it made a loss here 3% not
really necessary and now it's in the trade
and it's also in profit so right now
it seems to actually capture the current trend
would I use the strategy myself no because
it has a high drawdown and it also
seems to be trading way too often for
my taste I rather trade less often but
then be right more often but my argument
is that most people maybe including you would
be better off using a strategy like that
compared to trading with emotions and listening to
social media people giving you buy and sell
signals which you cannot back test as efficiently
as you can a strategy like this where
you see the numbers in front of you
and you can decide which strategy to use
based on actual proof and mathematics and not
based on emotions but there's more let's go
to the third strategy okay this strategy is
quite funny actually because it's called moon phases
now what do you think that is well
you look at the moon and depending on
how the moon is you buy Bitcoin and
you sell Bitcoin yeah somebody developed that crazy
strategy funny enough it is in profit 651
% over the whole time frame of Bitcoin
that is not a great performance but still
and 81% max drawdown horrible but funny
enough 60% of the time it is
correct buying and selling in a profit if
we zoom out here we can see that
it traded from December 2014 and then until
December 2021 and then since then somehow it
didn't trade maybe because the data was not
updated about the moon phases because the strategy
needs to have some input from somewhere about
the moon phases otherwise it can't trade so
I don't know let's give it the benefit
of the doubt and say that it would
have continued the same way as it has
in the past of course you should not
use the strategy but I wanted to show
you that there are crazy strategies like this
which are in profit while most people are
losing money even moon phases are better than
what most people are doing okay but seriously
let's go to the actual third strategy I
want to show you the third strategy is
quite crazy as you can see there is
a lot happening in the background but why
I'm choosing this one is because it's not
trading that much and I really enjoy that
so let's go very quickly through the numbers
you already know how to look at them
and by the way this is the name
of the strategy yes it's crazy I will
not speak it out loud but you will
find it down below so you can copy
paste it and then you pick the one
from Duke of Dolman click on it so
three thousand three hundred sixty percent net profit
since the beginning of Bitcoin with the max
drawdown below fifty percent so that's forty four
forty five percent it wins forty eight percent
of the time and it doesn't trade that
often what I mean by that when you
zoom in here and you try to ignore
all the lines instead you are looking only
at the buy and sell arrows you can
see that it was buying here and then
selling here so that's nice just one trade
keep it simple right it made three hundred
sixty six percent profit and then it protected
from the downside nicely forty four percent downside
protection and then only bought back in here
and then sold here with basically five percent
profit that's fine and then it made a
loss here this was 14% loss but
then it actually protected from the downside again
quite nicely made another loss here but then
again it protected from the downside massively because
it sold here at forty thousand and then
didn't buy back in for a long time
which is good because the price crashed down
minus sixty percent and that capital was protected
and then it went back in here in
January 2023 started to make some profit 28
% and so on and so on and
now let's look at the current state of
affairs in the current market conditions is doing
quite well it was buying here at twenty
seven thousand five hundred and then selling here
at forty two thousand five hundred making a
profit of fifty four percent that's quite nice
and currently it is in a trade as
you can see here I think it bought
in a bit late but still it's in
profit and let's see what's gonna happen here
overall this is a decent strategy it made
good profit and also it is below fifty
percent drawdown which I like it doesn't trade
too much so this could be a strategy
that I use but do I use such
a strategy do I use any of these
strategies that I showed you in this video
but before I talk about what I do
I want to add some more value to
you I have a video showing you how
to automate buying and selling from all of
these strategies actually any strategy from trading view
you can automate buying and selling on your
exchange you can get the signals you can
send them to your exchange and they will
actually buy and sell okay if you want
to do that because you want to have
an hands-off approach and you want to
eliminate emotions by just letting it happen right
automatically then check out the video it's quite
nice it might actually change the way that
you invest okay let's go back to what
we wanted to talk about which is what
I'm doing am I using any of these
strategies am I doing other things what am
I doing well I'm an engineer and that's
why I like automation and I spend quite
a lot of time thinking about my own
strategies so I created my own okay I
can show you one of those strategies here
in the back you do not have access
to this because this is VIP only don't
worry about it so do not search for
it in trading view but I want to
show you the comparison between the free strategies
which are still better than what most people
are doing and professional strategies for example like
this one same chart Bitcoin it made a
net profit of seven hundred twenty three thousand
percent with a max drawdown of 17 let's
say 18% rounding up also it didn't
trade a lot and it won 63%
of the time you have seen the other
strategies now you can compare the numbers so
now you know what I'm talking about my
point still stands any of the other three
strategies I showed you are better than what
most people are doing better than maybe what
you are doing and I'm here to help
that's why I'm sharing with you all of
this information what I think is the best
is to automate the strategy okay because otherwise
it's quite hard to stick to it there
is a lot of emotion involved right there
is a good signal but then you hesitate
right or it's weekend or you're on vacation
or whatever right that's why I really like
automation this is why I'm telling you watch
the video I mentioned before because it shows
you how to automate strategies even if you
choose one of those I showed you before
they're good enough for starting with automation and
once you have your feet wet you can
go further and further and improve your performance
and reduce your drawdown also you can talk
to me as well if you like you
have a link down below you can book
a call we can talk automation makes sense
and it's very easy to set up and
this is what I'm all about so finding
a good strategy automating the strategy and then
sticking to the strategy this is the winning
recipe alright I hope I inspired you to
check this out even further all the links
that you need are down below and while
you are down below there you can also
click the like button and also the subscribe
button and while you're there you can also
click the bell why because I'm here to
make you money literally I'm showing you how
to find strategies automate strategies which strategies are
good and I'm even sharing with you the
signals from my own strategies actually just for
Bitcoin but still so join my telegram group
where you can get all the Bitcoin signals
there for free and now we have deserved
a coffee so get yours and I see
you in the next video Cheers