In today's video, I'm going to share with
you eight dividend stocks that pay me $660
per month.
Now, a year ago, I made this exact
same video, but my monthly dividends at the
time were around $508 per month.
So a lot of changes have happened, and
I wanted to share those changes with you
today, as well as go over the eight
stocks.
The dividend stocks in my portfolio are what
I like to call sleep well at night
stocks, or SWAN stocks for short.
Essentially, they are good, stable companies with a
history of paying dividends.
And while I sleep, I generate passive returns,
which is the best feeling that you can
get.
And stock number one today is Procter &
Gamble, or P&G for short.
P&G is one of the biggest American
consumer good companies out there.
And at the time of this recording, they
pay a 2.52% dividend yield.
And that means for every share of Procter
& Gamble that you own, you'll get roughly
$3.76 per year.
2.52% doesn't sound like a high
yield, but the benchmark S&P 500 actually
has a dividend yield of 1.58%. So
it's much higher than the out there.
What you'll actually find is that most safe
dividend paying stocks pay between a 2%
to 4% yield.
And sometimes a higher yield is not necessarily
better, which we'll talk about later in this
video.
Since last year, P&G was a dividend
stock that I've added recently to my portfolio.
And I did that for a multitude of
reasons.
The first reason being that it's a dividend
king with 67 consecutive years of increasing their
dividend.
Second, I think that retailers like Target and
Walmart this year are going to get squeezed,
especially with the high cost of living and
high inflation these days, as well as student
loan repayments starting back up again.
I think the average consumer is going to
be really squeezed when it comes to buying
retail goods.
Procter & Gamble, however, they sell staple goods.
So these are goods that are going to
be needed no matter the economic environment.
So if we actually take a look at
a list of their current brands, they are
brands like Bounty, Charmin paper towels, Head &
Shoulders shampoo, Dawn for dish soap, and the
list goes on.
Lastly, they are diversified globally as well as
in terms of their selection and product mix.
So they actually offer five different segments of
different types of products, including beauty, grooming, healthcare,
family, and baby care, as well as fabric
and home care, which means that investing in
P&G is like investing in an index
fund just for consumer staple type of goods.
Now, Procter & Gamble is a huge brand.
Yes, but an even bigger brand out there
is JPMorgan Chase.
This is the second stock on today's list.
And basically, I've held this stock since last
year's video when it was trading for about
$110 per share.
That means year to date, it's up around
30 to 40%, which is absolutely crazy.
Now, while we can't count on that appreciation
every single year, what we can count on
is their dividend.
And right now is paying a 2.89
% dividend yield, which gets you about $4
.20 per share of every share that you
own of JPMorgan Chase.
The main reason I like JPMorgan Chase is
that they are the largest bank in the
United States, as well as they have $495
billion in cash and cash equivalents on their
balance sheet, which means that they are going
to provide a huge sense of security for
any of their shareholders.
This year, the higher interest rate environment, it
hasn't been that great for many companies, but
in terms of JPMorgan Chase, it's actually benefited
them a little bit because they can make
some money on the interest rates that the
Federal Reserve sets.
Their net interest income this year has been
growing every single quarter, and I don't really
see that slowing down anytime soon because the
Fed has signaled that they're going to hold
rates steady at least until the end of
2024, if not early 2025.
With some of the collapses of the smaller
banks this year, like Silicon Valley Bank, it's
really good to have a bank like JPMorgan,
which has strong fundamentals, and that's not going
to go anywhere.
This is one of my favorite dividend stocks,
and it's one of the biggest contributors to
the $660 a month that I generate passively.
Now, before we get into stock number three,
I wanted to share with you guys that
Webull is giving away between six to 12
free stocks whenever you sign up and make
any deposit.
I know that sounds crazy, six to 12
free stocks, that's a lot of stocks, but
yes, it's true.
Webull is an investing app where you can
buy and sell stocks on, and it's also
a registered broker dealer, and I personally use
it to check in on some of my
dividend stocks.
As long as the link is down below
in my description, the promotion will be active.
I'm not sure how long it's going to
be active for, so make sure to get
it while you can, and I think it's
one of the best promotions out there on
the market right now.
Stock number three is Home Depot.
It's actually one of my favorite places to
go, especially if you need a fiddle leaf
fig plant.
They actually have them pretty cheap there, and
I just got one recently, but they also
pay a $8.36 dividend per share for
every share that you own every single year,
which is 2.75% of a dividend
yield.
Home Depot is the largest home improvement retailer
in the United States with over 2,000
stores in just America alone, with over $154
billion in revenue in the last 12 months.
If we look at their revenue breakdown from
this popular website, 4 Week MBA, we can
actually see that their revenue stream is quite
diversified across the different types of products pretty
evenly.
Funny enough, the indoor garden section is actually
the largest revenue driver for Home Depot, so
shout out to those fiddle leaf figs.
I contributed to that.
The other great thing about Home Depot's revenue
breakdown is that half of that revenue comes
from professional contractors versus the other half comes
from do-it-yourself customers, so that means
even if one segment is lagging behind, the
other segment can bolster Home Depot's sales up.
With a gross margin of 33% as
well as strong cash flows, it's one of
these companies that is going to be really
stable and one of those companies that I
like to call a swan, so you can
sleep well at night knowing that you own
it.
Its counterpart is Lowe's, and that's also another
great company to own as well.
It's also a home improvement retailer, and both
of these companies have actually outperformed the S
&P 500 over the last decade.
When it comes to Home Depot and Lowe's,
there's not many other big box home improvement
retailers in the United States, so what I
like to think of is that these two
combined have a really strong economic moat, something
like Google does.
Google owns the search market, so whenever you
make a search online, you're usually using Google,
which means that it has a strong economic
moat, and I kind of see the going
on with Home Depot.
Now, another company with a strong economic moat
out there is actually Coca-Cola.
We all love and know Coca-Cola because
of their premium drinks, but did you know
that they also own other brands like Vitamin
Water, Powerade, Fairlife, Smartwater, and Topo Chico?
They currently have a dividend yield of 3
.26%, so that means for every single share
of Coca-Cola that you own, you'll get
about $1.84 per year.
Coca-Cola's main advantages are the fact that
they have really strong branding, a consistent business,
profit margins of over 17%, as well as
the fact that they have a ton of
pricing power over consumers.
In an inflationary environment like the one that
we are in now, it costs more to
produce things, so if Coke wanted to raise
the prices of their goods, they could increase
them without having their demand suffer too much.
I also own Pepsi in my portfolio, and
I think both of these companies are really
good to have in your portfolio because they
sell goods that are always going to be
needed no matter the economic conditions.
They kind of operate like a consumer staples
company, like Procter & Gamble, like we talked
about earlier.
Now, you'll notice that a lot of the
stocks today have a lower dividend yield, somewhere
between 2% and 4%, like I said
earlier.
Stocks that tend to pay a high dividend,
let's say 10% or more, that's something
that should be raising alarm bells in your
head because if they're paying that much of
a dividend out to their shareholders, it means
that they don't have enough money to reinvest
in the business, and therefore their growth might
be stunted.
I'm not saying that all high yielders are
bad stocks, but if you ever see a
yield of 5, 6, 7, or even 10%,
that's something you want to be aware of,
and maybe do some research and be a
little more cautious before you invest.
A company that is the polar opposite of
this with extremely low dividend yields is a
company like Apple.
Apple's been in my portfolio since day one,
and while they do have a really low
dividend yield of 0.55%, what I find
is that as I continue to add to
my Apple position, because I like to do
that every time I get paid, I notice
that the dividends are starting to add up.
Right now, they pay around $0.96 per
share of every Apple that you own every
single year, and I almost didn't include it
in today's list because it's not like a
true dividend stock, but what I've noticed is
that it is one of the biggest contributors
to my $660 per month.
I typically own it for capital appreciation reasons,
but the fact that it pays a dividend
is just like a really nice little bonus.
With Apple, you can probably expect them to
be within the top five companies in the
world for the foreseeable future, even up to
20 or 30 years from now, and with
their product offerings like the Apple Vision Pro
that's going to be coming out, as well
as the Apple Watch Ultra 2, they are
trying to diversify their revenue mix.
Surprisingly also, a large portion of Apple's revenue,
up to 25% right now, is coming
from things like services.
It's been growing every single quarter, and services
include things like music, movies, TV, the iTunes
Store, App Store, etc.
Alright, another dividend company that's been in my
portfolio for quite a while is AbbVie.
AbbVie is a biopharmaceutical company with a portfolio
of drugs in different types of departments, like
oncology, immunology, as well as neuroscience.
The stock currently pays a 3.85%
dividend yield at the time of this recording,
which is around $5.92 per share of
every single AbbVie that you own.
The biggest news from last year is that
they actually lost their exclusive patent right to
Humira because it expired, and so basically that
was their best-selling drug at the time,
but they still have a lot of robust
other drugs in the pipeline to offer to
the market.
Financially, AbbVie has actually been handling this quite
well, much better than expected, because some of
their other drugs like Skyrizzy and Rinvoke are
actually having their sales up almost 50%
this year.
A lot of analysts expected Humira to be
a really big blow to the company's financials,
but even the loss of that patent hasn't
eroded the sales of AbbVie that much this
year.
I have this in my portfolio because it
offers me some diversification from my other holdings,
so right now it's the only pharmaceutical company
that I own, and while it has been
trading flat this year, I remain a little
bit cautiously optimistic because if we actually look
back a full year, it's up around 9%.
They still do generate a ton of cash
flow and have actually increased their revenues, so
$24 billion in operating cash flow compared to
$22.9 billion last year, but they do
face many challenges that we've talked about.
So out of all the stocks listed today,
I'm probably most cautious on this one.
I'm gonna see how things play out in
the next few quarters to decide if I
want to continue to hold it or not.
Alright, the next stock is a stock that
needs no introduction.
It is called Kraft Heinz.
You probably have heard of it.
They make ketchup, A1 steak sauce, mustard, and
even Kool-Aid.
They currently pay a dividend yield of around
4.64%, which equates to around $1.60
per share annually.
With net sales last year of $26.45
billion, it's no wonder that Warren Buffett still
owns his original position of Kraft Heinz.
In early 2019, he actually even told CNBC
that he'd be happy to own the stock
even 10 years from now.
So Kraft Heinz is another one of those
companies that, in my opinion, they offer consumer
staples.
I mean, seriously, I think it's a staple.
If you saw how much ketchup I put
on my fries as well as my burger,
you would definitely think it's a consumer staple.
Food-related goods will always be in demand
because people have to eat, and even condiments
are going to be in demand no matter
the economic conditions out there.
This is probably one of the weaker dividend
companies in my portfolio in terms of growth,
so Kraft Heinz, while they are profitable, their
profits don't usually translate to huge capital appreciation,
which some investors are looking for.
I'm not worried about their dividend, but if
you are looking for a stock with more
potential upside, then perhaps you want to stick
to some of the other stocks on today's
list.
For now, I'm holding Kraft Heinz as my
smallest position in my portfolio, and if things
don't really look up in the next few
quarters, I might actually sell them off.
All right, I actually do have a bonus
stock for you guys today, and that's going
to be stock seven and a half, and
that is ticker symbol VOO, which is the
S&P 500 ETF by Vanguard.
This fund buys a small percentage of every
single stock that is in the S&P
500, and they actually do pay a dividend
yield of around 1.5 to 1.6%.
For every share of VOO that you own,
you'll actually get $6.30 per share, which
is pretty good for owning a well-diversified
ETF.
Every time I get paid, I put a
little bit of that paycheck into VOO as
well, and so it's just a little bit
of a bonus for owning that ETF in
terms of index fund or ETF investing.
So even if you don't go for individual
stocks in your portfolio, you can still get
a dividend yield from an ETF like VOO,
or Charles Schwab even has one that's called
SCHD.
It's their US Dividend Equity ETF, and it's
actually one of the most popular dividend ETFs
out there.
Okay, so our final stock for today is
Johnson & Johnson.
This is another favorite of Warren Buffett's.
It currently has a 3% dividend yield,
which is $4.76 for every share that
you own.
Again, this is one of those companies where
you will sleep well at night.
They offer staples that they sell, so Tylenol,
Band-Aid, Listerine, and even Aveeno lotion.
You probably see a theme in today's videos.
I like companies that are stable.
They offer a product selection that is really
good during economic uncertainty so that I don't
really have to worry about them.
J&J has also increased their dividends for
61 consecutive years, which means that they are
also known as a dividend king.
Its value stock has a strong cash position,
and it's one of these companies that's going
to do well even in the worst of
recessions, so I have no problem owning this
for the long term.
All right, so how much money do you
need to make $660 per month in dividends?
Well, I want to tell you guys it
is quite a lot.
If you take the average dividend yield of
4%, you would actually need around $200,000
invested at a 4% dividend yield to
get yourself around $8,000 per year, which
is around $666 per month.
Now, if this is discouraging to you, don't
let it be discouraging because I've personally been
investing in this portfolio for over 12 years
now, and every time I get paid, I
consistently invest into it.
The harsh truth is that it does take
some time to build up to, but as
you build up and you start to see
those dividends accumulate, it is one of the
best feelings that you can get.
I hope you enjoyed this video.
Make sure to grab those 6 to 12
free stocks with the link down below.
As long as it's there, it's going to
be active, and make sure to check out
my next video on dividends, which I'll put
right here or right here.
All right, so I will probably see you
in the next video.
Thank you for watching.
Have a great day.