Hello, and welcome to this free CodeCamp course
on algorithmic trading in Python.
My name is Nick McCollum.
I'm going to be your instructor for this
course.
And in this course, we're going to focus
on building three large quantitative finance projects.
In the first project, we are going to
build an equal weight version of the popular
S&P 500 index fund.
In the second project, we are going to
build a quantitative momentum strategy that selects the
best stocks based on a variety of momentum
investing metrics.
And in the third project, we're going to
build a quantitative value screener that selects stocks
that are attractive based on a number of
value metrics.
So that's a quick summary of the three
projects that we are going to build in
this course.
Before we move into learning more about the
course and those projects, I have a couple
of housekeeping items that I have to go
over first.
To start, this free CodeCamp course on algorithmic
trading in Python is made possible through a
grant from IEX Cloud.
If you've ever read the book Flash Boys
by Michael Lewis, you may have heard of
IEX.
In this course, we're going to be using
some of their tools and APIs to populate
some of the data that we will need
for these algorithmic trading strategies.
The other quick thing that you're going to
notice starting now is a little message at
the bottom of the screen that's going to
stay there for the rest of the video.
And what that message intends to represent is
that this course is for educational purposes only.
I'm going to be providing some high level
finance concepts, but nothing in this course or
in this video should be construed as investment
advice.
So just to reiterate, this course is for
educational purposes only, and none of this should
be considered investment advice.
So with all of that out of the
way, let's dig into a little bit more
about what this course is going to teach
you.
So let's start by just going over a
quick course overview.
The first thing that we're going to discuss
is some basics of the field of algorithmic
trading.
Then we're going to discuss some API basics
and kind of just quickly go over how
the course is configured and laid out.
The next thing we're going to discuss is
the first project of this course, which is
an equal weight version of the popular S
&P 500 index fund.
And then we're going to talk about our
second project, which, as I mentioned earlier, is
a quantitative momentum strategy.
And then we're going to discuss briefly our
third project, which is a quantitative value strategy.
So that's kind of a 30,000 foot
view of what you're going to be learning
in this course.
Let's zoom in a little bit and talk
about some algorithmic trading basics.
So for anyone who's completely unfamiliar with algorithmic
trading, it basically means using computers to make
investment decisions.
So in the past where you may have
had a team of financial analysts or investment
researchers to kind of consider stocks and decide
what to buy, many of the popular investing
strategies that are implemented today actually use more
computers than they do humans.
So algorithmic trading just means using computers to
make investment decisions.
Now, there are many different types of algorithmic
trading.
On the one hand, you have, you know,
your super high frequency trading, big brain, really,
really sophisticated and complex strategies.
And then at the other end of the
spectrum, you can kind of basically map any
type of fundamental strategy that humans have implemented
in the past and just make it a
little more efficient by providing some computer software
in there.
So as, you know, this slide kind of
alludes to the main difference between the many
different types of algorithmic trading is generally the
speed at which those trades are executed.
Now, before we actually dig into more about
the world of algorithmic trading, it's kind of
helpful to have a high level understanding of
who the main players are in this space.
And one of the reasons I wanted to
kind of provide this information at the start
of this course is so that you can
see that the feel of algorithmic trading is
very big.
And if you do want to make a
career of it, there are lots of employers,
lots of opportunities and lots of jobs in
this space.
So right now, I'm just going to briefly
discuss a few of the largest players in
the algorithmic trading landscape.
The first one, which is kind of the
50,000 pound gorilla in the room is
Renaissance Technologies.
I believe they're based in Long Island and
they have 165 billion dollars in assets under
management.
Now, Renaissance Technologies is mostly famous for their
Medallion Fund, which is only open to employees
at this point, which I think has returned
something insane, like 50% a year for
20 years or something like that.
Now, none of us can access that fund
because it's for employees only.
But Renaissance Technologies probably has one of the
best performing investment funds in the history of
finance.
And perhaps most interestingly is that Renaissance Technologies
was not founded by a finance major or
a investment analyst to start.
The person who actually started Renaissance Technologies was
a math PhD from, I believe, a California
university.
His name's Jim Simons and many people would
kind of consider him to be one of
the forefathers of quantitative finance.
So that's kind of the largest player in
this space.
Another popular one is AQR Capital Management, which
was founded by Cliff Assis and a few
other managing partners.
And they have 61 billion dollars in assets
under management.
Now, unlike Renaissance Technologies, AQR Capital Management actually
has strategies that you and I can invest
in through mutual funds and other types of
strategies.
And one last interesting thing about that firm
is that their name is kind of the
IBM of investment firms, where IBM is International
Business Machines, a very bland name, AQR Capital
Management.
The AQR component of that name actually stands
for Applied Quantitative Research.
So if you're ever curious what that stands
for, that's what it is.
The last one is Citadel Securities, which has
32 billion dollars in assets under management, and
they're a much more high frequency trading firm
than the first two that I mentioned, kind
of famous for their role in the market
making space.
So they are founded by Ken Griffin, and
that kind of summarizes three of the large
players.
You can tell by just the assets under
management of these three firms alone, more than
200 billion, that there are lots of opportunities
and jobs, and this is a very large
space.
So definitely something worth learning a bit about.
Now, in this course, as you probably can
tell by the title, we are going to
be using Python for these algorithmic trading strategies.
Now, before we dig into actually how to
use Python and how to write the code
for it, there's a few high level things
you should understand.
The first one is that Python is probably
the most popular programming language for algorithmic trading,
and the reason why is just because it
has a lot of libraries.
But the downside to using Python is that
it's a fairly slow programming language.
So if you want to execute high performance
code, Python is typically not your best bet.
Now, the solution that many practitioners have found
for this is that Python is often used
as a glue language to trigger code that
actually runs in other languages.
A common example of this is the NumPy
library for Python, and that's actually a library
that we'll be using in this course.
Now, NumPy is the most popular Python library
for performing numerical computing, and it's perhaps most
popular for its data structure called the NumPy
array, which easily allows you to store and
manipulate one or two dimensional data structures in
Python.
Now, although NumPy is actually a Python library,
and it is called and manipulated using the
Python programming language, the core underlying functionality is
written in C, which is a much faster
language and provides lots of performance enhancements to
Python users who use the NumPy library in
their code.
So just to quickly summarize, the main idea
of this section is that Python is the
most popular programming language for quantitative finance, but
it's also a slow language.
So a lot of times you will use
Python to trigger functionality that actually runs in
other programming languages that are faster.
So now let's quickly talk about the algorithmic
training process can kind of be broken down
into the following steps.
The first step is to collect data.
The second step is to develop a hypothesis
for a strategy.
The third step is to back test that
strategy.
Now, back testing just means formulating your strategy
and then seeing how it would have performed
historically over time.
And generally, there's kind of two ways you
want to do that.
You want to take the strategy back as
far back in time as you can, and
across as many markets as you can.
So to provide a quick example, let's say
that you have a hypothesis that the largest
firms outperform, you would probably want to test
that here in the United States and go
back as far back in time as you
can.
And then you would also want to test
the performance of the largest firms in Canada,
Europe, Japan, China, India, all the other international
markets as well.
And if that strategy performs well in all
of those markets, then you can be sure
that you're probably onto something.
Now, the fourth strategy would be to implement
that or sorry, the fourth step rather would
be to implement that strategy in production.
So you've collected data, you develop a hypothesis,
you back tested the strategy, and now you're
going to start actually trading that strategy with
real money in real accounts, moving forward and
seeing how it does with real money in
the strategy.
Now that you have a high level understanding
of the algorithmic trading process, there's a few
ways that this course will be different from
a real algorithmic trading strategy.
And I just want to highlight those quickly
right now before we dive into some information
about the three projects we'll be building.
Now, just to quickly summarize, there's three major
ways that this course will be different.
The first is that we'll be using random
data.
The data provider that we're using for this
course, which is IES Cloud, is a paid
API.
So if you want to use real data,
you can follow the steps in this course,
but actually pay for an account and use
a real API token.
What we'll be using instead is we will
be using a sandbox API token, which provides
random data, but it's also free.
So what that means is you can, you
can do all the normal things that you
can with the IES Cloud API, but the
data will be randomly generated.
So you may see some interesting results because
of that.
The second thing that is different is that
we will not actually be executing trades in
this course.
Now, the reason why that is, is because
many of the people who take this course
will be using different custodians to execute their
trades.
And each one of those custodians will have
a different API infrastructure.
So I wanted to make this course as
widely applicable as possible.
So what we're going to be doing instead
is we're going to be imagining that we
work at a firm where our traders expect
us to generate a sell documents and send
them to them to execute trades.
So the output of each of these three
strategies will be an Excel document that has
the name of each companies that need to
be purchased and the number of shares of
each one of those companies that the trader
needs to purchase.
So we won't be executing trades, but instead
we will be generating order sheets to send
to our imaginary traders further down the line.
And just to reiterate that second point, we're
going to be saving these recommended trades to
Excel files, which could then be sent to
the traders afterwards.
All right.
So now that we have a bit of
a high level understanding of the algorithmic trading
landscape, it's time to talk about API basics
and course configuration.
So to start, let's discuss what is an
API?
API is an application programming interface.
And you probably aren't familiar with that if
you've ever heard the term API before, but
that doesn't actually tell you what it does.
I think the easiest way to understand what
an API is, is it's a way for
your software to interact with and potentially control
someone else's software.
So in this case, we're going to be
using the IEX Cloud API.
And what we're going to do is use
their API to access their database of financial
data and import it into our Python script.
So like I say, APIs allow you to
interact with someone else's software using your own
code.
And in this course, we're going to be
using the IEX Cloud API to gather stock
market data to make investment decisions.
And to provide you a quick example of
what that looks like, here's a code snippet.
So this is a cell from a Jupyter
notebook that has four lines.
You can see on the first line that
we declare a symbol AAPL, and that is
the stock symbol for AAPL on the NASDAQ
exchange.
On the second line, we're creating a string
called API URL that has some interpolated values
that interpolate and the symbol and our IEX
Cloud API token.
And on the third line, we're using the
requests library of Python to provide a get
request to that API URL.
And then on the last time, we're just
printing the data that gets returned.
Now, this is kind of a lot.
And if you don't fully understand this, not
to worry, you'll see this in a lot
more detail when we actually build the projects
for this course.
So that's kind of what an API call
looks like.
And broadly speaking, in this course, we're only
going to be using get requests to gather
data from the IEX Cloud API.
Now, if you've never used an API before,
there's many different ways you can interact with
them, but there's four major ones.
And I'm going to show you briefly some
of the other ways to interact with an
API right now before we proceed through this
course.
So get requests allow you to get data
from the API, and that's what we'll be
using in this course.
An alternative is a post request, and that
is a method for adding data to the
database that's exposed by the API.
So a get request allows you to get
data from the API and a post request
allows you to push data to the API.
A put request allows you to add and
overwrite data in the database that's exposed by
the API.
Now you can think of a post request
as a create only request.
And you can think of a put request
as a create or replace request.
So there's a slight difference there.
And but even though it's a small difference,
it's an important difference because that's kind of
a common source of bugs for software developers.
And the fourth kind of important type of
API call is a delete, which as it
may implies, it deletes data from the API's
database.
So to provide a quick summary of this
section, we're going to be using exclusively get
requests in our course, but there's three other
main types of requests that you should understand
those are post, put and delete.
Now, like most software concepts, APIs are best
learned through rigorous practice.
Because of that, here is a URL that
you can use to get a long list
of public API's that are great practice for
you to interact with API's.
Now, I would probably recommend if you've never
used an API before to proceed through this
course, that will give you a base fundamental
understanding of how to work with API's.
And then once that course is done, you
can go to this public URL and practice
with some other API's that are of interest
to you personally.
So this is not something for you to
look at right now, but it's a good
resource for you to hit later on.
Alright, so now that you have a high
level understanding of the course configuration and some
API basics, let's move on to talking about
our equal weight S&P 500 fund.
So if you've never heard of it before,
the S&P 500 is the world's most
popular stock market index.
And many investment funds are benchmarked to the
S&P 500.
That means that they seek to replicate the
performance of this index by owning all of
the stocks that are held in the index.
Now, if you've never really researched how stocks
are added to the S&P 500, there's
a bit of a, there's a committee process
and some, some sophistication there.
But the easiest way to understand it is
that the S&P 500 broadly covers the
500 largest companies in the United States.
So if you own the S&P 500
index fund, you basically own the 500 largest
companies in the US.
Now, aside from the fact that it owns
the 500 largest companies, one of the other
most important characteristics of the S&P 500
is that it is market capitalization weighted.
Now, market capitalization is just a finance term
that means basically size.
So coming with a large market capitalization just
means that it's a large company.
And what this means is that larger companies
get a correspondingly larger weight in the S
&P 500 index.
For the first project of this course, we're
going to build an alternative version of the
S&P 500 index fund that provides that,
that assigns the same weight to each company
in the index.
So instead of Apple having a very big
way and Best Buy having a small way,
every company will have the same weight.
So that's going to be the first project
of this course.
In the second project, we are going to
build a quantitative momentum screener.
Now, momentum investing means investing in assets that
have increased in price the most.
To help you understand, let's kind of go
through a quick example.
Imagine that you have the choice between investing
in two stocks that have had the following
returns over the last year.
Apple has stock has gone up 35%
and Microsoft stock has gone up 20%.
A momentum investing strategy would suggest investing in
Apple because of its higher recent price return.
There are many other nuances to momentum strategies,
including the concept of high quality momentum.
And that basically means all else being equally
good we want a stock that has steadily
increasing price rather than no price change for
a while and then a large jump at
the end.
But we'll explore those when we actually build
our quantitative momentum strategy later in this course.
The third project we're going to build is
a quantitative value screener.
Now, value investing just means investing in stocks
that are trading below their perceived intrinsic value.
So if you kind of want to make
a very simple analogy, value investing is kind
of the idea of buying a dollar for
75 cents and hoping that you can sell
it again for a dollar later.
So value investing is a very popular investing
strategy because many of the world's best historical
investors like Warren Buffett, Seth Clareman, and Benjamin
Graham have employed this strategy.
Creating algorithmic trading investing strategies relies on a
concept called multiples.
And multiples are simply a way that investors
use to estimate how valuable a company is.
So to be more specific, multiples are calculated
by dividing a company's stock price by some
measures of the company's worth, like earnings or
assets.
So three examples of multiples that are used
in value investing are the price to earnings
ratio, the price to book ratio, and the
price to free cash flow ratio.
Now, as their name applies, the price to
earnings ratio is calculated by dividing a company's
stock price by its earnings per share.
The price to book value ratio is calculated
by dividing a company's stock price by its
book value per share.
And the price to free cash flow ratio
is calculated by dividing a company's stock price
by its free cash flow per share.
So lots of different ways you can calculate
multiples, but those are kind of a three,
three of the most important ones anyway.
Now, each of the individual multiples used by
value investors has its pro and cons.
One way to minimize the impact of any
specific multiple is by using what's called a
composite.
Now, a composite is just a average of
many different valuation strategies.
So in our strategy that we build in
this course, we're going to actually be using
a composite of five different value investing metrics.
Now, with all that out of the way,
you have a solid understanding of what we're
going to be doing in this course.
And it's time for us to dig into
the first project.
So without further ado, let's do just that.
All right.
So it's now time for us to start
tackling our first project.
If you skipped ahead to this section of
this course, there's a couple of things that
you should do before proceeding.
So the first is to rewind back to
the last section and install all of your
dependencies.
If you're a pretty experienced Python developer, the
main dependencies for this course are NumPy, Pandas,
and XLXX writer.
So if you already have those on your
machine, that's fine.
If you've already been following throughout this video
so far, I'm in our algorithmic trading Python
folder that we cloned to our local computer.
I have my virtual environment activated.
And what I'm going to do now is
launch the Jupyter notebook for our first project.
So to do that, the command is python
dash M and then notebook.
So this should open up a browser window.
And what we want to do is navigate
into the starter files folder of the algorithmic
trading repository and then open up the equal
weight SMP 500.iPyMb notebook.
It should look like this.
So basically, this is what we're going to
be working through in this video.
It has some instructions written in markdown and
some blank code cells.
And that's what we're going to complete as
we work through this section.
So let's start with just some background information.
What we're going to do in this project
is to build an equal weight version of
the SMP 500 index fund.
The SMP 500 is an equal weight or
not equal weight market weight market cap weighted
basket of the 500 largest companies in the
United States.
Interestingly enough, it actually has more than 500
stocks in it because five or so of
the largest companies in the U.S. actually
have multiple share classes.
So an example of that is Google.
It has a class A and a class
C share that trade on the stock exchange.
So since Alphabet, the company is included in
the SMP 500, both of its stocks are.
And because of that, there's usually around 505
stocks in the SMP 500, despite the index
only representing 500 companies.
So anyways, to move on, what we're going
to do now is create a different version
of the SMP 500 index fund that doesn't
weight the stocks in the index by market
capitalization, but instead equal weights them.
So what this means is that the larger
companies in the index will have less weight
than the traditional version.
And the smaller companies in the index will
have a larger weight than the traditional version.
So there's some background information here.
It just says that the largest fund that's
benchmarked to this index is the SPDR SMP
500 ETF trust.
That's commonly known as the ticker SPY SPY,
which is the ticker that it trades on
on the stock exchange.
And that ETF has more than $250 billion
of assets under management, which is pretty crazy.
Most asset management firms don't have that much
AUM.
So a really big fund, to be sure.
And it says here, the goal of this
section of the course is to create a
Python script that will accept the value of
your portfolio and tell you how many shares
of each SMP 500 constituent that you need
to purchase to get an equal weight version
of the index fund.
So the first thing we need to do
is, you know, like most Python scripts, this
project will rely on a number of open
source software libraries.
So we're going to import those first, we
install them to our local computer in the
dependency section of this course.
So now we just need to import them
and we're going to go through them one
by one here.
And I'll briefly explain what each of these
libraries does in case you haven't worked with
them in the past.
Alright, so the first library we're going to
import is NumPy.
And the command to do that is import
NumPy, NumPy as NP.
Now, NumPy is a numerical computing library and
it's known for its fast execution speed.
And the reason why NumPy is so fast
is because it's actually a C or maybe
C plus plus module.
So when you call a Python function in
NumPy, it actually executes the code in a
different programming language and that programming language is
kind of faster by design.
So NumPy is often used in finance and
other applications to speed up, you know, basic
functions like summing or multiplication because it has
modules written in a different programming language that
is naturally faster.
So that's NumPy.
We're also going to import pandas as PD
and pandas is a portmanteau for panel data
or panel data is, I guess, because it
has an S on it.
And what pandas does is it makes it
very easy to work with tabular data in
Python.
So tabular data is anything that has rows
and columns.
You can think of an Excel spreadsheet as
perhaps one of the most commonly known versions
of tabular data.
And pandas is most widely used for its
data structure called the pandas data frame and
a data frame is just a data structure
that holds tabular data.
So pandas allows you to store data in
a data frame and then use many different
built in pandas functions and methods to manipulate
the data within that data frame.
You'll see lots of examples about this as
you work through the rest of this course.
And if you're interested in learning more about
pandas, free code camp has an excellent YouTube
video on the topic that I would highly
recommend.
So that's pandas.
And then there's a couple of others we
need as well.
So actually, before we move on, one thing
that's worth talking about is these aliases.
So we didn't just import NumPy, we imported
NumPy as MP and we didn't just import
pandas, but we imported pandas as PD.
So why do we do that?
This just saves us a bit of typing
because we're going to be often calling functions
from these libraries.
So an example would be let's just run
this so those imports run and then create
a new code cell.
If we wanted to create a pandas data
frame that, you know, we'll just create an
empty one as for an example.
If we had just imported pandas without importing
it as PD, we would have to write
pandas.dataframe. And this calls the class that
instantiates a pandas data frame object.
Now, because we imported it under the alias
PD, we can just do PD.dataframe and
it's a little bit more readable and faster
to type.
So it's not necessary to import them under
aliases.
I know a few developers who just run
pandas.dataframe, but importing pandas under the alias
PD and NumPy under the alias NP is
pretty common and kind of widely considered to
be a best practice.
So that's what we're going to follow in
this course.
All right, let's move on to importing the
other libraries we need.
So the next one is requests.
And requests is a very popular Python library
that is kind of considered the gold standard
for making HTTP requests.
Now, an HTTP request is just basically an
internet request that you can send to an
API to get back some data.
And in this course, we're going to be
using the requests library to execute our API
calls to the IEX cloud API to, I
guess, receive our stock market data that we
need to calculate the weightings for our S
&P 500 index funds.
So the request library is for HTTP requests.
And that's basically all you need to know
about it for now.
And the next thing we need to import
is XLSX Writer.
This is a library that makes it very
easy to save well formatted documents, Excel documents
from a Python script.
So that's XLSX Writer.
And the last library we need is Math.
So Math is just a basic Python library
that provides many of the basic mathematical functions
that you need to, I guess, execute operations
within a Python script.
So all right.
So once you run that code, all of
your libraries will be imported.
And the next thing that we need to
do is to import our list of stocks.
Now, like I said, this is going to
be a list of about 500 stocks, maybe
a little more if there's any stocks that
are dual listed in the S&P 500.
And one thing to note about this project
is that since these constituents change over time,
in an ideal world, you would actually connect
right to an index provider or an API,
a financial data API or something like that,
so that if a stock is added or
removed from the S&P 500, then your
equal weight S&P 500 strategy would reflect
that.
Now, all of the tools that would provide
that information are paid.
And this is a free course.
So I didn't want to provide any paid
resources in the free course that kind of
defeats the point of it being free.
So what what I did instead was I
saved a list of the 500 stocks in
the S&P 500 into a CSV file.
And you can click this link here to
download that file.
So what we need to do is click
that it'll go into our downloads folder and
then we need to move that file into
our starter files, starter files, excuse me, we
need to move this file into our starter
files folder so that it can be accessed
by the other files in that directory.
So let's do that now.
And then once that's done, we can import
it into our Jupyter Notebook.
So open up your finder app or I
guess it would be finder app or Windows
Explorer or whatever app you have on your
operating system to explore files and navigate to
your downloads folder in one tab.
And then in your other tab, you're going
to want to navigate into that algorithm we're
trading in Python course.
So here it is.
And then specifically, you want to navigate into
the starter files folder and then drag this
S&P 500 stocks dot CSV into the
starter files folder like that.
Okay, so now that that's done, what we
need to do is save the S&P
500 stocks as a pandas data frame.
And the way to do that is we're
going to assign it to a pandas data
frame named stocks.
So stocks equals P dot read CSV, and
then the name of the file.
So if you just type in SP and
then tab, it might auto complete.
There it is.
And if it doesn't auto complete, just type
in the file name.
So what is this?
It is a, this is a method that
lives within the pandas library that takes in
data in the form of a CSV and
then stores it in the pandas data frame.
So you can verify that by just doing
type of stocks and this should return pandas
data frame.
Yep.
And then if you print it out, it'll
actually show the data.
So Jupyter notebooks have this kind of special
feature where if you type a variable on
the last line of a code seller, we'll
print it.
So this is what is contained in our,
in our pandas data frame.
Like I said, there's actually 505 stocks within
this data frame, which means that there's five
stocks that have dual share share structures in
the S&P 500 at this time.
So that's what we're going to be working
with throughout the rest of this tutorial.
The next thing we need to do is
acquire an API token.
Like I mentioned in the introduction to this
course, we're going to be using the IEX
cloud API to gather all of our financial
data.
And like most APIs, it requires some form
of authentication before you can pull data from
it.
So what we're actually going to be using
in this course is the sandbox mode of
the IEX cloud API.
And sandbox mode is a kind of like
a play mode where you can make sure
that all of your API calls work, but
it doesn't actually return real time financial data.
Instead, it returns randomized financial data.
And the reason why sandbox mode exists is
because it allows you to test whether or
not your API calls function properly before you
actually start to use the real API and
incur data usage as a result.
So the easiest way to handle this, in
my opinion, when building this course was to
create a secrets.py file.
And secrets.py files are files that are
stored in your repository or on the server
that's running this code that doesn't actually get
pushed to GitHub or any kind of remote
git store.
So the reason why is because most of
the information stored in a secrets.py file
is sensitive or confidential in some way.
And you just don't want that type of
information stored in a centralized git repository.
So you'll notice in the git ignore of
this course, the secrets.py file is actually
included in the git ignore, which means that
if you ever fork this repository to work
on it and then push your changes up
to GitHub, the information contained in the secrets
.py file doesn't actually get pushed up as
well.
So since it's actually a sandbox API key,
it doesn't really matter in this specific instance,
whether the secrets.py file is exposed.
But keep in mind for future Python courses
or anything else that you work on that,
you should never share your secrets.py file
with anyone.
But this course is kind of an exception
since we're working with a sandbox API key.
So to start, we're going to click here
and this will download a secrets.py file
to your downloads folder.
Now you may get a warning that says
something like this.
In my case, it says this type of
file can harm your computer.
Do you want to keep secrets.py anyway?
And we're going to keep it and then
move it into the same starter files folder
that we moved our CSV file of stocks
into.
So if you open back up your finder
app or whatever app that you have on
your operating system, you should have your two
tabs still open.
You can click and drag the secrets.py
file into the starter files folder.
And then we need to import our IEX
cloud API key into our script.
So what we're going to do for that
is we're going to say from secrets, import
IEX and then if you hit tab, it
should auto complete.
It says cannot import IEX cloud API token
from secrets.
I wonder what that is.
User download.
Okay, so this is equal is 100.
All right.
So sometimes what happens with these Jupyter notebooks
is that when you add a file to
the working directory that the Jupyter notebook is
open in, it actually doesn't recognize that it's
there until you reset the kernel.
So let's try that.
We're going to say, restart the kernel, and
then we're going to go back to the
top and run all of our code cells
from the start.
Awesome.
And this time it imported correctly.
So in a lot of cases, I might
run into little hiccups like that when working
through this code.
And in some courses, people edited out for
a more clean experience.
But I would say in the majority of
cases, I'm going to leave them in so
that you can see the debugging process and
what I actually do to fix the problems
that I encounter.
So that was a small example of that.
You'll see more as you work through this
course.
So now we're going to make our first
API call.
So making API calls is a bit of
an art because every API works a little
bit differently.
And some APIs have lackluster documentation.
In this case, the IEX cloud API has
excellent documentation.
And I'm going to kind of show you
a bit of the documentation as we work
through this section that creates our first API
call.
So in this specific case for the S
&P 500 index fund, there's two things we
need.
We need the market capitalization for each stock
and the price of each stock.
So to start, we're just going to do
an API call for one single stock.
And then to generalize that for our entire
universe of stocks, what we're going to do
is loop over every stock that's contained in
the pandas data frame that we created earlier
and then run that same API call it
for each one of those stocks using a
Python for loop.
So to start, let's just create symbol equals,
and we're going to make this a string
that is apples toxic, which is AAPL.
And then on the next line, we're going
to say, what is the API URL?
And that's a good question.
What API endpoint is that?
That's what we're going to find out next.
To do that, we're going to navigate over
to the IEX cloud documentations.
And the easiest way to find this is
just go to IES cloud docs on a
Google search.
And it's this first hit here that is
not an ad.
So click through to this.
And what this is, is basically a massive
single page resource for all the possible information
that you might need about the IEX cloud
API.
IEX cloud has remarkably good documentation.
There are other APIs out there that maybe
aren't as commercialized or are not as mature
that won't have documentation that that's this good.
So as you kind of look through this,
keep in mind that this is probably a
better than average documentation page for a public
API.
Now, the first thing we need is the
base URL for the API.
And what the base URL is, is it's
basically a URL that will start every HTTP
request.
And then after that base URL, you have
to add which specific endpoint that you want
to retrieve from the API.
The way most APIs work is they only
expose certain data through each endpoint, which makes
things faster if you only need to retrieve
certain data.
So one example might be, if you have
the Google Maps API, you might only want
the name of a location.
So you would send coordinates and get back
its name.
You wouldn't get back other information like population
or other sorts of things because you only
want name and sending only that limited information
is faster than sending information you wouldn't need.
So API endpoints are limited in that respect.
But to start, the first thing we need
is the base URL.
Now, you can see in this first block
of text called API reference that the base
URL for the API is HTTPS forward slash
cloud dot IEXAPIs.com.
We're actually using the sandbox mode of this
API in this course, which means that we're
not charged for any usage, but we get
randomized data in exchange.
So you couldn't actually use the sandbox mode
to create real investment strategies, but it's free
and it's still a good way to learn
about how data APIs work in general.
But because of that, we can't use this
base URL.
What we need to do is a control
F for sandbox.
And if we kind of search through the
first little bit, we find this section called
testing sandbox.
It says this, IDX cloud provides all accounts
a free unlimited use sandbox for testing.
Every account will be assigned to test tokens
available via the console.
All sandbox API or sorry, all sandbox endpoints
function the same as production.
You only need to change the base URL
and tokens.
So what does that mean?
We need to change the base URL, which
means we need to grab this instead of
the base URL that was provided earlier.
So copy that to your clipboard, move back
to our Jupyter notebook and paste that right
there.
Awesome.
So we have our base URL.
The next thing we need to do is
figure out which end point we need.
And as you can see, from looking at
this, we ideally want to find an endpoint
that provides both market capitalization and stock price.
There is one API endpoint provided by IEX
cloud that provides both of those.
But I'm going to show you first how
you would find just any endpoint that provides
one of those metrics.
And then I'll show you the endpoint we're
actually going to use.
So let's start with market capitalization.
Note that IEX cloud does have this search
bar over here in the top left.
But for some reason, I always just find
myself using a control F instead.
So what we're going to do here is
do market cap, or let's just do market
cap, not market capitalization, because it's sometimes abbreviated.
So what do we have here for the
first?
It's enterprise value and price to sales.
So these are both metrics that are calculated
using market capitalization.
They don't actually give us market capitalization.
So neither of those is what we need.
The next one is actually a true market
cap metric.
And this is exactly what we need.
But if you look through the rest of
the response attributes from this API endpoint, this
doesn't actually give you stock price.
So we, like I said, we ideally want
to find an endpoint that has both price
and market cap.
And with a bit of searching, you would
find that the quote endpoint provides both of
those.
So I just did a control F for
forward slash quote forward slash.
And this takes us to the information section
about the quote endpoint.
Now, every endpoint description on the IEX cloud
API starts with a section on how to
execute the the HTTP request for that endpoint.
So in this case, we want to execute
a get HTTP request.
And the endpoint is forward slash stock and
then symbol and then forward slash quote.
So if we just copy this and add
this to the API endpoint that we have
in our Jupyter Notebook, this actually won't work
because this curly bracket symbol thing here doesn't
mean anything in the context of this string.
If we tried to execute this HTTP request
as it is, this will return a 400
error probably.
So what we need to do is we
need to transform this API URL into an
F string.
Now, an F string, if you've never used
them before, I'll give you a very brief
introduction.
So if you have string equals free code
is awesome.
And then you said I need to change
the values within this string based on some
outside variable.
We will say, we'll create a variable called
adjective, and this just describes a word that
we want to call free code camp, we
will say the adjective is superb instead of
awesome.
And then we want to pass that adjective
variable where this awesome word is within within
the string.
So the way to do that is you
create an F string.
Now, F strings are called F strings because
you simply put an F on the start
of the string, and then this allows you
to interpolate values in.
So here, curly brackets, and then we type
adjective.
Now, what this string actually stores is free
code camp is superb.
And you can test that by printing the
string.
Free code camp is superb.
Now, we're going to use this F string
functionality to create our API endpoint and we're
sorry, yeah, no, to create our API URL.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to cut this and just get rid
of it.
And then here, this already has the curly
brackets that are associated with an F string.
So all we need to do, and actually,
in addition to the curly brackets, it has
the right variable name that we called here.
I think I did that by design while
kind of building the code for this course.
So what we're doing is adding an F
there.
And then if we print this, if we
print this, API URL, this should print out
this string, but instead of symbol, it should
say APL all caps.
Perfect.
That's exactly what we need.
Okay.
The last thing we need to do is
we need to add an appendage to the
end of this API URL that passes in
our API token to authenticate us through the
IEX Cloud API and basically say, this user
does have permission to access this API endpoint.
Now the way to do that is you
say, question mark token equals, and then we're
going to use an F string again and
say IEX Cloud token that we imported earlier.
If you just type all caps IEX and
then hit tab, this will auto complete for
you.
Now, if we print this, oh, sorry, I
didn't actually have a print statement there.
If we print this, this gives us a
fully fledged IEX Cloud endpoint that we can
ping using the requests library.
So moving on to that, what we need
to do now is execute an HTTP request
and store the results of that HTTP request
in some outside variable.
We're going to call that variable data.
And what we need to assign it to
is a requests dot get method.
Now, if you've never used the requests library,
that's what we imported at the top of
our script here.
It's kind of known as the world's best
Python library for executing HTTP requests.
Their tagline is their tagline is HTTP for
humans.
And I quite like that because it does
describe well what they do.
So what we need to do here is
just type in requests dot get and then
pass in our API URL.
Now, if we run that, what the heck
is this data variable?
The easiest way to check is to just
do the type function and pass in data.
And what it is, is it's a response
object, which is contained within the law models
module of the request library.
Now, this response object has many different things
inside of it.
And one of the more interesting ones is
the status code.
So we can do print data dot status
code.
I'm going to hit tab and see if
that auto completes.
Okay, it didn't set up another it is.
And this gives us a 404.
Now, why the heck does it give us
a 404?
Clearly, I did something wrong here.
Okay, so I just figured out the error.
And what I missed here was there's an
additional kind of suffix that needs to get
added to the IX cloud endpoint called forward
slash stable.
Now, why does that exist?
If you look at this section here, there's
two different naming conventions they can use.
You can use stable or latest stable is
kind of the latest stable API version, as
you can see here.
Well, latest, you can access the latest API
version, which may be in beta.
So basically stable is what you want to
use if you want to make sure that
your application never breaks.
And latest is what you want to use
if you want access to the most bleeding
edge tech that might not be fully tested
yet.
So all we need to do is go
back here and here type forward slash stable
forward slash and then run this.
Now we get a response to 200 error
or a response to 200 code, I mean,
which means that the HTTP request was executed
properly.
And I actually don't like this format.
It's not as accessible as this status code
attribute that we can access.
And the reason I like this better is
you can say, you can test it using
equality operators.
So is this equal to 200?
True.
And that's kind of an easy way to
handle exceptions with HTTP request.
You say if it's not equal to 200,
oops, you could say if it's not equal
to 200, then do something.
Anyways, what we need to do now is
this object is not in any format that
we can really access.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to transform the data that this HTTP
request return to us into a JSON object
using the dot JSON method.
It actually accepts no parameters.
So that's all we need to do.
Now if we print the data object or
the data variable, it gives us a long
JSON type kind of Python dictionary object that
we can use to kind of parse objects
out.
Now, if you've never worked much with Python
dictionaries, they're very useful.
I'll make a very quick example here.
Dictionary equals now dictionaries are always kind of
created using curly brackets.
And what you can say is say a
equals sorry, a colon one and B colon
two.
So this is a Python dictionary called dictionary,
very creative naming.
The reason why dictionaries are useful is because
you can pass in.
So these entries here are called key value
pairs.
This is the key, this A, and this
is the value one.
The reason why dictionaries are useful is because
you can pass in the key and it
returns the value.
Now, this data variable will behave exactly the
same way.
So as an example, if you want to
access this, so this is one key value
pair.
And if you want to access the value,
which is AAPL, all you have to do
is pass in the key, which is symbol
in square brackets like that.
And this should return apple.
Perfect.
So the two attributes that we wanted of
this are market capitalization and price.
So we're going to parse that in the
next section of this course.
Okay, so what we're going to do here
is say price equals data.
And then where is the price contained in
this?
The easiest way to tell is to do
a control F and you can see there's
a whole bunch of different price variables here.
The one we want is probably not calculation
price, latest price sounds right.
So that's the latest price provided by EIS
Cloud API.
Now, if you ever see something like this
and you say, huh, I don't know what
latest price means, that's kind of a bad
example.
But let's look at something else in here
that's not as obvious.
All right, this variable extended change.
Now, what the heck is extended change?
The IEX cloud documentation should tell you.
So if you just copy that extended change
string to your clipboard, and then go back
to the IEX cloud docs, run a control
F search and type in extended change, it
will take you not just to this JSON
object, but there should be a description below.
So as you can see here, extended change
refers to the price change between extended price
and latest price.
So without knowing what those two means, this
is kind of meaningless.
But this was just an example to show
you how you can look up the meaning
of different data points within the JSON response
in the IEX cloud docs.
Okay, so that's how to parse price.
We can print that out and see what
the actual price is.
5 1528.
Now, I actually know I'm not sure if
the IEX cloud price data is randomized in
their sandbox mode.
You can test it pretty easily by just
doing NASDAQ Apple on Google search.
497.
Did it ever get to 515?
Okay, so I don't think that this price
is accurate, but it's actually not far off
from the real world price.
So this price that is randomized, but it's
it's interestingly quite close to the real price.
So that's how you price out price.
And then for market cap, we'll just say
market cap equals data and then market cap.
And similarly, you can print market cap.
Awesome.
This gives like a, I think this is,
I'm going to divide this by a trillion.
Oh, no, that's sorry.
That's only a billion.
That's a trillion.
So this gives us a market cap of
2.18 trillion, which again, I think it's
pretty close to Apple's real market capitalization.
Yeah.
So they're at 2.13 trillion.
So in both cases, pretty similar, although still
not exactly correct.
Okay.
So that's how you parse a API call.
What we're going to do now is we're
basically going to scale up that process to
all of the stocks within our S&P
500 CSV and then store all of the
responses in a pandas data frame that we
will later save into an Excel file.
So that's what's up next.
All right.
So the first thing we need to do
is actually, well, we're going to exit out
of this control F box here because it
was lighting that up and causing me some
eggs.
The first thing we need to do is
specify the columns of our pandas data frame.
And to do that, we're going to need
to know exactly what we're building.
So we're going to build a pandas data
frame that has a few columns.
It's going to have the ticker for each
stock.
It's going to have the stock price for
each stock.
It's going to have the market capitalization of
And then it's going to have the number
of shares to buy for each stock.
So let's start by specifying that in a
variable called my columns.
And this is just going to be a
Python list.
And the entries are going to be ticker,
stock price, market capitalization.
Hopefully I can spell everything right.
Number of shares to buy.
Okay, so that's the Python list.
And then what we're going to do now
is create a blank pandas data frame that
has those columns specified.
So to do that, we're going to call
this variable final data frame, because we're going
to, this will be the final output of
this program at the end.
And to create a pandas data frame, use
the p.data frame class instantiation.
And inside of this, we're going to pass
in columns equals my columns.
Now, you notice that since this is columns,
I didn't want to call this columns because
columns equals columns is a bit confusing, although
I think it would work.
Let's try to guess that does work.
I just think it's quite a bit easier
to read it to say my columns, it
kind of removes that repetition.
Okay, so our pandas data frame has been
created.
What does it look like?
Pandas data frames are, there's kind of two
ways to print them as with most things
in a Jupyter notebook, you can actually either
use a formal print statement like that, or
you can just list a variable name as
the last line of a code.
So this is kind of what it looks
like.
There's no data in here right now.
So it's kind of empty.
But what we can do is just to
create a list of a list that's going
to be 0, 0, 0, 0.
And this is kind of how pandas data
frames typically render.
So one of the advantages of not using
a formal print statement is that when you
just list the data frame variable name on
the last line of a code cell, it
will render in this nice format that kind
of allows you to mouse over it and
it changes color.
And it's just a little bit nicer to
look at them.
The alternative if you use a print statement
will print like this in just plain text,
and it's not quite as nice.
So that's what it looks like when you
print it with plain text.
I actually, you know, the, I'm not a
big fan of it at all.
So we'll stick to printing data frames specifically
like this.
So that's what our data frame looks like.
I'm going to get rid of this line
of zeros because that was just to show
you how they render.
And that's what we're going to be working
with moving forward.
So what we're going to do now is
I'm going to show you how to append
these data points to this pandas data frame.
So what we're going to use to do
that is the append method.
So final data frame dot append.
And then what we need to put in
here is a pandas series that lists all
of the entries in the data frame.
So I'll just quickly explain what a pandas
series is before, a pandas series is before
we move on.
So if we add back this row of
zeros to our pandas data frame like that.
So a pandas data frame is a two
dimensional data structure, which means it has rows
and columns.
Whereas a pandas series is a one dimensional
data frame.
If you've ever worked much in Python, it's
similar to a Python list.
And if you've ever worked with NumPy, it's
similar to a NumPy array.
It just has different methods and functions associated
with it.
But within a pandas data frame, every row
and every column of that data frame is
a pandas series.
So in order to append data to the
bottom of a pandas data frame, that data
needs to be a pandas series.
I'll show you what I mean now.
So let's take this row zeros out and
rerun this code cell.
And then what we need to do in
here is create a pandas series with pd
.series. And then the pandas series accepts a
Python list.
So lots of different layers here, but what
we're eventually going to work out to is
adding a row to this pandas data frame.
So the first thing we're going to add
is the name of the stock that we're
adding, which was stored in the symbol variable
earlier.
And then we're going to add our price
and market cap variables, which we created earlier
price market cap.
And then we're going to add another cell
called N A.
And what does this N A mean?
Well, this last column, the number of shares
to buy, we actually can't calculate it until
we have pulled in all the metrics for
every stock.
So what we're going to do is just
store it as N A now.
And later on, we'll go back in, access
that data and change it once we've actually
pulled in data for all of our stocks.
So what happens when we run this code
cell?
Oh, we missed a comma there.
Now we get an error.
Can only append a series if ignore index
equals true.
So this is super super common when we're
working in pandas.
This ignore index equals true.
Basically almost always needs to be added to
the append method whenever you're appending data to
a pandas data frame.
So this is what we get.
Whoa, this isn't what we wanted.
And as you can see all of these
columns that we created to have N A
N values in them, which means not a
number.
And then over here, we have the data
that we actually wanted.
Now, why is that?
It's because we didn't tell the append method,
which columns to add that data to.
So what we need to do to fix
that is we need to add another argument
here that says, index equals my columns.
Oh, I missed a comma, I think.
No.
Oh, so the, sorry, the problem here is
that this index equals my column needs to
be within the pandas series and not within
the pandas data frame.
So small difference there.
So when we run this, we're missing a
comma again, when we run this, this actually
generates what we wanted.
So to give a quick recap, we created
a final data frame dot append method.
And then within that final data frame dot
append method, we created a pandas series that
has all of the data points we wanted.
And then we specified index equals my columns,
which tells the append method, which columns to
add this data to.
And then the last thing we did was
we added ignore index equals true, which is
kind of necessary whenever you're appending data to
a pandas data frame.
All right, so what we need to do
now is loop through every ticker in our
stocks variable and execute an API call for
that stock and then store the results of
that API call in our pandas data frame.
So to start, we're going to overwrite our
old pandas data frame variable with an empty
pandas data frame that has the same columns
as before.
So columns equals my columns, then we need
to create a for loop that says for
stock, stock in stocks, ticker.
And to start, let's just print all of
these print stock.
What happens?
Great.
So we're successfully looping through all the stocks
in that data frame.
We can get rid of that print statement.
Now what happens next?
We, we need to actually create an API
call for each stock.
So to do that, we'll scroll up to
our old API call cell, and we're going
to copy both of these lines, copy, and
then scroll down.
All right, so both of those are getting
copied in here.
This needs to get indented.
And then instead of symbol here, we're going
to write stock.
Our IDX cloud API token is the same.
The data is the same.
So that's all good.
Now, one thing to note about looping through
our list of stocks in this way is
that it's going to be really, really slow.
And the reason why it's slow is because
executing an HTTP request is one of the
slowest things that you can do in Python.
So this line here where we actually execute
the request is very, very slow.
Later on, we'll see how to improve the
performance of this code by doing batch API
requests that make it very easy to retrieve
information on multiple stocks with a single API
requests.
But that's kind of a more advanced topic.
So we're going to go through with single
API requests first.
Okay, so now we need to basically recreate
the append statement that we used earlier.
So final data frame dot append.
Inside the append statement, we need to create
a panda series.
Oh, sorry.
pv dot series.
And inside that panda series, we need to
create a Python list.
So lots going on here.
The first thing that we're going to add
is stock.
Now what is stock stock is the incrementer
of this for loop.
So this will actually be the ticker of
the stock we're working with.
The next thing we need to add is
data and parsed to latest price.
So this is the same parsing that we
did before.
This will give us our stock price, which
is the second column of the data frame.
The last thing is data and then market
cap, which is the market capitalization just like
we did earlier.
And then just like before, we will do
n a for the last row.
Within this panda series function, we need to
add index equals my columns.
And then outside of the panda series as
before, we need to add ignore index equals
true.
Now, since this is going to be so
slow, like I mentioned, let's just do this
for five stocks and see what happens.
Oh, there's a missing comma right there.
Run.
Great.
Now if we create final data frame, what's
going to happen?
Do you think it will have information for
all five stocks?
And nothing's there.
Why is that?
Now, the reason why that is is because
this final data frame dot append method doesn't
actually modify the original data frame unless you
tell it to.
So to do that, the easiest way is
to just say final data frame.
I can't spell today final data frame equals
equals and then the append statement.
So if we run this and then run
the following cell, we should see a different
output.
Awesome.
So this is for the first five stocks
in our list of stocks.
If we take off this little argument here,
this will take a very long time to
run.
Let's just see that in action.
I'm going to run this print statement too.
And then while this runs, I'm going to
have a little sip of my coffee and
cut out the rest of this until it's
done.
All right.
So as you can see, this is a
very long pandas data frame that has all
of the information we needed.
Since it took so long, we're going to
move on now to using batch API calls
to improve the performance of this code.
Now, IEX cloud, like most data providers actually
gives you discounts if you use batch API
calls because it's a lot less load on
their infrastructure.
So that's one reason to use them.
The fact that it speeds up your code
is another reason to use them.
Overall, if you can use batch API calls
in your scripts, it's generally a good practice.
So pay attention to this section because it's
really important.
IEX cloud is a data provider limits their
batch API calls to 100 tickers.
So what we need to do first is
find some way to split our list of
tickers up into sub lists of length 100.
Now, it's not super intuitive on how to
do that.
But basically what I did just to show
you is I said how to split a
list into sub lists and in Python.
Awesome.
Here's the sorry, that took a bit of
time.
I had to skip ahead, but here's the
function that I was talking about.
So it's called chunks and in the finished
files of this course, you'll see that actually
gave credit to this.
It has 3000 uploads, which is pretty crazy
even for Stack Overflow.
So this is what we'll be using to
split our list or our panda series in
this case into chunks of size n.
So we'll run that code cell to define
this function.
Okay, what we need to do now is
use this chunks function to create a list
of lists where every list is no longer
than 100.
So to do that, we'll say symbol groups,
that's what we'll call this equals chunks and
then the list we want to split is
stocks index ticker.
Now, the reason why we have to pass
this as ticker is because this is a
panda's data frame and ticker is the header
of the only column.
So if we just did stocks, this gives
us the data frame.
If we do stocks at header ticker, that
gives us a series which we can pass
into this chunks function.
And then we want to say 100.
So this gives us a chunks generator.
And to get the actual lists, we just
have to pass it into a list function.
So we'll do that and then we'll say
symbol groups, see what that gives us.
Okay, so this gives us a list of
lists or more specifically, it gives us a
list of pandas series.
So this is from index zero to index
99.
This is from index 100 to index 199.
This is from index 200 to 299, 300
to 399, 400 to 499.
And at the end, we have this one
that's much shorter.
It's 500 to 504.
And that's because there's 505 stocks in the
S&P 500.
And this just gives us groups of 100
at most.
And since this one only has five minutes
shorter.
Okay, so moving back up, what we need
to do now is make a for loop
that lists loops through every list or sorry,
every pandas series within that list, executes a
batch API call.
And then for every stock in that list,
appends the information from that stock to our
final data frame.
So first thing to do is for I
in range, zero to length of symbol groups,
and then print.
So what does this give us this gives
us 012345.
Now, those are all the indices of this
symbol group groups list.
So if we do this, oh, sorry, that's
not what I want to do print that.
This will just print out all of the
lists within our list of lists called symbol
groups.
So now what we need to do is
we need to transform all of the stocks
that's in each of those lists into a
string.
And that string will be passed into the
URL of the HTTP request that we're executing.
So first we'll just create an empty list
called symbol strings.
And what this says is it's going to
be a list of strings where each string
is a comma separated string of all the
stocks in this object.
So what we need to do is use
the append method to add these in.
So we're going to do symbol strings dot
append.
And then what we're going to use is
the join method called on the comma character
join, and then symbol groups.
Now, if you've never used the join method
before, basically what this does is it says,
take all of the elements of this and
join them together by separating them with this.
So to see that in action, we'll just
do print, symbol strings, strings at index i.
All right.
So here's one example.
Here's another example.
And you can tell these examples apart because
at the end of the line, there's a
gap.
Sorry, this is one example.
I had one extra line there.
You can see this example ends there because
there's a gap and it starts on the
line after this, because this is the last
line of the first example.
So there we have our five lists of
symbol strings.
I'm going to comment this out because we
don't want that printing every time we run
this code cell.
The next thing we need to do is
create a blank final data frame again.
So we're using the same variable name, which
is probably not a good practice, but we're
over writing it each time.
So equals p dot data, frame, and columns
equals my columns.
You guys know the drill by now.
Now let's just print that to make sure
that it looks okay.
Awesome.
So we can delete this out.
Okay, the next thing we need to do
is loop through every string in our symbol
strings object and then use that string to
execute a batch API request.
So we're going to use a for loop
for this.
And to keep the, the nomenclature pretty simple,
we're going to just say for symbol string
in symbol strings.
And then we can actually print these out
to make sure that this is working right.
Single string.
Awesome.
That looks good.
We're going to take away that print statement
now.
And then we need to create a batch
API call URL.
And as before, this is going to be
an F string where we pass in the,
the base URL of the API endpoint, and
then pass in all of the strings through
for each of these symbol strings into the
endpoint to get 100, to get data for
100 stocks back.
Now, if you've never run a batch API
call through IEX call before, you probably are
unsure how to do this.
Let's just go to the docs here and
do a control F for batch and see
what comes up.
Batch requests.
Okay.
So so what it says here is that
use market to query multiple symbols.
Okay, so this is what we want this
stock market.
And then as you can see, you pass
in one of the parameters as symbols equals
a comma separated value of symbols.
And then types equals a comma separated value
of API endpoints that you want to hit.
And then if applicable, range tells you how
much data to pull for.
And then at the very end of this,
you would pass on your token as well.
Okay, so we're going to do is oops,
did not mean to click that.
What we're going to do is copy this,
go back to our Jupyter Notebook.
We're going to pass that in here for
now.
And then we're going to scroll up to
our last API call and get this base
URL, including the stable that I missed earlier.
We're going to copy this here.
Going to delete the double forward slash, and
then we're going to move over to the
end of the API call and change a
few things.
So the first thing we're going to do
is remove this last parameter and this range
parameter.
We don't need those for the API call
that we're doing.
The next thing we're going to do is
remove the chart and news endpoint from that
example, because we don't need them.
Next, we're going to actually remove these symbols
that are hard coded into this, we're going
to do a variable interpretation for symbol string.
And then what we're going to do is
move to the very end.
And as before, we can just copy on
the IEX cloud API token that we had
in our original API call.
So copy this, scroll back down, go to
the end of the string and add it.
Awesome.
Now let's just do for symbol string and
symbol string up to, but not including the
first one.
And then we're going to just print this
and see what it gives us.
Oh, and I spelled batch wrong here, which
I'm going to now.
And then print batch API call URL.
Now we're getting an error batch API call
URL is not defined.
There's three L's here.
That's why run that again.
All right.
So this gives us a long URL that
looks okay to me.
One really easy way to test this is
to just click on it.
It's a 400 bad request.
I'm not sure why stable slash stock slash
batch.
Let's make sure that that matches slash stock
slash market slash batch symbol symbol string.
Oh, so the problem here is that when
you're passing on multiple parameters to an API
request.
So this first character is a question mark.
And then every successive character that chains these
parameters together needs to be an ampersand.
So we're going to copy this ampersand and
replace this question mark with it.
And I think that should fix the problem.
Great.
So this is actually opened in a browser,
the JSON that is going to be returned
from this API request.
So now we can do what we did
before use the requests library to get this
data.
So we're going to data equals requests dot
get and then that URL.
And then as before, we're going to pass
the JSON method onto this.
Actually, before we do that, let's just do
print data dot status code.
So it returns 200, which means it's working
properly.
Now what we can do is pass the
JSON method onto this data variable.
And then we need to parse data from
this.
So more specifically, we need to parse data
for every specific stock that's in this symbol
string.
Now the way to do this is just
like before how we use this join method
to join together all of the different strings
that were contained in that list, you can
use the split method to basically do the
opposite.
So we can say for symbol in symbol
string dot split, and we're going to split
on the comma character.
Let's just print every symbol and see what
happens.
Awesome.
So it looks like it's successfully looping through
all of the first 100 stocks there.
And what we need to do now is
parse the bash API call for data for
every specific stock in the order that we
need, and then append that data to the
pandas data frame.
So just like before, we're going to use
the append method, we're going to say final
data frame equals final data frame dot append.
And then in here, we're going to specify
that it's a pandas series.
And inside the pandas series, we're going to
pass in a Python list.
So all of that is exactly what we
did before.
So I kind of skipped over it.
And then here, we're going to pass in
the same four variables.
So symbol, and then price, which will be
data.
And then we have to do actually multiple
levels of parsing this time, because not only
do we have to parse the metric for
that stock, but we also have to parse
the batch API call to get the information
for that specific stock.
So here's how you do that.
We do simple and then quote.
So this is the stock and then the
endpoint.
And then we need to parse out the
metric, latest price.
And we can follow similar logic here to
get the market capitalization.
So market cap.
And then just like before, we are going
to not specify the last column, we will
calculate that later.
Let's run this and see what happens.
Actually, I'm going to add one last line
of this that prints out our data frame.
All right, let's run this and see what
happens.
Type error can only append a series.
This is that ignore index specification that I
mentioned earlier.
So that needs to get added in right
here.
And actually, now that I think about it,
inside this pandas series class instantiation, we need
to pass in index equals my columns.
All right, let's try this.
Invelds index index and ignore index equals true.
I'm missing a comma there.
One more time.
Awesome.
So as you can see, we've successfully appended
the ticker, the stock price, the market capitalization
and the number of shares to buy.
The only other change we have to make
to this code cell is to remove this
little appendage right here that made it loop
only over the first instance.
So now when we run this, it will
actually loop over every symbol string and add
every stock within our list to our pandas
data frame.
So let's try that.
Awesome.
As you can see, that was way, way
faster than using individual API calls for each
stock.
The other one took probably two or three
minutes and that was only a few seconds.
So huge improvement there.
I mean, in theory, if all the API
requests take the same amount of time using
batch API calls should make it 100 times
faster because it does one call for every
100 stocks.
But anyways, much faster than the case.
And it looks like we go all the
way from A to Z.
All the data looks okay.
So we're ready to proceed to calculate the
number of shares to buy.
All right.
So the reason why we left this calculating
the number of shares to buy step until
later in the script is because I want
this to actually work regardless of how big
your portfolio is.
So how we're going to handle that is
we're going to create a Python input that
says how large is your portfolio and then
based on what you tell Python, it will
calculate the number of shares to buy accordingly.
So to do that, we're going to use
Python's input function.
And more specifically, we're going to say portfolio
size is equal to input.
And then inside this input, it accepts a
string and that string is kind of what
question you want Python to ask you.
So here's how it looks.
Enter the value of your portfolio.
Now, if we run this, you can see
there's an input that says enter the value
of your portfolio.
We can write, you know, $1,000.
And then we can access that value later
on in the script.
So now if we do, you know, portfolio
size, it'll print out a thousand note that
this is actually a string.
So that fact that this accepts a string
is actually something we need to make sure
we handle because since it's a string, you
could say, I don't have a portfolio.
And that would actually kind of break the
rest of the script because it's going to
try to do mathematical operations on this string,
which is obviously impossible.
So what we need to do is create
kind of a try accept statement.
So if you're not familiar with try accept,
basically the way these work is try accept,
you could say, try to do this.
And if this doesn't work, it will do
whatever specified here.
So one example would be like if you
say, two plus n, n is not defined.
So then it will print out, you know,
n is not defined.
We're going to comment this out so it
doesn't run.
Now if we run this, it should print
n is not defined.
Awesome.
Now if we say two plus two, it
will doesn't print it.
But if we wrapped it in a print
statement, it would for okay, so we're going
to use this same logic to handle the
fact that people might not put number variables
into this portfolio size input.
So the first thing to do is uncomment
this.
The next thing we need to do is
to try to kind of handle our input
as a float variable.
So to do that, we're just going to
create a variable called val.
And we're going to say that's equal to
float portfolio size.
Now this float function is basically going to
take this portfolio size variable and try to
force it to be a float.
So if we say print val, actually no,
ignore that.
What we're going to do is put that
in here and say print val.
And then for this except we're going to
say, please enter an integer.
Now if we put in a sentence, we'll
say again, I don't have a portfolio.
It returns, please enter an integer.
Now this broad try accept statement is actually
not good.
And the reason why is because this will
react regardless of what type of error is
happening.
So what we need to do to make
sure that it only handles the specific type
of error that we're trying to address is
we need to try to do this and
kind of force an error.
So put a string in there.
And then as you can see, the type
of error that's created is a value error.
So we need to basically change this script
so that it only reacts to value errors
instead of reacting to all types of errors.
And the way that you do that is
you put the type of error right here.
You can run this again and see that
it does handle this properly.
Okay, so what we want to do now
is instead of just handling this, instead of
just handling this and saying please enter an
integer, we need to actually make it redo
this.
So how does this look?
Please enter an integer.
What we want to do is say in
here, enter the value.
And then above this, we want to tell
them exactly why they're getting this input prompt
again.
So we're going to print and say that's
we'll use double brackets.
That's not a number.
And then four slash n.
So that'll create a new line.
Please, please try again.
And then val equals float.
Awesome.
So just to recap, we try to get
the value of someone's portfolio using the input
function.
In the first step of the try accept
block, we try to force that that that
inputted value to be a float variable and
assign it to a variable called val.
If that doesn't work because of a value
error, then we print out that's not a
number, please try again.
And then we prompt them to enter the
value of their portfolio again.
And then we, we force it to be
a strongly type float again.
Now, one interesting thing to note about this
is that if you do it twice, string
and then string, it will still trigger a
value error.
So you need to kind of rely that
the user of this script is going to
be like, I guess astute enough to not
enter a string twice.
So it might look something like this, they
go and say, enter the value of your
portfolio $1,000.
And they say, that's not a number, please
try again.
So then you say, Oh, it's $1,000.
And then you can proceed to the rest
of the script.
Okay, so now that we've accepted the number
from the user of this script, we need
to actually use that number to base our
share calculations on.
Now, since this is equal weight, every stock
in the portfolio will have the same position
size and position size is kind of just
a fancy financial term that says how much
money you're going to invest in each stock.
Now, since there's 505 stocks, an easy example
would be if your portfolio is $505,000,
all you would do is invest $1,000
in each stock.
So as you can see, the easiest way
to calculate that is just to say position
size is equal to value divided by the
length of any column from the final data
frame.
So in this case, we'll just do final
data frame dot index and then print position
size.
So this says we made a small portfolio
here of $1,000.
So it's just saying give us $1.98
in each stock.
Let's use something more reasonable like a million
dollars.
Awesome.
So now it's saying invest $19,000 in
each stock.
That sounds about right to me.
Oh, hang on.
Is this a million or one, two, three?
That's 10 million.
So $19,000 in each stock or almost
$20,000 makes sense for a $10 million
portfolio.
All right.
So we have the position size now.
Now we need to calculate how many shares
of each stock need to be purchased to
get to that position size in that stock.
So let's take an easy example.
Apple stock price is about $500 right now.
So if we wanted a number of Apple
shares to buy, you would just say position
size divided by Apple stock price, which is
$500 ish.
And then you can print the number of
Apple shares.
And in this case, it says, okay, buy
39.6 Apple shares.
Now, this introduces an interesting concept in that
a lot of places do not support fractional
trading, which means that you can't buy a
portion of a share.
You can only buy whole shares.
So you can buy 39 shares or you
can buy 40 shares, but you cannot buy
39.6 shares.
So how do we handle this?
Well, it's tempting to just say, let's round
it to the closest number up or down.
But what might happen then is that if
you are rounding up more integers than you're
rounding down, you'll actually end up buying more
stock than you have money for.
And that is not a good thing.
You would get to the end of your
allocation and say, oh man, I don't actually
have enough money left over to get to
my position size target on this stock.
So because of that, we actually have to
round each of these down.
And that's where that math module that we
imported earlier comes in.
So math dot floor is Python's round down
function.
So if we print this, it should give
us 39.
Oh shoot, math is not defined.
I think it might be lower case.
Yeah, math dot floor.
So that gives us 39.
Okay, so this is kind of like the
logical intuition on how to do this.
We now need to programmatically loop through every
row of our pandas data frame and actually
apply this logic to the number of shares
to buy column.
Now to do this, I'm just going to
comment that out because it'll be useful for
us later.
All right, so we're going to say for
I in range from zero, and then we
needed to go to the last row of
the data frame and the easiest way to
do that is just say the length of
any row within the data frame.
And what I typically use is final data
frame index.
As you can see, this logic is actually
basically what I used here as well.
So let's use this and then just print
everything in here.
All right, this goes from zero to 504.
Let's just make sure that adds up with
the data frame we clicked earlier or printed
earlier, I should say it goes from zero
to 504.
Awesome.
Now we need to access this cell in
each row of the data frame.
The easiest way to do that is using
the LOC method.
So what we're going to do is say
final data frame dot LOC and this is
basically like an easy row column way of
accessing data in pandas.
So for the row, we're going to say
I and for the column, we're going to
say number of shares to buy.
And let's just print this to see if
it prints a bunch of NAs because that's
what it should print.
Awesome.
So we're correctly accessing the data.
Now we need to actually assign the data.
So to do that, you can just use
the equality operator and then say math dot
floor.
And then we need to do basically this
calculation here position size divided by the stock
price.
So we'll say position size divided by now,
what are we going to do for stock
price?
Do we have to execute another API call
and pull that data from IEX again?
We actually don't and the reason why is
because that data is already stored in the
pandas data frame.
So we can take similar logic to this
LOC method here and put that there, paste
it and just change this to stock price.
Well, this tab autocomplete is not working.
So if we run this, what happens?
It ran correctly.
Let's do this again and print the data
frame to see if it looks okay.
Awesome.
So as you can see it correctly kind
of shows the number of shares to buy
here.
One easy way to fact check this.
Well, there's a couple things you do.
The first thing is to say, okay, this
Apple stock price is close to the 39
that we calculated earlier.
So that's a good sign.
Another thing you do is say, look at
two stocks that have different stock prices and
the one that has the higher stock price
should be recommended to buy less shares than
the one that has a lower stock price.
So let's just use the first two rows
of this data frame.
As an example, you can see that for
this stock with ticker A, it costs $100
to buy it and you're buying $197.
And then the second stock has a much
lower stock price.
And because of that, you have to buy
many more shares to actually reach your target
position size.
Now that kind of all looks good.
So we can move on.
I'm going to take away this comment code
and just tidy this up a little bit
and we can proceed to the next cell.
All right.
So this brings us to the last section
of this project, which is to save our
pandas data frame into an XLSX file for
non technical users to access through Excel.
So the big idea here is that we
did all of the work in a Python
script.
You could schedule this script to run periodically.
And then the output would be sent to
your trading team to actually buy and sell
stocks in response to the output.
So to do this, we're going to use
the XLSX writer library for Python.
Now, oops, the new environment.
If you remember, at the start of this
project, many lines of code ago, we actually
imported this here.
So it's actually in our script already, we
just need to use it now to save
our data frame as an Excel file.
Now, XLSX writer is an excellent package and
offers an insane amount of customization.
But the trade off for this is that
the library can seem a bit complex to
new users.
I'm going to do my best to explain
well throughout this section.
And because of that, this might be a
bit long.
So if this seems easy, or you use
that, if this seems easy, or you've used
XLSX writer in the past, you can feel
free to speed up the speed here a
bit or skip ahead.
Alright, so the first thing we need to
do is actually initialize our XLSX writer object.
And the way that we do that is
by saying writer equals PD dot Excel writer.
And then here, we need to pass in
the file name that we want to save
to in this case, we're going to do
recommended trades dot XLSX.
And then we need to specify the engine,
which is XLSX writer.
Now, let's break this down a little bit
to kind of describe what's going on here.
As you can see, the class that we're
initializing here is from the pandas library and
not actually from XLSX writer.
And the reason why that is, is because
since pandas deals with tabular data, and so
much tabular data is actually saved to Excel
files, they have a very tightly coupled integration.
And it actually kind of is easiest to
initialize a new writer object from pandas rather
than XLSX writer.
And kind of by default, you always save
these objects to a variable called writer.
It allows you to reuse your code without
having to change the object name later.
And it's kind of just the best practice.
So we're going to say writer equals p
dot Excel writer.
And then this is the file name that
we want to save to and then the
engine equals XLSX writer.
It may seem a bit redundant, but this
library can also be used to save XML
file.
So we have to actually specify that we
want to work in Excel.
So that's the first thing we need to
do.
The next thing we need to do is
actually to pass our pandas data frame into
this object in specify which tab of the
Excel file we want it to be saved
to.
So to do that, we do final data
frame dot to Excel.
And then the first thing we pass in
is that writer object.
The next thing we pass in is the
name of the tab we want it to
be saved to.
So we'll say recommended trades again.
And the last thing we pass in is
an index equals false argument.
Alright, so our object has been created.
The next thing we need to do is
to create the formats we need for our
XLSX file.
Now earlier when I said that this library
can be confusing or complicated to new users,
this is where it gets really, really complicated.
Formatting Excel files with XLSX writer is a
science and there's a lot to it, but
I'm going to try to keep things simple
here and hopefully you guys won't run into
any hiccups.
The first things we're going to do is
create, I guess two variables that specify the
color scheme for our Excel sheet.
And then we will reference those variables in
all of the formats that we create later
on.
So that if we want to change one
color, it will be reflected across all the
different formats that we create later instead of
hard coding them in and having to change
many different instances of a specific color.
So specifically, what we're going to create is
a background color variable and a font color
variable.
So background color.
And these are just going to be empty
strings for now, font color.
Alright, so what goes in here, these actually
store the HTML hex codes for the very
for the colors that we want to select.
So I'm going to use two colors that
kind of match the style of the free
code camp website.
I really like it.
It's command line chic and very modern.
So we're just going to follow that to
make things easy.
The background color is going to be 0A0A23
and the font color is going to be
F6F.
Alright, so that's that.
Now we need to actually create a few
different formats that we will be referencing when
we actually apply the formats to our cells
of our Excel sheet later on.
So as you can see up here, we
need a string format, a dollar format with
decimals, a dollar format without decimals and an
integer format.
So let's start with string format.
And then what we're going to do here
is create a writer.book.add format method.
Inside this add format method, we have to
create a dictionary and this dictionary specifies the
format of the cells that are going to
have this applied to them later.
So what goes in here?
There's three main attributes, font color, background color
and border.
Now each of these should actually be strings.
I'm going to fix that indenting issue.
Since this is a dictionary, what is going
on?
I find the indenting on Jupyter notebooks leaves
a lot to be desired.
Since this is a dictionary, these should be
strings and we have to add colons to
each one.
Alright, so the font color is going to
be font color.
And this font color variable is what we
defined up here.
This background color is going to be background
color.
And this border is going to be one.
This just means to add a solid border
around each one.
Now this is our first one.
Let's run this code to make sure it
works properly.
Awesome.
Now we need to basically template off of
this and create a few other formats.
So we have a string format and then
we need to name the other ones that
we described before this code cell.
Say string format, dollar format and integer
format.
Now all of these are going to share
the same attributes that the string format specified.
We just need to add a few things
to each one.
So for dollar format, we need to specify
a number format attribute like this.
And the way that this works is actually
pretty easy.
You just pass in a number with zeros
in it, templated the way that you want
it to be formatted.
So in this case, it will look like
that.
And then we will do the same thing
for the integer format.
So num format.
And then we're just going to say zero.
Awesome.
Let's run this code cell to make sure
there's no syntax errors.
Excellent.
Alright, so now we need to apply the
formats that we just created to our XLSX
file.
And this is like a big complicated.
So what I did here was I actually
provided an example and we can kind of
use this to template on for all of
the columns in our sheet.
So what we need to do is say
writer dot sheets and then parse out the
recommended trade sheet from that object.
And then we use the set column method
on that item to specify information about the
column we're doing.
Now we're going to do this one by
one first and then we're going to kind
of put everything into a loop because it'll
be a bit more efficient on code and
much more readable.
So let's start with column A.
You actually can't just put A you have
to put A through A like that.
So that tells you the column and then
we need to specify the column width.
Let's do 18 pixels.
And then you need to say which format
you want to apply to it.
Column A is our ticker format.
So we need string format.
It's not a number.
Now, if you run that it returns zero.
And that basically tells you that it ran
properly.
The way to actually see this in action
is you need to actually save your writer
object.
Now to do that you say writer dot
save.
And then if you go to your working
directory where you're running through this you should
be able to open up your recommended trades
excel file and see that the first column
has actually been formatted properly.
So let's do that for all the other
columns and then we can change a couple
of things to make it formatted better.
So how to do this.
We'll just copy this a few times and
change the letter four times to be specific.
So this should be B through B.
This should be C through C and this
should be D through D.
Now let's run this and see that what
happens to the excel sheet.
Only one was formatted.
Why is that?
Oh, I think we have to go back
here and re initialize this.
All right.
Let's try now.
Awesome.
So as you can see, the columns are
being formatted properly, but the headers aren't just
so you know, we're going to solve that
later.
It's not something that I'm ignoring, but we
will solve that in a few cells.
So what we need to do now is
we're going to simplify this by making two
loops and each of those loops is going
to work with this column formats dictionary that
we're going to create.
So let's create column formats and make a
dictionary.
Now what this dictionary is going to be
is it's going to have a key for
each column.
So A B C and D and the
value for each column is going to be
a list inside that list.
The first item is going to be the
title and the second item is going to
be which format we want to apply format.
So ticker string format and then stock price
dollar format.
Oh, comma there.
Market cap.
And the last one is going to be
number of shares to buy and integer format.
So let's run that.
So that cell ran correctly, which tells you
that that dictionary is formatted properly.
And now we're ready to start building a
couple loops to do all of the work
that we did up here, but automatically.
So the loop that we're going to be
building specifically is going to loop through every
key in that dictionary.
So we're going to say four columns in
column formats dot keys.
If you've never used the keys method to
iterate through a dictionary before, it basically just
returns all of these.
So you print the column, it should print
A B C B.
Yep.
Now what we need to do is create
a writer dot sheets, recommended trades dot set
column.
We're basically doing all the work we did
up here.
So set column.
Here we're going to do an F string
that interpolates in column column.
So this would just be like for column
A would be a colon A.
We're going to MS string and then we're
going to do 18 pixels wide.
And then we're going to do column formats
at column.
So this will be this dictionary at key
A.
So this would return this list.
And then we need the second element of
this list.
And since Python is zero index, we parse
one.
Great.
So that runs properly.
Awesome.
So if you if we redo all of
this to okay, here's what we're going to
do.
We're going to comment out this.
We're going to put a writer dot save
method there.
And then we're going to go back to
the start, reinitialize our writer object and run
all of this code.
Awesome.
Let's take a look and see what our
Excel file looks like.
Great.
So everything's being formatted properly.
In that loop, our code is a lot
cleaner.
It's easier to read.
It's a big improvement.
Now what we need to do is handle
these.
And columns in XLSX writer are kind of
hard to deal with.
What I always do is I just overwrite
them.
So writer dot sheets, recommended trades.
And then I do dot write.
And this write method, you pass in what
information you want stored in the cell and
what format you want to apply to that
cell.
You also need to specify the location of
the cell.
So here's what we're going to do.
A1.
We're going to say ticker and we're going
to say string format.
Now, if we go back to the top
again, reinitialize this and run through the rest
of this and go back to our Excel
file.
The first cell is formatted properly.
So now we just need to do the
same thing for stock price market capitalization and
number of shares to buy.
Let's go back.
Easiest way to handle that is to just
copy and paste.
So this will change to A1, B1.
No, sorry, that should be A1 or sorry,
A2 or B1.
Yeah, B1.
Okay, perfect.
All right.
A1, B1, C1, D1.
And this will be stock price with dollar
format.
This will be number
of shares to buy with integer format.
All right.
As before, we're going to go back to
the top.
We're going to reinitialize this Excel writer object,
run our code to the very end and
then take another look at our Excel file.
Awesome.
So everything looks formatted properly.
The only thing that might be worth improving
is to widen this a little bit.
But I mean, anyone who has an auto
format or for Excel will be able to
handle that pretty easily.
All right.
So this violates the programming principle of do
not repeat yourself.
This is very, very loopable.
So we're going to create another loop here
that basically does this logic.
So all right, so we're going to add
this in here.
And what we need to do is say
column here and convert this to an F
string.
So as this loops through, this will go
from A1 to B1 to C1 to D1.
And then we need to capture this value
here.
So it's going to be column, column, format.
So this is the dictionary.
And then we parse out columns.
So this is the value of a key
value pair.
And then we want zero.
And this will be the first entry of
the list that is the value in the
key value pair.
So that's this.
And then this needs to get replaced with
the second entry of the list.
Easiest way to do that is to just
copy this and replace the zero with a
one.
So let's go there.
One.
All right.
As before, we're going to scroll all the
way up to the top, reinitialize our writer
object, move all the way through to the
end.
Let's open this up and see if everything
looks okay.
Great.
So this is the final output of the
first project from this algorithmic trading and Python
course.
It says here that the last step is
to save the writer output.
That's actually this line.
So we're already done.
And just like that, you build your first
algorithmic trading project in Python.
I hope you had fun.
The next two projects are going to be
even more awesome and you're going to learn
a lot more.
So I hope you enjoy the rest of
this course and kudos to you for sticking
through it so far.
All right.
So welcome to the second project for this
course where we're going to build a quantitative
momentum strategy.
What we need to do to start just
like before is we need to open up
our Jupyter here in my terminal in my
home root directory.
And what I need to do is navigate
into my dev folder.
And within that dev folder, I need to
navigate into algorithmic trading in Python, which you
can see here, autocompleted for me.
So we'll move into there.
And now that we're here, we need to
activate our virtual environment.
So you'll remember from before that the command
to do that is source and then V
and V forward slash bin forward slash activate.
If you look to the left of your
terminal command here, you can see that that
V and V in parentheses there shows that
the virtual environment has been activated correctly.
And now that the virtual environment has been
activated, you can launch it with Python dash
M notebook.
That will launch your Jupyter notebook.
Now, one thing that I'm not sure I
mentioned before is that you can deactivate a
virtual environment by simply typing deactivate.
And if you try to launch your Jupyter
notebook without this, it will actually fail because
it'll say no module name notebook.
So we need to reactivate our virtual environment
and then launch your Jupyter notebook.
This will start the server in our browser
and we can get started.
Just like before, we're going to want to
navigate into starter files and then open up
the second project this time, which is quantitative
momentum strategy.
So let's open that to get started.
All right, so just like before this Jupyter
notebook starts with a bit of background information.
So it says momentum investing means investing in
the stocks that have increased in price the
most.
For this project, we're going to build an
investing strategy that selects the 50 stocks with
the highest price momentum.
From there, we will calculate recommended trades for
an equal weight portfolio of these stocks.
So this project will combine a lot of
the stuff that we used in the last
section.
So that repetition will help you remember what
we actually just did because I know that
that last project actually contained a lot of
stuff.
And then we're going to build on top
of that by not just equal weighting a
already selected universe of stocks being the S
&P 500, but we're going to actually select
a subset of those stocks based on their
momentum characteristics.
So let's get started by first importing some
libraries.
All right, so just like before, we're going
to need NumPy and we're going to import
that as NP.
We're going to need pandas, and we're going
to import that as PD.
So as a quick recap, NumPy is the
best Python library for numerical computing and pandas
is a data science library that makes it
very easy to work with tabular data in
Python.
You'll remember that we worked a bunch with
the PD.data frame structure in the last
project, and we'll do the same thing in
this project.
And we're also going to need the requests
library for making HTTP requests.
We're going to need the math library for
performing some basic math functions.
And we're going to need the SciPy library.
Actually, we're not going to need the whole
library.
We're just going to need the stats library
from SciPy import stats.
And the last thing that we need is
the XLSX writer library, which we saw in
the last section allows us to easily format
and save Excel files from a Python script.
Now we've seen all of these before, except
for the SciPy stats module.
And what this does is it makes it
very easy to calculate percentile scores.
So we'll see later on in this project
that what we're actually going to do is
we're going to gather and parse momentum metrics
for all of the stocks in our universe.
And then we're going to calculate percentile scores
for those momentum metrics.
Then we're going to rank the stocks on
those percentile scores.
And we're going to select the 50 stocks
that have the highest average percentile score across
a broad basket of momentum metrics.
So if you haven't seen SciPy stats, it's
pretty easy.
We're just going to use the percentile score
calculation feature of it.
And yeah, so that's it for our libraries.
Let's move on to importing our list of
stocks.
So actually, we should run this code cell
first.
All right.
So now that our imports have been done
for our open source Python libraries, we need
to actually import our list of stocks.
Now we also need to import our API
token.
We did both of these steps in the
last project as well.
So before I actually code this out, try
to go through and without looking at your
last one, figure out how to import your
list of stocks into a pandas series and
figure out how to import your API token
from your secrets file.
So cut here and try to do that
before proceeding.
Okay, I hope you had success doing that.
If you didn't, the command to import your
list of stocks is pd underscore, sorry, dot
read underscore csv and then type in your
list of stocks.
Now this should auto complete if you just
type in sp and then you can print
it out to make sure it looks okay.
Just like before it has all five hundred
and five stocks in the S&P five
hundred and then for the secrets file we
want from secrets import and if you hit
tab, you can see that the IAS cloud
API token actually shows up here.
So that is great.
We can run this code cell to get
both of those imported and we can move
on to make our first API call.
Now this is where this project will start
to be quite a bit different than the
last project that we worked through because we're
actually going to be pulling different stock market
information from the IAS cloud API.
More specifically, instead of trying to pull price
and market capitalization, we're going to be pulling
price and one year stock returns.
So to do that, we're going to go
to the IAS cloud docs.
Oops, let's try and keep this all in
one browser window.
There we go.
So IAS cloud docs and we're going to
go here.
It's usually the first non add entry in
a Google search and then we're going to
run a control F and see what kind
of a return metrics we can actually find
in here.
Okay, so return is clearly not a good
thing to search for because it gives 341
hits and you can see why that is.
It's because a lot of these will say
most endpoints return.
So the fact that endpoints can return something
and stocks can also return a percentage is
not good.
What if we just type in momentum?
These are all more complex momentum metrics than
we need.
Okay, what if we type in price return?
Zero.
What if we type in price return with
no space?
Okay, what if we type in year return?
This might give us an API endpoint that
gives us a one year return or something
like that.
Still nothing.
What if we do performance?
Okay, this gives us 21 hits.
Sector performance.
As you can see, it's not always super
straightforward on how to find these.
Okay, so now
I'm searching through return again.
It is a lot of hits, but I
feel like it's going to be near the
top of this documentation page.
Okay, so this looks promising.
This is a historical prices endpoint and this
would actually allow you to get the job
and you could pull in historical prices for
let's say one year and use the today's
price divided by the price one year ago
and then subtract one and that would give
you your one year price return.
However, I know that IEX actually calculates this
metric in a separate endpoint.
So we're going to keep moving through this
until we find it.
All right, so I had to cut there
turns over.
We're actually looking for is the word change,
not the word return.
And I do a control that if it's
the first thing we find, of course.
So this is the key stats endpoint, which
you can get with the stats keyword in
the URL.
And if you look down here, there's actually
an awesome group of momentum metrics.
So you can do maximum percent change, five
year percent change, two year percent change, one
year, year to date, six months, three months.
In case you can't see this, I'll zoom
in a little bit.
I guess you can't zoom.
Oh yeah, there we go.
That's a lot of zoom.
There we go.
All right, so max change, five year, two
year, one year, year to date, six months,
three months, one month, three days, sorry, 30
days and five days.
So this is the stats endpoint.
What we're going to do is we're going
to copy this and we're just going to
put it in our Jupyter notebook for now
to come back to later.
And we also need the sandbox base API
endpoint.
I'm going to zoom back to normal zoom
because it's a little easier for me to
navigate.
So here's the testing sandbox.
We're going to find that this is the
base URL.
We're going to put this in here right
here.
And then remember from last time, we need
to actually include stable here.
So this is a example of the base
URL that we need to hit with our
API call.
We're going to call this string API underscore
URL, and then we actually need to specify
a symbol.
So just like before, we're going to use
apple as an example symbol, and we're going
to use an F string to interpolate that
symbol variable into this.
We can take this right off the end
because we're not actually trying to parse a
specific stat.
And then we can use the requests library
to make an easy API call to get
this data.
So to that, we're going to say data
is equal to requests dot get.
And then we're going to do API underscore
URL.
And then we're going to print the status
code of that HTTP request to make sure
that went through properly.
So this gives 400.
We did something wrong.
What is it?
Sandbox that is, oh, we didn't pass on
our IEX cloud API token.
So we need to do question mark token
equals IEX and then tab it should auto
complete.
Try that.
Alright, so returns 200, which means the API
call is working properly.
Let's transform this into a JSON and print
this again.
Alright, so as you can see this can
as you can see, this contains all the
information that it should contain.
The information that we specifically want is the
one year price returns for every stock in
the universe.
So to do that, it's actually quite easy.
We're going to cover that next.
So to parse a JSON object like this,
we saw in the last section that you
just pass in square brackets and then the
key of the dictionary.
So the key that we want now is
one year change percent and all these keys
generally don't start with integers.
They start with letters.
So that's why it says year five instead
of five year and etc.
But this is the key we want.
So we're going to copy this.
We're going to move down here.
We're going to add that in and then
this should give us one point four two.
So what does that mean?
That means that Apple has increased in price
one hundred and forty two percent in the
last year, which is pretty impressive.
It means that the stock has more than
doubled, but I guess that's what happens when
you sell a lot of expensive iPhones.
So just like before, we're going to kind
of loop through all of the stocks in
our universe and provide API calls for all
of them.
Instead of living through them one by one,
like we saw in the last section, which
is extremely slow, we're going to move right
on to executing batch API calls because that's
kind of a better practice and there's no
point practicing executing single API calls when you'll
generally never do that in practice.
So the first thing we need to do
is chunk our list of stocks into groups
of one hundred using the chunks function that
we created last time.
So to make this easy, I've actually included
a bunch of reusable code from the last
project here.
So just run this code cell.
That will give us the chunks function.
And then we use the chunks function to
divide our list of stocks into symbol groups
of length one hundred.
Then we create an empty list called symbol
strings and then for every one hundred stocks
in this symbol groups list, we create a
comma separated list of strings and then add
them to this symbol strings variable.
So if you go through every symbol string
in that list, we did this last project
as well, but we're going to do it
again just for practice.
And then you print it.
You'll see that this is basically just five
lists and I'm sorry, this should be four
in.
Yeah.
So this is just five lists of length
one hundred.
So when I say lists, they're not Python
lists, they're actually strings separated by commas, but
there's five of them.
So here's one, here's another, here's where the
third one ends, fourth one, the fifth one.
And I said there's five, there's actually six,
sorry.
That's because we have this short one of
length five at the end.
Okay, so that's all of this.
I'm going to delete this out.
And we are going to move on to
creating a blank pandas that data frame.
So just like before, we're going to call
this final data frame, and we're going to
instantiate it by saying PD dot data frame,
and then columns equals, and then you'll see
up in this code.
So I've actually defined the names of the
columns we want here.
So it's ticker price, one year price return
and number of shares to buy.
These are basically the same column names as
we used in the last project, except market
capitalization has been replaced by one year price
return here.
So we can go down here and specify
those columns by saying columns equals my underscore
columns.
And then if we print this, we should
see an empty pandas data frame with the
columns we specified.
Awesome.
So that's good.
We're going to delete that.
And then we need to loop through all
of our symbol strings in the symbol strings
object and create a batch object also for
symbol string in symbol strings.
And then we want to create a batch
API call URL.
We're going to leave that as an empty
string for a moment.
And then we want to create a data
variable and that's going to be a request
dot get method that accepts batch API call
URL and then calls the JSON method on
it to transform it from a requests object
to a JSON object.
So what goes in here?
Let's go back to the IACrowd docs to
look at batch API call syntax again.
All right.
So I just did a control F for
batch here to find this section, which tells
you everything you need to know about batch
requests.
So stock and then symbol and then batch.
Actually, we want to query.
So this syntax here is for querying multiple
end points for one stop, but we want
to query one endpoint for multiple stocks.
So we actually want to use this syntax
here.
So I'm going to copy this link address
and I think this just gives us the
last bit.
No, it gives us the entire thing.
We're going to want to change this to
sandbox because by default, the docs give you
a live URL, not a sandbox URL.
And then we're going to want to move
down here and change a few things here.
So what endpoint do we need first?
Actually, to start, move this up here so
you can actually see it.
To start, let's take off this last parameter
and the range parameter.
So those can both be gone and then
we're going to have to add back our
token equals and then IEX cloud.
Oh, sorry, this isn't an F string.
So that won't auto complete IEX cloud and
yep, IEX cloud API token.
Then we're going to want to change the
endpoints next.
So what goes there?
Let's scroll back up to see which endpoint
we actually queried earlier.
All right.
So we use the stats endpoint.
So let's put that down into our batch
API call stats.
And then here we want to change our
symbols to be an interpolated variable that matches
whatever the incrementer is of our for loop.
So that is symbol string.
All right.
So now what we need to do is
we're going to run over this loop once
just to make sure that we're getting a
200 HTTP code to make sure that the
HTTP request is being executed properly.
So to do that, we're going to print
data.status code.
And for this to actually work properly, we're
going to have to remove this JSON method
temporarily from the HTTP request.
And then here where we're specifying what we
loop over, we're going to want to change
this to a colon one, which tells this
to loop only over the first entry of
that string.
So if this is working properly, we'll get
a response of 200.
Awesome.
So that's good.
We can get rid of this status code
attribute from the data object and call this
JSON method on it to see what the
structure of the HTTP response actually looks like.
So this is basically a huge dictionary.
It has many levels.
So at the top level, there is a
key for this ticker and a value of
a dictionary.
And then within that dictionary, there is a
key for the endpoint stats and a dictionary
for the value.
And then within that dictionary, there's a key
for every metric with a value that corresponds
to that metric.
So we have to do multiple levels of
parsing here.
But before we do that, we actually have
to loop over all of the stocks.
So let's let's build that loop first.
What we're going to do is we're going
to say for symbol in symbol string dot
split, and we're going to split on the
colon character, which separates all of the tickers
in the symbol string.
So let's see what that split method actually
returns before we go any further.
Copy that, comment that out, and then print
that, oops, print that, no, print this is
what I want to print.
There we go.
Awesome.
So let's run that and see what it
gives us.
As you can see, this is a Python
list where each item in the list is
a symbol that corresponds to all the comma
separated symbols in the symbol string.
Okay, perfect.
So we'll get rid of this.
Did not mean to open my dev tools.
We will uncomment this and then we will
start parsing the data in this loop.
So we're going to say, so what we
want to do here is we want to,
for every ticker in this list, we want
to append the relevant metrics to the final
data frame.
So to that we're going to say final
data frame is equal to final data frame
dot append.
And then within this append method, there's a
few things we need.
We need a pandas series and that pandas
series will accept a Python list and it
will also accept the index equals my underscore
columns argument that, as you'll recall from the
first project, this tells the append method where
to actually put the new metrics in the
existing pandas data frame.
And then outside the pandas series, we're going
to actually add ignore index equals true.
Okay, perfect.
So this is where we want to do
our parsing.
The first metric we want is symbol.
The second metric we want is price.
So to get price, we're going to need
to do data and then parse the symbol
and then parse the stats endpoint.
And then we're going to have to actually
see what the name of the price metric
is within this.
So let's right here, let's just print out
one example of this.
Oh, sorry.
Not right there.
Right here.
Let's print data and then we'll use Apple
as an example ticker and then we'll use
stats and then let's just see what this
gives us.
All right.
This is giving us an error because we
didn't actually format the rest of it properly.
But let's look and see here what we
have for price.
I'm going to do control F for price
and see if anything highlights up here.
Let's do some market cap employees.
Doesn't look like this actually has any price
data.
So we need to add here to our
endpoints.
We're going to say price and stats.
Let's see what that gives us.
If we parse price, I think this just
gives us.
Yeah, $504.
Okay, perfect.
So this is what we need to do
for price.
We're going to replace Apple with the symbol
that we're looping over and then we're also
going to pass in one year price return.
So we can use this print statement up
here to see what we need.
We're getting an error here because we're trying
to append two values to a data frame
that has four values.
So for now I'm just going to put
in N.A. placeholders for both of them.
And actually for the number of shares to
buy that N.A. placeholder is actually going
to stick.
So we only need to figure out the
one year price return.
So we'll run this to get rid of
that error and then look in here to
see what we need to parse out for
the one year price return.
All right.
Year one is what we need to search
for.
Okay, here's the metric year one change percent.
So we'll copy that.
We will paste that there for now.
And then what we want to do is
copy this.
Paste it there and then add this in
as an additional level of parsing to that.
All right, let's run this.
I'm going to take this off and this
means that instead of looping over just the
first symbol string, we're going to loop over
all of the symbol strings.
And then inside of this big loop, I'm
going to print the final data frame so
we can see what it looks like.
With any luck, this should be okay.
Oh, I'm sorry, I'm going to do this
again and remove this print statement.
All right, float object is not subscriptable.
Hmm, that's because we need to change this
endpoint to stats not price.
All right, so this will take a sec
to run.
It's a pretty big data frame to build.
Awesome.
Everything looks good.
So just to recap, what we did here
was we created an empty pandas data frame
with the columns that are specified here.
And then we looped over all of the
symbol strings in our symbol strings object.
We created a batch API call URL for
those symbol strings that hits two different endpoints.
It hits the price endpoint and it hits
the stats endpoint.
And then we used the requests library to
execute an HTTP request to get that data
in the form of a JSON object.
For every string in that comma separated string
of string, or sorry, for every symbol in
that comma separated string of symbols, we split
them using the split method to get a
list of them.
And then we looped over that list to
append the data for each symbol to our
empty pandas data frame.
And then we printed the pandas data frame
and it looks like this.
Everything seems to be working so far so
we can move on to removing low momentum
stocks from our pandas data frame.
All right.
So like the other code cells in this
project, this has a bit of background information.
It says the investment strategy that we're building
seeks to identify the 50 highest momentum stocks
in the S&P 500.
Because of this, the next thing we need
to do is remove all the stocks in
our data frame that fall below this momentum
threshold.
To do that, we'll sort the pandas data
frame by one year price return and then
drop all stocks outside the top 50.
That sounds easy enough and pandas actually makes
it very easy to sort data within the
data frame.
So we're going to use some built-in
functionality of the pandas library to do this.
All right.
So the first thing we're going to do
is call final data frame and then on
this final data frame, we're going to call
the pandas method that allows us to sort
the data frame based on values containing its
columns and that method is sort values.
Now this takes a few different parameters.
The first one is the column that you
want to use to source.
So we're going to use one year price
return.
If you just type in one and then
tab, it might autocomplete.
Now, if it doesn't autocomplete, you can just
go up here and copy it.
Copying is always a good idea because there's
lots of different ways you could spell this
and just kind of avoid any typos.
Although typos are a pretty easy bug to
fix.
All right.
So one year price return.
And then the next parameter it accepts is
whether or not you want it to sort
ascending or sort it by descending.
Now we want to sort descending values so
that the highest momentum stocks are at the
top.
So do that we'll say ascending equals false.
And then the last thing we want to
say is in place equals true.
Now, if you've worked with pandas lots in
the past, you're definitely familiar with this in
place equals true method.
What this does is it changes the function
from just returning a sorted data frame to
actually modifying the original data frame.
Now to see this in action, you can
take it away, run this, and it shows
the highest one year price return stocks at
the top.
But then if you run that line and
then print the original data frame right below
it, it will not return the sorted data
frame.
It will just return the original one.
So this shows you that without the in
place equals true method, it doesn't actually modify
the original data frame.
Now, if you add the in place equals
true method, that's not true.
It will return the sorted data frame.
So that's how we sort the values.
Now what we need to do is modify
the pandas data frame so that it only
includes the first 50 rows.
Now to do that, it's actually quite easy.
You can just pass in the dash 50,
yeah, dash 50, or sorry, not dash, colon
50, specification into square brackets like this.
Now the indices are all different now because
it's been sorted.
So I'm actually going to just make sure
that this is right by doing length.
Yeah, so it's 50.
Great.
So this has 50 stocks now.
And then to make this so that it
actually modifies the original pandas data frame, all
you need to do is say final data
frame equals final data frame equals 50.
And now if you print it, it will
just return a data frame with 50 rows.
So awesome.
So one last thing that we can do
is to reset the index so it doesn't
start and have kind of this random list
of numbers.
So the easiest way to do that is
just with pandas reset underscore index method doesn't
actually accept any parameters.
But as you can see, it does the
job.
Now, just like before, without the in place
equals true method, this doesn't actually modify the
original data frame.
So we'll have to specify that in here.
You'll notice as you work more and more
with the pandas library that this in place
equals true parameter works in almost all of
the functions that you use regularly in the
library.
So there we go.
So just to recap what we did here,
we took our final data frame object, which
contains price and momentum data on all the
stocks in the S&P 500.
And we sorted its rows based on their
one year price returns such that the highest
momentum stocks are at the top.
And then we use the in place equals
true parameter to actually modify the original data
frame instead of just returning a temporary copy.
Once that was done in the next line,
we modified the data frame such that it
only contains the 50 stocks with the highest
price momentum.
And then we use pandas reset underscore index
method to change the index of the data
frame so that it actually runs from 0
to 49 or 0 to 50 I should
say, 0 to 49.
Yeah, 0 to 49.
And then we just printed out the final
data frame on the last line.
So with that out of the way, we
can move on to actually calculating the number
of shares to modify for this simple momentum
strategy.
Alright, so just like in the last project,
this is going to be kind of similar.
The only change we're going to make is
that we're going to wrap the functionality of
accepting the portfolio size inside of a function
because we'll actually be using the same functionality
later in this tutorial when we build a
better and more robust momentum strategy.
You can actually see that heading here.
We started in the next code sale.
So to do that, we're going to have
to wrap it in a function and it's
probably not necessary to wrap it in a
function.
You could just copy-paste code.
It is a Jupyter notebook after all, but
it is definitely better to create functions if
you're ever going to reuse any code.
And since we're not building too many functions
in this Python course, it's kind of a
good excuse to practice building Python functions.
So if you're familiar with Python functions, and
since we've already done this same functionality in
the last project, try to pause this video
here and try to complete the function yourself
without watching me code through it.
So break now and try that yourself.
Alright, so what we're going to do is
we're going to say def portfolio underscore size.
So if you're not familiar with function syntax
in Python, this is just defining a new
function called portfolio size.
And the empty brackets here means that it
accepts no parameters.
And then the first thing we're going to
do is we need to create a global
variable in here.
So this function can define a variable and
then it can be accessed outside that function.
So the keyword to do that is global.
And we're going to call this variable portfolio
underscore size.
And then what we're going to do is
we're going to call this portfolio portfolio underscore
size equal to input.
And then just like before, we're going to
say enter this size of your portfolio.
Now, as we saw in the last project,
we need to make some special functionality here
such that if someone tries to enter a
string into this Python input, it will tell
them to reenter a float value.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to say try float portfolio underscore size.
And if this returns an error, we're going
to say print that is not a number.
And then we're going to print again and
say, please try again.
And then we are going to say basically
this exact same functionality.
Great.
And then the only other change we need
to make is to actually specialize this except
statement so that it only works on the
certain type of error that would happen if
someone entered a string into this.
So that type of error is a value
error.
So we'll do that here.
And actually, now that I look at this,
this is a bit unnecessary with two separate
print statements.
So I'm going to copy this here and
do a new line character and try that.
Okay.
So let's run this to see if it
defines properly.
Awesome.
It does.
So we're going to use this portfolio size
function to accept a portfolio size now.
And then we're going to use it again
later to accept a portfolio size for our
better and more realistic momentum strategy.
So now we're going to make sure this
works.
And actually, before we proceed, one thing that's
worth knowing is that this function should be
called portfolio input.
And it doesn't actually have to be called
portfolio input, but it definitely should not be
called portfolio size because then it has the
same name as this variable.
And that's kind of an easy way to
introduce logical bugs into your code is by
having a function and a variable with the
same name.
So we're going to change this to portfolio
input, and then we're going to run this
code cell to define it.
Then we're going to test it by running
portfolio underscore input.
And then we are going to print portfolio
underscore size.
Now here it's especially important to print the
variable that's defined inside the function because we
need to make sure that this global keyword
is working properly.
So let's run this and see what happens.
So another size of your portfolio will enter
a thousand dollars and it should print a
thousand dollars.
Awesome.
Now let's try this again but put in
a string.
So we'll say my portfolio is too small
to matter to you.
That's kind of sad, but we're going to
try it.
And then it says that is not a
number.
Please try again.
Okay.
So my portfolio is one.
Awesome.
So our portfolio input function is working properly.
We can now move on to looping through
our pandas data frame and calculating the number
of shares to buy.
So the first thing we need to do
is actually calculate our position size and to
do that I'm going to actually enter a
slightly larger portfolio.
So we're going to say that's a thousand.
That's a million.
Let's do 10 million.
And what we need to do is calculate
position size.
So to calculate position size we're going to
do position size is equal to float portfolio
size divided by the length of our pandas
data frame.
So we'll say length of final data frame
and then you can take the length of
any column.
I usually do dot index for this.
So this gives us let's print it out
to see what the position size is.
This gives us is that 200,000?
Yep.
200,000.
And that makes sense because we're just doing
10 million divided by 50.
So that kind of math checks out.
And then the next thing to do is
we need to loop through all of the
rows in the pandas data frame.
So for that we're going to say 4i
in range, 0 and then the length of
the data frame.
Final data frame and then let's just print
i to see what happens.
So this goes from 0 to 49.
And if we go back up to our
pandas data frame, we can see that the
last index is 49 and the first index
is 0.
So that's awesome.
That looks like it should work properly.
Let's take away this print statement now.
And we're going to loop through all of
the entries within the number of shares to
buy column.
Now the way to do that is with
pandas loc functionality.
We're going to pass in i for the
row and we're going to pass in number
of shares to buy for the column.
Now what we want to do here is
just make sure that we're accessing this properly.
So we're going to say 0 and then
at the bottom we're going to say final
underscore data frame.
Now if this works properly what should happen
is every entry in the column of number
of shares to buy should be replaced with
a 0.
So let's try this.
Awesome.
Now we're getting a warning here because it's
saying I think this is actually a bug
with pandas although I'm not sure of the
setting with copy warning.
Because it says value is trying to be
set on a copy of a slice from
a data frame.
So we're going to try using dot loc
equals value instead and that's kind of exactly
what we're doing.
So I'm not really sure what's going on
here.
But you can definitely ignore that for now.
So now what we need to do is
calculate actually how many shares to buy.
So to do that we're going to have
to access the price column of the data
frame and we're going to have to divide
the position size by that price.
So first we'll take position size and then
we will divide it by this loc method.
But instead of number of shares to buy
we're just going to replace it with price.
Now let's run this and see what happens.
Awesome so as you can see this is
giving us fractional shares for everything and like
we talked about in the last section of
this course we don't want fractional shares for
this.
So the last thing we need to do
is wrap all of this in a math
dot floor function.
Oops.
And this will round every number in this
number of shares to buy column to the
lowest closest energy.
So let's try that.
Awesome.
It's looking good.
I think we are ready to proceed to
building our better and more realistic momentum strategy.
So let's do that now.
All right.
So it's time for us to build a
better and more realistic quantitative momentum strategy.
Now what does it mean for a momentum
strategy to be better?
There's a lot of different ways you could
define it.
Obviously a strategy is better if it performs
better but it's kind of hard to tell
that in without foresight.
So what I mean by building a better
momentum strategy is that real world quantitative investment
firms typically differentiate between high quality momentum stocks
and low quality momentum stocks.
So a high quality momentum stock is a
stock that over a long period of time
shows slow and steady price returns.
So you know if a stock returns half
a percent every month for a year that
would be kind of like a high quality
slow and steady momentum stock.
A low quality momentum stock might not show
any momentum for a long period of time
and then surge upwards over a short period
of time.
So if you have a stock that returns
zero percent for 11 months and then 10
percent in one month that would be considered
a low quality momentum stock even though its
one year price return would be 10 percent
it might be better than a lot of
other stocks.
So it might be hard to tell why
that definition of high quality versus low quality
momentum stocks is important but the reason why
is because you want stocks that are seeing
price returns in reaction to slow and steady
business progress not one time business news.
So the example that I used here is
I said the reason why high quality momentum
stocks are preferred is because low quality momentum
can often be caused by short term news
that is unlikely to be repeated in the
future like an FDA drug approval for a
biotechnology company.
So this kind of begs the question how
do you identify high quality momentum stocks and
the best way to do it is to
take a basket of different time series momentum
metrics and use them all when calculating with
momentum stocks to include in your strategy.
So to identify high quality momentum we're going
to build a quantitative momentum strategy that selects
stocks that have the highest percentiles of one
month price return, three month price returns, six
months price returns and one year price returns.
And we're going to call this our high
quality momentum strategy so you'll see that I
use the abbreviation of HQM fairly often and
that stands for high quality momentum.
Let's start by building our data frame.
So the first thing we need to do
is actually specify our columns.
This is going to be a much longer
Python list than what we used in the
past for columns because it's going to include
so many more metrics.
So the first thing we're going to use
is ticker and then price and then number
of shares to buy.
We're going to have to create a bunch
of slots for our return metrics and our
percentile metrics.
So to give you like a broad overview
we're going to fill in one column for
each time period that has how much that
stock has returned in the last year and
then right beside that column there's going to
be another column that has the percentile score
of that return relative to all of the
other stocks in the universe.
So we're going to do one year price
return, one year return percentile and then
six month price return and then six month
return percentile and then what's the next one
three months three month price return and then
three month return percentile and then one month
price return and one month return percentile.
Alright, let's run this just to make sure
it's formatted properly.
Awesome.
So now we can create our data frame
which is going to be hqmdataframe is equal
to pd.dataframe and we're going to specify
columns equals hqm underscore columns.
Awesome.
Now let's print this hqmdataframe to make sure
that it is an empty pandas data frame
with the columns that we specified.
Awesome.
Now we can start looping over our simple
string object that we created earlier for symbol
string and symbol strings and here's where we
have to create our batch API calls and
do kind of all the similar logics that
we used before.
So the first thing we're going to do
is execute our batch API call.
So we can actually use very similar logic
to that as before.
So we're going to scroll up here find
our old batch API call and use the
same logic because we don't actually need any
metrics that weren't included in this.
So we'll copy both of these lines so
what we're grabbing here is the batch API
call URL and the HTTP request that grabs
the JSON object from that URL and stores
it in our Python script.
So we'll scroll back down to where we
were here and we're going to add this
to this loop.
All right.
And now we need to loop through all
of the symbols in that symbol string.
So we're going to do for symbol in
symbol underscore string dot split on the comma
characters just like before.
And then in here we need to parse
out all of these metrics.
So whenever I'm doing high level parsing like
this I find that it's easiest to just
literally copy this in and then you can
replace each metric with what you need.
So this is going to be an append
method first.
HQM underscore data frame is equal to HQM
underscore data frame dot append and then in
here we have to pass in all the
things that we've been using throughout this course.
So first it'll be a panda series and
inside that panda series there'll be a python
list.
We'll fill that in later.
And then we have to say index equals
HQM underscore columns.
And then here we have to add the
special ignore index equals true.
All right.
Let's move back inside this python list.
We're going to paste those metrics and then
I'm just going to get the indentation looking
a little better here.
So I'll do that.
All right.
So one easy thing we can do is
all of the percentile metrics we're just going
to fill in to start with N.A.
And we will loop back through all of
those metrics and use the SciPy library to
calculate their percentile scores later.
All right.
So that's easy.
ticker will be replaced by symbol which is
the incrementer of the for loop that we're
in here.
Price will be replaced by the price metric
the price endpoint from the IAC cloud API.
So to do that we're going to create
data and then symbol and then price.
The number of shares to buy just like
before will be filled in with an N
.A. placeholder and the one year price return
we actually already parsed out in our last
example.
So we can just go back up and
copy that down to our new high quality
momentum strategy.
All right.
So here's the original parsing of the one
year price return.
We can copy that.
Scroll back down to where we were.
Sorry right here.
All right.
And we will replace this with the parsing
of the equivalent metric.
Awesome.
And then as you can see here we
are just going to copy this down to
all of the other price returns and then
change them to fit.
So this is month six instead of year
one.
And then we'll copy this and move it
down to here and this will be month
three instead of month six and this will
be month one instead of month three.
All right.
So let's run this to see if it
works and then I'll do a quick recap
of everything we did in that cell.
So there is invalid syntax here.
There's a missing comma there.
Let's try this again.
Length of pass values is eleven index implies
ten.
What's going on?
One two three four five six seven eight
nine ten eleven.
So we were missing a comma here and
if we run this now it should work.
All right.
So that is running correctly it looks like.
We're going to run this again and print
out the final data.
Sorry it's not the final data frame anymore.
It's the HQM data frame and see what
happens.
All right.
So this is a big data frame quite
a bit bigger than the ones we worked
with in the past.
It has ticker price number of shares to
buy one year price return one year return
percentile six month price return six month return
percentile three month price return three month return
percentile one month price return and one month
return percentile.
So we have lots left to do to
this data frame but first we're going to
go through to each of these percentile columns
and we're going to replace these N.A.
values with a percentile score that shows how
high a company's momentum is for that time
period relative to all the other stocks in
the universe.
So this is where we're going to do
this at.
There's going to be a lot of repeated
logic in this section.
So I find the easiest way to do
this is to create a ray called time
periods and then inside this array we're going
to create a string for each time period
that we're going to be looping over and
then we can use string interpolation to make
this much easier.
So we're basically going to say our time
periods are one year and six month and
three month and one month.
Now if it's not exactly clear yet how
we're going to be using this what we're
going to do is we're going to loop
through all of our columns and replace this
value with a value from this list so
that we have to write the logic ones
but we can actually use a loop to
calculate the percentile scores for all of the
percentile columns.
So that's kind of what we're doing here.
Now the next thing to do is create
the actual loop.
So for or row in HQM dot data
frame dot index and then we need to
use another loop inside of this.
This inner loop is going to loop over
the time periods object that we just created.
So for time period in time periods and
then here we're going to use the pandas
loc method to change the value of each
time period column.
So we're going to say HQM data frame
dot loc.
The row is going to be this row
incrementer that we're looping over here and then
the column is going to be we're going
to make an F string here and we're
going to say it's going to look something
like this with an interpolated value.
So let's copy that.
We will put that in here and then
this is the time period that we want
to interpolate.
So we will oh and just so you
know you've probably seen me do this quite
a few times in this course.
All that I'm doing there is I highlight
the string and then I do a you
know I enter the curly bracket character.
So I just enter that character and it
will automatically wrap whatever you have highlighted in
those curly brackets.
It's quite a nice little feature.
Okay, so we're going to replace this with
time period and then what we want to
do is assign that to something.
So to start let's just try assigning them
all to zero and then oops didn't need
to edit that and then at the end
of this code cell we will print HQM
underscore data frame.
Let's see what happens.
All right, so you can see all the
percentile scores are being replaced with zero which
is awesome.
But that's not quite exactly what we need
to do yet.
We need to actually use the sci-fi
stats module to calculate the percentile score based
on whatever is inside of this.
So let's do that now.
The function we're going to use is stats
dot percentile of score and then how this
function works is it takes two arguments.
The first argument is the entire column and
then the second argument is an entry from
that column.
So to start we're going to need the
column which is simply HQM underscore data frame.
I'm going to scroll this up to make
sure you can see it.
And then we need to pass in this
string.
Sorry, not that string.
We need to pass in this string as
the column name and then interpolate in the
time period.
So it will look like this.
Awesome.
Now what we need to do next is
interpolate in the time period value.
So we need to change this to an
F string and then change this to time
period.
Alright, the last thing we need to do
is put a comma here and add in
the actual value that we want to calculate.
So what we're going to do is use
the LLC method.
I'm going to copy this and put it
in as a placeholder and then all I
have to do is change the column name
to match this.
Now I know that this is a really
long Python line.
We're going to refactor it in a second.
So just hang tight.
Copy that and put that in here.
Alright, looks like I got some duplicate Fs
in parentheses.
Okay, let's try this.
Alright, so these look quite good.
You can see that Apple, which has one
of the highest percentile scores for one year,
has a sorry, has one of the highest
momentum scores for one year, has a 99th
percentile.
So that's good.
Everything here looks pretty logical to me.
So what we're going to do now is
refactor this code so it's much more readable.
So first thing we're going to do is
we're going to say change column equals
something and percentile column is equal to something.
The percentile column is this.
So we can copy that and replace this
with this.
And the return column is this or the
change column I mean, sorry.
Alright, so let's go back through and replace
these.
And we'll go down here and replace this
with the same thing.
Okay, this is quite a bit more readable.
Scroll up so you can see what I
actually did here.
So basically, this is saying we're going to
take the HTML data frame and at row
of row and in the percentile column, we're
going to assign it to this calculation stats
dot percentile of score.
And then we're going to call this HTML
data frame at change call.
So this is the column that we're using
to base our percentile calculations on and this
is the entry from that column whose percentile
score we want to calculate.
Now, one other thing that we could do
to this is we could say change this
import somehow.
So if we go back to the top
and we say, copy this and move up
to here and from sci-fi import stats
and then we could say, okay, percentile of
score is what we want.
Score as score.
Okay, so what this is, if we run
this import now, so we're saying from sci
-fi's stats module, import the percentile of score
function as score.
So we can go down and erase that
very long function call and just type score
instead.
And all those changes will make this much
more readable.
It means you won't have to scroll horizontally
to actually see the entire line.
Just so you know, in Python and most
software development, it's kind of considered a bad
practice to have really long lines.
So if you can break it up like
this, it's much more readable and much better.
I think I believe too much.
Take this.
All right.
So that almost fits on one line now.
It's still quite a long call, but if
we run this now, it should have all
the same functionality.
Great.
So now we can move on to actually
calculating the HQM score.
Now, we haven't actually talked about the HQM
score yet, so let's do that now.
The HQM score is just going to be
an arithmetic mean of all the percentile scores
for the momentum returns that we calculated in
the last section.
So to do that, we're going to import
the mean function from Python's built-in statistics
module.
So we're going to say from statistics, import
mean.
Let's run that to see if it works
properly.
Now, the way the mean function works is
you can just say like a few numbers
in here.
What's the mean of two and six?
Well, this should be four and mean takes
one position.
Sorry, this has to be a list in
here.
Yeah.
So that's kind of how the mean function
works.
It's kind of exactly what you'd expect.
We're going to use that to calculate the
average of all the percentile scores that we
calculated in the last section of this project.
And we actually have to do this row
by row.
So the first thing to do is to
create a loop.
We've been using lots of loops in here,
but it's good practice.
So for row in HQM data frame dot
index.
And then the first thing we're going to
do is create a empty python list called
momentum percentiles.
And then we're going to loop through all
of the appropriate columns in the data frame
to get the momentum score for that row.
So let's first do momentum percentiles equals empty
python list.
And then we need to loop through all
of the time periods in the time period
object that we created earlier.
So for time period in time periods.
And then we need to append the momentum
scores to this momentum percentiles list.
So momentum percentiles dot append.
And then in here we want to say
an loc method on the HTML data frame.
HQM underscore data frame dot loc.
The first entry will be the row.
The second entry will be an F string.
And inside that F string we are going
to say time period and then return percentile.
Let's try this just once and see if
we actually get a reasonable momentum percentiles object.
All right.
So we get eighty five, eighty five, sixty
two, thirty five.
Let's go up here and see if that
looks right.
Eighty five, eighty five, sixty two, and thirty
five.
Awesome.
So now what we can do is calculate
the mean and we're going to put that
mean in the HQM score column.
Now looking at this in hindsight, we don't
actually have an HQM score column, do we?
What we're going to do now is go
back up to the top and add our
HQM score to our columns.
So first add this to this column.
For now it's going to be an NA
placeholder just like all of these were.
So we have to add an NA placeholder
here.
And now we just need to go back
to here and rerun all of our code
cells.
If this runs correctly then we know that
everything we just did worked.
Awesome.
So now we need to say that HQM
column needs to be assigned the mean of
all of the values in the momentum percentiles
list.
So we can do that again using an
LLC method.
We'll say HQM data frame dot LLC and
then the first entry of this is row,
the second is HQM store, and this needs
to be assigned the mean of momentum percentiles.
And now if we print the HQM data
frame after running this, all of the entries
in our HQM data frame should have a
HQM score calculated on the very right.
Now the only other change we need to
make is to delete this limiter on the
end of index and let's see how this
looks.
Awesome.
So it looks like we've successfully calculated an
HQM score for every stock in our pandas
data frame.
Let's do a quick recap of what we
did here.
So from the Python statistics module we imported
the mean function and then we looped over
all of the rows in our pandas data
frame.
For each row we re-instantiated an empty
Python list called momentum percentiles and then for
every time period in our time periods list
we loop through the time periods and to
the momentum percentiles list we appended the percentile
scores for that stock and then we used
the LOC method to assign the average of
all of those percentile scores to the HQM
score column.
Then to conclude we printed out that pandas
data frame.
All right, let's move on to selecting the
50 best momentum stocks.
So as before we can identify the 50
best momentum stocks in our universe by sorting
the pandas data frame on the score that
matters stuff.
So in the last section that was one
year price return and in this section it's
actually going to be HQM score.
So the logic here is very similar.
We're going to do HQM underscore data frame
and we're going to use the sort values
method.
Sort underscore values.
And what we're going to pass in here
is the HQM score and then we also
need ascending equals false.
So this will put our highest ranked momentum
stocks at the top and the last thing
we need is in place equals true.
This will cause the sort values function to
actually modify the original data frame.
So let's print it out and see what
this looks like.
All right, we can see our top few
stocks all have extremely high momentum here which
is a sign.
Okay.
The next thing we need to do is
to drop all stocks except for the top
50.
And we saw how to do this earlier.
You just say HQM data frame equals HQM
data frame and then index it from colon
50.
And if we print this out now you
can see that it is shorter than it
was before.
It's hard to tell how much because we
haven't reset the index yet.
So let's do reset underscore index.
Sorry, that's a method not an attribute.
And it goes from 0 to 49.
Awesome.
The last thing we need to do is
place in place equals true into this.
And then if we print it out we
should see our finalized HQM data frame that
goes from 0 to 49 on the index
column.
Awesome.
Great.
So we are ready to start calculating the
number of shares to buy and we'll use
the portfolio input function that we created earlier.
So let's run that.
And name portfolio input is not defined.
That's because I spelt it wrong.
Let's do a $1 million portfolio.
And then in the next section we need
to calculate the number of shares to buy.
And this is exactly what we did before.
So first we need to calculate position size
which is going to be the size of
our portfolio divided by how many stocks are
in it.
So the first thing we need to do
is take the float value of portfolio underscore
size and then divide it by the length
of our HQM data frame.
And you can take any column here.
I usually take the index just like that.
And then let's print out position size.
20,000 that looks right.
Awesome.
Now we need to loop through a row
of our pandas data frame.
So we'll say 4i in HQM data frame
dot index.
And then we need to assign the number
of shares to buy to the number of
shares to buy columns.
So we'll use the LOC method to do
that HQM data frame dot LOC.
And then we'll pass in i comma and
then the number of shares to buy.
To test this out let's assign them all
a value of zero first and then print
it out to see what happens.
That comma shouldn't be there.
Awesome.
Number of shares to buy has all been
assigned zero.
Great.
So like before, what we're going to do
now is we're going to divide our position
size by the company's stock price.
And the easiest way to do that is
to copy this over and replace the number
of shares to buy column with the price
column.
Price.
Okay, this looks good.
We're getting decimals again.
So the last thing to do is wrap
this in the math dot for function.
And just like that, we successfully calculated the
number of shares to buy for each stock
in our HQM data frame.
Oh, there's one thing actually that we did
wrong earlier.
So you know just now that there's a
new column called index.
And the reason why that's there is because
when we did our reset index earlier, I
can't believe I didn't notice this at the
time.
But there's an optional parameter here.
And just to give you a bit more
information about how to use Jupyter Notebooks, if
you want to know what possible parameters are
available for a function or a method, you
can do shift tab and this will pop
up.
And what we want to do is say
drop equals true.
What this does is drop equals true.
What this does is the old index just
gets removed from the pandas data frame completely.
That's not the case.
I'm going to show you exactly how you
debug this.
I'm going to do pandas dot and then
reset index to go to the actual documentation.
Oh, sorry.
I'll tell you exactly what the bug is
here.
The reason why this happened is because we
ran this more than once.
So if we just go back up here
to where we initialize the HQM data frame
and then run all the way down, this
problem will be solved.
See, just like that it's gone.
It goes index and then ticker.
Okay.
So just to recap, we should have originally
put this here.
Drop equals true in our reset index method.
We didn't and that caused there to be
an extra index column, which we've now fixed.
So now when we run this, we get
the number of shares to buy and all
the other columns we need.
All right.
So the next thing we need to do
is format our pandas data frame into a
Microsoft Excel document for use by non-technical
OSI users.
So the first thing we need to do
to do this, we're going to actually back
up a bit.
To do this, we're going to be using
the same library as we did in the
last project, which is XLSX writer.
And to start, the first thing we need
to do is initialize a writer object.
So to do that, you do writer equals
kd.xcel writer.
And then the first thing you need to
pass in is the name of the Excel
file that you want to create.
In this case, we're going to call it
momentum underscore strategy.xlsx. The next thing you
want to add is the engine, which is
engine equals xlsx writer.
All right.
So the next thing we need to do
is say H2M data frame dot two underscore
Excel.
And the first argument of this function is
going to be the writer object we just
created.
The second argument is going to be the
sheet name.
In this case, it's going to be sheet
underscore name equals momentum strategy.
And the last argument is going to be
index equals false.
All right.
So run that code cell and we can
proceed.
Now, the next thing we need to do
is actually create the formats that we need.
We actually created all of these formats in
the last section of this course.
So or in the last project of this
course, I should say.
So I'm not going to make you work
through this again.
Instead, we're just going to run this code
cell to proceed.
And now we need to actually loop through
the columns format dictionary again to apply the
formats that we created to the columns that
we have.
So the easiest way to do this, in
my opinion, is to scroll all the way
back here to where we initially created our
columns, which is right here.
And then I'm going to copy all of
these and use this as kind of a
basis for our dictionary that we're going to
build.
All right.
So we're going to paste that there.
Now we need to start with column name.
So it's just going to, we're just going
to be doing this to start A, B,
C, D, E.
Now note that if I was in like
an actual development environment, I typically write big
programs in the VS code.
I can do this much faster with multi
cursor.
Jupyter notebooks are better for visualizations and other
sorts of things, though.
All right.
So our columns are going to be from
A through L.
And then we're going to want to wrap
each of these inside of a list.
Now, depending on your operating system, there's different
ways that you can enable this multi cursor
functionality that I'm using right now.
I am using Linux and I'm just control
clicking so that I can add the start
of the list to each line.
And then, oops, I'm going to move back
to the start of the list.
Oh, shoot.
Try this again.
Now what I'm going to do is
try to move to the end of the
line and add the closing list brackets.
Not going to be super pretty because some
of these have columns and some of them
don't.
Move back before the karma.
Try that.
Okay.
What do we have?
Any of these broken?
The last one is great.
Okay.
So now we have a columns format dictionary
where the keys are each column letter and
the values are a list with one item
where that one item is the name of
that column.
The last thing we need to do is
work through these one by one and apply
the template we want.
So this will be a string underscore template.
Price will be dollar underscore template.
Number of shares to buy will be string
integer template not string template.
One year price return will be percent template.
One year return percentile.
So most of these are going to be
percent template moving down.
So I'm just going to copy this and
paste it.
All right.
This is looking good so far.
Let's run this code cell next to make
sure that this dictionary is actually formatted properly.
So it ran correctly, which is good.
All right.
So the next thing we need to do
is move through every key in this dictionary
and apply the right formats to that column.
So let's try this.
We're going to say for column in column
underscore formats dot keys and let's just print
column and make sure this is working right.
A B C D E F G H
I J K L.
That looks good.
All right.
The next thing we need to do is
use the method for Excel as a writer
that actually applies a format to a specific
column.
As we saw in the last project, the
way to do that is we need to
call the writer object and then from that
writer object we need to access its sheets
attribute, which is a list of all the
sheets in the Excel file.
And then we need to access the momentum
strategy tab from that list.
And then we need to call the set
column method on that.
I was going to take three parameters.
So let's put two commas in here to
reflect that.
The first parameter is the format that we
want to apply.
So the first parameter is the column that
we want to apply the format to.
So it will look something like this A
through A.
The second parameter is the column width, which
we're going to say is 18 pixels.
Actually, let's do something like 22.
And then the last is which column we're
going to want to apply to that.
So we'll say string underscore format.
And then let's just test that this is
working.
I will say writer dot save.
And then if we run this, what happens
writer dot sheets and momentum strategy string format
is not.
Oh, it's because string template.
All right.
Now let's go to our folder and see
if this is working right.
Starter files, momentum strategy.
So it's there, which is good.
If we open this up, we can see
that the get out of here.
We can see that the first column has
been formatted properly.
We're going to go format the headers in
the same way that we did in the
last section.
So don't worry about that yet.
All right.
So now we need to change this set
column method such that it actually is dynamically
applying formats to each column in the deadline.
So first thing to do is change the
column like this.
And the second thing to do is to
add a to here, we're going to access
the column format dictionary.
We're going to pass in the column key.
All right.
Let's try that.
What happens now columns is not defined.
That's because that should be column.
Now if we go to our Excel file,
it's still not working.
And that is we saw this in the
last project too.
We need to go back up and reinitialize
our writer object and go down to the
bottom again.
All right.
What is happening here?
We have some kind of bug on writer
dot save.
Why is that save?
Oh, I see.
Okay.
So here in the writer dot sheets dot
set column method, this is actually a list
and we need to actually parse it to
get the format that we want.
That format is in the second item of
the list, which is that index one.
So if we pass one there, then this
should work properly and we can go see
our, oops, ignore that.
We can go see our newly formatted Excel
file.
All right.
So the formats are being applied to each
column properly.
You can see that they're not actually wide
enough because the column names in this project
are longer than the column names in the
last project.
So let's change that 22 to 25.
And then the last thing we need to
do is actually format the column headers.
And we saw in the last section that
the easiest way to do that is just
overriding them using the right methods.
So the right method is similar to the
set column method, except instead of taking an
entire column for the first one, it takes
just a cell from a column.
So what we're going to do here is
we're going to access the column and then
one.
So that's the first cell of that column.
Here we're going to specify the column width.
And then here we are going to do
the exact same thing and apply the format
from the second entry of that list.
All right.
Let's go back to the top of our
formatting the Excel format section, run through all
of this again.
And with any luck, this should be formatted
exactly like we want.
There we go.
All right.
So you can see that this is not
good because what is going on in this
top row?
Well, oh, I see.
This doesn't actually take column width.
This takes the value that we want to
put in it.
And that's just a mistake on my part,
a logical mistake.
That should be this list at index zero.
So let's copy that list, put it here
and put index zero.
We'll move this writer dot save method back
down to the last column of this Jupiter
notebook or the last cell of this Jupiter
notebook rather then we'll move back up to
where the writer object was initialized and run
it to the bottom.
Now when we open up our Momentum Strategy
Excel file, we should see that the entire
notebook is done.
We have ticker, price, number of shares to
buy, one year price return, one year return
percentile, six month price return, six month return
percentile, three month price return, three month return
percentile, one month price return, one month return
percentile and HQM score.
Now you can see that all of these
aren't actually formatted like they should be.
So all these percentile scores are multiplied by
I guess 100 over what their actual value
should be.
So let's go back into our notebook and
fix that.
If we scroll down to the bottom, we're
going to scroll up here.
We're going to go all the way back
to where our percentile scores were originally calculated.
And that is right here, I think.
Yeah, so no, sorry, this is the HQM
score.
We need to go up a little bit
further.
Right.
So this is where they originally calculated.
We're going to move to the end of
this calculation and divide it by 100.
And then we're going to go back to
where we created our HQM data frame and
run this entire notebook to the very end.
All right.
So this should all run with no problems.
We were waiting on our input here so
I'll do a million dollars again.
And this should run to the bottom with
no problem.
All right.
Let's check out our new Excel file to
see if those percentile scores were reduced in
magnitude like they should have been.
All right.
So we have one year price return and
99.2. That looks good.
All right.
So you can see that this has been
sorted by HQM score properly.
We go from 99.1 down to 81
.9. And just like that we have a
list of the 50 highest momentum stocks in
the S&P 500 along with the number
of shares that you should buy if you
want to create an equal weight basket on
those 50 stocks.
So that concludes our second project for this
algorithmic trading and Python course.
I hope you enjoyed this project.
In the next section we're going to learn
how to build a value investing strategy that
buys the 50 cheapest stocks in the S
&P 500 based on a composite score of
a number of different value investing metrics.
So I will see you there in the
next project which is going to be a
value investing strategy.
Now for anyone who's not familiar with value
investing it just means trying to buy stocks
and other investments that are cheap relative to
our cell.
For anyone who's not familiar with value investing
it just means trying to buy stocks and
other investments that are cheap relative to our
assessment of their intrinsic value.
There's many different ways to try to estimate
the intrinsic value of the stock or other
investments.
So what we're going to do in this
project is we're going to build a simple
value strategy that relies on one metric and
then we're going to improve that value strategy
by creating a composite value strategy that takes
into account many different metrics when trying to
estimate intrinsic value.
So to start let's navigate into I'm in
my terminal here in my home directory.
Let's navigate into our algorithmic trading and Python
folder and then let's launch our Jupiter notebook.
Sorry before we do that we actually have
to launch our virtual environment and then we
can launch our do the notebook with Python
dash M notebook a Jupiter notebook will open
up in your browser and then you're going
to want to navigate into our starter files
folder and open up the quantitative value strategy
dot IPANB notebook.
All right.
So like I said before value investing means
investing in the stocks that are cheapest relative
to common measures of business value like earnings
or assets.
For this project we're going to build an
investing strategy that selects the 50 stocks with
the best value metrics.
From there we will calculate recommended trades for
an equal weight portfolio of these 50 stocks.
So like before the first thing that we
need to do is import the open source
Python libraries that we'll be using through at
our Jupiter notebook.
So it's going to be the same libraries
as we used in the last section so
import NumPy as MP as a quick recap
NumPy is a numerical computing library that you
need to work with pandas and then we'll
need to import pandas as PD then we'll
need to import XLSX writer.
This is the module that we use to
save our pandas data frame as an Excel
file at the end of this Jupiter notebook.
We're going to import the requests library which
is used for making HTTP requests.
You'll recall from our first project that the
slogan for requests is HTTP for humans which
I quite like and then we're also going
to need to import the stats module of
SciPy.
And the last thing we're going to import
is the math module.
So let's run this code cell to import
all of these libraries into our Python script.
Great, that's done.
The next thing we need to do is
import our list of stocks and our API
tokens.
So just like before we're going to import
our list of stocks into a pandas data
frame called stocks and we're also going to
import our IAS cloud token from our secret
spot.
So let's do that.
First we'll say stocks equals PD dot read
underscore CSV and then we're going to type
in SP and hit tab to auto complete
the file name.
Let's just print this to make sure that
it is working like we intend.
So this is a list of all the
stocks and this is a pandas data frame.
You can get the pandas series that's associated
with the only column that data frame by
parsing out the ticker column.
We'll do that later.
And the other thing we need to do
here is say from secrets import and then
if you just hit tab here it'll give
you some options.
What we want is this IAS cloud API
token.
Great.
So that is how we import our list
of stocks and API tokens.
And the next session we're going to make
our first API call using our IAS cloud
token.
Great.
So like before what we need to do
now is figure out which endpoint of the
IAS cloud API that we need to hit.
So I said in the introduction to this
project that we're going to start by building
a simple value strategy that screens for stocks
based on a single value metric.
And that value metric is going to be
the price to earnings ratio.
Now for anyone who's not familiar with a
company's price earnings ratio it's basically you take
their stock price and you divide it by
how much earnings you expect them to have
over the next year.
So as a basic example let's say we'll
look at Apple again.
So Apple's current stock price is five hundred
and eight dollars and six cents.
Now if you wanted to calculate a price
to earnings ratio for Apple we need to
find an earnings estimate.
So we'll just type Apple earnings estimate.
And it looks like these are all quarterly
estimates and we want an annual estimate.
So whenever you're calculating a price earnings ratio
or any other kind of valuation metric you
always use annual numbers in the denominator.
So it looks like this chart from NASDAQ
provides some estimated earnings metrics.
So yearly earnings forecast.
This is what we want.
And we will use the fiscal year ending
in September 2021.
It looks like they have consensus earnings per
share of sixteen dollars per share.
And that means that to calculate the price
to earnings ratio we just calculate to take
the company's current stock price and divide it
by sixteen.
So what does this give us?
Thirty one.
So that means Apple's price earnings ratio is
thirty one.
That's some high level background on what the
price earnings ratio is.
Fortunately IEX cloud makes it very easy to
access price earnings ratios because if you go
to their documentation they actually provide the price
to earnings ratio natively here.
So we'll just start by trying to control
F find a price to earnings and it
looks like we have it right here.
So PE ratio in this API endpoint refers
to the price to earnings ratio.
Oh I don't know what that was a
link in here somewhere.
I clicked the epic timestamp there.
So anyways PE ratio refers to the price
to earnings ratio for the company.
You know what endpoint is this?
This is the quote endpoint.
Now this is good because one of the
other things that we'll need for this screener
is we're going to need the latest stock
price for the company.
So you look in the JSON response here
you'll notice that they have latest price here
and they also have down at the bottom
PE ratio.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to take this API endpoint.
We're going to copy it into our Jupyter
Notebook and we are going to go back
to the sandbox mode here and get our
base URL for every API call that we're
going to make.
So here is the sandbox base URL.
We're going to copy that move it back
here put it there and you'll recall from
the first project that we actually have to
add stable here to show that stable there
to show that we want the latest stable
version of the API and not any kind
of bleeding edge version of the API that
might have beta features that aren't fully tested
yet.
So this is going to be kind of
a sample API endpoint that we'll use to
get our price earnings ratio.
We're going to call this API URL and
we're going to make it a string.
Now we need to make two small changes
to this.
First of all we're going to take this
field off the end because we don't actually
want to parse a single metric out of
this endpoint.
We want to parse the entire Json response.
We're going to leave symbol there, but we're
going to turn this into an F string
so that that symbol actually becomes interpolated.
Now we need to make a symbol variable
here and we're going to say the symbol
is apple and the next thing we need
to do is create an actual API call
using the requests library.
So to do that we're going to say
data equals requests dot get and then inside
of this get method we're going to pass
in this API underscore URL and then we
are going to print out the status code
of this HTTP request.
Now we've talked about this before, but status
codes tell you whether your HTTP request was
successful or not.
A successful HTTP request will return a status
code of 200 and most erroneous HTTP request
will return a status code that's somewhere in
the 400 range.
So 500 is actually also an indicator error.
So we're going to do a print statement
that prints out data dot status underscore code
and if this gives us 200 then we
know that our first API call was executed
correctly.
All right, so this gives us 400 and
the reason why I've done this actually before
in this course, but I forgot to add
on our authentication token.
So to do that we're just going to
interpolate in this question mark token equals and
then inside these curly brackets we're going to
add our IEX Cloud API token and this
gives us a status code of 200.
Awesome.
Now we'll transform this data variable into a
JSON object using the JSON method which accepts
no parameters and then we can print out
this JSON response to see what it actually
contains.
Okay, so you can see that it has
a number of different data points available in
this HTTP response including symbol, company name, primary
exchange, calculation price, whole bunch of other stuff.
You can see actually since we're using sandbox
mode this primary exchange, quadons, that's not a
real stock exchange.
It looks like they actually just took the
company's real exchange which is NASDAQ, spelled like
this, NAS DAQ, and then they scrambled it
or yeah, it looks like they scrambled it
somehow.
Anyways, that's kind of an interesting part of
using the sandbox mode of the IEX Cloud
API.
So what we want out of here is
this latest price endpoint and this PE ratio
endpoint here.
So we'll parse out both of those variables
in the next code cell.
Okay, so the first thing we want to
do is calculate it with the stock price.
So we'll say price equals data, and then
this is just a Python dictionary.
You can actually verify that by just printing
out its type like this.
This will give us a dict.
Yeah, it's a class of dict.
So we'll take out that print statement.
Since it's a Python dictionary, you can access
the value stored in the dictionary by passing
the keys and using square brackets.
We've seen this earlier in this course, but
it's always good to have a little refresher.
So the two things we want are so
we will assign that to the price variable
and let's just print it to make sure
it is parsed out correctly 513.89. That's
awesome.
The other thing we want is price to
earnings ratio.
So we'll say PE underscore ratio equals data.
And then we're going to parse out this
PE ratio string here.
And just like we did with price, we're
going to print this out to make sure
that it is working properly.
PE ratio 39.6. You can see that
this is a little bit higher than the
31 PE that we calculated manually.
And that's probably because IEX Cloud is using
a different kind of earnings.
One of the tricky things about running any
kind of value strategy quantitatively like this is
that when you're using earnings or any kind
of other fundamental metric, there are numerous different
ways that they can be calculated.
You can use earnings estimates, which is what
I did in my example.
You can also use trailing earnings, which some
people believe are more reliable because they're actually
reported earnings instead of relying on someone's estimate.
But if you ever calculate a PE ratio
and you're confident that your math is right,
but it doesn't match someone else's math, the
reason why is probably because they're defining the
ratio slightly differently.
So when you're doing any kind of work
like this in the future, it's always good
practice to strictly define what you're doing.
So if you're using trailing earnings, say I'm
using trailing earnings when I'm calculating my PE
ratio.
If you're using forward earnings, you might want
to call it a forward PE ratio instead
of just PE ratio so that it removes
that ambiguity.
Alright, so like before, we can now move
on to executing a batch API call.
And just like I did in the momentum
strategy for this course, I've actually provided some
reusable code that we have used earlier on
so that you don't actually have to kind
of redundantly write the same code over and
over again.
Although if you're up for the practice, what
you could do is just delete this entire
code cell and try to write our chunks
function and our symbol strings variable from scratch.
So for now, for the sake of brevity,
I'm going to just run this code cell
and proceed with executing our batch API call.
So actually before I do that, I'll give
you a quick recap of what's going on
here.
So first off, this comment at the top
just tells you where I sourced this chunks
function from.
Since I didn't write this myself, it's always
good to attribute a function to wherever you
received if it's someone else's work.
So what does this chunks function actually do?
This chunks function takes in a list, which
is this LST, and it also takes in
this variable n.
And what it does is it, you can
see in the doc string here that it
yields successive and sized chunks from lists.
And to be more specific, if you have
a list of five hundred and five, like
this, which is what we're going to pass
in, it will return five lists of, and
sorry, you pass in a list of five
hundred and five and a value of n
of one hundred.
It will pass you back a list that
is five entries of length one hundred and
one entry of length five.
So that's what that is.
Next up, we create a list using this
chunks variable that takes all of our stocks
and divides them into five lists of length
one hundred and one length of list five.
And then we create an empty symbol strings
list.
And then with this for loop, we take
every group of stocks that's in the symbol
groups variable and we create a comma separated
string that has all of the tickers from
each list.
And if you want to see what those
look like, we can actually uncomment this print
statement and run this code cell.
So you can see, this is one list.
This is another list.
This is the next list.
This is the end of the fourth.
This is the end of the fifth and
this is the entire fifth list, which is
shorter because it wasn't long enough to actually
fill out the length of one hundred that
was specified by the function.
Okay.
And then the last thing that's done in
this code cell is we specify the columns
for our pandas data frame.
So the columns are ticker, price, price earnings
ratio and number of shares to buy.
So I'm going to run this again with
this print statement comment today to remove that
large print.
Okay.
We can now move on to writing code
from scratch.
So the first thing that we want to
do is to create a blank pandas data
frame.
And we saw how to do that.
We're going to call it final data frame
and we're going to assign it a value
of PD dot data frame.
And within this class instantiation, we're going to
pass in columns equals my underscore columns.
Now we saw before that we could have
just called this columns, but then you have
columns equals columns and that can be a
bit unreadable.
So this is what we're going to do
to make sure that that data frame was
created properly.
We're going to print it out.
And as you can see, it is an
empty pandas data frame with four columns.
And the column names are the four names
that we specified in this list in the
previous code cell.
So now that that's done, what we need
to do is we need to loop over
every symbol string in our symbol strings object.
And to do that, we're going to say
four symbol string in symbol strings.
And then we need to actually create another
loop inside of here that loops over every
ticker in that symbol string.
So we're going to say four symbol in
symbol underscore string got split.
And you'll recall from the last two projects
that if we call this split method, what
it does is it basically does the opposite
of this join method that we saw in
the last code cell.
So this is what our loop is going
to be.
And then we're just going to print out
symbol.
And this will allow us to make sure
that we're actually iterating over every symbol in
our universe.
Great.
So it goes all the way from A
and this should go to Z because these
are in order.
Yep, all the way down to Z.
So that looks like it's working okay.
All right.
So within the first four loop but outside
of the second four loop, we're going to
create a variable.
We're going to call that variable batch API
call URL.
And what is this going to be?
It's going to be a URL that is
a string and it's going to be an
F string and it's going to query this
endpoint that we used earlier, this quote endpoint
for every stock in our universe.
And it's going to do that in batch
API calls for a hundred stocks at a
time.
Now to get the proper syntax for that,
we're going to go back to the IEX
Cloud docs and we're going to search for
batch API call.
And that doesn't come up with anything.
So I'm just going to search for batch
and here you can see batch requests.
Now I'm going to scroll down here to
this example, which is what we copied in
the past.
I'm going to copy the link address.
I'm going to go back to my Jupiter
notebook and I'm going to paste that in
here.
And then we have to make a few
modifications.
So the first thing we want to change
is the symbols.
And what we're going to do here is
we're going to actually change them into an
interpolated value.
This interpolated value should be symbol underscore string.
Now, what is that symbol string variable?
It is the iterator of this first for
loop.
So it will be if you uncomment this
and run this.
This is one example of such a symbol
string that you can interpolate into that API
call URL.
So we'll comment that out and run it
again.
Great.
So there's a few other changes that we
have to make to this batch API call
URL.
One of the first things is that if
you look at the types of API endpoints
that we're hitting here, we have quote, we
have news and we have chart.
We actually only need the quote endpoints.
So let's take away all the other ones.
Awesome.
And then there's two other parameters specified here,
range and last.
And we don't need either of those.
So we can take them both off and
replace them with our token equals IEX five
URL.
All right.
So let's just run this to make sure
that that's formatted properly.
And instead of this print statement, we're going
to comment it out and just replace it
with a pass keyword.
Oops, ignore that.
All right.
So we're going to replace this with a
pass keyword.
Great.
So that ran properly, which indicates that the
syntax is okay.
Now it's time for us to actually, so
we've created our API call URL, but we
haven't actually executed the HTTP request yet.
And that's what we'll do next.
So to do that, we're going to use
the requests library to execute a get request.
And we're going to store that response in
a variable called data.
So data equals requests, press dot get.
And we're going to pass in batch API
call URL.
And then we're going to call the JSON
method on that.
Actually, no, we're just going to leave it
as is and we're going to print data
dot status underscore code for each one.
Now, since there's six entries in our list,
if everything is working properly, then they should
print 200 six times.
We get 403 for each one.
Now, this is actually interesting.
So I mentioned earlier that 400 and 500
codes and when I say 400 and 500
codes, I don't mean exactly 400 and exactly
500.
I mean anything from 400 to 499 and
anything from 500 to 599.
These are generally indicate errors.
So let's go look exactly what type of
error this is.
I'm just going to type HTTP 403, run
a search and Wikipedia is actually pretty good
resource for this.
It says the HTTP 403 is an HTTP
status code, meaning access to the requested resources
forbidden for some reason.
Now, this is a very, very specific HTTP
response that usually means that you have you
not entering the proper API token and I'll
show you exactly why that is.
I know without looking because we didn't change
this cloud keyword to sandbox.
If we do that again and run it,
we should get six 200 codes.
Awesome.
123456.
Great.
So the next thing we need to do
is actually parse the data and using an
append method, add it to the final data
frame.
So we've seen this before.
What we need to do is add that
here.
We'll take away this print statement and pass
keyword and then we'll add the final underscore
data frame equals final underscore data frame dot
append.
And then within this append method, we need
to create a panda series.
We've seen this before and within that panda
series, we need to create a Python list.
So what goes inside this Python list?
We need basically one data point for every
column.
We need ticker price price earnings ratio and
the number of shares to buy.
So we'll say symbol.
That's our ticker.
We'll say data and then we'll parse out
the latest price data point.
And then we'll say data and we'll parse
out the P.E. ratio data point.
And then for the number of shares to
buy, we will parse out nothing and just
say n under n slash a.
Now for this panda series, we have to
specify what the index is.
We'll say index equals my columns.
This tells the append method which columns of
the pandas data frame need to be considered
when you're appending it each time.
So that's very important.
And then we also need to add ignore
underscore index equals true.
All right.
So if we run this code cell now
and then print out our final data frame,
we should get a data frame that has
505 rows and each row corresponds to one
stock with the four metrics that we selected.
So with any luck, it should run successfully
and we're getting response object is not subscriptable.
I'll show you what the problem is here.
When we ran our HTTP request, we didn't
do dot JSON on the end to actually
turn it into a Python dictionary.
So if we run this now, that should
be fixed.
Latest price.
Oh, I grossly oversimplified the parsing here.
So since this is a batch API call,
we actually need to do multiple levels of
parsing.
The first is symbol.
The second is which endpoint you want to
hit.
So if we add that to both of
these parses, we should be okay.
All right, so here's our data frame.
It goes from index zero to index five
hundred and four, which indicates that all five
hundred and five stocks have been successfully added,
and it has four columns, ticker price, price
to earnings ratio, and the number of shares
to buy.
So now that that's done, we can move
on to removing glamour stocks.
All right.
So now we need to remove the glamour
stocks from our pandas data frame.
And for anyone who's not familiar with the
term glamour stock, it's basically the term that's
used in the data frame used to describe
the opposite of a value stock.
So if a stock ranks very poorly on
value metrics, then instead of being called a
non-value stock or something like that, it's
just called a glamour stock.
Now, since the goal of this strategy is
to identify the 50 best value stocks from
our universe, our next step is to remove
glamour stocks from the data frame.
And to do this, we'll kind of follow
similar logic as we did before.
We're going to sort the pandas data frame
such that the stocks with the lowest price
to earnings ratios are at the top, and
then we're going to remove all of the
entries from the data frame, except for stocks
that fall below the top 50 in that
ranking scheme.
So let's do that.
The first thing we need to do is
sort the pandas data frame.
And through that, we will say final data
frame dot sort underscore values.
Now, you'll recall that this is the exact
same method applied to the pandas data frame
that we use to sort values in the
momentum strategy section of this course.
And then what we want to pass in
first is the column that we want to
sort out, and that is price to earnings
ratio.
I just tried to do a tab auto
complete and it didn't work.
So what I'm going to do is just
go up here and copy this.
That means I don't have to worry about
making sure I get the capitalization right and
everything.
The next thing we need to do is
specify the ascending parameter.
Now we want it to be descending, which
means that sending is equal to false.
And the last thing we need to say
is in place equals true.
This parameter tells pandas that instead of just
returning a modified data frame, we want to
modify the original data frame.
Let's print out the final data frame object
to see if this worked correctly.
So as you can see, we have a
price earnings ratio of 2400 at the top
and a price earnings ratio of not at
the bottom.
I actually did this backward.
This should be true.
Now we see that our lowest values are
at the top and our highest values are
at the bottom.
Now, one important thing to know about this
is that since ascending defaults, having a true
value, we can actually remove this completely and
it'll give us the same output as you
see.
Another thing that's worth mentioning is that all
of these stocks that have negative price to
earnings ratios, if you think about the mathematical
definition of the price earnings ratio, it's price
divided by earnings.
So in order for price to earnings ratio
to have a negative value, then either price
has to be negative or earnings has to
be negative.
Now, stocks can't actually have a negative price.
So what this means is that these stocks
have negative earnings.
There is kind of a wide body of
evidence to say that you might not want
to invest in stocks that have negative earnings.
So in a real investment strategy, you may
want to remove all stocks that have negative
price to earnings ratios.
And one easy way to do that would
be something like this.
Final data frame such that final data frame
at the price to earnings ratio column is
greater than zero.
Now, what does this return?
Should return the final data frame with all
of the negative values removed.
So we're going to include this and to
actually modify the original data frame, we have
to assign it.
You'll notice that if we print this, this
gives us the final data frame with negative
values.
So what we're going to do is take
this out.
We're going to say final data frame is
equal to that.
And then we need to return just the
top 50 stocks.
According to this order schema, we saw how
to do that in the momentum project of
this course.
It's pretty easy to say final data frame
is equal to final underscore data frame.
And then you want to access out with
square brackets colon 50.
Now, if we print this, it should be
a data frame that ranges from zero to
50.
Okay, so this looks good to me.
There's a couple of things we can do
to make sure that this is working properly.
We can print its length.
This should be 50.
Awesome.
And then the last thing we want to
do is reset its index so that the
index actually runs from zero to 50.
So we'll do reset underscore index.
What does this give us?
All right.
As you can see, this now goes from
zero to 49, which means there's 50 entries
in the pandas data frame.
The only other thing we need to do
is get rid of this new index column.
We saw one way to do it in
the last section of this course.
I'm going to show you a different way
now.
First, one thing I forgot here is we
want to say in place equals true within
this.
And that means that the reset index method
will actually modify the original data frame.
Now, if we print this out again, we
should see the modified data frame.
Awesome.
And since I ran this twice, we actually
have two separate reset indices.
So let's go back up here and we'll
rerun this.
We run this and we run this and
we should just have one duplicate index.
Okay.
What we want to do now is we're
going to call the drop method and we're
going to pass in the index column.
We're also going to pass in in place
equals true.
Here, what does this give us?
It gives us a key error because index
is not found in access.
Okay.
Uh, the drop method by definition automatically acts
on rows, not on columns.
So to change that, we have to say
access equals one.
What does this give us?
Cannot insert level underscore zero.
That's because we already ran that cell.
So if we run this now, what happens?
All right.
Everything looks to appears to have worked properly.
So we'll print this out again to make
sure it looks good.
Awesome.
So now let's just do a quick recap
of what we learned in this section.
Um, I've explained briefly what a glamor stock
is.
Uh, we sorted our final data frame such
that the stocks with the lowest price to
earnings ratios were at the top of the
data frame and we specified the in place
equals true parameters so that the original data
frame was actually modified and it didn't just
return a modified data frame.
So that's what that line does.
Next up we, uh, we sorted the data
frames such that all rows that have a
price to earnings ratio value below zero were
dropped from the data frame.
Then we trim the data frame to only
include the stocks with the 50 lowest price
to earnings ratios.
We reset the index and then we drop
the new index column that was created by
way of this reset index method.
Now one important thing to note about this
is that we could have actually specified the
drop parameter here to do the same thing.
That's what we did in the last section.
But the reason why I showed you this
method instead is just to reinforce the idea
that whenever you're doing any kind of software
development, there's usually multiple different ways to solve
a given problem.
So that's that.
Let's now move on to calculating the number
of shares that we need to buy.
Just like we did in the momentum strategy
section of this course, we're going to use
the portfolio input function to do this and
to make things easy for you.
I actually included the portfolio input function there.
I encourage you to try to delete that
formula and recreate it from scratch if you
want the extra practice.
For now, I'm just going to run this
and then I'm going to use the portfolio
input function to accept a portfolio size variable.
So let's do that.
And I'm going to test here that the
try accept value error statement is working by
putting in a string.
So I'm going to say my portfolio is
one million dollars.
And then if I enter this, then it
should print it.
That's not a number.
Try again.
Awesome.
Now I can say one million dollars.
That's six zeros, one, two, three, four, five,
six.
Awesome.
The next thing we need to do is
calculate the position size.
So just like we did before, position size
can be calculated by dividing the portfolio size
by the number of shares in the portfolio.
So we're in the position size divided by
the length of our final data frame.
And you can take any column of this
data frame to find its length.
I'm going to use the index and there's
no kind of right or wrong answer here.
I just, the index is what I typically
use for this.
So that's that.
And this position size should be twenty thousand
dollars, I believe.
Now here it says type error unsupported operand
type.
That's because this portfolio size, despite it actually
being a number, is still formatted as a
string.
So we need to wrap it in a
float function.
This gives us twenty thousand dollars.
Awesome.
Now we need to loop through the every
row in the pandas data frame and modify
the value that's contained in the number of
shares to buy columns.
So to do that, we're going to say
for row in final data frame index.
And then we are going to say final
data frame dot LSE.
This is the exact same method that we
used to modify this before.
We're going to do row and then number
of shares to buy.
Then we're going to use the assignment operator
to say divide our position size by that
stock's stock price.
So if we put pricing here, that should
be the trick.
Now we'll print out our final data frame
to make sure that this is operating correctly.
This looks good.
Let's just compare two stocks here.
So we have a stock at thirty five
dollars and a stock at eighteen dollars.
So this is interesting because this is roughly
double this.
So this should be roughly double this and
it kind of passes the eyeball test.
So that's good.
Now the only other thing we need to
add here is the floor function.
So as you'll recall from the last section
of or the last project of this course,
you can't usually buy fractional shares at some
brokers.
So if we wrap this in the floor
function, it will give us the closest lower
integer to the number of shares that it
calculated.
So if we run this, we can see
that those have all been transformed to integers.
Awesome.
We are now ready to move on to
building a better and more realistic value strategy.
All right.
So it is now time for us to
build a better and more realistic value strategy.
Now, just like in the momentum project that
we built earlier in this course, what we're
going to do to make a better value
strategy is to build a strategy that takes
into account many different metrics.
And the reason why that makes the strategy
better is because every valuation metrics tend to
have certain flaws.
For example, as we saw earlier in this
project, the price to earnings ratio doesn't exactly
work that well with stocks that have negative
earnings.
Similarly, another popular valuation metric is the price
to book value ratio.
And that ratio doesn't work well with stocks
that perform a bunch of share buybacks.
So there's lots of different things to consider
for every valuation metric.
And one common way that investment managers reduce
any of the flaws, reduce the impact of
any specific valuation metrics flaws is by creating
value strategies that take into account a composite
of value.
So instead of just saying we're going to
rank stocks on price to earnings ratio, they
rank percentiles for a bunch of different valuation
metrics and then rank stocks according to the
average of those percentile scores.
So that's exactly what we're going to do
in this section.
Here are all the ratios we're considered.
So price to earnings ratio.
We already saw that.
Price to book ratio.
Now, this is the company's stock price.
The company's stock price divided by its shareholders
equity per share.
The price to sales ratio.
This is the company's stock price divided by
its revenue per share.
Enterprise value divided by EBITDA.
Now that is a more complicated valuation metric.
EBITDA stands for earnings before interest taxes, depreciation
and amortization.
Enterprise value is basically the number that you
would have to pay to buy out the
company in full.
So that doesn't just mean buying it all
of its stock.
You would have to also buy it all
of its debt and any minority share holdings
that exist.
So that's what enterprise value is.
And then another common valuation metric is enterprise
value divided by gross profit.
So all of these five valuation metrics we're
going to now pull in from the IEX
cloud API.
Now to do that, we're going to start
by just making a single API call and
then we will loop through that same API
call for a bunch of different stocks that
are listed in our stocks data structure to
build a pandas data frame that contains all
the data.
So to start, we'll just do this for
one symbol and that symbol is going to
be Apple.
And then we're going to do a batch
API call here.
And unlike before, we're not going to use
a batch API call because we want to
query the IEX cloud API for multiple symbols.
But instead, we have to use a batch
API call because we're querying the API for
multiple endpoints.
So since the different valuation measures listed here
are all so different, they're not all actually
going to be stored in the same endpoint.
So we need to find where they are
in the IEX cloud API and then add
those endpoints to a batch API call URL.
So let's start by just creating the variable
batch API call URL.
And just like before, this is going to
be an F string.
Now let's to make this easy, we're just
going to base this off of the batch
API calls that we executed earlier in this
project.
So let's scroll up and find that.
All right.
So here is where it is.
I am going to highlight all this and
copy it to my clipboard.
I'm going to scroll back down to where
we were just working and paste this in.
Okay.
Now we have to make a few changes
here.
The first is that we need to replace
this symbol string with just symbol and then
let's actually execute an API call against this
to make sure that it's working properly.
So we've seen this many times by now,
but we're going to do data equals and
then to define the variable we're going to
say requests.get and then we're going to
pass in that batch API call URL not
the bad URL.
Batch API call URL.
And then let's do print data.status underscore
code and if this returns 200, then we
know it's working correctly.
That is awesome.
Okay.
So let's go through all of these metrics
one by one.
I'm actually going to copy these and paste
them down here and comment them all out.
Oops.
There we go.
And then underneath each of these comments we're
actually going to parse that value from the
IS cloud API.
So the first thing we need to do
is get the price earnings ratio and we
actually saw how to do this in the
last section of this tutorial.
So if you go back up here, we
are going to go to where we copied
this original batch API call URL.
And we are just going to grab this
parse here.
So it's data and then symbol and then
quote and then PD ratio.
So let's copy that and scroll back down
to where we were just working, which is
right here.
And if we print this, this should give
us what we need.
Okay.
Now we're getting this error response object is
not subscriptable and that's because I haven't called
the JSON method on our API call.
So we're going to add that here and
then we're going to remove this data.status
code because that's now going to return an
error.
Let's run this code cell again.
Great.
So this tells us that Apple has a
current price earnings ratio of 38.84 according
to the IEX cloud API.
Let's now assign this variable to this value
to a variable called PE ratio and we're
going to do similar things down here.
So PB ratio is going to be price
to book ratio.
And for now we're just going to assign
that a value of not a number.
So this is a not a number data
structure that's stored within the NumPy library.
If you've never seen that before.
And we're going to PE, or sorry, PS
ratio.
Same thing, NT.NAN. And then down here
we're going to do EV to EBITDA.
Same thing, NP.NAN. And then we're going
to do EV to gross profit.
EV to gross profit.
Equals NP.NAN. Okay, we've now filled these
all with placeholder values of NP.NAN. Let's
now go into the IEX cloud docs and
figure out where these data points are contained
within the IEX cloud API.
So just like before, all I did for
this was I Google IEX cloud docs and
it's the first non add hit that I'm
clicking.
Alright, so now I'm going to do a
control F search for PB.
And with any luck, this will show us
where the price to book ratio is held.
There were seven hits.
I just searched through all of them.
It wasn't any of them.
So now I'm going to try price to
book.
It only gives two hits and both of
those hits are this value score, which looks
like it's its own composite metric here.
So let's try price to book with hyphens.
There we go.
Price to book.
What endpoint is this?
So this is the advanced stats endpoint.
And to add that to our batch API
call URL, I'm just going to copy it.
And I'm going to add it here right
after the quote.
So comma advanced stats.
So now we are going to print our
data object and see what we have to
parse out.
So do that.
Alright, so we're going to have to do
multiple levels of parsing here.
We're going to print data, Apple, and then
within that we are going to parse out
the advanced stats endpoint.
Alright, so now when we run this code
sale, this will show us what's contained inside
the advanced stats endpoint.
We want PB ratio.
So I'm going to do a control F
for PB here and see if it highlights
anything.
I don't see it there.
So I'm going to do a control F
for book and I see it right there.
So price to book.
Now we can copy this in and parse
it out.
Alright, so this tells us that Apple has
a current price to book ratio of twenty
three point eight eight.
I'm going to copy this and assign it
to our variable of PB underscore ratio.
Then what I'm going to do is I'm
going to remove the final section of parsing
from this line.
I'm going to print out the JSON object
again, and I'm going to try to find
the price to sales ratio.
So just like before, I will start by
saying PS.
There is one hit within this data structure,
but it's TTM EPS.
If you've never seen that before, all that
stands for is trailing twelve months earnings per
share.
And that's not what we want.
So I'm going to do a control F
search again for sales and you can see
right here we have price to sales ratio.
Awesome.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to copy this price to book ratio
data point.
And instead of price to book, I'm going
to change this to price to sales.
And then I'm going to print the PS
ratio so that we can see what value
we get.
So this tells us at the bottom here
that Apple has a current price to sales
ratio of eight dollars and point or sorry
eight point two eight.
So I can delete that.
Now we have to parse out enterprise value
to EBITDA and enterprise value to gross profit.
Now both of these are a little more
complex but where you could still make it
work.
The reason they're more complex is because the
V to EBITDA ratio and the EBITDA gross
profit ratio they aren't actually provided explicitly by
the IEX cloud API.
Instead we're going to have to pull in
their constituent metrics.
So enterprise value and EBITDA or enterprise value
and gross profit respectively.
And then we're going to have to do
the division ourselves.
So to start let's try and find enterprise
value.
We'll create a variable called enterprise value.
And to start we will assign that a
value of NP dot man.
And then we're going to want to do
a control S search within this endpoint for
enterprise.
And interestingly enough the IEX cloud API does
provide one of the enterprise multiples but it's
enterprise value to revenue which is not one
of the ones we're going to use.
So instead we're going to pull in this
enterprise value endpoint.
We're going to grab this for price to
sales and we're going to copy it down
to the enterprise value variable and then replace
this with enterprise value.
And then let's print it.
Now since Apple is a very large company
this enterprise value should be huge.
Yeah it looks like it's more than two
trillion if I'm just eyeballing it there.
Actually let's divide that by a trillion to
see if I'm right.
One and then we should be nine zeros
one two three four five six seven eight
nine.
Sorry not nine zeros twelve zeros so we
need three more one two three.
And it looks like it's around two point
two trillion dollars of enterprise value for Apple
right now which is pretty crazy.
All right so we have our enterprise value.
Now we need our EBITDA.
Let's do a control F search for EBITDA
and see if it pops up in this
endpoint.
You can see right there that it is
pretty easy to access.
What we'll do is we will just copy
this paste it there.
Change the variable name to EBITDA and then
change the parsing to EBITDA as well.
It's all capital so make sure you capitalize
this as you're working through it.
And then for our EV to EBITDA ratio
what we're just going to do is say
enterprise underscore value divided by EBITDA.
And that ran correctly.
What we need to do now is print
it to see what value we're actually storing
EV to EBITDA.
So this tells us that Apple has a
current EV to EBITDA ratio of twenty eight
point two.
Awesome.
So using this information we can now proceed
to calculating our EV to gross profit.
We already have our enterprise value and it's
stored in a variable up here.
So what we need to do now is
create a variable called gross profit and parse
out the gross profit number from this from
this JSON object.
So to do that I'm going to do
a control F search for gross and you
can see the gross profit metric is right
there.
So what I'm going to do is copy
the parsing that we did for our EBITDA
variable earlier in this code cell.
I'm going to paste it here and then
I'm going to replace the EBITDA parsing with
a gross profit parsing.
Now if we print out gross profit what
does it give us?
This shows you that Apple had gross profit
of I'm going to say that's ten billion.
I'm not really sure just by looking at
it there's no commas which makes it a
little harder to read.
Anyways the number is being pulled in successfully
and that's the main thing.
So now what we're going to do is
say EV to gross profit is equal to
enterprise value divided by gross profit.
And then we will print this on the
next one.
I'm going to print EV to gross profit
and I'm actually going to run this code
cell again without that statement.
So this shows us that Apple has an
EV to gross profit ratio of twenty two
point six.
Okay so we've now done all of the
parsing and calculations that we need to get
all of our value metrics for one stock.
Now it's time for us to generalize this
logic and build a pandas data frame that
stores all of this information.
So we'll do that next.
Now you'll see in the header for this
code cell that it says you'll notice that
I use the abbreviation RV often and that's
sort of the acronym that we're going to
use for robust value which is kind of
the name I'm going to use for this
investment strategy.
It's kind of the equivalent to high quality
momentum that we used in the last project.
So as before the first thing we need
to do is say RV underscore columns and
then we need to create a Python list
that defines all of the columns that we're
going to use in our pandas data frame.
So the first thing will be ticker.
That's the stock ticker of the company we're
looking at.
The next thing will be price and that
is the stock price of the company we're
looking at.
The next thing is number of shares to
buy.
Just like in our first two projects that
tells our trader team how many shares of
the specific security to buy when they're rebalancing.
And now we're going to start working through
all of our valuation metrics.
So more specifically we're going to say price
to earnings ratio.
And then we're going to say a percentile
score for price to earnings ratio.
So we'll call that PE percentile and then
we'll, we need a column for our price
to book ratio, so price to book ratio
and then we need a column for the
percentile score of price to book, so PB
percentile.
And then we need a column for our
price to sales ratio.
So that's priced to sales ratio.
and then we need price to actually we'll
say PS percentiles and that matches the abbreviation
that we use for our first two percentile
scores and then we need enterprise value divided
by earnings before interest taxes depreciation amortization so
so for that we're just abbreviated right from
the get-go because it's quite long and
we will say EV to EBITDA and then
on the next line we will do a
percentile score for that metric so EV to
EBITDA percentile and then we need our EV
to gross profit so we'll say EV to
GP and then EV to gross profit percentile
the last thing we need to do is
calculate our robust value score so we'll do
that right from the get-go this time
our RB score awesome I'm gonna run this
code so just to make sure that the
syntax here is all working that is awesome
we can now move on to creating an
empty pandas data frame so we'll call this
data frame RB data frame and that stands
for robust value data frame and to associate
it we're gonna say PD data frame and
then inside of this class call we're gonna
say columns equals RV underscore columns and what
does that look like it doesn't look like
anything because I didn't get it yet so
let's add our V data frame on the
last line and as you can see this
has all of the columns that we specified
and we are ready to start creating our
loop now we have already created our symbol
strings object earlier in this project so if
you scroll up here a little further what
am I looking for here it is so
this code cell was already provided when you
guys open this up and this has created
symbol strings that we can loop through when
creating our data frame so we don't have
to do that again because those variable values
are already stored in this Jupyter Notebook so
we're ready to create the loop what we
need to do now is say for symbol
string in symbol strings and to make sure
this is looping correctly let's just print out
the symbol string awesome that looks good and
then within this loop we have to create
our batch API call and we're gonna do
that in the same way that we did
before we're first going to create the URL
and then once the URL has been created
we're going to use our requests library to
actually execute the HTTP request so we'll call
the URL batch API call URL and then
we already created this URL a few cells
earlier so we can just go up to
here and copy this with a few minor
changes so the minor changes I was referring
to are that we have to replace this
symbol with symbol string and then it should
be good to go to make sure this
is working properly I'm just gonna print the
batch API call URL and let's see what
happens awesome you can test easily whether any
of these is working by just clicking on
and what that will do it was in
a separate browser window it will open up
the JSON object that you'll be pulling in
so let's see awesome in a browser window
like this this is pretty useless because you
can't really manipulate it but that's a quick
easy way to tell that your API calls
working right now let's execute our HTTP request
so we're gonna do that in the exact
same way that we did before data is
equal to requests.get and then inside that
get method pass in batch API call URL
and then we're gonna print out data.status
code and since we already clicked on the
URL to open up the JSON object in
a separate tab a few moments ago we
know that these API calls are working but
printing the status code is another way you
can check it so if these API calls
are functioning as we want them to this
should print out HTTP code of 200 for
each API call so let's see one two
three four five six and there should be
six so that is awesome all right so
now we're ready to start parsing our data
frame and to do that the first thing
you need to do is add the JSON
method to the request.get method and what
this does is it turns this object which
is a request response object into a JSON
for us to manipulate now if you print
out the data for each one we'll get
a bunch of big JSON objects and this
is what we need to start manipulating so
now that we're in here we need to
loop through every ticker within our symbol string
and append the data for that ticker to
our empty pandas data frame to do that
we need an inner loop and that inner
loop will look like this we'll say for
symbol in symbol underscore string split and then
we're going to split on the common character
just like we did in the other two
projects to make sure this is working properly
let's print out our symbol awesome so you
can see we're going through all of the
symbols in our stocks pandas data frame that
we created at the very start of the
alphabetical order okay so now that that's done
we can start using the append method to
add data to our empty pandas data frame
and to do that what we're gonna say
is our V data frame is equal to
our V underscore data frame dot append now
we're gonna use same we're gonna use similar
logic inside of this append method as we've
used earlier in this course so we need
a series and then inside of that pandas
series we need a Python list and we
also need to specify index is equal to
our V columns now in case you're not
remembering what this does this index equals our
V columns specifies which columns of the empty
pandas data frame each item of this pandas
series should be appended to and then inside
of the pandas series we want to add
the ignore index equals true now I haven't
really done a super guitar explain this but
to be very specific what this does is
it means that every row that you add
to the pandas data frame will have its
index column automatically calculated for you so the
first row will have index 0 the second
row will have index 1 the third row
will have index 2 the 50th row will
have index 49 and so on so that's
what this ignore index does now within this
pandas series we need to parse out all
of these data points so like I did
in the last project what I'm going to
do here is I'm actually just going to
copy these in and since it's a comma
separated list we can just replace each element
of this list with the data that we
want to parse out so we'll do that
one by one ticker we want to replace
with a symbol and remember that symbol is
the incrementer of the inner for loop that
we're building here for price we want to
parse it with price and we saw how
to do that up here that's actually not
true we didn't see how to do that
there but what we can do is go
back up to our earlier project where we
did this for for just a screener that
only factors in price earnings ratio and we
can copy this parsing that we used here
so we'll do that and scroll back down
here and then we want to replace this
price with that awesome now number of shares
to buy just like in the in the
other projects that we work on in this
course we're just going to replace with a
placeholder value and a price earnings ratio we
actually parsed in the last code cell along
with all of the other valuation metrics that
we need so what we can do here
is just say copy that and add it
where the price earnings ratio is and then
we come to the section where we need
price to earnings ratio percentile and all of
the percentile scores in this pandas data frame
just like in the ones that we worked
with earlier in this course we're going to
replace them with a placeholder value of NA
because in order to calculate percentiles you need
the pandas data frame to be fully populated
first so we will calculate these a little
later on in this project for now we're
going to replace them all with NA and
one more and for that matter this robust
value score in the last column also needs
to replace with NA so let's do that
now too all right the next thing we
need is our price to book ratio and
just like the price to earnings ratio we
had parsed that out in the last code
cell so I'm going to copy that I'm
going to add that here oh sorry not
there down here I knew something didn't look
great so I got there we're gonna do
the same thing with our price to sales
ratio so that's right here all right now
for EV to EBITDA and EV to gross
profit we actually have to do some special
logic here because there are metrics that are
used in both of those calculations that aren't
available for every stock so here's how we
handle that the first thing we need to
do is pull in our enterprise value our
EBITDA and our gross profit metrics and we're
going to do that it was side of
this append method so there's enterprise value here's
EBITDA and here is gross profit awesome
and then in here for now I'm not
going to do this special logic that I
just referred to earlier because I want to
show you what happens if you go into
it oh and this isn't EBITDA it should
be enter price value and then here we're
going to enter price on this value divided
by gross profit all right let's run this
and see what happens so far so good
72 and then we get a key error
for a P L and that's because all
of those Apple instances need to be replaced
with a symbol let's do that try that
great we have another key error because there's
more instances of Apple up here that is
embarrassing like I said earlier in this course
I'm not going to edit this out because
I want you to see how I debug
stuff in real time it might be useful
to see the debugging process of a different
developer okay what happens now here's what we're
getting so it says unsupported operand type for
division integer and none type and that's referring
to this line right here okay what's going
on let's print out our enterprise value so
we have a value for enterprise value now
let's print out our EBITDA none now that
is the source of the error so to
fix this we need to find some sort
of workaround to fill this value even when
there's a none type for one of the
metrics that it contains now there's lots of
different ways that you can handle this but
what we're going to do is this I'll
show you so we saw when building our
portfolio input function in earlier projects have this
course that try accept statements can be used
to handle exceptions so that's what we're going
to use we're going to use try this
and if that doesn't work we're going to
make an accept statement that handles specifically the
type of error one counter which is a
type error and then we're going to say
MP not and now because this is in
on a pen statement we actually can't put
it there instead we're going to create an
EV to EBITDA ratio and put this outside
of the append statement I'll show you more
about what that looks like in second after
I create these okay so this is going
to be put inside the append statement right
here after we create all these and since
the indenting is in a loop I have
to tab that in and then we will
replace this with EBITDA now okay what this
does is it tries to calculate EVD EBITDA
using this and if that fails because of
a type error then it will fill it
in with NP dot NAN now that's not
good because NAN stands for not a number
and how are you supposed to source dogs
on value metrics that aren't numbers well we're
going to see later on in this section
or later on in this project I should
say that there's a number of different ways
that you can handle missing data in the
pandas library to fill in that values that
aren't there with reasonable values by performing calculations
on the other values in the data set
so I will see more about that later
but the main idea to remember now is
that even though we're filling our pandas data
frame with null values now those aren't going
to stay there for our final calculations because
we're going to replace them with something more
meaningful later okay the next thing we need
to do is we haven't seen it yet
but this type error happens with the gross
profit metric as well because some companies don't
actually report gross profit depending on how what
what their operations look like in those sorts
of things so what we're going to do
is create a similar EB to gross profit
metric here and use the exact same type
error exception handling to to handle this okay
so if you two gross properties will enterprise
value divided by gross profit this looks good
the only other thing we need to do
is take this variable and replace the actual
divisor in the expense data okay now I'm
going to delete this other code cell that
we were working with and run this again
to see if it works so far so
good awesome so that code cell ran with
no problem let's print our data frame now
see what it looks like awesome so we
have ticker stock price number of shares to
buy price to earnings ratio PE percentile price
to book ratio PB percentile price to sales
ratio PS percentile Evita percentile Evita GP percentile
and the RE score everything looks like it
was added properly here so we can now
move on to dealing with missing data in
our data frame now our data frame contains
missing values because we use that try accept
logic in the last section to fill in
missing values whenever the IES cloud API provided
a non response for a metric that we
were using and that's basically what this is
it says our data frame contains some missing
data because all the metrics we require are
not available through the account we're using so
to see where this missing data is what
you can do is use the pandas is
null method so this is kind of the
the statement you execute to see all call
sorry all roads that have missing data in
our data you say RV data frame and
then in square brackets you would say RV
data frame is null and then on that
isn't all you want to say any and
then access equals one okay so to break
this down we're taking our RV data frame
and then we are filtering in the square
brackets to say any part of RV data
frame where the is null method is true
and then on that we want to apply
to any columns and this access equals one
tells us columns not rows so when we
run this this is going to return a
modified version of our pandas data frame that
only contains rows where there's missing data alright
so as you can see there is quite
a bit of missing data and you can
actually see how much there is by calling
the length of this so there's 55 rows
that have some sort of missing data in
the pandas data frame which is about ten
percent of the entire data set so let's
look at this again as you can see
all not all of the indices of the
pandas data frame exists so it starts at
17 18 20 26 there's lots of missing
rows because all the missing rows have no
missing data so let's take a look at
this first row which covers the stock Aflac
which is an insurance company there is a
non-value here for price to sales ratio
there is a non-value actually that's the
only non value for that column now if
you look in other columns like this column
there's a non value for price to earnings
ratio and overall these non values aren't super
problematic because in the next section we're going
to see how to deal with it so
this says dealing with that dealing with missing
data is an important topic in data science
and there's two main approaches you can either
drop the missing data using the drop NA
method or you can replace the missing data
with a fill in a method so the
fill in a method is pretty interesting because
you can actually pass the information that allows
it to fill in missing data with summary
data from that same column so as one
example if we have missing data in our
price to earnings ratio column we can fill
it in with the average value of all
price earnings ratios for all the other stocks
in the data sets so that's exactly what
we're going to do we're going to replace
missing data with the average non null data
point from that column so here's the code
to do this I need to create a
for loop that loops over all of the
columns in our pandas data frame so we'll
say for column in RV underscore data frame
columns and then let's just print this out
to see what's happening great as you can
see this is successfully looping over our pandas
data frames and then what we want to
say is RV underscore data frame dot fill
and a now if you've never used this
before one easy way to see which parameters
it accepts is to mouse into the the
parentheses of the method and then hit shift
tab and this will pop up a little
bit of documentation so what we're going to
do is we're going to say fill in
the missing values with the average value from
that column so to get the average value
we're going to say fill and a and
then we're going to say RV underscore data
frame we're going to select that specific column
from the data frame and then we're going
to call the mean method on dot mean
and one other thing I forgot to add
here is that we don't want to apply
this to the entire data frame we want
to apply to this specific column of that
data frame now the reason why you have
to add this is because if you didn't
for the first iteration of this loop when
it looks to the ticker column it would
fill the entire data frame with the average
value of the ticker column which is not
what we want so if we run this
we get a value error and says could
not convert string to float now the reason
why this is is because you can't actually
so what this is doing is it's trying
to calculate a mean for the ticker column
which is obviously impossible so we actually need
to create a subset of our columns and
to do that the easiest way is probably
to just print out our columns to RV
data frame columns we will grab this and
then we need to modify our for loop
so that it only loops over certain columns
of the pandas data frame so we will
put that there and then does it still
work with it being multi-line it does
awesome so we want to take out all
of our non numerical columns so that would
be all the percentiles it would be PB
percentile PS percentile EV to even data percentile
EV to GP percentile and RV percentile and
I'm actually going to take out this price
column too because there's not going to be
any missing price data all right so if
we run this this shouldn't look a these
all in one line just for readability there
we go all right what happens when I
run this awesome now if we run our
same command from earlier to identify missing data
in our data frame if we have done
this properly this should return an empty data
frame because there should be no values anymore
and there still is why is that this
price to sales ratio still has quite a
bit of no values why is that oh
I see so within this fill in a
method you actually have to pass the in
place true and this says don't just return
the modified column modify the original column instead
so we'll do that and then when we
run this we get an empty pandas data
frame which shows us that we have successfully
dealt with all the missing data in the
original data frame so that's kind of a
high-level introduction of how to deal with
missing data in pandas there's lots of more
information to learn about this and deal with
missing data is a full topic in and
of itself so this is just a high
-level introduction we can now move on to
calculating value percentiles all right so what we
need to do now is we need to
calculate value score percentiles for every stock in
our universe more specifically we need to calculate
percentile scores for the following metrics price to
earnings ratio price to book ratio price to
sales ratio Evita Evita and Evita gross profit
now unlike before we can't use the start
of every string as a way to interpret
in that string because in the last project
we had the same two words at the
start of every momentum metric like an example
would be we had one year price momentum
and one year return percentile so we can't
do that anymore because we use some abbreviation
so if you look here you can't use
price to earnings ratio to find the price
earnings ratio percentile column because there's an abbreviation
so I did that intentionally so that you
could see a different way of approaching this
problem what we're gonna do instead is I
just copied the column names to my clipboard
like this and we are going to turn
this into a dictionary we're gonna call this
dictionary metrics and here's what we're gonna do
so we need to wrap this entire thing
in curly brackets and for every metric column
that column name is going to be a
key for the dictionary and the percentile column
is going to be the value of the
dictionary like that so if we do that
same operation on a few different lines this
will fill it pretty quickly all right
let's put these on their own lines like
that okay so basically what this does I'm
gonna run this code so to make sure
it's formatted properly and the way we're gonna
use this dictionaries we're going to pass in
a a metric and it will return back
the name of the corresponding percentile row so
to calculate our percentile scores we are going
to loop through every metric in this metrics
dictionary so here's how we'll do that we'll
say for metric in metrics dot keys and
then within here we need to calculate percentile
scores and we need to do that for
every row so we need to create an
interlet that says for row in rv underscore
data frame dot index and then here's where
we're just going to print the row now
this should print how many metrics other five
five times this should print zero to five
hundred and four so we have one two
three four five awesome okay now here we
need to use the pandas loc method to
access the percentile score columns now here's how
we'll do that we'll say rv underscore data
frame dot loc and then the first entry
of this loc method will be the row
and the second entry will be the column
name and that will be metric no sorry
that won't be metric that will be metrics
hat metric and this funny looking dictionary access
statement is basically pulling in the percentile column
to make sure that that's working properly let's
just print this and what this should do
is just print a whole bunch of NAs
awesome so this shows that we're accessing all
of the different percentile columns and what we
want to do here is use the percentile
of score to calculate a percentile so to
do that we'll say that is equal to
stats dot percentile of score and then within
this we're gonna have two items so this
will be the entire column and this will
be the value of that row at the
column so to get the entire column we're
just going to say rv underscore data frame
and then we're gonna pass in the name
of the column so that will be metric
and then over here we need and then
over here we want to get the value
of the row at that column to do
that we're gonna say rv underscore data frame
at loc and instead of saying the metrics
dictionary at that metric we're just gonna say
the metric so let's run this and then
print our pen this data frame to see
what that looks like great so
here we have all the percentile scores now
you can see this appears to be right
because here we have a low EV to
GP and it has a low percentile here
is a high EV to GP with a
higher percentile and you can see the same
logic for all of these now just like
before this Python line is very long it
doesn't actually all fit on one line so
I'll show you how you can easily make
that a little cleaner we'll import the function
specifically so we'll say from scifi dot stats
import percentile of score as score and then
we can replace this with just score and
actually since we use a different dictionary method
this now fits on one line and is
much more readable if you run it they'll
give the same output great so that's how
we calculated our percentile scores as a quick
recap of what is done in this code
cell we imported the percentile of score function
from the scifi dot stats module and we
named it score and then we created a
dictionary of metrics where every key in the
dictionary is one of the valuation metrics that
we're using and every value of the dictionary
is the corresponding percentile column of our pandas
data frame and then we created a double
nested for loop where the first for loop
loops over every metric in our metric dictionary
and the second for loop loops over every
row in our pandas data frame and then
within both of those for loops we have
an operation here that calculates the percentile score
of every valuation metric and assigns that value
to the corresponding percentile score column and at
the very end we just printed our pandas
data frame now we can move on to
calculating our least score so just like before
we're going to use the mean function from
the built-in Python stats module so we'll
say from stats import mean and then we're
just going to calculate the mean of five
and ten to make sure that this is
working properly we say no module named stats
that's because I should have said statistics great
so the mean of five and ten is
indeed 7.5 so that seems to be
working properly now what we need to do
is we need to loop through every row
of our pandas data frame and calculate the
the average calculate the RV score for that
row so to start we'll just say for
row in RV underscore data frame index and
let's just print that row so this should
print a bunch of numbers from 0 to
504 so it goes 0 all the way
to 504 that is excellent now we need
to access this row of the pandas data
frame and like before we can do that
with the LLC method so what I'll do
is I'll just copy this paste it here
and then I'll change which column we're accessing
to RV score and to make sure this
is working properly let's just print this all
right that looks good now what we need
to do is access all of the different
percentile scores from our pandas data frame and
calculate their mean so on this side we
will say mean and then since this will
be a fairly long line I'm actually going
to create variables for all these so PE
ratio, PEV ratio, PS ratio, EV to even
dollar ratio, and EV to gross profit
now I need to grab the LLC method
from up here actually I just thought of
a better way to do this what we're
going to do is we're going to delete
this we're going to create an empty pandas
list and we're going to call that value
percentiles then we want to grab this same
for loop here so for metric and metrics
.keys and we are going to
say grab the value from the corresponding percentile
awesome we want metrics
all right we are going to now just
do this over one iteration of the loop
to make sure it works properly and before
we do that we actually have in here
to calculate the mean of this value percentiles
and outside the loop we are going to
print the RV data frame awesome now
one other thing we can do to test
this actually is print that value percentiles all
right so to make sure this is working
properly all we have to do is compare
this to this you can see they're the
same we have to compare this to this
you can see that the same we have
to compare this to this and you can
see that they're the same and we have
to compare this to this and this to
this awesome so that is working properly and
what we can do now is delete these
print statements make this loop iterate over the
entire pandas data frame and then inside the
loop we can print the RV underscore data
frame awesome you can see all of our
percentile scores were correctly calculated and now we
can move on to calculating and now we
can move on to selecting the 50 best
value stocks great so as before we can
use the pandas sort value method to identify
the 50 best stocks in our universe according
to the RV score column so to do
that we access our RV data frame we
call the sort values method on it and
then in here we have to pass in
a few things you have to pass in
the column we want to sort on and
then we have to specify the ascending method
and we want this ascending to be true
because we want the lowest valuation metrics at
the top and then we have to specify
in place once that's done we can print
our pandas data frame outside of the sort
values getting like this to see what modifications
have been made alright so now you can
see the cheapest stocks according to a basket
of different valuation metrics we have a Kohl's
we have FTI I'm not actually sure what
company that is but we can find it
pretty easily FTI and it's Technic FMP it
looks like they're a global oil and gas
company it makes sense that they're cheap right
now because oil prices are so low HFC
is Holly Frontier Corporation they are also an
oil and gas company an AL is an
airline they are priced very cheaply right now
because the entire travel industry has experienced significant
headwinds due to the COVID-19 pandemic and
HP I believe is Hewlett-Packard I know
the actual Picard enterprises and they make printers
and those sorts of things they've kind of
always traded out a pretty cheap valuation so
that's that on the other end of the
spectrum you can see what stocks are trading
at extremely high valuation so DX CM I
believe is Dexcom they make continuous glucose monitoring
yeah they make continuous glucose monitoring systems for
diabetes management now I'm not sure what stock
that is but we can find out this
is ServiceNow and they're an American software company
every software company in the world is trading
at pretty high multiples right now then we
have AMD they make CPUs and other sorts
of computer hardware just like Nvidia and then
PAYC I think is Paychex which is a
if it is Paychex they are a payment
processing company no Paycom although they're in the
same business it's an American online payroll and
human resource technology provider based in Oklahoma City
okay so that's done what we need to
do now is we need to drop all
of the stocks that are after the 50th
index so to do that we will say
RV underscore data frame is equal to RV
underscore data frame at index 0 to index
50 and I actually didn't print that so
what we can do now great so this
looks like it's been truncated to only contain
the 50 cheapest stocks in our universe to
make sure that there's like 50 what we
can say is we want to calculate the
length of the index of the different and
that is 50 awesome the only other thing
we need to do is we need to
filter or start not filter we need to
reset the index of the payment to stay
the thing we saw before that we do
reset underscore index and then we want to
pass drop equals true into it to avoid
duplicating the existing index of the pandas data
frame and then we also want to pass
in in place equals true and like all
the other instances including right here what this
in place equals true parameter does is it
means we're gonna actually modify the original pandas
data frame instead of just returning a modified
version temporarily so we're gonna score data frame
and see what this looks like awesome so
now our index goes from zero and should
finish at 49 yep and these are the
50 cheapest stocks in our universe so now
that we've selected the 50 best value stocks
we can move on to calculating the number
of shares to buy now earlier in this
Jupiter notebook we defined a portfolio input function
that will allow us to easily create our
portfolio size so to do that we will
say portfolio underscore size we will run this
for sale and then we will enter a
string object is not calling well why is
that that's because we need to pass in
portfolio input in our portfolio size all right
now we want to enter the value of
our portfolio so that's going to be a
million dollars so one and then six zeros
one two three one two three actually let's
spice things up a bit and do something
different so we'll do two and a half
million so two five and then five zeros
one two three four five awesome now let's
print our portfolio size object or variable I
should say to make sure that it's stored
correctly awesome now we need to calculate our
position size and we've done this twice now
first in our equal weight S&P 500
strategy and then in our momentum strategy so
you should be good to do this on
your own I would encourage you to pause
this video and try to do it by
yourself but if you want to follow along
you can so to do this we will
say position size is equal to and then
the numerator of this division is going to
be the portfolio size variable that we just
created and the denominator is going to be
the length of our pandas data frame so
I've mentioned this in earlier videos but I
prefer to just do length of the RV
underscore data frame index and then we can
print our position size now what does this
give us an unsupported operand type for string
in it that's because I actually ran into
this problem in the momentum project as well
we need to force this to be a
float now what is this giving us $50
,000 and if you think about it our
portfolio is two and a half million dollars
and there's 505 stocks in our sorry 50
stocks in our universe so if we want
to make sure that this is right we
can just test using the double equality operator
whether the position size is equal to two
and half million divided by 50 and if
this returns true then we know that the
calculation has been done properly awesome now we
need to figure out how many shares of
each stock we need to buy to reach
a position size of $50,000 in each
stock so to do that just like before
we're going to create a for loop that
loops through every row of our pandas data
frame so we'll say for row in RV
underscore data frame index and to make sure
that's living properly we'll just print them it
should go from 049 and it does which
is awesome and then we will say RV
underscore data frame dot LLC and in here
the first thing that we need to put
into the row the second thing we need
to put in is the number of shares
to buy column and to make sure that's
working properly let's just the reason I always
test these LLC methods is because sometimes if
you type the column title wrong it won't
work and it looks like that's exactly what
happened here so let's see what happened we
have number of shares to buy and to
see what the difference is I'm going to
scroll up to where we originally defined that
column title and I'm going to paste it
beside it so that's way up here and
so we have number of shares to buy
number of shares to buy huh they look
the same to me maybe that's not actually
what the error was let's go back down
and actually read the error message that could
help hey during handling of the above key
error okay let's
print out our column names to see what's
going on number of oh my soul it
is it is just a typo I didn't
put an S on shared so that's the
problem and now this prints out all the
entries in our number of shares to buy
column of course that's not what we want
we need to actually change the value of
those cells in the pandas data frame so
to do that we'll use the assignment operator
the equal sign and then we need to
do a division so what goes on the
top it's our position size and then in
the numerator we need to figure out our
stock price so to do that we will
use another LLC and paste it there we
will replace the column with price and that
should be all we need to calculate the
number of shares we need to buy so
now the best time let's print our RV
data frame and run this code cell great
so we can see here that for Kohl's
it says by 2,000 shares for FTI
it says by 6,500 shares and you'll
notice that since we used a bigger portfolio
size these numbers are just broadly larger than
when we used a 1 million dollar portfolio
size which makes sense you can also quickly
sanity check this by looking at this stock
it has a lower stock price than this
stock and because of that you need to
buy many more shares of that stock to
reach the required position size so everything looks
to be good here the only other thing
we need to modify is to say math
floor and what this does is it rounds
every entry in that number of shares to
buy column down to the nearest integer for
all the reasons that we described in the
first two projects of this course so that
is done we can now move on to
formatting our Excel output great so just like
before the first thing we need to do
is create our writer object and to do
that we will say writer is equal to
PD Excel writer and then in here we
have to pass in a few things the
first thing we have to pass in is
the name of the excel file we want
to create which is value underscore strategy dot
xlsx xlsx not xslx and then the next
thing we need to pass in is the
engine the engineer we use here just like
before is xlsx writer now to make sure
this is working properly you can just do
the writer dot save method that we have
learned about earlier and then if you go
into the folder that we're working in starter
files you should see the file here and
it should just be empty so here it
is and if you click on it it's
just an empty Excel document which is awesome
because we haven't done any work on it
yet so what we need to do now
is we can delete this save method from
that code cell then we need to access
our RV data thing and we use the
to excel method to pass in the name
of to pass in the pandas data frame
to the excel file that we're working with
now this takes three things you have to
say writer and then you have to say
she underscore name is equal to value strategy
and then you have to pass in index
equals and this just means that the index
here won't get passed into the pandas data
frame so we'll do all that that creates
our kind of save frame the next section
is that we need to create the formats
that will need for our xlsx file and
you'll recall from our first project that we've
already have lots of practice with creating these
formats and since we've already done this we're
just going to run this code cell and
then continue through this tutorial so the next
thing we need to do is actually apply
these formats to each of our columns and
to do that we're going to start by
creating a dictionary and then we will loop
through that dictionary afterwards so let's go up
here to where we first created the columns
of our pandas data frame and from there
we will paste them in and create a
dictionary so here's all of our columns we
will scroll to the bottom paste those in
here we'll get the indexing set up properly
and then we will say column formats equals
and there is that I'm going to add
this to its own line and then I'm
going to put this ticker on a new
line and then I'm going to get the
indenting all set up nicely awesome that looks
a bit better what we need to do
now is actually format this like a dictionary
so I'm going to use the multi cursor
functionality of this jupyter notebook to add my
cursor to every one of these and then
I'm going to add some boilerplate each of
these lines so the first thing we're going
to do is specify a column I'm going
to put a on each line and then
we will fix it afterwards then we need
to put the semicolon which define basically is
the defining characteristic of a Python dictionary and
then I'm going to create a Python list
and to do that we're going to move
every person to the end of each line
there we go move back one and then
add the closing list character the other thing
we're going to do is move back another
one and add in a comma and then
string underscore format now this worked well for
every every line except for a few so
it's always good to go through and just
sanity check these that one needed a bit
of work and this one here something wrong
with it that used to go there and
we can delete that okay I'm going to
just run this post out to see if
this is formatted properly it's not string format
is not defined okay that's because it's called
string template that is not good what I'm
going to do is do a find and
replace so I haven't showed you guys this
yet but it's an interesting feature of the
jupyter notebook if you hit edit here and
then scroll down to find and replace what
I'm going to do is I'm going to
search for a string underscore format and replace
all of those with string underscore template boom
that fixes that problem now if I run
this code cell code cell we should be
good to go and we are so that
is awesome what I need to do now
is change the column letters for each of
these so I hope you guys all know
your alphabet will go a b c d
e f g h i j k l
n alright now we can actually move on
to formatting our our excel file so what
we'll do to start is we will say
for column so what
this does is it loops through all of
the column letters that are keys of this
dictionary and to make sure that's working properly
let's just print out all the column letters
it loops from a through n and the
dictionary goes from a through n so that
is good now what we need to do
is we need to call writer dot sheets
and then we need to access the sheet
that we named our pandas data frame and
that is value strategy so we will copy
that we will move back down here and
we will fix that in there and then
we would call the set column method and
you'll recall this takes a few different parameters
it takes the column so that will look
like that it takes the column width so
we'll use 25 pixels and then it takes
the format so that will look something like
this string underscore template now I'm gonna run
this loop and you'll notice that the statement
that is being run with each loop doesn't
actually change with response to the loop so
that this is just going to make sure
that this is working properly for column a
and then once that's done we can go
in about changing the values for each iteration
loop I'm also going to call the writer
save method to save it and we can
now look in our working directory to see
if this has formatted column a successfully and
it has so we can now move on
to interpolating some values into this so here
we want to use column and we need
to change this to an F strings that
actually interpolates properly we need to use column
there and then here we need to access
the second item of this list so to
do that we will say I can't quite
scroll this up enough to get it away
from my webcam so here we want to
say column underscore formats at column so this
gives us the list and then we want
the second item of that list so we'll
try that and now we'll see what our
data frame looks like actually to do that
we need to go back up here and
run all of this awesome go to our
working directory open this up and they've all
been formatted with this string format so that
is good what we need to do now
is we need to go up here and
actually change the format that's being applied to
each one so we have string template dollar
template integer template float template a percent template
and this float template here actually did run
this should be zero run that and then
we'll go through here and change each format
according to the dollar this should be an
integer this should be a float PE percentile
should be a percent price-to-book ratio
should be a float price-to-book ratio
percentile should be a percent price-to-sales
ratio should be a float price-to-sales
ratio percentile should be a percent if you
think that should be a float you need
to even up percentile should be a percent
you need to GP should be a float
you need to GP percentile should be a
percent and robust value score should also be
a percent because it is an average of
all the different percentiles in our pandas data
frame so we'll run all this again and
see what this looks like awesome so we
have ticker which is a string price which
is a dollar number of shares to buy
which is an integer price-to-earnings ratio
which is a flow PE percentile everything looks
to be good here great so the only
other thing that needs change about this is
that we need to format our columns and
we also need to change our percentiles because
just like in the momentum project they are
two orders of magnitude bigger than what they
should be so we'll fix the percentile score
calculations first that's pretty easy all we need
to do is scroll up to here find
the loop where we calculated our percentile scores
calculated by percentiles so if we divide this
by 100 and that should fix the problem
so we can do this run a bunch
of code cells do a two and a
half million dollar portfolio again and then we're
back down to format our excel I'm actually
gonna go through all of this and say
that again just to make sure that that
was done properly if we open this up
and we go here we can now see
that the percentiles all range from 0 to
100 as desired awesome the next thing we
need to do is actually format our column
headers so to do that we will say
brighter dot sheets and then passing value strategy
select these sheets that we want to format
and then we call the right method now
you'll recall that the right method takes a
few different things it takes the cell we
want to write so this will be for
each row or sorry for each column it
will be the the first cell of that
column so we will say column and then
one so that's the first cell of that
column the second thing we need is the
actual value that we want to write into
that cell so that will be the first
entry of each of these lists just like
before so we paste that in and use
index zero and then the last thing that
it takes is the format that you want
to apply to that cell so that just
like the set column method that we use
here is going to be the second entry
of that list so we will pass in
index one all right so that should be
all the formatting what I'm going to do
next is just move this writer dot save
down to here I'm going to delete all
of these empty cells and then I'm going
to scroll back up to where we created
our Excel file I'm going to run all
the code and you should be good to
go so this started here so I'm going
to click that and then do shift enter
until I reach the end of the Jupiter
notebook and here's our final spreadsheet so as
you can see all the formats have been
applied successfully and you have now created a
quantitative value investing strategy that identifies the 50
cheapest stocks in the S&P 500 using
a basket of different valuation metrics and that
concludes our third project so kudos to you
for making it all the way through this
algorithmic trading in Python course