Hey guys, in this video I will show
you my favorite scalping strategy for Bitcoin, which
is designed for the 5-minute time frame
specifically.
So, what is scalping?
Scalping is the fastest form of day trading,
where the goal is to make a lot
of small trades to gain a big profit
over time.
With this strategy, you can make around 5
to 10 trades per day.
It's using three different indicators, and in this
video, I will show you how to use
this strategy step by step.
Also, in this video, I will do a
300 USDT giveaway.
So, I will give away 100 USDT to
three of the viewers in this video.
Somewhere in this video, I will give instructions
on how to get this giveaway.
So now, let's go through the strategy step
by step.
So, the first step is to add the
indicators to the chart.
So, click the indicator button in trading view
and search for EMA.
Then, click the moving average exponential indicator twice.
One, two.
And then, go to the settings for the
first EMA and change the length to 50.
And then, change the color to yellow.
You can pick any color, and I prefer
to make the line a bit thicker.
Now, go to the settings for the second
EMA and change the value to 200.
And I prefer to use a green color
for this one and a bit thicker line.
Just like this.
And now, we also need to add MACD.
So, search for MACD and use the default
one.
And in this strategy, we will not need
the signal lines.
So, untick the MACD and the signal line,
so we only have the histogram.
And we also need to change the time
frame for the MACD.
In this strategy, I use the MACD from
the one minute time frames.
In the MACD settings, in the indicator time
frame setting, you can choose another time frame.
So, let's choose the one minute time frame.
And then, click OK.
So, notice that we are in the five
minute time frame in the chart.
But for the MACD, we're using the one
minute time frame.
Then, we also need to add the RSI
indicator.
So, search for RSI and add a default
RSI indicator to the chart.
And we can use the default settings for
the RSI.
So, the next step in this strategy is
to know when to enter a trade.
So, we will use the 50 and the
200 EMA as a trend indicator.
And we will always take trades in the
same direction as a trend.
So, when the 50 EMA is crossing the
200 EMA to the upside, when the yellow
line is above the green line, then we
are allowed to make long positions.
And then, we will enter the trades on
pullbacks.
So, when we have a big downtick on
the MACD, then we enter the trade right
away.
So, we're looking for a downtick on the
MACD that is bigger than the average.
I would enter the first trade here on
this downtick.
So, right here.
And then, we set the target profit to
0.5% and the stop loss at
0.4%. And as you can see, this
trade was a win straight away.
And then, we're looking for another downtick on
the MACD that is bigger than the average.
And I will say it's this one right
there.
So, we take the profit at 0.5
% and we have a stop loss at
0.4%. And as you can see, this
trade is also a win.
And then, we're looking for another downtick that
is bigger than average.
And I will say it's this one right
here.
So, we enter the trade right here and
take a profit at 0.5% and
have a stop loss at 0.4%. And
we want to enter trades as close to
the crossover as possible.
The probability of a win is a lot
higher closer to the crossover.
So, after you made about three to five
trades after the crossover, stop trading and wait
for the next crossover.
And the same thing applies to shorting as
well.
When the 50 EMA is crossing the 200
EMA to the downside, then we can only
take short positions.
So now, we're waiting for an uptick on
the MACD that is bigger than average.
And then, we can enter a short position.
So, I would say this uptick is bigger
than average.
So, we would enter short right here and
take profit at 0.5%, put the stop
loss at 0.4%. This is also a
win.
And then, we're waiting for another uptick that
is bigger than average.
And I would enter right here and take
the profit at 0.5% and set
the stop loss at 0.4%. And this
is also a win.
Then, we have another big uptick here.
I would enter right there and set the
target at 0.5% and the stop
loss at 0.4%. And this is also
a win.
And then, after a few trades, stop trading
because it's getting riskier and riskier the further
after the crossover we get.
Since we are on a five-minute time
frame, crossovers like this happens a few times
per day.
And we only need to make five trades
So, there's no stress.
After the crossover, we can stop trading after
a few trades.
Of course, using high leverage is super risky.
So, trade with gamble money.
Don't trade with money that is important to
you because scalping with the high leverage is
the riskiest trading strategy you can use.
It has a very high reward if you're
successful.
But if you're doing any mistakes, you can
wipe out your entire balance.
So, be really careful.
Use money that's not important to you.
And this type of trading requires some experience
as well.
The next step is to trade on the
right exchange.
To trade a scalping strategy like this, you
really need to use an exchange that is
good for scalping.
There are hundreds of exchanges out there and
only a few of them are really good
for scalping.
So, what you need to look for in
an exchange is super low fees because we
are taking profit at 0.5% and
we use a stop loss at 0.4%.
So, if your trading fees are high, it
will eat too much of the profit and
the strategy will no longer work.
For example, if we use Bitfinex here as
an exchange, look at these fees.
0.1% for limit orders and 0
.2% for market orders.
0.3% from the profit will be
taken in fees.
So, that is obviously too much.
So, if we run the strategy with Bitfinex,
we would lose all the money after just
a few trades.
You also need to use an exchange with
very high liquidity in the order books and
a really low slip rate because slip rate
is also a threat when scalping.
Since we're using a high leverage, the position
size can be very large when the account
balance starts to grow.
And if there is not enough orders in
the order book, that can actually hurt the
profits as well.
And you also need an exchange that is
really easy to use so that you can
execute your trades really fast because this is
a very high speed type of trading.
The only exchange for me that ticks all
of these boxes are Bybit.
On Bybit, I will make money when I
use limit orders.
I would actually make 0.025% from
limit orders.
And when I'm using market orders, I only
pay 0.075% in fees.
And this is the lowest I have found
out there.
So this is really, really good for scalping.
And I'm using market orders for my entries
and I'm using limit orders for my exits.
So I will pay an average 0.05
% in fees on each trade.
And that's based on this strategy after 150
trades.
Bybit is also one of the exchanges with
the highest liquidity in their order books.
So a lot of the times there's no
slip rate at all, but when there are
slip rates, it's really low compared to other
exchanges.
And in my opinion, they have the best
user interface out there to place trades really
fast and it's super easy to use.
So that's a platform I'm recommending for scalping
strategy like this.
But if you can find another exchange with
super low fees, high liquidity in the order
book, low spread, and a super easy to
use interface, you can use that exchange as
well, of course.
If you want to try Bybit, you can
go to my video description down below and
you can use my affiliate link here to
create an account.
It takes only 25 seconds to create an
account.
Again, Bybit has the lowest trading fees.
In my opinion, it's the best crypto exchange
out there.
And if you use my specific link here,
you can get the welcome bonus up to
$600 after your first deposit.
The next step is to execute the trades
correctly in your exchange.
When I'm trading this strategy, I have one
tab with trading view open and one tab
with my exchange open, in this case, Bybit.
And I also have my calculator ready.
So let's say that I want to enter
a long position on Bitcoin right now.
I will go to market, 100% of
the quantity and press open long.
The first thing I want to do, and
I want to do this really, really quick.
I want to add my stop loss.
So clicking here, add stop loss.
And now I will bring up my calculator
and I will take my entry price.
You can see it right here, 46,731.
And I want to have a stop loss
at 0.4%. That would be times 0
.996, right?
In that way, we will have a stop
loss at 0.4%. So now the stop
loss price would be 46,544.
46,544.
So now we have the stop loss set
and we can confirm it by clicking here.
And now we have the entry price here.
We have the stop loss price here and
we can confirm that the stop loss is
correct by hovering at the entry price and
holding shift and then clicking downwards to the
stop loss.
And we can see that it's set to
0.4%. And you always need to add
a stop loss as soon as possible after
your entry and add it before the target
profit.
Because if the price would drop suddenly and
your stop loss is not set, it can
wipe out the profits from a lot of
trades that you made before.
So be really fast with the stop loss.
And now we want to add the target
order with a limit order.
So you can go to close by and
click limit and bring up the calculator, reset
it and take the entry price again for
the 6,731 times 1.005 to get
the target at 0.5%. And you can
round it to the closest 0.5. So
that would be 46,964.5. 46,964
.5 and press confirm.
And we can confirm it by shift clicking
here to here and it's set at 0
.5%. So it's all correct.
And now we can relax and just wait
for the trade to close.
And this is just an example.
So I will cancel my trade here.
I will close the position at the small
profit here and I will show you how
to short as well.
So let's say I want to short right
now.
Do the same thing again.
Go to market and 100% of the
quantity open short.
And now I want to add a stop
loss as soon as possible.
So when adding a stop loss to a
short position, you need to do it the
opposite way.
So click add stop loss, then bring up
the calculator and take your entry price for
the 6,784.
You can see it down here and do
times 1.004. That would be 46,971.
46,971 and press confirm.
So now we have the stop loss all
set here.
You can confirm it by hovering here and
shift clicking to your stop loss 0.4%.
So that is correct.
And then we need to add our target
with the limit order.
So press close by limit here and take
your entry for the 6,784 times 0
.995 to get a 0.5% target.
That would be 46,550.
46,550 and we can confirm it by
shift clicking and dragging down.
And we now have a target at 0
.5%. So that's how easy it is to
execute the trades on Bybit.
You need to really look at the order
book here.
This is the order book.
You can see the open orders in the
order book and you need to confirm that
there's enough liquidity in the order book for
your trade when you get to this size.
And I usually limit my trading size to
between $100,000 and $150,000 because the
higher trading size we use, the harder it
will be to execute the orders.
As you can see here, if we want
to buy Bitcoin right now, there's 70 BTC
at the current price in the order book.
So there's no problem right now, but if
you're using very high volumes, you need to
keep track on the order book and just
confirm that there's enough volume here for your
order to execute.
Otherwise, you might get some slipperage.
However, slipperage on Bybit has not been a
problem for me so far, but I feel
obligated to just let you know that trading
with a big account might cause some slipperage
if you're not careful.
The next step is to make sure that
you're entering the trades on the candle close.
To know when the candle is closing, you
can right click on the right edge of
trading view here on the price axis and
then enable countdown to bar close.
And you can see that you have two
minutes left to this candle close.
So wait for the candle to close before
you enter the trade.
The next step is to only trade large
cap coins.
I'm trading this strategy primarily on Bitcoin because
Bitcoin has very high volume and high liquidity
in order books, but sometimes I might even
trade Ethereum.
But I never trade smaller coins because the
volatility is different on smaller coins and the
volume on smaller coins might not always be
enough.
Also, make sure to use the chart in
trading view for your specific exchange.
So when you add a coin in the
exchange, you search for BTC USD, for example,
then make sure that you use your exchange
in trading view.
For example, I'm using Bybit, so I will
always use the Bybit chart when I'm trading
this strategy because sometimes the price can be
a bit different on different exchanges.
The next step is to avoid overtrading and
avoiding bad trades.
So when you have a crossover and you
already made like five trades on this crossover,
because eventually the next crossover will happen.
So it's better to wait for the next
crossover and then go back to shorting at
that crossover instead.
It's also good to look at higher timeframes
as well to make sure that Bitcoin is
not overextended on the higher timeframes.
If Bitcoin has a very high RSI, for
example, on the higher timeframes, you might not
want to enter long positions.
So use your skill and look at the
higher timeframes and look at other indicators, for
example, the RSI to avoid overtrading and to
avoid taking long positions when the price is
overextended and to avoid shorting when the price
already has dropped a lot already.
Overall, be patient.
You only need about five trades per day
to make huge gains from this strategy.
So only take trades that feels right and
that you believe in and try to follow
the trend overall.
If you are bullish on Bitcoin on, for
example, the one hour timeframe and the four
hour timeframe, then it might be a good
idea to avoid the shorting at that time.
And now I will give away $100 to
three of the viewers in this video.
The only thing you need to do to
have a chance to get this giveaway, you
need to like the video, subscribe to the
channel and create an account on Bybit using
my link.
It takes only 25 seconds to create an
account and then write I'm in in the
comment section down below.
And I will pick three random winners.
And if you are one of them, I
will reply to your comment and then I
will send $100 to your Bybit account.
If you don't reply to the comment within
seven days, I will give the $100 to
someone else.
So that's all you need to do.
Next week, I will post a video where
I'm trading the strategy for eight hours straight
and showing all the trades in that video.
In the meanwhile, check out my other videos
on my channel.
Thanks for watching and see you in the
next video.