Fibonacci Retracements It is a tool that displays
horizontal lines based on the Fibonacci numbers.
These lines can then be used as key
support and resistance levels.
To use the Fibonacci retracement tool, you first
start by identifying a swing low and swing
high on a chart.
Then, drag the tool from the swing low
to the swing high.
Next, wait for the price to make a
pullback to one of these levels, ideally the
0.382 Fibonacci level, because that's the most
common level where price tends to reverse from.
So if price touches that level, that could
be a good buy entry.
Keep in mind that price could also reverse
from other Fibonacci levels.
Combine it with other confirmation signals to get
a better entry.
Breakout Patterns It is when price makes a
sudden and significant movement towards one direction.
This usually forms after the market makes a
consolidation period.
For example, here we can see that the
price is consolidating.
Then, it suddenly moves sharply to the downside.
This is called a breakout.
To take advantage of this, traders could use
specific patterns as a guide to identify breakouts
before they happen.
Most notable breakout patterns include wedges, triangles, and
the rectangle pattern.
Reversal Patterns It is when price moves in
the opposite direction of the current trend and
forms a countertrend.
Specific patterns could be identified in a chart
which could help traders predict reversals before they
happen.
Most notable reversal patterns are double top and
bottoms, triple top and bottoms, head and shoulders,
cups and handles.
Elliott Wave It is a theory that suggests
that market tends to move in a series
of 5 waves before reversing and forming another
set of waves in the opposite direction.
By understanding the Elliott Wave sequence, traders could
predict where the price is heading by following
the pattern.
In a chart, we can label each point
of the wave as 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, and ABC.
Now, there are specific rules to ensure that
a movement is considered as a valid Elliott
Wave.
First, wave 2 cannot be longer than wave
1, and usually pulls back to the 0
.618 Fibonacci level.
Second, wave 3 must be the longest wave
amongst wave 1, 3, and 5.
Third, wave 4 must remain above the peak
of wave 1, and usually pulls back to
the 0.382 Fibonacci level.
So here's an example of the Elliott Wave
in action.
In this chart, we can see that the
price resembles a possible 1, 2, 3 Elliott
Wave.
And so, based on the theory of wave
4, which is that price tends to pull
back to the 0.382 Fibonacci level before
continuing upwards, we can use this as a
potential buy entry when price makes a pullback.
Fair Value Gaps A Fair Value Gap occurs
when a candle forms a significant gap due
to an imbalance of buying or selling.
To find a Fair Value Gap, you first
need to find a candle with a large
body.
Then, draw a rectangle at the gap.
Place it between the previous candle's wick and
the next candle's wick.
This level now acts as a potential magnet,
where price may revisit before continuing its movement.
Candlestick Patterns It is a technique that traders
use to analyze future price movements by looking
at specific candlestick shapes.
Notable candlestick patterns include Engulfing Patterns, which signals
strong momentum towards the direction of the engulfing
candle.
Hammer and Shooting Star Patterns, which indicates rejection
as shown by the long wick on one
side.
Doji Patterns, which signals neutrality in the market.
Heikinashi It is an indicator that fully replaces
a traditional candlestick chart to a Heikinashi chart.
When applied, it tends to give less noise
than a traditional candlestick.
A green Heikinashi candle signals that the price
is on an uptrend, and a red Heikinashi
candle signals that the price is on a
downtrend.
The size of the candle's body also indicates
how strong a trend is.
The larger the candle, the stronger the trend.
Keep in mind that the Heikinashi only acts
as an indicator.
It does not display the real market price.
Moon Phases It is a concept that utilizes
moon cycles to time the market.
Moon phase traders believe that moon cycles are
correlated with human emotions and behavior, which could
have an influence on the market.
Specific moon phases are believed to be favorable
towards a certain trend.
A new moon means the market tends to
be bullish, and a full moon means the
market tends to be bearish.
Today, it is used mostly as a confirmation
tool.
Renko It replaces a traditional candlestick chart to
a Renko chart.
Unlike a traditional candlestick which forms a new
candle based on a certain period of time,
a Renko chart forms its block based on
the change of price.
For example, every 1% change in price,
a Renko block appears.
This means that each Renko block represents a
1% change in price.
Of course, you can change the parameters of
this through the indicator settings.
Traders could utilize Renko charts to filter out
noise and identify trends.
A green Renko block signals an uptrend, and
a red Renko block signals a downtrend.
And keep in mind that Renko charts only
act as an indicator.
It does not display the real market price.
Harmonic Patterns These are advanced price patterns that
follows a specific shape based on Fibonacci numbers.
Traders can then use these specific shapes to
predict future price movements.
For example, a bullish-bad pattern is formed
when price makes a series of 4 movements
that is shaped like the letter M.
Each point can be labeled as X, A,
B, C, and D.
And each of these points has a specific
guideline.
For example, point X to point B needs
to have a value between 0.382 and
0.5. Point A to C needs to
have a value between 0.382 and 0
.886. And the same thing works for the
other points.
Next, these specific guidelines can then be applied
onto a real chart.
So, if you see a price forming a
series of 4 movements, you can apply the
Harmonic Pattern tool to check if the price
that formed matches a pattern's guideline.
If it does, then you can take a
position based on the pattern that formed.
There are multiple Harmonic Patterns that exist.
Most notable are Butterfly, Bat, Crab.
And each have their own unique values.
Support and Resistance These are key levels that
formed horizontally where the price has bounced off
in the past and could possibly bounce again
in the future.
If the level is below the price, it's
called Support, where you can take a buy
position if the price approaches it.
And if the level is above the price,
it's called Resistance, where you can take a
sell position if the price approaches it.
Dynamic Support and Resistance Similar to Support and
Resistance, Dynamic Support and Resistance also acts as
key levels.
But instead of using static horizontal lines, it
uses indicators like the moving average to act
as our key level.
Trendlines Trendlines are key levels that form diagonally
during a trending market.
You can use trendlines to identify the overall
direction of the price.
Upwards trendline means bullish.
Downwards trendline means bearish.
And similar to Support and Resistance, you can
also use the trendline to identify possible entry
scenarios.
For example, if price retraces back to a
trendline, it can be a good opportunity to
take a buy position.
Gone Angles It is a tool that displays
multiple lines that spread continuously on different angles.
These lines can then act as possible key
levels and could also help you measure the
strength of a trend.
Price moving within the steep angles of the
tool indicates a strong trend, and price moving
within the shallow angles of the tool indicates
a weak trend.
To apply the Gone Angles, first, you go
to Settings.
Then, make sure to check the lock price
to bar ratio.
Next, identify a market range and mark the
swing low and the swing highs of that
range.
Then, draw a straight vertical line at the
start of the range.
After that, select the Trend Angle tool and
measure 45 degrees.
Then, use the Gone Fan tool and place
it at the 45 degree angle.
Momentum Indicators These are the types of indicator
that measures the direction and strength of a
trend.
It is most effective when used in trending
markets.
Some of the most notable momentum indicators are
MACD An upwards crossover indicates a bullish trend
while a downwards crossover indicates a bearish trend.
Moving Averages Price being above the moving average
signals a bullish trend and price being below
signals a bearish trend.
Parabolic SAR A dot below the price indicates
a bullish trend and a dot above the
price indicates a bearish trend.
Super Trend Green signal indicates a bullish trend
and red signal indicates a bearish trend.
Oscillators These are the types of indicator that
displays the relative strength of a price.
It is most effective when used on choppy
or sideways markets.
Most notable oscillators include RSI – when the
line is in the oversold region, it indicates
a possible reversal to the upside.
If it's in the overbought region, it indicates
a possible reversal to the downside.
Stochastic – if both lines are at oversold,
it signals a possible reversal to the upside.
And if both lines are at overbought, it
signals a possible reversal to the downside.
These two lines can also cross over each
other to predict future price movements.
Divergences – Divergences occur when an indicator displays
an opposite signal of the real price movement.
When this happens, it is usually a sign
that the trend might reverse.
Divergences can occur in many indicators, such as
the MACD, Stochastic, and the RSI.
For example, here, using the MACD indicator, you
can see that the price is forming higher
highs, which is bullish, but the indicator shows
the opposite, a lower highs, which is bearish.
In this case, this is a bearish divergence,
which signals that the price may form a
reversal, and so you can take a sell
position.
Volume Indicators – These are types of indicator
that shows the strength behind a price movement
by tracking the trading volume.
Notable volume indicators include Price Volume, which displays
the volume for each candle.
The longer the bar, the higher the volume.
Volume-Weighted Average Price, which shows the ratio
of an asset's price to its total volume.
It can be traded like a moving average
or as a dynamic support and resistance.
Volume Profiles – It displays a volume bar
horizontally, which can be treated as key levels
for potential entry positions.
Supply and Demand – Also referred to as
order blocks, these are zones where significant price
movements have occurred.
If price moves significantly upwards from a level,
it is considered a demand zone, and if
price moves significantly downwards from a level, it
is considered a supply zone.
Just like support and resistance, these zones can
be treated as key levels for potential entry
positions.
Market Structure – Market structure is when a
trader analyzes the behavior, condition, and flow of
the market.
An uptrend structure is characterized by price forming
higher highs and higher lows, while downtrend structure
is characterized by price forming lower highs and
lower lows.
Break of Structure – It is when price
breaks the previous price peak during a trend.
For example, if the price forms a higher
highs and higher lows, this break of the
previous highs is called break of structure.
Change of Character – It occurs when price
breaks the previous structure during a trend, often
signaling a reversal from that current trend.
For example, if the price is forming higher
highs and higher lows, then it breaks the
previous lows forming lower lows, this is called
a change of character.
So did I miss any strategy?
Let me know in the comments below.
And if you find this enjoyable, kindly do
a small favor by liking the video and
subscribe to the channel.
It only takes 2 clicks but it means
so much to me.
You can also check out my other videos
as well.
So thank you for watching and I'll see
you in the next video.