Every investor is quick to talk about NVIDIA
and Palantir.
But the days of those companies hitting 500
% growth in a single year are quickly
disappearing.
I'm not saying it's impossible, I'm just saying
it's not likely.
If we want to see that type of
growth, then we need to look at small
cap stocks that are often priced lower than
$10 a share.
For example, 18 months ago, SoundHound AI was
trading at $3.47 a share, and now
it's up 572%, where NVIDIA was up 205
% that same time period.
That means that $10,000 invested 18 months
ago into these two companies, well, it would
now be worth over $57,000 from SoundHound
AI versus $20,000 from NVIDIA.
That's a $37,000 difference, which is huge.
The problem is, these small cap stocks are
extremely risky, and they can go way up
and way down in a matter of days.
That's why I'm going to do my best
to showcase the top five growth stocks under
$10.
And this is a remake of a video
that I'd done 18 months ago, where I'll
list out on the screen what those companies
were, and how they've performed over that time
frame.
Overall, as you can see, not a bad
set of stock, and only one major dog
in the group.
I have spent a lot of time researching
for today's video, and I'm the first to
state that there just aren't that many good
stocks that are available under $10.
But I'm doing my best to pick the
ones that I believe have the most upside
over the next couple of years.
And I'm not going to waste everyone's time
by keeping you hostage.
I'm listing them on the screen right now,
where I hope that you can appreciate my
upfront approach.
And I also hope that you stick around
to find out why they made my list.
Let's jump right in with Fiscal Note Holdings,
with the symbol N-O-T-E, where
they are a technology company specializing in global
policy and market intelligence.
By combining artificial intelligence with comprehensive data and
expert analysis, Fiscal Note provides organizations with critical
insights to navigate complex policy landscapes.
And maybe it's the craziness of a new
presidential administration, or shifts in foreign policy, or
maybe even it's the simple fact that technology
is racing forward at a crazy speed, which
makes it necessary for a company to specialize
in market and policy intelligence just like this.
Now, not to get off topic, but with
regards to technology flying at breakneck speeds, have
you seen how one of Tesla's competitors has
an electric car that can automatically sense potholes
in the road and jump over them?
Or the fact that a no-name Chinese
company created DeepSeek, which seems to rival the
best US AI models available.
And it just came out today about the
news of DeepSeek, and the stock market is
starting to drop quite a bit.
So you can tell when I'm actually filming
this.
So it's no surprise that companies need a
company like Fiscal Note to keep them at
the tip of the most of up-to
-date market intelligence.
At a quick glance at their financials, they're
not awesome.
Margins are improving, but still highly negative.
Their debt-to-assets are climbing, and they've
missed on forecasts.
But analysts seem to give them a lot
of love with over 100% upside over
the next 12 months.
Look, I'm not going to lie, this stock
is a big unknown.
I believe that it's one that has a
lot of value to provide the companies right
now with all of the different policy changes.
But this is a company that I'll want
to watch over the next earnings to see
if they can move more in the right
direction for their sales and margin.
Like I said at the beginning, small cap
companies carry a lot more risk, so make
certain to do your own research and watch
them closely.
This next company meets all the requirements of
having a low entry point and a large
potential for growth, seeing as how it's up
over 370% for the past year.
But I couldn't include this one on my
list because of them being today's sponsor, and
that would be Poet Technologies, where they have
made several announcements since I last spoke about
them.
Poet is revolutionizing data centers and AI networking
by tackling data transfer bottlenecks and heat using
its patented optical interposer platform.
Traditional electronics use copper wiring, which consumes substantial
power and limits data transfer speeds.
But Poet replaces these wires with efficient lasers,
reducing power consumption and increasing data speeds, which
overall lowers costs.
And recently, Poet announced a partnership with a
global financial services leader to develop a custom
optical engine for high-frequency securities trading, demonstrating
the versatility of its optical interposer and low
latency, allowing for trades that happen much faster
than traditional hardware allows.
In addition, Poet's acquisition of Super Photonics integrated
circuits enhances its production capacity for optical engines.
And with all the news around DeepSeek's R1
program demonstrates the increasing accessibility and market opportunities
for AI, further highlighting the value of Poet's
optical connectivity solutions.
Poet's technology is a crucial solution for the
future of AI by reducing costs and latency.
Learn more about Poet Technologies via the link
down in the description.
The next company is Archer Aviation, and truth
be told, I could have easily have chosen
Joby since they're both priced about the same
and they're both at about the same stance
in becoming operational.
So either one is a good choice.
But for right now, I'm just going to
focus on Archer, where they are an aerospace
company developing electric vertical takeoff and landing aircraft
for urban air mobility.
And their flagship aircraft, Midnight, is designed to
carry four passengers and a pilot on short
urban trips.
And by short urban trips, I'm talking 10
to 15 minute flights in urban areas, where
it would have easily taken an hour or
more to drive that same distance.
This is a company that has had some
big contracts with the Air Force, and they've
also partnered with Anduril Industries, where they plan
to provide our military some extremely high-tech
offerings.
In addition to all that, they plan to
have operations starting by the end of this
year.
I see this as getting in early on
something like Tesla, where it may be very
slow for quite a while, but I expect
it to take off over time.
And trust me, I had a ton of
friends 10 or 11 years ago that would
say that electric cars would never become mainstream.
And we all know how that panned out.
As for financials, they are up and down
across the board.
They look to be building up their assets,
and they've beaten estimates several times.
But this is a stock that can slide
down just as fast as it blows up.
And analysts see Archer as having over 22
% upside for the year.
And as I say with any stock, I
wait for a dip before I buy into
it.
Patience has always seemed to work in my
favor, and I see this stock as being
a long-term growth driver.
The next company is a repeat from my
video 18 months ago, and that's Big Bear
AI, with the symbol BBAI, where they are
a technology company specializing in AI-powered decision
intelligence solutions across sectors such as government and
defense, manufacturing and warehouse operations, and healthcare and
life sciences.
Additionally, Big Bear AI was awarded a five
-year production contract valued at $165 million to
deliver the U.S. Army's Global Force Information
Management objective environment, enhancing its role in national
security.
And during the taping of this video, the
stock has had a major correction due to
the news from that AI model, DeepSeek, which
I find sort of ridiculous in having a
correction because a lot of experts state that
LLMs are simply becoming a commodity.
But the real value is creating the AI
systems to drive real growth, sort of like
what Palantir has already been doing.
That, and with so much of Big Bear
AI's revenue coming from the government, it won't
really have any big impact from the new
model like DeepSeek, making this a pretty good
opportunity to buy the dip.
Because in looking at their financials, they've shown
margin inconsistency, but revenue is steady, and their
debt-to-assets have dropped way down.
But they've also been missing in their forecast
in the lower right.
Despite that, analysts show Big Bear AI with
nearly 20% upside.
And given its price below $10, this happens
to be a pretty good pick for today's
video.
Our next company is D-Wave Quantum, which
is a leader in quantum computing systems, software,
and services, recognized as the world's first commercial
supplier of quantum computers.
The company also partnered with Kerasoft Technology to
expand the distribution of its quantum computing solutions
to the U.S. public sector, aiming to
enhance government adoption of quantum technologies.
I've spoken about this company a few different
times in other videos because I see quantum
computing as being an area of extreme growth
over time, and in my opinion, we're in
the early innings of this particular game.
And when we look at the financials, it
doesn't really tell me much of a story
because they're still in startup mode.
But with their push to gain usage from
government agencies, I expect their margins to quickly
grow, and they've already been beating forecasts semi
-regular in the lower right.
And analysts see D-Wave with over 50
% upside, and I can easily see that
being the case.
And like all small cap companies, it has
huge swings in the stock price.
So definitely, as I say, buy on the
dips because they've been happening a lot lately
depending on which CEO wants to talk about
quantum And our next company is Biomerica Inc.,
with the symbol BMRA, which is a global
biomedical technology company that develops, patents, manufactures, and
markets advanced diagnostic and therapeutic products, focusing on
gastrointestinal and inflammatory diseases, where they secured three
key international patents for its InFoods technology, targeting
gastroesophageal reflux disease, Crohn's disease, and ulcerative colitis.
Additionally, Biomerica has launched its InFoods IVS test
directly to consumers, aiming to help individuals identify
foods that may trigger irritable bowel syndrome symptoms.
This initiative reflects the company's commitment to provide
accessible solutions for gastrointestinal health.
And I was shocked to learn that about
20% of the U.S. population has
GERD, and another 10% of the population
has irritable bowel disease, which makes Biomerica a
leader in the potentially multi-billion-dollar business
with regards to advanced diagnostics.
And in looking at their financials, the revenue
and margin is cyclical with no consistent story.
But this is a company heavy in R
&D, where they've just been granted several new
patents and just started its direct-to-consumer
test kits.
I believe this to be in the early
stages of the company's growth story, but it
happens to be so early in its story
that analysts don't seem to have any projections
to work from.
So this makes it a very challenging company
to gauge where it's going to go.
But given the patents and the market, I
believe this may be a little bit of
a hidden gem.
Now, if small cap stocks that may be
hidden gems aren't your thing, I do have
plenty of other large cap stock and ETF
videos for you to check out at any
time.
Thanks so much for watching.