Our economy is going to change in 2025,
and in this video, I want to show
you how you can find the investment opportunities
that most people are overlooking.
Take a look.
President-elect Trump is entering the White House
in January, and he wants to make some
sweeping changes to our government and economic policy.
To be clear, the goal in this video
is not to talk politics.
There's enough people that do that already.
The goal in this video is to show
you how these changes will create a unique
investment opportunity.
Let me show you why this matters.
In 2024, the United States economy is about
$28 trillion big.
This is our GDP.
GDP is a measure of all spending that
happens in our economy.
Every smart investor wants to own a piece
of this.
More specifically, they want to own a piece
of where the economy is moving because that's
where you're going to see the most growth
with your investments.
Most people understand that.
But what many people don't understand is that
the largest spender in our economy is not
you and me.
It's not corporations.
It's the government.
So when you have a new president that
comes with new economic policies, which changes how
money moves.
But now when you have a president like
Trump coming in, who's proposing big sweeping changes
like deporting millions of illegal immigrants, or slapping
tariffs on China, or passing big tax breaks,
somebody is going to be making money off
of these changes.
And you want to know a little secret?
Wall Street is going to find a way
to profit off of whoever's in the White
House by studying how the economy is going
to change.
But the average person has no idea how
to do that until now, because that's what
I'm going to be showing you through this
video.
So make sure you stick with me until
the end.
And just around the same page, there might
be some topics that make you feel not
so good.
And what I want you to understand as
an investor, that when you make an investment
decisions, it has to be three pieces of
criteria.
Number one, this investment has to be legal.
Number two, it has to be financially sound,
meaning hopefully you'll make some money.
And number three, it has to make moral
sense.
This moral compass is going to be subjective
to you.
I'm not going to tell you what's morally
right for you or not, because I have
my own moral compass, and there are certain
things that I refuse to invest in.
My goal is to show you what's happening.
I want to show you where the money
is moving, that way you can make your
own decisions based off of this triangle right
here, because you will have a very different
moral compass than me.
Seven of the largest proposals that President-elect
Trump has talked about up until now are
number one, doing mass deportations.
Number two, slapping tariffs on many countries.
Number three, investing in the military.
Number four, deregulating financial service companies.
Number five, investing in space exploration.
Number six, deregulating the oil and gas industry.
And number seven, providing some big tax cuts.
Now what I want to do is go
through each one of these and talk about
how the money will move if this gets
passed, and how this can create a unique
investment opportunity for you.
Now let me remind you of a couple
of things.
Number one, investing is risky.
You are never guaranteed to make money when
you invest.
In fact, you will lose money at some
point, so make sure you always do your
own due diligence, and never blindly trust a
random guy on YouTube.
And of course, if you are investing your
money as a passive investor, then you don't
need to worry about the changes that are
happening in the White House, because if you
were just investing your money into something like
the S&P 500, then all you do
is A, B, B.
Always be buying.
You buy when markets are up, you buy
when markets are down, because the reality is
we will see another recession, we will see
a market crash.
When?
Nobody knows.
But the way you win as a passive
investor is you always be buying.
You buy when markets are up, when markets
are down, and you just let the markets
do their thing.
So if that's what you're doing, you can
ignore this video.
But if you want to be more involved
with your investments, and you want to find
more active investments, not trades, that's what I'm
going to be talking about here.
But understand that that comes with more risk,
more potential returns, but it's going to require
you to be a little bit more involved
with your investments, because the reality is we
can talk about what's going to happen here,
but if we see a recession, then all
of this can go down as well.
This is where you have to be a
smart investor, and the things that I'm going
to focus on for this video are the
changes that Trump is proposing in these seven
different areas, and how this can create a
shift with money, but that doesn't always mean
that these stocks are going to just shoot
up, because there's a lot of other factors
that can impact the stock market.
It's no surprise that Trump has been talking
about doing mass deportations, but do you know
who these mass deportations benefit from a business
sense?
Private prisons.
Let me read you what NBC News had
to say about this.
And if you're wondering why private prison companies
love the idea of doing mass deportations, well,
read this from Investor Business Daily.
I'm going to say this one more time.
You have to decide what's morally right for
you.
My job in this video is to show
you what's happening financially, because we're going to
see a lot of changes in our economy
as President-elect Trump enters the White House,
but this is where you have to understand
what really makes a good investment decision.
This goes on to number two with tariffs.
How does that potentially create an investment opportunity?
Now, before we go too deep into tariffs,
I want to remind you that if you
are interested in learning more about how you
can really build your wealth in 2025 in
this changing economy, I'm hosting a free and
live and virtual workshop on January 7th, where
I'm going to show you how you can
systemize your money to build wealth, how you
can find unique investment opportunities, and how you
can actually research those investment opportunities.
How do you actually research a stock?
I'm going to be going over all of
these things on my free and live and
virtual workshop on January 7th.
I'm going to do it twice on the
7th, once in the morning at 10.30
a.m. Eastern Standard Time, and then again
in the evening at 8.00 p.m.
Eastern Standard Time.
It's completely free, but you do have to
register because there's a limited number of people
that can actually join me live.
So if you'd like to join me, it's
on January 7th.
We have two different times, and if you'd
like to register, all you got to do
is click the link down in the description
below.
Remember, a tariff is a tax.
So if I'm Nike or Ford or Walmart,
and I'm buying things from China, well, now
there might be an additional, let's call it
25% tax on those items to come
into the United States.
So if I'm Nike, and I'm buying something
from China, it might cost me 25%
more money in order to pay for that
product.
And that could mean a few things for
Nike.
That could mean, A, I'm going to sell
my stuff for 25% more to make
up for this higher cost, or B, it
might mean that I will shrink my profit
margins as Nike to eat up this additional
cost, or it might mean, 3, I move
my manufacturing in order to avoid this cost.
I could potentially move my manufacturing here to
the United States or a different country.
Now, it's hard to say what's going to
happen because, of course, this is just a
proposal.
We have no idea what's actually going to
get passed.
But what we do know is if manufacturing
does come back into the United States, there's
going to be certain industries that benefit.
I mean, if manufacturing comes back into the
United States, that could mean that more manufacturing
plants have to be built.
That could benefit those real estate companies.
If more manufacturing comes back into the United
States, that could mean that railroads would benefit
because they'd have to transport products from one
plant to the other inside of the United
States.
In fact, read this.
So if tariffs get passed, and if those
tariffs encourage companies to bring their manufacturing back
into the United States, that could then benefit
companies like railroads, who then have to transport
products between one plant and the other.
Again, we don't know what's going to get
passed until it actually gets passed.
But this is the way that I want
you to think, is understanding when these decisions
happen, where does the money move?
Now, let's talk about number three, investing in
the military.
During Trump's campaign, he talked about investing in
the military here in the United States.
But what you have to remember is that
the military has goods that are produced by
companies.
So let's play through this scenario.
We're investing in the military, which means we
have more people practicing shooting guns.
More people are shooting bullets.
More people are driving tanks.
More people are flying in these fighter jets.
Well, all of these things have to be
produced by somebody.
They're not produced by the government, which means
that some of this government spending in our
economy could potentially go more to those companies
that are producing all these products.
And we can take a look online to
see some of the top defense companies in
the world, and many of them are in
the United States, like you can see over
here.
So if the government actually invests in the
military, they could potentially give more and larger
contracts to some of these defense contractors.
The largest defense contractor in the world is
Lockheed Martin, which is a United States-based
company, also trades on the stock market.
And so they could potentially be getting some
of those contracts.
But again, do we know for sure?
No.
We don't know what's going to get passed.
We don't know what that company would get.
And we don't know if the company manages
their cash wrong and does what Boeing does
and just runs their company to the ground.
This is where your financial research comes into
play.
My goal is to show you how money
could potentially be moving depending on Trump's proposals.
This brings us to number four, much more
aligned with the financial space, which is Trump
has talked pretty openly about deregulating the financial
service industries, which essentially means deregulating Wall Street.
Now, regulations in general make doing business a
little bit more difficult because they create rules,
more rules, more difficulties.
Now, those rules are generally in place to
protect consumers, but sometimes they can also hurt
the businesses.
And this is where what Trump is saying
is he wants to roll back some of
these regulations to make it easier for these
businesses, banks, investment institutions, hedge funds to potentially
do more business, which some people are concerned
that it could create a bigger bubble.
But that's why you want to work on
your financial education and making sure that you're
protected for anything that could happen.
Let me read you a quote from S
&P Global.
Investors bid up bank stocks following President-elect
Donald Trump's victory in the 2024 presidential election.
The rally was immediate and widespread as the
market expects less severe government regulation starting in
2025, including a more supportive regime for approving
mergers and acquisitions.
That means we have a lot of investors
that are hoping that this gets passed, that
the financial service industries are going to be
deregulated to make it easier for Wall Street
companies, banking institutions, investment institutions to hopefully make
more money.
Now, of course, we don't know what's going
to get passed until it actually gets passed.
I'll be covering that here and on Market
Briefs, which is my free financial newsletter.
But this is where you want to understand
if this does happen, what does that mean?
It can make it easier for these investment
institutions to operate their business, which could make
it easier for them to drive up their
revenues, which could impact their profitability.
This brings us to number five, investing in
space exploration.
And the way that we can get insight
here is by taking a look at Trump's
first term where he began the Space Force
as a way to invest in space and
space exploration.
And based off of some of the talks
that Trump has given over the last number
of months, many people are excited and hoping
that Trump is going to continue this investment
into the space and space exploration and the
companies that are involved in space stuff.
In fact, let me read you what CNBC
had to say after Trump won the election
in regards to space exploration.
This past week, right after the election, saw
several pure play space stocks rally.
Just this week, we saw Rocket Lab up
41 percent, Intuitive Machines up 28 percent, Spire
Global up 26 percent, Planet Labs up 16
percent, Redwire up 15 percent, and AST Space
Mobile up 10 percent.
I hope you start to see why I'm
always being cautious with the things that I
say, because there's a lot of speculation here,
because we don't know exactly what's going to
get passed and we don't know to what
extent it's going to get passed.
But a lot of investors are excited about
the idea of space exploration potentially happening after
Trump is in the White House.
Again, we don't know what's going to happen
until it happens.
But if this is something you're interested in,
it's something you may want to pay attention
to to create a potential investment opportunity.
Which brings us to number six, deregulating oil
and gas, which is something that Trump has
been talking about pretty openly, about changing the
energy industry here in the United States.
Let me read you what CNBC had to
say about Trump's proposal to deregulate oil and
gas here in the United States.
Increasing liquified natural gas exports and leasing more
federal land for drilling are at the top
of the oil and gas industry's wish list
from Trump's second term.
Now, I'm not an expert when it comes
to the oil and gas industry, but what
we do know is that people in the
oil and gas industry are generally in favor
of Trump's proposals to deregulate the oil and
gas industry, because what we do know is
deregulations, again, generally make doing business easier.
They allow the companies to do more business,
to do more stuff, and in this case,
it's probably drilling more gas.
In fact, let me read you what Wall
Street Journal had to say about this.
The title is Trump's Energy Secretary Preaches the
Benefits of Climate Change.
And if you scroll down, what you see
is that Trump's Energy Secretary pick is fracking
CEO Chris Wright, who points to positive changes
produced by global warming in contrast with what
some oil giants say.
So what does all this mean?
Well, it seems like it's not good news
for renewable energies, and it seems like this
would be good news for companies that are
involved with oil and gas.
Now, I hope that you can see that
my goal with this video isn't to tell
you what to believe or to tell you
what's right, but rather to tell you what's
going on, that way you can be a
smarter investor and understand how the system works,
because now you have to understand how tax
cuts can impact your investments.
Now, while we don't know Trump's tax proposal,
what we do know is that he's been
talking about cutting taxes.
And according to the Center on Budget and
Policy Priorities, bigger tax cuts generally lead to
more stock buybacks.
While the corporate tax cut hasn't done much
to enhance the well-being of workers, it
has fueled a large increase in corporate stock
buybacks.
A corporate stock buyback is when a company
takes the cash out of their bank account,
or maybe they use debt or other forms
of dollars, but they take this money and
then they use this money to buy back
their own stock.
And the reason why they do this is
to reduce the supply of stock available, which
then artificially, generally inflates the price of their
stock.
Or in simple English, a company does a
stock buyback to increase the price of their
stock.
Now, are stock buybacks good for the company?
Well, generally, no, they don't really do much
for the company except increase the valuation of
the company or the stock.
Are stock buybacks good for the economy?
Well, not particularly, except the sense that investors
become wealthier, and maybe that means that they'll
use this more wealth to spend more money
in the economy, which I guess could indirectly
benefit the economy in that way.
Are stock buybacks good for employees in a
company?
Well, not necessarily, unless an employee owns stock
in a company, because otherwise it doesn't really
benefit them.
Are stock buybacks good for your investment in
the short term?
Yes, because they can help the stock price
go up.
So a stock buyback is kind of like
a dividend.
A dividend is when a company takes money
out of their bank account and they give
it away to shareholders in the form of
a check, or money being deposited in your
brokerage account.
A stock buyback is a similar concept.
A company takes the money out of their
bank account and then they just buy back
their own stock to make your stock more
valuable.
It's good for the investor, but doesn't really
do much for anybody else.
But this is where, of course, I want
you to understand the entire scope of this,
because, of course, stock buybacks have a risk
as well.
Because if a company empties their bank account
during the stock buyback, that could put them
up for potential risks in the future, because
those stock buybacks do not actually create any
real value for the company.
For example, you might remember, in 2019, Delta
did a huge stock buyback where they spent
billions of dollars buying up their own stock,
which helped inflate the stock price.
And then came 2020, the pandemic hit, nobody's
flying, and then Delta had to ask for
a multi-billion dollar bailout from taxpayers because
they no longer had money to pay their
employees.
So again, we don't know exactly what's going
to happen with tax cuts, but if we
do start to see some big corporate tax
cuts that could create an increase in stock
buybacks, which could create a short-term benefit
for those companies that are doing those buybacks.
This is why I say it is so
important for you to be financially educated, because
most people are operating in this economic system
on a motion instead of actually understanding how
our economic system works.
And the reality is, this economic system that
we live in is designed to benefit investors.
Now you can hate it or love it,
that really doesn't matter.
I want you to understand it, that we
can find the opportunity to build wealth.
Now again, all of these things create risk.
We have no idea what's going to happen
in 2025 or 2026.
I mean, even if one of these things
get passed, we could see a recession causing
the entire market to go down, even if
money is moving into one of these directions.
This is why I want you to be
a financially savvy investor and a financially sophisticated
investor, which means understanding your strategy.
Because if you are not the type of
person that can manage your psychology through a
market crash, through a recession, then you don't
have to worry about all of this.
Instead, do what I said in the beginning
of the video, which is A, B, B.
Always be buying.
You find a broad basket fund.
Maybe it's the total stock market.
Maybe it's the S&P 500.
Maybe it's the Dow Jones.
You find a broad basket fund, and then
you just A, B, B.
You don't worry about what's happening in the
White House.
economy.
You don't worry about what's happening in the
stock market.
You don't worry about the weather.
You don't care about what day it is.
You just keep buying.
Every week, every two weeks, every month, you
just keep buying no matter what.
And if you do this for the next
10, 20, 30 years, you will build wealth,
because we have seen the stock market go
up by around 10% a year for
the last 100 years on average.
Does that mean that the stock market always
goes up?
No.
We've seen about 16 recessions over the last
century.
And the problem is many people are going
about this economy, going about this stock market,
thinking that things are just going to continue
going up forever.
That's a very dangerous way to think, because
we will see a downturn.
And when the downturn happens, a lot of
people are going to panic.
A lot of people are going to be
blindsided.
But I want you to be able to
find the opportunity.
And that requires you to understand the strategy.
If this is your game, you just keep
buying.
You don't change it.
If you want to be a little more
involved, well, then you can look for where
money is moving that way you can find
a little bit more of a niche opportunity.
Again, more risk, more potential return.
But this is where your research and your
financial education becomes very valuable.
Again, if you want to join me on
my free workshop on January 7th, I'm going
to be walking you through how you can
create an investment system, how you can do
the research, how you can find unique investment
opportunities.
I have that link for you down in
the description.
And if you want to know how you
can stay up to date on what's happening
in the markets, when it's happening, Market Briefs
is another free resource that I have for
you.
I also have that link for you down
in the description as well.
This long-term debt cycle, if it happens
every 50 to 100 years, you might only
live through one.
We've seen how these short-term debt cycle
recessions work.
We saw it happen with 2008 with the
great financial crisis.
So the question you're going to naturally have
is, where are we on this long-term
debt cycle now?
Back in 2019, Ray Dalio said that we
are very late in this debt cycle.
So what does very late mean?