What if I told you that there was
an investor who achieved much higher returns than
Warren Buffett, Ray Dalio, Peter Lynch, George Soros,
Charlie Munger, and essentially all of the other
great investors that you can think of.
Not only did he beat them, his returns
blew theirs out of the water.
So if we look at this, Warren Buffett's
annual average return is 20.1%, Dalio's 13%,
Lynch 29.2%, Soros 20%, Charlie Munger 19
.8%, Jim Simmons 66% average return.
Out of all of the investors that I've
studied, no one has got a yield anywhere
near close to his.
And this is not just over one or
two years, this is over the past 31
years of consistently just destroying the market.
To put that into perspective at how impressive
that is, if you invest at $100 and
were able to achieve a 66% return
every year, after 31 years, that $100 would
be worth $665,810,000.
To regularly achieve something that high is unheard
of until Jim Simmons came along.
But how did he do it?
Jim Simmons relies on quantitative analysis to decide
the trades he makes.
He's a numbers man, he was a math
genius growing up, getting a bachelor's and PhD
in mathematics when he was young.
Just for some reason, math turned him on.
Now, the old excuse is, when do you
ever use math in the real world?
Well, Jim Simmons was about to answer this
question in a big way.
He used his math skill to become uber
-rich.
Originally, he used it to break codes with
the National Security Agency, as well as teaching
at MIT.
Although this paid good on a relative scale,
this is not generally the profession you'd go
for to amass a fortune.
He then made the decision that he wants
to step into finance and trading, where the
real money is.
Now, naturally, Simmons keeps his trading secrets behind
closed doors as much as possible.
Of course, if you had a fund earning
a 66% return every year, making you
a multi-billionaire, you probably wouldn't tell your
secrets either.
However, there is quite a bit that has
gotten through the cracks on his trading strategies.
So in this video, we're going to go
over seven of his key strategies that Simmons
used to trade in the market.
Back in 1982, quantitative analysis was not a
thing.
The models that we see traders use today,
no one had thought of.
So people generally relied a lot on perception
and homemade systems to trade.
For the first two years, Simmons did just
this.
He used ordinary, fundamental, and technical approaches to
trade in the market.
A lot of it was based around intuition
and instinct.
No models for the first two years, like
normal people do.
It was a similar approach to the way
everyday regular traders trade in the market today,
except, unlike most, Jim actually made money.
Because one, he was a math genius, and
two, because back in those days, there were
so many more opportunities.
Less competition, less computers trying to arbitrage the
market.
So he was able to make a decent
amount of money this way, but at least
according to Jim, he felt that it was
mainly luck and also emotionally draining, not knowing
if you're going to be making profits the
next day or not.
We were extremely successful.
I think it was just plain good luck,
but nonetheless, we were very successful.
But this was a very gut-wrenching business.
You know, you come in one morning, you
think you're a genius, and the next morning
you come and you feel like a jerk.
The market's against you.
He disliked the emotional side of trading, and
he wanted to find a way where you
could almost guarantee that money would be made.
Kind of like at a casino, the house
is always going to profit because the odds
are rigged in their favor.
They don't get emotional, they just want you
to keep playing.
Simmons aspired to create a model like this,
but for trading in the stock market, where
if you just keep trading, you're guaranteed to
win because the odds are in your favor.
In order to do this, Simmons needed a
lot of data.
For a quantitative analyst, data is obviously key,
and he would gather information on everything.
Weather, annual reports, monthly, quarterly reports, the historic
data itself, volumes, you name it.
Whatever there is.
We take in terabytes of data a day.
So his team would gather all of this
data up, backtrack it across history, and search
for anomalies.
Where is there something consistently odd happening that
I can profit from?
And the anomaly might be something like, every
time the date is leading into Christmas, the
stock would increase in price.
Most investors would try explaining the reasons why.
Simmons did not care why, he just cared
that the data showed it consistently happened.
And once he found the anomaly, he simply
would buy the stock leading into Christmas, and
sell after Christmas, each time making a profit.
That is a simple example of anomaly trading.
But Simmons would do this across thousands of
data sets, and search where the abnormalities were
that he could benefit from.
Secondly, he and his team would look for
trends.
This was an approach that worked very well
in the early days of trading.
The best place to go find trends, at
least back in the day, was in the
commodity market.
Copper, gold, silver, oil, corn, wheat.
These things would often follow a pattern.
So here's a simple example of the price
data of a commodity for a year.
We'll say it's wheat.
Simmons would zoom in on a smaller time
frame, say 20 days, and he would notice
that the commodity is trending.
Maybe it's trending upwards because less farmers are
able to sell during this time, or trending
downwards because of oversupply.
As we said before, Simmons doesn't care on
the reasons why.
All he cares about is that it is
happening, and how he can profit.
So if it was trending upwards, he would
trade it and buy, and if it was
downwards, he could short it, and make some
profit on the way down.
This system worked very well for him early
on, even though it sounds quite easy.
But after a while, people started to catch
on with this method, and it became more
and more obsolete.
Years ago, such a system would work.
Not beautifully, but it would work.
So you'd make money, you'd lose money, you'd
make money, but it's a very vestigial system.
Simmons would need to upgrade his strategy if
he wanted to keep making money in the
market, or risk going bust.
In the book, The Man Who Solved the
Market, Gregory Zuckerman stated that Medallion, which is
Simmons' flagship fund that averages the 66%
return, earned profits from trending and reversion-predicting
signals, especially a one called Deja Vu.
Reversion, in terms of trading, is when a
price of a particular stock will revert back
to the average, or it will revert back
to a particular metric.
Sometimes it will fall below the average, sometimes
above, but the job of Simmons' team will
be to profit from these fluctuations.
For example, you would place a stock like
Apple in the algorithmic model.
Then, it would look at a bunch of
different data points.
Maybe revenue, book value, peg ratio, and the
price to tangible book value.
And next, it would start to look for
patterns.
Where would it see the same things happen
over and over again?
Where would you get that feel of Deja
Vu?
And maybe the model would spot that over
time, Apple generally has a price to tangible
book value of 43.
Sometimes it would dip below, sometimes above, but
the pattern would always revert back to 43.
Again, Simmons would see this, he wouldn't care
about the reasons why, he would just know
that it happens.
And he would take advantage of this pattern.
His firm would simply make a trade when
the price goes below 43, it reverts back
to 43, and he makes some profit.
If it goes above 43, he could short
the stock, and they would just keep doing
this until the pattern would change.
That's a basic example of reversion predicting signals.
And maybe in the early days, it was
as simple as just a few data points
that you can profit from.
But as more and more traders started to
click on to these techniques, Simmons would develop
more complicated models to profit in the market.
Instead of just simple pairs, he created a
fund that involved complex signals and equity trades.
It would go through all data it could
find on a particular stock, correlate multiple variables,
and then use machine learning and their models
to find irregularities where they can make profits.
In order to create models that could take
in such vast and complex amounts of data,
then find patterns, and then profit, Jim would
need to find a team of very smart
people, like the Avengers.
But instead of helping the planet, they would
help solve complex trading algorithms.
People with PhDs, doctorate degrees, top 1%
of IQs, people who could code.
Instead of going for people on Wall Street
and with finance backgrounds, Jim looked to universities.
He started hiring people with doctorate degrees in
math and physics, astronomers, and statisticians.
People who could solve complicated problems.
They didn't necessarily have to have a finance
background.
In fact, he didn't want this.
Simmons said the important thing was that they
were very smart.
I like to say that you can teach
a physicist finance, but you can't teach a
finance person physics.
And this great team of what can best
be described as nerds would begin to crack
the codes for trading in the stock market.
And the smart thing about Simmons' strategy was
that he didn't hire these people as employees,
he hired them as partners.
The only way that you can be an
owner in the medallion fund is to be
employed there.
So this way, all of these very smart
workers are incentivized to make as much money
as possible, because the money would not just
go to a company, but to themselves as
well.
So you have hundreds of these PhD level
geniuses, all with one incentive to make as
much money in the market as possible.
This was a recipe for success.
During the mid-1980s, a top researcher of
Simmons' team began identifying ghost patterns in market
prices.
So the project was based on similar code
cracking that Jim and his team had worked
on at the National Security Agency.
The main idea was to look for patterns
that others failed to detect and then profit
from it.
The medallion fund would feature a collection of
a minimum of 8,000 signals based on
the short-term patterns of the entire batch
of scientists who work for medallion.
The fund then leveraged these signals, aka they
borrowed money, to trade in the market countless
times per day.
Reports say that they borrowed around $17 for
every $1 that they invested.
And this was a bit of a secret
to their success, the fact that they didn't
even have to use their own money.
They could borrow the money, quickly make some
trades and profit, and then return the borrowed
amount back.
Or just do the same thing again and
again.
The co-chief executive of Simmons' company said
on an un-lavid basis, aka not borrowing,
our models produce modest returns with very low
volatility.
Borrowing money helped change these returns into something
that wasn't modest at all and basically put
the company's returns on steroids.
The beauty of hiring PhD nerds over regular
investors is that they would have one focus
on the numbers.
Astronomers, physicists, mathematicians, they don't worry too much
on the emotions of the market, what investors
are saying, the strength of the brand or
anything like that.
No, to them it's kind of like a
science experiment or putting together an equation.
The only thing that matters is the numbers
and making sure that they work.
So instead of solving problems on how to
get to space, or the force needed in
a rocket, or solving a physics calculation, they
would solve trading algorithms.
Just like a science experiment, you just need
to keep changing the variables.
Does this one work?
Does this one make profit?
No, let's try another.
Does this one work?
Does this one?
No, let's try another.
And they'll just keep fiddling with the equation
and the variables until they find something that
makes them a profit.
By their very nature, they were perfectly suited
for this type of work.
As Jim Simmons was growing his fund, so
too was the rise of machine learning.
So machine learning is the ability of a
machine to use information to improve performance on
some set of tasks.
Whether that task be email filtering, speech recognition,
chess, or finding profitable trades in the stock
market.
Just like with chess, the machine can analyze
thousands of different moves and the consequences of
making each move.
It can predict if a move is beneficial
for the player or if it's going to
make the position worse.
And it's the same thing with a stock.
Machines can test thousands of different moves and
see which one leads to making money.
It's what's called machine learning.
So you find things that are predictive.
You might guess, oh, such and such should
be predictive, might be predictive, and you test
it out in the computer, and maybe it
isn't, maybe it isn't.
The beauty about machines is they can test
almost infinite amounts of data and theories in
the time it takes for a human to
test one thing, the machine can do a
million tests.
And Simmons realized this very early on, so
he incorporated machines into his trading strategy, which
gave him a huge advantage over his competition.
So those are seven strategies that Simmons used
to become what he is known as today,
the greatest investor on Wall Street, and also
the most successful hedge fund manager of all
time.
So if you're currently a PhD major or
just a high IQ individual, the next move
might not be to become a professor, teacher,
engineer.
Maybe you can also get into trading and
become the next Jim Simmons, but if you
do, be sure to learn from these seven
strategies.