Big forehead, take two.
Hi, my name is Andrei Jikh, hope you're
doing well.
Come for the finance and stay for the
beginner video on options trading.
This is the big video that I've been
meaning to make for so many years, but
the truth is, I didn't know how to
do options trading back then, and after playing
with it for several years now, I still
don't.
So in today's video, I wanted to invite
somebody who does know what they're doing, and
his name is Alex Pandrea.
He's somebody that I had on my YouTube
channel when I first started almost three years
ago, and back then, when I created his
Robinhood account for him, he had zero experience
with investing.
He started with about $15,000, he started
to play around with options, and in just
two short years, he was able to turn
his $15,000 into well over a million
dollars, which is kind of crazy to see
that progress.
Now, in this video, I'm going to show
you how to do options trading with Alex,
and it's going to be very complicated.
Halfway through, you're gonna get bored, you're gonna
be tired of it, you're gonna be like,
where is this going?
But I promise, if you watch this video
all the way through till the end, you
will learn three investing strategies that anyone can
do, starting with very little money that you
can apply today, and hopefully make some money
with.
Now, in this video, I'm not gonna sell
you a course.
This is not about collecting emails or phone
numbers from people.
This is all 100% free, so I
hope you enjoy it, and hopefully we can
simplify options trading and have it go from
this, to this.
So having said all that, let's get Alex
on and finally start the video.
What is up?
This is Alex Pandrea.
What's up, man?
What is going on?
Super excited to finally learn options trading.
It's something I've always wanted to learn.
I already know what you're thinking.
What's up?
You wanna take your monthly salary and put
it into out-of-the-money spy call
options expiring tomorrow, make a lot of money,
right?
If you said yes, you're in the wrong
place.
Get out.
It's my house, bro.
When we did a video together two years
ago, you started with about $16,000.
I set up your Robinhood account, and in
two years, show everybody your portfolio.
I'm gonna make you do this.
He's gonna make me do this.
This is what it is.
All right, so this is from trading options
in the last two years from about $16
,000.
It is now worth about 1.2 million,
which is a crazy return.
It doesn't really seem realistic to me.
You started my account with about, in Robinhood,
I've been investing long-term for, since I
was 20 years old or something, consistently, but
when I got into Robinhood, I started learning
more about trading and investing in different types.
So I've been trying to learn over the
last few years.
He's like, Andre's dividend investing is so boring.
None of that Warren Buffett stuff.
Well, I was watching the videos, and I
was like, I need something else, man.
This is just like, yeah.
The thing is about options trading is you
don't have to be like this crazy day
trader.
Definitely not.
There is definitely a stigma to it that
it is risky and that it's like almost
going to the roulette table and putting it
all on black, let's go.
But that's the preconceived kind of thoughts that
people have, especially in the last few years
with Wall Street bets and the forums and
everything that's going on.
You're like, options, stay away.
Or if you're like a gambler, baby, options,
sign me up.
I'm terrified of options, which is why I've
always wanted to learn it because I know
there are very safe ways of doing options
in a way that makes you some extra
money.
And you can essentially turn any portfolio into
an almost dividend paying portfolio.
There's many different choices and options, no pun
intended, for options.
When you buy a stock, you can buy
a stock, you can sell a stock.
There's very few, it's limited.
Let's just get started with it.
We've pumped it, we've hyped it enough.
The first question I have is, what is
the difference between buying stocks normally, like buying
and selling stocks, which I totally understand, and
options trading?
Well, that's a very good question, Andre.
I'm glad you asked that.
So get your phones ready because we're gonna
go into this right after that.
You got it?
Yeah.
He's ahead of the game, this one.
So when you're buying a stock, you can
hold it forever.
Sure, if you can live that long.
But in options, you have expiration dates and
the contract will expire at some point.
So it's not a forever thing.
The second thing is leverage.
You have to understand that one option contract
controls 100 shares of whatever the underlying stock
is in your company.
Okay, so if I buy one option contract,
whatever it is, in Apple, you're controlling 100
shares.
So you're leveraging up the position with less
money.
So you're telling me one option is worth
100 shares?
I don't even know how you do that
and I'm watching from behind.
Yeah.
Yeah, this is totally incredible.
And the last thing is that there's just
more choice.
There's a variety of different things that you
can do rather than just buying and selling
a stock, which is basically what you could
do with stocks.
There's just a lot more choice.
All right, so pull your phone out and
follow along.
This is not gonna make any sense to
you.
When I first was shown this, I didn't
make any sense to me, but I don't
know about you.
Look, it didn't make sense to me either,
but that's why we're here, right?
To learn the basics and contract and options
have a few key elements that I think
are important to understand.
Okay.
And we're gonna go through them one by
one and then we're gonna go through examples.
Yeah, and then I promised we're gonna apply
these techniques to actually make some money with,
but here's the interface.
So walk me through to the beginning.
Okay, so go ahead, grab your phone and
go to your favorite underlying, your favorite asset,
your favorite stock company, whatever you wanna call
it, whatever turns you on.
We're gonna use our capital to purchase these
underlying equities.
While adjusting your bow tie, yeah.
So go ahead, in this case, we chose
Apple.
Okay.
So as you can see at the bottom
right-hand corner, you have trade.
You might have to turn this feature on
in Robinhood if it's not turned on already
to get option trading, but you'll notice a
few options here.
You can buy the shares, you can sell
the shares if you have them, or you
can trade options, and that's what we're gonna
go on.
So go ahead, click trade options, and you're
gonna get something that pops up that looks
a little bit like this.
Now, at first, you're gonna be like, oh,
I gotta read all of this.
It's very confusing looking, yeah.
Gonna be like up, down, left, right.
You're gonna be turning around in circles, you'll
get dizzy, and then you wouldn't wanna do
any of this anymore because you'd be like,
I just need to lay down.
So don't worry, take it easy.
We're gonna go through each of the key
elements, starting with the top.
Now, the top has a bunch of dates
on there.
Okay.
This is called the expiration date and is
the first key feature of an options contract.
And basically, what the expiration date is is
how long is the contract gonna be valid
for.
Two people make a contract, there's an expiration
date, it expires then, and that is what
the dates here represent.
So you'll notice that it has August 6th,
which is tomorrow, right?
August 13th, which is next week, or September
3rd, which is next month.
So as you can see, the options go
out even to a few years out, right?
So the farther out you go, the less
risky it is.
And the closer you pick a date, the
more risk you're taking.
100%.
Because it's very hard to predict what's gonna
happen tomorrow.
But we could probably predict that two years
from now, the market will probably go a
little bit higher.
Yes, or probably not do something.
Right.
As you'll see in the next example.
So let's pick a date.
Let's go September 3rd, a month from now,
all right?
Now, you'll notice once you hit a date,
a whole bunch of things pop up.
Yes.
Looks like a jet pilot screen.
For those jet pilots out there, you'll be
like, oh, wow.
This is my jam.
But for everybody else, us included, we gotta
just learn a little bit about the basics.
Right.
So if we look in the middle here,
we see share price, $146.
This is what the current price of Apple,
in this case, is right now at the
time of recording.
Now on the left side, you have strike
prices.
We call them strike prices, which is basically
the future potential price of the stock.
Okay.
So it could go up or it could
go down.
This is pretty basic.
But we have strike prices.
We have 147, 148, 149, 150.
So strike prices are basically what the stock
should be worth at the end of the
contract.
But investors could never use really simple words
like that's what the price is.
So far, so good.
Okay.
Now the third key piece is just the
premium and the contract, which is here on
the side where you see all of these
little numbers, $3.40, $3.95. This is
called the premium.
And the premium is the amount of money
that is paid by the buyer or collected
by the seller for the contract itself.
So those are the three key elements that
you need to know.
The expiration date, all right?
When the contract expires, how long it's valid
to, the strike price, the potential future price
of the underlying stock, and the premium, which
is either paid or collected.
Let's give you an example of actually applying
this stuff.
So you'll see it and it'll make a
lot more sense.
So in our contract, there's a few things
that we have to discuss, right?
Is the key elements that we just talked
about, right?
The expiration date, the strike price, et cetera.
I wanna have the rights to buy this
deck of cards six months from now.
And that is the expiration date, six months
from now.
And now we also have to put a
price on it.
I am willing to buy this for, let's
say $13, okay?
I think it's gonna go up to 15.
So I'm gonna put my strike price in
at $13, let's say, but I think it
could go maybe even more than that.
So I'll just pick a strike price, $13,
but I know this is selling for 10
right now.
So now we've had the strike price figured
out as well, okay?
We have the expiration date, we have the
strike price.
And now Andre comes to me and goes,
why would I wanna enter into an agreement
with this guy?
Why would I want the contractual obligation?
The reason I would ever wanna go into
a contract with this guy is because he's
gonna pay me a premium.
Cough it up, son.
What do you want, a dollar?
Give me that dollar.
Oh, it didn't work.
So that's my premium that I get to
keep.
And that's the benefit for entering into a
contract.
Now our contract represents a hundred of these
decks.
It's not one deck, it's a hundred of
them.
And we already know that, right?
One contract controls a hundred shares of the
underlying asset, or in this case, Apple, that
we did, or in this case, a deck
of cards, all right?
So with this contract, we've already established our
terms and we're gonna see how it plays
out, okay?
So options could be broken up into two
sections, calls and puts.
Option is basically just two things.
It could either be a call or it
could be a put.
And you can do one of two things
with those options.
You can buy a put or you can
sell a put.
You can buy a call or you can
sell a call.
Simple.
These are the four options.
We're gonna jump right into exactly what each
of those mean.
Very important to understand.
And once we do that, we can go
into some examples and make some money.
Okay, so now that Alex is gone, let
me just explain it in my own words
because it's pretty complicated, but hopefully this helps.
First, you can buy a call option.
This makes you a bull because you think
that the stock is going to go up
in value beyond the strike price at or
before the date of expiration, at which point
you have the option to buy that stock,
but you also have to pay somebody a
premium for doing that.
Now you can buy what's called a put
option, which is just a way for you
to be a bear, which means that you
think the stock will go down below the
strike price at or before the date of
expiration, at which point you have the option
to sell your shares, but you also have
to pay someone a premium for doing that.
Now you could also sell what are called
call options, which means you have the obligation
to sell your shares at a strike price
at that expiration date, and you make money
by collecting those premiums for selling those call
options.
Now, if the stock does not hit the
strike price, you do not have to sell
your shares and you get to keep your
premium, but you can also sell the put
option, which is the obligation to buy the
stock at the strike price at or before
the date of expiration.
And again, you make money by collecting the
premiums.
And if the stock does not hit the
strike price, then you don't have to buy
those shares.
That's how it works.
Those are the four things you can kind
of do.
That's a very simple explanation, which I know
is still complicated.
So just press the J button on your
keyboard a few times to go back and
hopefully it makes more sense.
Now that you know all of that, let's
apply these techniques to your investing and hopefully
make some money.
There's three ways to actually do this.
And we're gonna start with the first one,
which is selling covered calls.
Yes, a very easy strategy.
If you are out there and you already
have a portfolio of a bunch of stock
with at least 100 shares of each, you
can then sell a covered call, which basically
means selling calls, exactly what you just explained,
and collect the premium on your already invested
shares.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So it's almost like you're getting some dividends.
So go ahead and show me how you
would sell an option.
So go ahead, trade.
Okay, trade.
And then you're gonna hit trade options.
And then again, like we did before, we're
gonna pick an expiration date.
I usually tend to think a safe route
is a few months out, let's say.
Call it two months out.
So go two months out.
Okay, so what is that, October?
Sure, let's do, yeah, October, September, that's fine.
So now, again, we're going to sell a
call, which means- Sell call.
Perfect.
So we're going to sell the call, which
means hit the sell button and hit the
call button.
And once you do this, all you have
to ask yourself is, I don't think Apple
will get to X strike price.
So go ahead and choose a strike price
of where you don't think that Apple will
be by October 15th.
And guess what?
Your opinion is fine, but Robinhood here does
the calculation for you.
As you can see here, you have your
strike prices and next to them, chance of
profit.
Now, if you go for a chance of
profit, let's say 83%.
I'm going to do that.
I want to do 83%.
Okay, which is 83% chance you're going
to make money off of this trade.
Which means Apple will most likely not get
to $160 by October.
That's right, and if it does, all that
means is you are going to be forced
or obligated to sell that- My shares.
Your shares at that price.
But it means that my investment doesn't go
to zero.
It's not like I lose everything.
All it means is just my stocks are
forced to be sold.
And that's okay because I'll still have money
to either buy back into Apple, or I
could buy something else.
And the best thing is you're still collecting
the premium on it.
So if you own a hundred shares, so
for example, for me, if I put one,
that represents 100 shares, my premium would be
$177, which is pretty incredible.
And if I put two, that's 200.
I know I have at least 200 shares.
I don't want to have 300, so I
can't put three, but I know I could
use at least two.
And that would give me a premium of
$354.
That's right.
So if Apple does not get to $160,
you get to keep that premium, all $354,
which you get right away.
And you don't have to sell your shares.
So let's do it.
Review.
Bam, swipe up.
And it's gone.
Now I still receive my dividends, even though
Robinhood took it as collateral, right?
That's right.
It's still your shares.
These are yours that you own.
They're just keeping it there just in case.
All right, so the second application of options
trading is buying stocks by selling puts, right?
Yes.
So basically you might be out there saying,
I want to buy whatever stock you're interested
in.
And before you go straight into buying that,
you take a second and you say, hold
on.
I can probably get a better price by
using options to get into my position.
So remember, selling a put is the obligation
to buy that underlying.
So we're going to use that to our
advantage.
So what company do you want to invest
in?
So I've always wanted to buy the win,
but maybe I can get a better price
on it.
Right now it's 98 bucks.
And maybe you're saying I could do better
than 98.
So go ahead, trade.
Go to trade options.
And we're going to pick first and foremost,
the expiration date.
So let's go to the end of the
year, let's say the December 17th.
Okay.
So now you have your option of, do
I buy?
Do I sell?
Do I call?
Do I put?
All of that stuff.
What do we do?
Sell.
What did you call me?
All right.
Sell, put.
Perfect.
So now you just have to ask yourself,
what price do you want to pay?
And are you okay owning win at?
Right.
So I'm okay with owning the win at,
I mean, even honestly at these prices, but
let's say $85.
$85 is perfect.
I'm perfectly happy with owning it at $85.
Okay.
So worst case, and we're not saying worst
case scenario now because you actually do want
to own it.
Sometimes you're selling the put just to collect
the premium, hoping it doesn't get there.
But in this case, and a lot of
institutions use this method to get into and
out of positions, we're going to go to
the strike price of 85.
Great.
And for every one contract, that's going to
have you buy a hundred shares.
So let's just say one, for example, and
you're going to collect a premium of $523.
There you go.
So if it doesn't reach 85, guess what?
You're going to collect that whole premium and
go home happy, pappy, get yourself some Uber
Eats and- Some Pokemon Uncut sheets.
Oh, for 500 bucks.
Nice.
That's not going to happen.
Good deals right here.
And if it does hit that price, then
guess what?
You are obligated- I'm forced to buy
those positions.
I will be forced to buy a hundred
shares at $85.
Which is okay because when selling options, you
just have to ask yourself.
And I'm going to ask you now, are
you okay owning win at 85?
We already established that.
The answer is yes.
That's good.
And we're good to go.
We're good to go.
So you're going to collect that premium.
Go ahead and hit review.
And you need buying power, right?
As collateral, just like we did covered calls.
You're using collateral of your shares.
In Robinhood, for this case, you need to
be enough to buy the 100 shares of
stock.
So make sure you have that.
Robinhood will keep that as collateral and you'll
be on your merry way.
So now I've just made $520 of premium
right away.
And on December 17th, if the win does
not hit, that $85, I get to keep
that $520.
Because the option will expire worthless and you
don't have to do anything.
Nothing happens.
But if the win does hit $85 or
below, then I would have to buy a
hundred shares worth at $85.
Which by his standards is okay.
Okay with me too.
We're good to go.
Done.
Bingo, bingo.
Bongo.
Bongo drums.
Where they at?
All right, and the third option is something
called leaps, which are pretty cool.
Yeah, so basically we understand the fact that
one option contracts controls 100 shares.
And again, we're taking advantage of all these
options, key features in our investing.
So if you want to, let's say buy
Apple.
So you want to buy Apple.
Yeah, which is pretty expensive.
And I might not have the money to
buy a hundred shares.
And that's perfect because we just learned about
options and we understand that one option share
controls a hundred.
You got it.
And they got it too.
They're yelling at the screen, 100 shares.
And smashing that like button.
It's so smooth.
You're so smooth.
So if you want to invest in Apple
and maybe don't have the capital to buy
a hundred shares, which is going to be
at this price, $146 times, it's going to
be $14,000 to buy 100 shares.
You can control that 100 shares by buying
some options.
So let's go ahead and do that.
This is really interesting.
So just quick math here, a hundred times
$146 is roughly $14,600 ish, right?
Now let's say I don't have $14,500
to buy a hundred shares, but this is
what we can do.
We could go to trade, trade options.
And we're going to pick an expiration date.
Really far.
Really far, yes.
So the farthest we can go in this
case is September 15th, 2023.
Great, so that's a few years out.
We're going to buy our call.
So now you have to ask yourself, what
price do I think Apple will be by
September 23rd, 2023?
Well, I don't know what price it will
be, but I think it'll be above a
hundred dollars.
That's a very good call.
Get it, call?
So we can make the bet that Apple
will be above a hundred dollars.
So we can go ahead and buy the
call option for a hundred dollars.
Now, in this case, you'll notice something.
If we go down to a hundred, the
strike price of a hundred, we're going to
give ourselves two years for Apple to be
above a hundred dollars.
But if you take a look right here,
break even, it says 153, because we have
to take into account the premium that we
paid.
So yeah, this is the interesting thing.
So even though it might seem as though
by buying one contract for a lot cheaper,
for example, if we click on this, you
could see that right now today, it's going
to cost me $5,340.
And for that amount of money, you get
to control a hundred shares and that's a
lot cheaper than paying $14,600.
Exactly.
But the catch is that this is a
premium.
You have to pay somebody to exercise this,
right?
To get a control of a hundred shares.
But that's why right here, the break even
number that you see shows you $153.
That means the strike price plus the premium
that you're right.
It's taking into account the premium.
So two years from today, if Apple is
$153 and 40 cents, that means you technically
broke even you didn't make any money.
So for you to actually make money, Apple
should be worth more than that.
So 153 is around what the price is
today.
We're basically saying our bet is it'll be
worth more than it is today.
Now, what if Apple actually drops below a
hundred dollars?
You lose money.
There's no easy way to say it.
I mean, there is an inherent risk of
options.
This is one of them, right?
But you have to keep in mind that
you do not have to hold a contract
to expiration.
You can sell it further.
So if you're in profit a little bit,
or if you're in profit loss and you
think you're going to lose more, you sell
it and you move on.
The reason that you want to do this,
maybe over buying a hundred shares is because
again, you may not have enough money to
do that with a hundred shares.
And because you want to leverage and be
exposed to the performance of Apple and still
make money.
You got it.
I'm impressed.
I don't know what else to say.
Wait, that means I could take your monthly
salary and put it into out of the
money, spied fall options expiring tomorrow, make a
lot of money.
And that was options trading.
So go check out Alex's channel on YouTube.
He just started it.
He's going to talk about investing options, trading
business, traveling, all sorts of things.
He's like the magic Harry Potter.
That's better looking and more talented than me.
And I'm really proud of him for turning
his portfolio into over a million dollars.
It's crazy what he's been able to accomplish.
And I think you'll learn a lot from
his channel.
So go check him out.
And in the meantime, go get up those
two free stocks with Weeble.
When you deposit a hundred dollars using the
link down below, you'll get up to $250
worth of free Bitcoin using this block by
link right here and go track those stocks
automatically with the Patreon link down below.
Love you.
Thank you so much for watching.
I'll see you soon.
Peace.