People are making thousands of dollars each month
in passive income by drop shipping products from
AI built Shopify stores.
I've made millions of dollars with drop shipping.
I've been able to make hundreds of thousands
of dollars with AI.
Five hundred dollars a day.
Working from home.
Hundreds of dollars a day from this side
hustle.
I've made six hundred thousand dollars this month
alone.
Apparently anyone can do this from anywhere in
the world, but is this too good to
be true?
Well, today I want to put it to
the test by only using free tools to
make a Shopify store and see how many
products I can sell online.
But I'm setting myself three rules.
Number one, I must use free AI tools
and keep the total cost of the shop
creation to under one dollar.
Number two, I have to be able to
do it all from my laptop.
And number three, I need to finish it
in less than an hour.
Okay, start the timer.
Right, I've got a list of steps to
complete.
The first thing on my plan is to
find a free AI tool to create our
Shopify store.
Now, I've done quite a lot of searching
around and the best one I found is
Build Your Store.
It claims to be able to build a
Shopify store for us and lets us sell
other people's products without needing our own inventory
or doing any of the work ourselves.
The idea is when the store receives an
order, the product is shipped directly to the
customer, which allows us to make a profit
without any more work on our end.
If you want to follow along, feel free
to head down to the description of the
video and click the top link.
So I've loaded up the page and now
I'm going to click this button here that
says Build My Free Store because that's exactly
what we want it to do.
Now they're asking for my full name, which
is of course Mark Tilbury, and they want
an email address.
And to pick a password, right, that's done.
And then just click Next.
Now it's asking me to choose a niche.
You have six options here to choose from.
Fashion and apparel, pets, electronics and gadgets, home
and garden, sports and fitness, and finally an
option for I'm not sure.
Lots of people would just pick something they're
interested in.
However, it's best to approach this with a
business mind and think to yourself, what do
you confidently know that has a large market?
Honestly, all of these options are pretty good.
However, I'm just going to go for sport
and fitness because my son is always at
boxing or running or in the gym.
So I'm pretty sure there's a big demand
for these types of products, especially amongst younger
people.
I've even heard that Gen Z are now
meeting people at running clubs instead of nightclubs.
Very different from back in my day, that's
for sure.
Right, that's the first one off my list.
The next thing on my list is to
customize the store and make it appealing to
our customers.
Now, there are six banners on here to
choose from.
So let's go through them and find out
what suits our store best.
The first one has a lot of different
sporting items, which may seem good, but if
we don't end up selling those products, it
could confuse our customers.
So we'll skip that one.
Then there's this one with just a woman
on her own.
While it's a nice design, it doesn't really
represent our entire audience and we want our
store to appeal to both men and women.
So using this logic, the bottom right one
also feels, well, a bit too female only.
So we'll pass on that.
So I have these remaining three.
I think the bottom left one works great.
And the middle right one pops really nicely
with the sunset, which could help grab attention
and create a positive first impression.
Remember, the banners are the first thing our
customers will see when they land on our
store.
So it's important they reflect what we're about
and what we're offering.
If you don't feel like any of these
work for you, then don't worry as you
can always change them later on.
Now that we've chosen our banners, let's hit
continue and move on to the next step.
To let the AI build our store, we
need to set up a free Shopify account.
So that's the next thing on my list.
The first thing I'm going to do is
click on access Shopify, which opens up in
a new tab.
Now I'm going to type in my email
address and then hit start free trial.
Then I just need to pick a password
and click create Shopify account.
Now, as you can see, Shopify is now
asking us a few setup questions, but since
AI is going to handle most of the
work for us, we can just select, I
don't want help setting up to save us
time.
Now it's asking us to choose a plan
for when the free trial ends.
The basic plan looks good enough for what
we're building as it's designed for solo entrepreneurs.
And it's also the most popular option.
So I'm just going to go ahead and
select that one.
Then I'll quickly add in my payment details.
So we're all ready when the trial ends,
but don't worry right now because it's completely
free.
And after the trial, it's just one pound
or $1 per month for the first three
months.
As we're not paying anything right now, this
doesn't count towards our $1 budget.
I know we'll probably have to pay it
before we get some sales in, but technically
I haven't paid it yet.
So I think you can let me off
with this one.
Once that's all set up, Shopify takes us
to this dashboard for our new store where
we can manage everything.
Now it does look pretty confusing, but that's
fine as we won't have too much to
do in here ourselves because soon the AI
will be taking control.
That sounded pretty scary.
I hope this AI stuff doesn't lead us
into a Terminator situation.
Now we need to install the Build Your
Store app.
This might seem like it's getting a bit
confusing, but after this, it gets a whole
lot easier.
So I'm gonna click Access Shopify again, which
opens another tab.
On this page, I'm gonna click the Install
button to add the app to our Shopify
account.
With this done, I can click Create My
Custom Store.
Now we just need to give the AI
a bit of time to work its magic
and build a store website for us in
the background.
We'll check out the results later to see
what it's created.
But for now, let's keep things moving and
jump onto the next step.
Right, the next thing on my list is
to find some winning products for our store.
This is so important because the right products
can make or break the store.
They attract customers, drive sales, and ultimately set
us apart from our competition.
To make this as easy and efficient as
possible, we're gonna register for AutoDS.
This tool does the heavy lifting for us
by selecting products that are proven to sell.
It also takes care of pricing, uploading professional
photos, and once we start making sales, it'll
also ship the products directly to our customers.
I'm going to go back to the Build
Your Store website and select Register to AutoDS.
This gives us the option to either sign
up with a Google account or to enter
your details manually.
Just make sure that you use the same
email address you use for Shopify and Build
Your Store to keep everything linked.
Okay, so now it's asking me, where will
we be selling?
So, of course, I'm choosing Shopify.
Now we need to pick the right plan.
AutoDS offers the first 30 days for just
99 cents on any plan.
This gives us a chance to test everything
out and see how well it works.
In my opinion, the basic plan doesn't have
enough features to make this truly passive, but
we don't need the advanced plan yet either.
The starter 500 plan looks perfect for what
we need, so I'm selecting Start Now for
99 cents.
There are a few different payment methods available.
I'm gonna go with PayPal as I always
use it.
Right, so there we go.
All sorted and just like that, that's my
$1 budget officially spent.
Hopefully there's nothing else left to pay for
while setting up this store because at this
point, I've only got one cent left.
Now it's finally time to publish our store.
I'm actually quite excited to see everything come
together.
The last thing we need to do here
is to click Access Shopify and then uncheck
the box that says Restrict access to visitors
with a password.
Now that's done, I'm gonna press Continue and
boom, our store is officially live with winning
products.
Now that our Shopify store is live, the
next thing on my list is to take
a proper look and make any tweaks we
might need before sending customers over there.
This actually looks a lot better than I
thought it would.
Our two banners are in place and the
AI has set up buttons that lead straight
to the new product arrivals page, which should
make it easy for customers to get around
the site.
Down here are some of the winning products
that AutoDS has added for us.
First, we have what looks like some kind
of breathing trainer.
Actually, I have seen my son use one
of these before.
It works kind of like high altitude training
by limiting the amount of oxygen you can
take in.
I think the idea is that when you're
in a competition, your body can carry more
oxygen in your blood, which should make you
perform better.
To be honest, the more I'm talking about
it, the more I want one for myself.
So I think this will sell really, really
well.
Next, we've got bag clips for your golf
clubs.
Now, I personally use these all the time
because they stop my clubs rattling together and
getting damaged.
And if you've ever had to replace a
carbon shaft, you know how expensive that can
be.
Then we have the classic resistance band, which
I imagine is always a good seller, and
a warm jogging hat to round things off
as it's getting a little bit chilly this
time of year.
So honestly, I'm pretty impressed with the items
it's picked, but if we did want to
pick more, then it's pretty simple to do
that too.
I just have to head over to AutoDS,
click Marketplace, and then Trending Products.
Now, this brings up a page with all
the products that are selling very, very well.
And we could pick any of these, even
if they don't necessarily fit with our niche.
To be honest though, it's probably not a
good idea to be too random with it,
as your customers need to know what your
store is about.
So I'm gonna click on this filter for
sports and fitness, and it pulls up some
products that would fit really well into our
store.
Now, if I wanted to add one of
these, then all I'd have to do is
click Import Draft and then wait for the
import of the product.
Then it gives me the option to adjust
all the information and photos before publishing it
onto the store.
Now, I'm pretty impressed so far, but let's
dive a bit deeper and check out what
our product page looks like and see if
we can spot any mistakes we need to
fix.
Let's click on the golf club clips.
Now, there is a decent selection of product
photos, and to be fair, they do look
quite professional.
There's also quite a wide range of different
shots, which is important because when I'm buying
something, I always like to look at a
few different photos.
According to AutoDS, these golf clips cost me
$6.84, and dropshippers normally sell their items
for two to two and a half times
their cost, so I should be able to
sell these for at least $13.68, which
would give us $6.84 profit per sell,
not taking into account any marketing costs.
Now, I'll be honest, that's not a crazy
amount of money, but when you're selling at
scale, it could definitely start to add up.
Plus, if I think these clips could sell
for more than $13, I can always bump
up the price manually and see how it
goes.
One small detail I really like on here
is the little animation on the PayPal button.
Now, I've always found that having PayPal payments
available on my website adds a bit more
trust and often improve sales.
The AI has even written the product descriptions
for us and thrown in some emojis.
I'll admit, that is handy and saves a
lot of time, which I'm a bit short
of right now.
It's also included related product suggestions at the
bottom of each page, which could help with
upselling.
I'll admit, it's fairly basic, but I found
that basic websites often perform better.
This footer is actually a bit of a
surprise.
I wasn't expecting much here, because let's be
honest, footers are usually an afterthought, but the
AI has done a decent job with it.
All the important pages are already set up,
like the shipping policies and terms and conditions.
These little details might not seem like a
big deal, but they do make the store
look a lot more professional.
Now, let me click into the terms and
conditions page and take a look.
Yep, most of the heavy lifting's already been
done.
All I need to do is drop in
a store name, our location, and some contact
details to finish off.
Now, the only thing letting the store down
right now is the domain name.
It's just a random jumble of characters, and
honestly, it doesn't scream professional.
A good domain name is so important, because
it's the first thing customers see.
So I'm gonna head back to Build Your
Store AI to sort that out.
I'm gonna set up a .store domain instead
of a .com, because it's specifically designed for
online stores.
There's actually been studies that show websites with
a .store domain get 87% more traffic
and rank two times higher on Google.
So using a domain like this should actually
help us sell more.
When you think about it, this makes sense,
because when someone sees a .store domain, they
know right away they're visiting a shop.
Luckily, we can get a .store domain for
free as we're using the Build Your Store
AI tool.
However, if you aren't using this, then you
can also buy one from sites like GoDaddy
and Namecheap.
Let's go with something simple like Tilbury Fitness,
because let's face it, I have the body
of a Greek god, and obviously everyone wants
to look like me.
Now, I've got to link the domain name
to the store, so I'm gonna press Connect
Now and enter the new domain name here.
Now, it will take a few moments to
verify, and then we're ready to go.
Before we officially start selling, I'm gonna spend
my last bit of time left on the
clock to tweak the website, stuff like filling
in the footer details, linking some social media
accounts, and making sure everything looks polished.
There we go, all done and just in
time.
Now it's time to move on to the
exciting part, promoting the store and getting those
first sales in.
Okay, so it's a couple of days later
now, as I needed some time to order
a couple of the products.
The next thing on my list is to
advertise our store.
So to get some eyeballs on our store,
I've decided to work with some influencers.
Now, Gymshark has proved this strategy works very
well in the fitness niche, and it's great
because I'll get a positive endorsement from a
trusted figure and traffic to my store.
So it's essentially killing two birds with one
stone.
But don't worry, I'm not gonna be spending
thousands of dollars working with huge influencers.
I've got a much better plan.
I'm gonna use micro-influencers.
These are accounts with anywhere from 10 to
50,000 followers, whereas macro-influencers are accounts
with 500,000 to a million followers.
So what does that make me then?
Super macro, that is terrible.
I'm not doing this just to save costs.
According to Socialbakers, micro-influencers boast up to
a 60% increased engagement rate compared to
macro-influencers.
Micro-influencers also have a 20% plus
higher conversion rate.
This can help brands boost their e-commerce
sales.
That sounds perfect for what we need.
So I've reached out to a couple of
lads I know called the Graze Brothers.
They've been making short videos for a couple
of years now and have around 14.5
,000 followers on Instagram.
They do have more on other platforms, but
I'm more interested in Instagram because I want
them to post a story with a link.
I could also get them to promote the
other products, but first I wanna test out
if their audience will actually buy before risking
any more money.
And who knows, people might even explore the
shop and buy other items without me having
to promote them directly.
I approved their script yesterday and they've just
sent me the final video.
But before we have a look, let's do
a bit of quality check on the items
I ordered.
This is the Breathing Trainer and it feels
pretty damn good and built to last.
I think my son might even take it
for himself.
But seriously, it's always good to know that
the quality is good because the last thing
we want is unhappy customers wanting refunds.
Okay, so we also have the hat.
Nice and woolly, that should keep nice and
warm.
I like the fact it's got a peak
on it.
Very stylish, can't be bad.
And the gold clips, do you know what?
They are really good.
They are better quality.
Because my ones slip off and they've got
a lot more power behind them.
So I think I'll be having those for
myself.
And then a resistance band.
They're always popular.
So I think we should be onto a
winner with those.
Right, let's take a look at the video.
What are you doing?
I'm just wearing my respirator.
Respirator?
You're in a gym, not a hospital, mate.
But it's improving my cardio.
What are you on about?
The Breathing Training Respirator restricts your breathing, which
increases your red blood cell count, helping you
improve your cardio.
Buy it today using the link in the
bio.
Well, that's definitely a bit wacky, but that's
part of the charm.
It's quick, attention-grabbing, and shows off the
breathing trainer in action, which is exactly what
we needed.
That high energy, slightly off-the-wall style
works really well on Instagram stories because it
stops people from skipping and pulls them in.
Even though it's not the most traditional approach,
it fits the Grey's Brothers audience perfectly.
Their followers love this kind of content and
it feels so natural coming from them.
I'm gonna get them to put this story
up with a link to the product page
and check back tomorrow.
So let's hope we make some sales.
So it's been 24 hours and I've got
some exciting news.
We've made some sales.
Now, it doesn't seem like my approach of
only promoting one product really worked as people
didn't buy anything else.
But as of today, we've sold 12 of
these breathing trainers.
Okay, two of those sales were technically me
for testing, of course.
But the other 10 were legit.
So not counting my two orders, 10 genuine
purchases for 13 pounds and 42 pence is
134 pounds and 20 pence.
And converted to US dollars is $170.85.
But of course, not all of that is
profit.
The items cost me an average of $3
.95 each.
So $39.50 went towards product costs and
shipping.
As Autodesk shipped all the orders for us,
we didn't need to worry about anything.
After factoring in the $50 I paid the
Graves Brothers and the $1 Shopify fee after
our three-day trial ran out, our total
cost came to $90.50. That leaves us
with a profit of $80.35. Now, I
know $80 might not sound life-changing, but
let's put this into perspective.
This was all done with minimal effort, using
AI tools and a budget of just $1
to set everything up and $50 for marketing.
Now, imagine scaling this.
If we promoted 20 products and they kept
ticking along making regular sales, this could easily
turn into thousands of dollars in profit every
month.
If you'd like to see a follow-up
video in the future, be sure to give
this one a thumbs up.
Of course, before I post this, I'll need
to change the name of the store to
make sure no one stumbles across the site
and starts buying products as that wouldn't make
it a fair test.
If you wanna see more ideas for making
passive income, I've got another video right up
there, but don't click on it just yet.
Make sure to subscribe if you wanna grow
your wealth, okay?
I'll see you over there.