Are you frustrated to have only a small
trading account?
Well, in this video, our Head of Options
Trading teaches you a strategy that requires surprisingly
little capital to produce income of $500 or
more per week.
I'm Mike Bellafiori and we're one of the
top proprietary trading firms located in New York
City and proud to develop number seven and
even eight figure per year Watch, take notes,
and learn so you can grow your trading
account.
Hi, I'm Seth Freyberg and I'm the Head
Trader of SMB Capital's Options Trading Desk here
in Manhattan.
And when most people think about options, they
think of them as a cheap way to
take advantage of big moves on stocks without
having to actually go out and buy the
stocks, which of course is a part of
what options trading is all about.
But what a lot of people don't realize
is that options can be used for a
completely different purpose, and that is to create
cash income on a steady basis week after
week throughout the year.
And that's through the use of a very
easy to learn option strategy that we're going
to be covering in today's video.
If you're absolutely brand new to options trading
and you don't know much about options and
how they work, we've created a video for
you to understand options basics.
And if you click the video appearing on
your screen right now, it will lay out
the groundwork for you to understand this simple
strategy that we're going to be covering so
that you can generate cash flow in your
trading account.
Then when you're finished, you can come back
and watch the rest of the video.
Okay, so what we're going to be teaching
you in today's video is a strategy for
making $500 in most weeks of the year.
Now, most people naturally think that to produce
that kind of weekly cash income, you'd need
a large trading account containing somewhere between $100
,000 and $200,000 to even have a
shot in making that kind of cash income.
But that's not the case at all for
the strategy that we're going to be teaching
you in this video.
In fact, all you need is a fraction
of that in your account to execute what
we'll be describing in today's video.
Okay, so let's get started.
As many of you know, the ETF known
as the Q's, which stands for the ticker
symbol QQQ, is an ETF which tracks a
basket of stocks, mimicking the NASDAQ 100 index,
which contains primarily tech stocks.
And so as you know, tech stocks have
been on a tear in 2023 after a
weak year previously.
And throughout the first five months and into
the first few days of June of this
year, the Q's were up 34% for
the year, a massive rally in five months.
So let's say that on the first Friday
in June, on June 2nd, with the Q's
trading at 354.65, you pulled up an
options chain expiring a week later on June
9th.
And you look for a put option on
that options chain with a price of around
60 cents.
And in this case, that was the 346
put, which was selling for 65 cents.
And you go ahead and sell 10 of
those while simultaneously buying 10 of the 321
puts for six cents, 25 points below the
10 that you sold up at 346.
And so when an options trader does that,
selling a put higher up on an options
chain and buying a put lower on that
same options chain, then he's entering what options
traders refer to as a put credit spread.
Okay, so let's take a look at the
cash flow of this trade.
So you can start to understand how it
works.
And so starting out with the 346 puts,
we sold for 60 cents.
Remember, each option represents 100 shares of stock
that can be assigned to the put seller.
So you multiply the 65 cents times 100,
and we sold 10 of them.
And so when you multiply it all together,
the result in cash income from selling those
10 puts is $650.
And using that same kind of math, those
321 puts we bought for protection cost us
$60, resulting in net cash income of $590
for this one week trade, which incidentally requires
24,410 in capital to execute.
Now, if you don't have that much in
your account, all you do is cut back
the number of credit spreads you sell to
fit your account size.
So for example, if you sold half of
those put credit spreads, you'd bring in half
of that amount of income and you'd require
half that amount of capital and so forth.
Now let's move to the day that this
credit spread expires on June 9th.
And as you can see, the stock barely
moved that week, closing at 354.50 on
that day.
And so what's the outcome of this trade?
Well, let's take a look at that.
You see, both the 346 puts that we
sold and the 321 puts that we bought
are located at strike prices well below where
the stock closed on the day that they
expired.
And so as a result, both of them
expire with no value because who would exercise
their right to sell shares at a price
of 346 or 321 when the stock is
trading for a price of 354.50 in
the open market?
Obviously no one's going to do that.
So those options just expire worthless resulting in
the result of the trade being that we
get to just keep that cash flow of
$590 that we first received when we first
opened the trade.
Okay.
So remember we're discussing a way to pull
500 or so out of the market most
weeks on average in this video.
And so that's going to be our first
trade that when we just completed.
And so on the day that those options
expire, we turn around and open up a
new trade expiring again a week later again
on June 16th.
And in this case, the put option that
sells for 61 cents is the 342.
And again, 25 points below that is the
317, which we're buying and paying eight cents
for resulting in $530 of cash flow in
this case, as you can see.
Now moving forward to the expiration date of
this second trade, you can see that on
June 16th that the stock rallied nicely in
that ensuing week, closing at 367.93. And
so again, with both the 342 and 317
puts expiring worthless being so far below where
the stock closed, we again just pocket the
$530.
And so we just go ahead and repeat
this same trade opening a 25 point wide
put credit spread with a short put priced
around 60 cents every week on Friday and
allowing it to expire the next Friday.
And as it turns out, we had a
pretty easy time of it throughout the summer.
And so since each trade is essentially the
same to move this along, we've created a
scorecard for you for each of those trades,
which you can go ahead and check for
yourself, by the way, if you have options
data available to you.
And as you can see through all of
June and all of July, the expiration closing
price of QQQ was above the strike price
location on both the short and long put
portions of the put credit spreads on their
respective expiration days.
And so we just kept collecting about, you
know, more than $500 in each of these
weeks.
Okay.
So now on July 28th, we entered our
first August trade.
And as you can see, just like we
did in all the previous cases, we sold
the 373 puts this time for 59 cents
and we bought the 348 puts for five
cents culminating in our receiving $540.
However, in this case, for the first time
since the campaign started in early June, the
stock closes below the short put strike of
373.
And so at this point, if we do
nothing, then we're going to be required to
buy 1,000 shares of QQQ for the
put strike price 373, which would cost us
$373,000.
But we have a small account.
So what are we going to do?
Well, here's how we handle it.
A few minutes before the market expires, we're
going to close that put credit spread, which
that day would have meant buying back the
373 puts for $1.02 and selling the
348 puts that we were long for just
one cent.
And when you look at that cash flow
of that buyback, you can see that the
cost of the buyback of the 373 puts
was $1,020 and we only got back
$10 for the long puts.
And we only received $540 for getting into
this credit spread trade in the first place.
And so once it's closed, we have a
loss, a net cash outflow this time of
$470.
And so we've experienced our first trade loss,
as you can see from our updated scorecard.
But we have no intentions of allowing that
loss to hurt us in the long run,
because we have a plan for this exact
situation.
So at the end of that same day,
just a few minutes later, we go to
the call side of the options chain that
expires a week later, the August 11th chain.
But this time we sell a call option
at the exact same strike price as the
short puts in the last trade.
In other words, we go to the 373
calls, and we sell 10 of those.
And as you can see, in this case,
we get $3.66 for those because those
are so close to where the stock is
trading.
And options close to the market price of
a stock will always be worth more than
the options farther away from that price.
And so in this case, we're selling the
calls this time.
But we're doing something else simultaneously with selling
those 10 calls.
And that is that this time we're going
to go way out to the end of
the year, December 29th, and we're going to
buy 10 of 370 calls expiring on that
date for $24.71. Now, why are we
doing this?
Well, here's our game plan.
Once we took that first loss on the
August 4th put spread, we're now going to
be essentially reverting to the call side.
And we are basically going to be selling
against those December calls by each week selling
373 calls expiring one week later.
And so if the QQQ closes below 373,
then we will let it expire and sell
the calls expiring in the next week.
So we're going to do this repeatedly until
the Q's rally back above 373, which point
we will close the short calls and the
long calls expiring in December and then resume
our selling of put credit spreads each week.
So that's our game plan.
Now, keep in mind buying those 10 calls
cost us $24,710.
And so you should think of that as
the capital that we've deployed in the trade
at this time.
And remember, at the same time, you sold
those 10 calls for $366.
So that part of the trade actually creates
positive cash flow of $3660.
Okay, so let's move out to August 11th,
the date the calls we sold expired.
And as you can see, the Q's closed
at $366.24 that day, which is way
below the strike of 373 calls that we
sold.
And so those expire worthless.
Why?
Because when you're talking about calls, those have
no value if the stock closes below the
strike price of the calls, because again, no
one will exercise their right to buy shares
of the Q's at 373 when it's trading
almost seven points below that in the open
market.
And so those calls expire with no value,
meaning that we can now update our profit
chart to show that we just gained a
profit of $3660 for selling those calls.
And so we just repeat the process, because
as we said, we're going to keep doing
this until we get a close above 373
on expiration.
So we go ahead and sell the 373
calls expiring yet another week later on August
18th.
But this time, because the stock has now
fallen to well below the 373 price, three
calls fetch a lot less, in this case,
$1.16, which as a result produces a
positive cash flow of $1.160. And so
let's update our scorecard throughout the end of
August.
And as you can see, the stock had
dropped to $358.13 on August 18th.
So those calls expire worthless and we get
to keep that $1.160 in cash.
And moving to the August 25th expiration, we
didn't get paid that much for those 373
calls, only $300, because in that case, the
373 calls were in even larger distance from
the Q's close on August 18th.
And so those had an even lower price
tag on them.
And so while the stock had begun to
bounce, it still did not reach 373 by
the end of that week.
And so we again sell the 373 calls
for the fourth time now, with this set
of calls expiring on September 1.
As you can see in this case, we
received 90 cents for those, producing $900, which
is an improvement upon the previous week.
And so now let's move to September 1,
when this tranche of calls expires.
And as you can see, this time the
Q's have closed at $377.59, which is
now well above our short calls for the
first time in a month.
If we don't buy back those short calls
when they expire in the money, we're going
to be obligated to sell 1,000 shares
of the Q's to the owner of those
calls.
But we don't own 1,000 shares of
the Q's.
And so remember, we said that when the
Q's close above 373, we'll close both the
short calls at 373 and the long calls
out in December at 370.
And so toward the very end of the
day, we're going to go ahead and buy
back those short calls, which are now priced
at 463, and simultaneously sell off the December
long calls for 2425.
And so analyzing what happened on that last
transaction, we'll first look at the short calls
for which we received, remember, $900.
But to close them, we had to pay
out 4,630.
So we lost 3,730 on that trade.
And don't forget, we sold off those long
calls in December, but that was for a
little bit less than we bought them for.
So that accounts for a small loss of
$460 as well.
And so updating our scorecard three months into
this campaign, we can see that adding in
the losses from closing the short calls and
selling off the long calls results in a
three-month campaign total gain of $5,030,
which incidentally, throughout the campaign, the most capital
we ever needed on any one week's trades
was $24,490.
So we'll call that our capital for the
campaign.
And that in turn results in a 20
.5% return for the three-month campaign
and an 82% return if you annualize
that three-month experience.
And so after this, you just resume the
original practice of selling, put credit spreads, bringing
in about $500 or more per week in
most weeks.
And then in weeks where the market closes
below the short put strikes, you can do
as we showed you in this case, buy
back the put credit spread, buy long calls
far out of time, a little bit in
the money, and combine that with a campaign
of selling calls against those far out distant
long calls repeatedly as we just showed you.
It's a very similar strategy to what some
options traders would call the wheel option strategy,
but this approach uses much less capital than
the wheel strategy, which is why it's so
advantageous to folks with smaller accounts.
So what I'd like you to take away
from today's video is that you don't need
to have a massive amount of capital to
generate substantial positive cashflow in your trading account
in most weeks.
A campaign of put credit spreads can yield
you incredible returns in most weeks.
And when you run into a bit of
a sell-off, you can use this call
selling approach that we taught you in the
video until you can close the call side
and resume your put credit spread selling campaign,
which can go smoothly for very long periods
of time as we saw, especially on stocks
with a mildly bullish overall direction.
Pro traders use these techniques all the time.
And now you've got the knowledge to do
this yourself.
Now, if you'd like to learn three more
options strategies that our pro traders use, including
the unique options trick that allows you to
make money while you wait to buy stocks
or ETFs at the price you want and
the options income strategy that allows you to
make consistent money, whether the market goes up
or down or sideways and how to make
money on a stock or index trade, even
if you're wrong on the direction, then click
the link that's appearing right now at the
top right hand corner of your screen that
will open up the free workshop registration page
in a new window.
So don't worry, you won't lose this video
or you can register directly for free at
optionsclass.com