Good afternoon everyone.
In this video we're going to build some
SPX trades for monthly expiration pins and we're
going to do so by analyzing gamma exposure
and dealer flows.
By the end of this video we'll craft
two different trade ideas.
Each one is going to be a low
risk trade idea.
One is risking $30, the other is risking
$80 and in both cases we're looking to
make more than $800.
The whole idea of this low risk high
reward trade is to analyze what is the
market's underlying gamma exposure for this February's monthly
expiration and take advantage of that information by
putting on some low risk trades where you're
okay losing if the trade doesn't work out
but if you win you get a disproportionate
reward for taking on this risk.
Now to understand gamma exposure we need to
first understand the gamma piece of this.
Here's a quick overview of what gamma is
but I would recommend doing a deeper dive
if this is something you find interesting.
Now you've probably heard of the concept of
delta.
If you trade options you've most definitely heard
of delta because you're purchasing whatever delta strike
price option that you typically tend to purchase
and you've heard it measured in deltas.
Delta measures the change in the actual options
price for each plus or minus $1 move
in the underlying.
So say you have Apple for example, for
each plus or minus $1 move that Apple
moves the delta tells you how much that
option will move.
So say a delta 50 options will move
$50 for every plus or minus $1 move.
Now in this case you also have to
measure that the delta today is not going
to be the same as the delta tomorrow.
You have this concept called delta decay and
the delta changes.
Now the rate at which this delta changes
is measured through gamma.
Gamma measures the change in the options delta
for each plus or minus $1 stock move.
Now once you aggregate this gamma data across
the same strike but the different expirations you
can then create this concept called gamma exposure.
You're essentially summing up all of the data
and you're then trying to figure out is
this gamma exposure, the net gamma exposure positive
or is the net gamma exposure negative.
Now a net gamma exposure being positive would
imply the following.
If the net gamma exposure is positive then
we know that we should expect less volatility.
Market makers, options market makers have sold options
at whatever those strike prices are and it's
in their best interest to essentially keep price
fluctuating and to be able to collect all
of this premium that they've sold to retail
traders who have purchased these options.
This is your typical scenario that you've seen.
In periods like this at near these strike
prices it's trades like the mean reversion trades,
a lot of the choppy market trades that
work exceptionally well and if you keep trying
to trade trends during when prices near these
strikes you'll find that those trend following trades
fail a lot more frequently.
Now on the flip side if net gamma
exposure is negative then we should be expecting
a lot more volatility as price gravitates towards
that particular strike price and a lot more
directional moves.
The reason for this is if our net
gamma exposure is negative then a lot of
the retail traders have sold the options and
we actually have the options market makers who
have purchased those options.
It's in their best interest to keep price
away from whatever that strike is in which
they've purchased these options.
So say that strike might be let's just
use an example of $60 then if price
came exactly to $60 all of that premium
that they have purchased would be eradicated.
Instead they want to get price away from
$60 as quickly as they can so this
option is actually worth something to them.
So that's how gamma exposure can start to
become useful and this is a very high
level overview but you'll see how this all
ties in.
Now I tried to sum this up in
a easy to read table maybe you find
this useful.
If the net gamma exposure is positive then
we know that dealers are incentivized to reduce
the volatility.
It's periods in this where you'll see a
lot of choppy and range bound price action
and as a result you want to take
advantage of these sorts of setups.
Mean reversion setups, volatility box reversal setups, the
fade setup works really well here.
That's because you're taking advantage of not just
a volatility edge but you also have gamma
exposure and really big money on your side
here as well.
Selling spreads and condors in this, joining the
options market makers and selling the premium is
usually a good strategy.
Now on the flip side if you have
negative gamma exposure then you're looking for a
lot more volatility and greater swings as price
approaches whatever that strike price is because dealers
want to get price way the heck away
from whatever that negative volatility is.
In periods like this buying mispriced inexpensive options
think out of the money calls for example
make a lot of sense because you start
to actually see a lot of these crazy
directional moves.
Also during this period the opening range breakout
setup works really well because you start to
see the crazy movements, momentum base setups.
So this is a quick way of how
you can use gamma and gamma exposure to
make slightly smarter options decisions.
But now let's try and actually apply this
on SPX.
This Friday is monthly expiration and I want
to try and see where does big money
have their interests in the underlying market.
Where do they want the market to go?
Where do they want to take the flow?
Now this is a chart of the gamma
exposure by strike and this is a free
resource.
I've left the resource link in the description
box below it's bar chart dot com.
In the free version I think they choose
the strikes where you get to see just
the near dated months.
So right now you get to see February
which works out perfectly because that's four days
from now.
So with February and they've aggregated the data
for us let's take a look at where
we see the larger spikes here.
So let me remove the expiration and let's
start to analyze each strike.
So I see three spikes the first at
the 6100 strike where we have positive net
gamma exposure we can see that here positive
plus 4.061. Second strike 6150 positive net
gamma exposure here as well and then the
6200 strike positive net gamma exposure here as
well.
So with all three of these strikes 6150
is the one that seems to be the
biggest then 6100 and then 6200.
Current price is at 6114 so we're right
in between these two periods of our high
gamma exposure areas.
Now take a look at where this gamma
exposure goes negative and that's near the 6050
price mark which tells us that as price
gets closer and closer to 6050 we would
expect to see dealers start to get a
little bit more aggressive in getting price back
up towards the 6100 mark.
So 6050 is a place where I would
expect to see near term support that's the
first place where our net gamma goes negative
and if you were to load in the
full chart here you would be able to
see the 6000 strike excuse me which is
also the large negative gamma exposure strike where
I would expect to see a lot of
support but 6050 is where it first goes
negative.
So before I move to the next slide
let me sum that up so 6000 which
is not even on this chart is where
we have a large negative gamma exposure strike
bar just like we see here.
6050 where we start to see this go
negative then we have 6100, 6150 and 6200.
Out of these three 6150 is the strike
with the greatest gamma exposure all three are
positive then we have 6100 and then we
have 6200.
Now let's bring this together on a chart
of SPX.
I've drawn out all four levels price currently
6114 we have that 6100, 6150 and 6200
all three of these are positive gamma exposures
suggesting that as we're in this we would
expect to see choppy price action which is
what I think we're likely to see.
6050 is down here which is the first
place that gamma exposure goes negative so as
we approach there I would expect to see
dealers very aggressively picking price action back up
so place of support.
So 6050 if we get there looking to
aggressively buy maybe even some out of the
money calls expiring this week.
Monthly expiration is this week and now we
bring back in the gamma so we have
6100, 6150 both are potential pins 6100 is
closer more in the money to where price
is 6150 would be a new high but
still just a stone's throw away.
Now let's use all of this to analyze
the options chain and craft some trades this
is where it starts to get a little
bit more fun and we get our hands
a little bit dirty.
Now we had the 6100 strike excuse me
and if we take a look at the
open interest here notice how the open interest
stands out this is the largest open interest
for our Feb expiration series and the sum
of the open interest there almost 53,000
contracts.
The next strike we have 6150 and we
take a look at the open interest here
almost 30,000 contracts so a lot of
open interest but not as much as 6100.
Now we take this information and let's come
into the analyze tab.
In the analyze tab I've built in two
separate trades here and both of these trades
are butterflies.
Now before we take a look at anything
more with these butterflies notice the middle strikes.
The middle strikes are the two prices that
we've been looking at where we have the
greatest gamma exposure and it's also where we're
looking to sell that premium.
Positive gamma exposure we're looking to join the
option market makers who have sold options near
that strike price so 6100, 6150.
Now I've made these butterflies very narrow they're
just $10 wide which is how we're able
to keep the cost so low.
The 6100 is $30 the 6150 is currently
$80.
In both cases your reward is greater than
$800.
Take a look at the box down here
if you were to get the pin at
the exact prices which is why we're putting
on these trades in the first place.
Now if price does dip below to $60
.50 then you might consider buying the 6100
call as the out of the money call
where you're looking for price to gravitate towards
but if you do buy that call keep
in mind you're going against what is really
the big money position here so all I'm
looking to do is take advantage of that
quick burst and very quickly get out before
expiration.
It's just 6100 is where there's a lot
of liquidity.
So these two butterflies are my two favorite
trades and they're the ones that look a
little bit more practical.
If we get closer to that $60.50
$60.55 mark excuse me then I'm looking
to aggressively use this as a support zone
and try and use that 6100 which is
where I still think there's a lot of
open interest where price is likely to gravitate
towards into the expiration.
So now if we summarize everything that we
covered in this video we started our conversation
by first understanding what is gamma and understanding
why gamma exposure is useful.
Then we moved on to taking a look
at this free graph of the SPX gamma
exposure for this Friday's expiration.
It includes two other expiration dates as well
and we made note of all of the
key levels where we thought price was likely
to react around and we then plotted those
on our chart and once we plotted that
we used the option chain to build two
separate butterfly positions each of which is fairly
low risk but has a disproportionately high reward
associated with it and all of these stem
from where we think big money has their
interest for expiration three days from now.
And for all volatility box traders I'm looking
at those mean reversion fade setups this week.
Maybe I might make a video talking about
a few of those setups this week.
I'll also be curious if you create your
own options butterfly position or maybe a different
position using all the information that might be
even better than the trades that I've discussed
in this video.
Take care everyone and I'll see you in
our next update.