It's been said that a good investor must
always strive to crush his most cherished beliefs
Well, during Berkshire Hathaway's 2021 annual shareholder meeting,
Warren Buffett and Charlie Munger crushed one of
mine What do you think of quants?
Jim Simon's medallion fund has done 39%
net of fees for three decades, which proves
that it works But they were very very
smart.
Yes, they got very rich.
Very very smart and very smart and very
rich And very high grade by the way.
Yeah, Jim Simons We're not we're not trying
to make money trading stocks.
No, we don't think we know how to
do it.
I mean it isn't Charles Darwin used to
say that anytime he found evidence that contradicted
his previous convictions He had to write it
down in the first 30 minutes because otherwise
the mind would reject the evidence for cherished
beliefs Well, how about reading a whole book
and making a video about it?
During the last few years I've read tons
of books on personal finance and investing and
I settled down on a conclusion that Value
investing and fundamental analysis is the way to
go while day trading and studying price charts
It's just pure bogus or you know bots
trying to sell you something Enter Jim Simons
Jim Simons is the world's richest mathematician Forbes
estimates his wealth to be at a staggering
24.6 billion dollars currently He gained most
of this wealth through conquering the world of
trading by starting the quant revolution with his
company Renaissance Technologies and the Medallion Fund The
Medallion Fund has the best track record of
any hedge fund in history It has averaged
a 62.9% return per year before
fees and 37.2% net of fees
versus 11% for the S&P 500
That is the most impressive investment record I've
ever heard about It's even better than Warren
Buffett's, although it has been accomplished with a
much smaller capital so Should you abandon value
investing to become a day trading quant?
Let's not get ahead of ourselves here, but
we'll get to that In this video, we
shall take a closer look at the Medallion
Fund's success and reveal a few of its
secrets You'll have to stay put for that
But I think that a quote from agent
Smith from the movie The Matrix may be
used to set the stage This is a
top 5 takeaway summary of the man who
solved the market written by Gregory Zuckerman And
this is The Swedish Investor, bringing you the
best tips and tools for reaching financial freedom
through stock market trade investing Takeaway number 1
From 0 to 25 billion Before getting into
the hows of Simons' incredible success, let's first
have a look at the what's What did
Jim Simons do to go from $0 in
1938 to $25 billion in 2021?
Simons was born in 1938 Early on, he
began to read a lot.
I know, surprise, surprise Jim Simons is another
one of those successful people who read a
lot To be honest, I don't think that
the medium through which you consume information matters
too much What matters is that you strive
for more knowledge Simons enrolled at MIT in
1955 and was even able to skip the
first year of mathematics thanks to his extensive
high school curriculum He decided early on what
he wanted from life coffee, cigarettes and lots
and lots of maths Simons was quite the
adventurous type.
Together with two friends, he decided to go
from Boston to Buenos Aires riding scooters They
named the trip Buenos Aires or Bust Well,
they busted in Bogota in Colombia, but it
must have been a crazy trip nonetheless While
getting his PhD at the University of California,
Berkeley, Simons had his first dabble in stocks
He got up early each morning to drive
to Merrill Lynch's office in Los Angeles just
in time for the opening of the Chicago
exchange He would stand there to watch prices
flash by and make a few trades Simons
got his PhD by age 23 in 1961
At age 26, he got a job as
a codebreaker at a US intelligence unit targeting
old Soviet Russia Simons learned something important about
hiring people here The unit worked very well
while primarily focusing on hiring people for their
creativity, ambition and brain power rather than any
specific expertise or education Another important lesson from
this place was its motto Bad ideas is
good Good ideas is terrific No ideas is
terrible In 1968, Simons published a mathematical paper
on something which I find quite difficult to
pronounce, let alone understand Minimal varieties in Riemannian
manifolds To this day, the paper has been
cited 1,722 times, which counts as an
incredible success for a paper on geometry Also
in 1968, Simons was asked to build and
lead a maths department at Stony Brook University
It's been said that the extroverted mathematician will
look at your shoes during a conversation rather
than his own Well, Simons was extroverted period
and he had an unusual knack for leading
his fellow mathematicians In 1978, Simons had had
enough of the world of academia though He
wanted new challenges and solving the market, conquering
the world of trading, was something which no
one had done before, which sparked his enthusiasm
He called his first hedge fund Monometrics, which
was a play of words combining money and
econometrics Simons was hinting that he would use
math to analyze the financial markets and score
big time Simons utilized his unusual combination of
being an exceptionally skilled mathematician himself while possessing
some incredible leadership and interpersonal skills to hire
and get the most out of many fellow
mathematicians He realized early on that he wouldn't
solve this puzzle by himself In fact, I
think that the book might as well have
been called The Men Who Solved the Market
But you'll hear more about these people and
their contributions later because that's more about the
hows than the whats of this incredible trading
success In 1982, Simons renamed the company to
Renaissance Technologies, a name that it holds to
this day In 1988, Simons launched the Medallion
Fund, which is the most successful hedge fund
of all time in terms of returns on
capital While others were still relying on instinct
and intuition for their trades, Simons employed automated
algorithms, tons of data and advanced mathematics But
again, we're getting ahead of ourselves Medallion didn't
charge the usual rip-off fee of 2
.20 that other Wall Streeters did.
No, no They charged 5.20, eventually raising
that to 5.44 This is insane numbers,
but in Renaissance's case it proved to be
worth it In 1990, the Medallion Fund had
its first year surpassing a 50% return
It scored as high as 77.8%
before fees for the 12 months Simons kept
up his leadership skills.
He created a culture of unusual openness at
Renaissance Moreover, he used smart monetary incentives where
people were paid bonuses, but only if the
company reached certain levels of profit This money
was paid out over many years to key
people in the firm Renaissance had almost no
employee turnover Simons also had an important role
to play in the hiring process He wanted
people who had little or no connection to
Wall Street and generally accepted business dogmas In
1993, the Medallion Fund closed to outside investors.
From now on, it was only available to
employees of Renaissance and their families In the
year 2000, Medallion had its first year exceeding
a 100% return, achieving a stunning plus
128.1% In 2003, stocks had officially
taken over as the most important trading instrument
of the firm, from previously having focused on
currencies, commodities and bonds In 2005, Jim Simons
received a personal gain of $1.5 billion
which was the highest compensation among any hedge
fund manager that year Simons retired as CEO
of Renaissance in 2009 and handed over the
role to two of his colleagues Robert Mercer
and Peter Brown Simons stayed as chairman, but
eventually left that post too, just recently in
2021 But he remains on the board of
directors He earned a cool $2.6 billion
with his financial stake in the company in
2020, reaching an estimated personal wealth of $24
.6 billion Okay Let's now get into how
Jim Simons, and his colleagues I should add,
was able to achieve these stellar results in
the Medallion Fund Takeaway number 2 Medallion is
a short-term predictive algorithm The secret to
Renaissance's and the Medallion Fund's success has been
to employ tons of data and advanced mathematics
to develop automated trading algorithms Renaissance was one
of the pioneers of using machine learning and
applying it to the world of investing Today,
this black box algorithm is an exceptional short
-term predictor of market movements The Medallion Fund
holds onto positions for an average of a
day or so But sometimes as little as
minutes or seconds It executed 150,000 to
300,000 trades per day back in the
year 2000, and probably even more of them
today One employee expressed that Medallion's goal is
the following Scrutinize historic price information to discover
sequences that might repeat under the assumption that
investors will exhibit similar behavior in the future
Simons understood quite early on that the stock
market moves because of a complex process with
many, many inputs Some of these inputs may
be difficult or even impossible to understand They
may not be related to traditional fundamentals such
as earnings, dividends, interest rates or similar But
there may be some other more obscure reason
for certain moves However, eventually, they will all
be reflected in pricing data So Simons decided
to study that data What type of human
behavior is it that Medallion is able to
take advantage of?
Well, to Simons it didn't matter as long
as the patterns reappeared with a certain degree
of statistical significance But it can be interesting
to speculate a little.
Medallion's profits probably stem from human biases and
misjudgments We may have a few of the
suspects in Daniel Kahneman's famous book, Thinking Fast
and Slow • Loss aversion – people hate
losing more than they like winning • Anchoring
– one's judgment is skewed based on previous
prices and experiences • And the endowment effect
– you like what you already have more
than what is objectively sound One of the
core strategies ever since the inception of the
fund has been to rely on mean reversion
Early on, back in the 80s and 90s,
the Medallion fund used simple linear regression models
to plot, for example, the price of crude
oil versus the price of gasoline If you
look at enough data points, you can spot
a trend line – a linear relationship between
the two assets When gasoline is cheap compared
to oil, you'll buy gasoline and short oil,
and vice versa Then you wait for the
prices to go back to normal, reverting to
the mean Today, Medallion uses a technique called
statistical arbitrage, which is about identifying a small
set of quantifiable market-wide factors that best
explain certain market movements If, for instance, Exxon
tends to move in tandem with petroleum prices
and interest rates, Renaissance identifies that Then they
bet on the stocks that have moved the
least in the direction of their market-wide
factors while betting against those that have moved
more than the factors predicted Again, reversion to
the mean Today, these relationships often consist of
multiple variables, and the relationships no longer have
to be linear, so they're often difficult to
identify for the naked eye To identify such
relationships, the Medallion fund needed data – mountains
of data Takeaway number 3 – Medallion requires
tons of data One of the former CEOs
of Renaissance Technologies, Robert Mercer, said it best
There's no data like more data This became
something of a mantra at Renaissance Any data
that could be quantified and was deemed to
have some potential for predictive value was gathered
– newspaper stories, internet posts, insurance claims –
nothing is too obscure An employee named Sander
Strauss noticed the need for data early on
if Simon's wish for a fully automated algorithm
was to become reality Back then, having more
data than your competitors meant buying books from
the World Bank and magnetic tape from various
exchanges The data went back as far as
World War II Strauss collected more than even
Simon's thought was necessary Among other things, he
started to collect the intraday tick prices betting
that it would become useful to them at
some point Strauss even began to model data
itself for a while There were gaps in
the data at certain periods due to unexpected
circumstances such as when a major flood had
suspended Chicago trading Sometimes, modelling data was possible
just like it is possible to sometimes identify
the shape of a missing jigsaw puzzle piece
Today, more than 300 people are employed at
Renaissance and they have more than 30 people
with PhDs with the primary focus of cleaning
up different data feeds so that they have
the best data available for making short-term
predictions While studying this much quantitative information, Medallion
must be careful as to not run into
data overfitting If you look at enough data,
you're bound to find some signals that seem
statistically significant, just by pure chance For example,
a quant investor called David Laneweber had identified
that US stock returns could be predicted by
combining the jelly butter production of Bangladesh, the
cheese production of the US and the population
of sheep in Bangladesh and the US True
story For this reason, Medallion always starts to
trade new signals with smaller amounts of cash,
gradually ramping up the capital committed as profits
roll in Takeaway number 4 Medallion is based
on advanced mathematics As I said before, this
book might as well have been called The
Men Who Solved the Market, as Simons definitely
couldn't do this alone He employed various mathematicians
who were specialists within their fields Among the
men who solved the market were Lenny Baum,
who was an early employee that helped Simons
with something called Hidden Markov Processes James Axe,
who held the largest stake in Medallion's predecessor
Axecom Axe was a great algebraist and exceptional
at exploring correlations Rene Carmona helped incorporate some
stochastic differential equations to the models He began
applying so-called kernel methods to analyze patterns
in the datasets He was the first one
to implement a full black box approach, where
they allowed the computer to teach itself which
patterns were most important Elwin Berlekamp, who helped
with advanced game theory He even founded a
branch of mathematics called Combinatorial Game Theory Berlekamp
had also worked for John Larry Kelly Jr.,
the creator of the Kelly Criterion The Kelly
Criterion determines how large or small a certain
trading position should be It can be used
for value investing too by the way, something
I've discussed previously in a summary of The
Dondo Investor by Monish Pabrai And then there
were of course Robert Mercer and Peter Brown,
who were appointed co-CEOs of Renaissance in
2009 They both brought even more experience with
hidden Markov processes to the group, but most
of all, they were exceptional computer scientists Simons
headhunted both of them from IBM's former speech
recognition team Takeaway number 5 – Don't try
this at home Here's a little thought experiment
for you Since 2003, the Medallion fund has
primarily been trading in stocks, although they also
do trades in commodities, currencies and bonds Also
since 2003, Medallion has returned an average of
73.7% per year before fees, while
the S&P 500 has returned on average
10.6% per year The returns could
be explained by the fact that Medallion uses
leverage, but to say that that explains the
full overperformance I think would be a little
bit foolish No, Medallion is also just on
the right side of trades This leaves one
questioning – who does it take these profits
from?
Who is on the other side of the
trade?
According to a 2019 CNBC article, index investors
control nearly half of the US stock market
If you are an index investor and you've
been investing without buying and selling too much
since 2003, you would have received those 10
.6% in average returns Medallion cannot have
stolen profits from the index investors as they
will get the average almost by definition Then
we have the long-term investors who invest
based on fundamentals and hold over longer time
periods That's the Warren Buffett's of the investing
world This represents an area where Renaissance and
its mathematicians haven't been able to produce any
above average profits yet In 2005, Renaissance founded
a new fund called Renaissance Institutional Equities Fund
or REIF to take in outside capital without
risking the profits of Medallion Supposedly, this fund
would make similar long-term predictions as the
Medallion fund has been doing successfully for the
short-term ones To this date though, it
hasn't been able to do that That's a
9.1% return on average for all
of the full years since REIF's inception versus
9.9% for the S&P The
forecasting methods that Renaissance uses are similar to
weather predictions Very useful for saying what is
likely to happen in the coming hours or
perhaps days but not useful for longer time
periods than that Therefore, it is unlikely that
it's the acolytes of Warren Buffett who have
been the prey of Medallion either Who's left?
It is the traders Renaissance's profits stem from
fellow speculators, both large and small The people
who do not have a trading algorithm which
trades without being influenced by emotions who do
not have access to the same amount of
data who do not have access to some
of the greatest mathematicians of our time but
who decides to take a short-term gamble
in the stock market nonetheless The people who
buy a course in day trading from a
guru on Udemy and draw trend lines on
a head and shoulder pattern Simons came to
this conclusion himself that these must be the
people who Medallion is taking profits from and
it is good for you to know as
an investor too Do not think that you
can do this at home The only thing
that will happen is that you'll hand over
your hard-earned money to Renaissance or some
other quants What was it that Agent Smith
said now again?
Never send a human to do a machine's
job So, Jim Simons became one of the
richest people on the planet through his Medallion
fund The fund is a short-term algorithm
which scrutinizes historic price information to discover sequences
that might repeat under the assumption that investors
will exhibit similar behavior in the future To
do this, the fund requires tons of quantitative
data Moreover, Simons needed the help of a
few of the world's greatest mathematicians Finally, don't
think that you can do this at home
As a smaller and private investor, I'd still
opt for the value investing approach of Warren
Buffett over a day trading technical analysis approach
any day Value investing is an area where
the machines haven't caught up to us yet
If you want to learn how to invest
in a Warren Buffett way one of the
best methods for learning his secrets would be
to study his most important investments of all
time In this video, I've summarized the 25
most important ones Sure, it is a long
video, but hopefully there's a lot of meat
in there Cheers guys, hope to see you
again soon!