That's right guys.
In this video, we're gonna learn how to
evaluate a trading strategy based on the numbers
from trading view.
You're gonna learn which numbers are good, which
numbers are bad, which strategies to stay away
from and of course how to compare them
against each other.
You guys are creating a lot of trading
strategies now that you know how to do
it with AI.
My previous videos went through the roof.
As you know, that's why you subscribe to
this channel.
Now the next level, right?
The next stage that you have to reach
is how to compare these trading strategies with
each other based on the numbers you're getting.
And guys, having these numbers is actually a
blessing.
It's very nice, right?
Because you were having no numbers at all.
Before that, you were using indicators.
Okay, now you're using strategies.
Okay, cool.
So you made the step from indicators to
strategies.
Great.
Congratulations.
But now you need to also be able
to use these numbers to make a decision,
right?
I'm gonna show you exactly how to do
that in this video.
We're gonna look at max drawdown, profit factor,
percent profitable trades, net profit and other numbers.
And we're gonna use some very simple mathematics,
which you're gonna learn.
And then you can do the same as
I do.
You can evaluate trading strategies against each other
very, very easily.
And thanks again for the massive support that
you give me, guys.
I appreciate each and every one of you,
which is why I urge you to come
to the Telegram group.
The link is down below.
It's fully free because I can give you
even more value, right?
You come to the group, you ask your
questions, you learn more about strategies, automation, numbers,
all of that, right?
And we help each other there.
We even have people that started to help
other people.
It's not just me.
Speaking of which, I want to mention these
awesome people, which are in Telegram helping other
people all the time.
And I'm very much appreciative of that.
I think everyone else is.
So thank you very much for being there.
You guys are awesome.
And if you want a shout out, then
just simply be helpful to other people and
you will make it in my next video.
So it's a great group for that.
It's not for trading signals.
Okay.
Don't come and expect buy this coin or
something.
Not that.
Okay.
Go somewhere else for that.
Here we're learning about trading strategies and how
to apply them, how to automate them and
how to increase our chances of success.
Having said that, this is not financial advice.
Crypto is risky.
You can lose all of your money, but
that is why you subscribe to this channel.
You click the bell and you make sure
to watch all of my educational videos because
only then your chances of making money are
at an all time high.
And with all of that in mind, let's
get started.
All right, guys, on the chart behind me,
you can see the following strategies that I
have prepared for you to go through in
this video.
We're going to look at the Gaussian channel
strategy.
We're going to look at also the improved
Gaussian channel strategy for my previous video where
I used AI to add the stochastic RSI
to improve a lot of the numbers.
We're going to look at the whole suit
strategy.
We're going to look at the huddle strategy
and also we're going to look at my
strategy just for comparison, not in detail.
Okay.
So we're going to go through all of
that and we're going to look at the
numbers and then figure out which strategy is
the best one.
Of course, all of that based on numbers
and not based on my opinion.
Let's go.
Okay.
I put myself here onto the bottom right
so that you can see the whole chart.
You can see all of the relevant numbers.
And the first number I want to talk
about is the max drawdown.
The first number I look at whenever I
put a strategy on the chart is the
max drawdown.
If the max drawdown guys is too high,
I don't care about this strategy.
In this case, it's 30%, but too high
is 50% or more.
Okay guys, so if it's more than 50%,
that means that my portfolio might end up
being 50% worth less money than before.
That is not good.
Okay.
So because the max drawdown is not the
max loss, that's true, but it could end
up in a loss and I don't want
to take the risk.
Remember guys, that trading and investing is always
about risk and reward.
So you cannot only look at the net
profit.
That's the reward.
You have to also always look at the
risk and you have to create a ratio,
hint, hint.
I'm going to show you how to do
that in this video.
Okay.
So 30% is fine because it's below
50.
Very simple.
So that's rule number one.
Rule number two is to look at the
net profit and the net profit is the
other part of the risk reward formula, right?
So it makes money.
Okay, cool.
It makes money.
But now the question is, does it make
enough money for the risk I'm taking?
Okay.
And I'm not talking about profit factor.
That's a different topic.
Okay.
So max drawdown and net profit are in
somehow in a relationship with each other, right?
But what is the relationship?
Well, it's very simple.
Let me put myself here and explain.
So what I do guys, right?
I take the net profit percentage.
I take the percentage because then it doesn't
matter how much money you invest and this
will always work.
So you take the 1,894.9. So
let's round up to 1,895 and we
divide it by 30 and then you get
a ratio of about 63.
Okay.
So remember that number because we're going to
do the same for other strategies and then
we can rank them based on that.
That's not the only number, but we can
rank them based on that as well.
So that is the next thing that you
have to do.
That's rule number three.
Okay.
So you had the max drawdown by itself,
the net profit by itself, and now the
ratio of those two, right?
Nice.
So we're making progress, but the next thing
I want to tell you is actually something
very important, which is that you will gonna
have the idea to compare this with the
buy and hold return.
Okay.
Nice.
It's not a bad idea, right?
But the problem is that you're only comparing
the reward.
You're not taking the risk into account, which
is why I want to show you this
stuff to keep you away from trouble.
Okay.
So if you want to now check what
is the buy and hold return for the
strategy, right?
It's 843%, because that's basically what trading view
calculates from the first trade that ever happened,
right?
From here until here, 800, something like that,
Very close.
But the problem is that trading view starts
from the first trade while the strategy actually
started trading over here on 1st of January,
2018, right?
As you can see here.
So if the strategy avoided a lot of
the drawdown and only bought at the bottom,
then trading view will start calculating from the
bottom, which is not really fair.
I'm just saying, right?
Okay.
So that's one thing you need to just
understand how trading view works.
So it goes from the first trade and
pretends that it was also invested from the
first trade.
That is not correct.
So that is why I have a strategy
here.
It's called the hodl demo strategy.
I just developed it myself.
If you want the code, I will put
a document down below, and then you can
just copy the code from that and you
can use it yourself.
Now, the only thing you need to do
is to always put it one day before
today, so that it also sells because it
doesn't sell.
Then you don't see any numbers, right?
So the max drawdown is 76%, okay?
So just looking at going back to the
Gaussian channel strategy, just looking at the buy
and hold return here will not give you
the full picture, okay?
You have to use the hodl demo strategy
to actually figure out what was the real
return of the hodl strategy, right?
If you start at the same time, right?
And then you take the risk from the
same point in time, which was the 1st
of January, right?
Then you have a drawdown of 77%
rounding up, now let's do the same ratio
calculation for the hodl strategy.
So we compare now the hodl with the
Gaussian channel preliminary because we're not yet fully
through with all the numbers.
So now take the net profit 573 divided
by 77, okay?
And you get a ratio of about 7
.4. This is way worse than the Gaussian
channel strategy.
You already know that the hodl is bad,
okay?
Like that's obvious, but you now also know
how I calculate this stuff.
Yes, sure, you can look at the drawdown
already and you know already that it's about
50 and so it's already bad, okay?
Yeah, Michael, but what about the DCA strategy?
Well, here you go, the DCA strategy from
the same timeframe selling yesterday so that we
have the numbers.
You can see 585% profit with the
max drawdown of 13.3. Let's divide these
numbers and you get to a ratio of
45.
Yes, that is better than the hodl strategy
because the hodl strategy is the worst strategy
in the universe for individual assets.
And if you're not sure what I'm talking
about, then watch this video here that a
lot of people have watched already and opened
their eyes, but watch it only after this
one.
We're going back to the Gaussian channel strategy
to understand the profit factor and that would
be rule number four, okay?
So the profit factor, first of all, how
is it defined?
You can see here, it is the gross
profits divided by the gross losses.
If you want to calculate this number yourself,
simply go to the performance summary and divide
this by this, right?
It's very simple to do and this is
the number 3.2. So the profit factor
and don't confuse it right with the net
profit versus max drawdown because that ratio is
how much your portfolio is actually fluctuating up
and down, but it doesn't mean that you
actually realized that max drawdown, okay?
It was just a max drawdown, but the
profit factor shows you how the ratio is
between the money you made and the money
you lost.
So that is the actual money that was
made and lost and obviously this number has
to be above one and the more it
is above one, the better, okay?
You see here 3.2, that is pretty
good, right?
But can we do better?
Yes, there are strategies that do five or
even six on Bitcoin, but on certain altcoins,
this could be a huge number.
This could be 40 or 30 and it
doesn't mean that that strategy is good on
every coin, right?
But often you have this massive volatility to
the upside and you were lucky to have
only a couple of losing trades or maybe
none at all and just make one massive
winning trade, then of course the profit factor
is huge, right?
I mean, you have to have at least
one losing trade, otherwise they divide by zero,
but let's say you had a losing trade
of 1%, but then you made 100%.
I mean, that profit factor would be massive,
okay?
So don't take that profit factor too seriously
if they're not enough trades on the chart
or also if the chart doesn't have enough
price history, okay?
So if you're looking at a new coin
that starts in 2024, it just launched a
couple of months ago, then the profit factor,
you can't really take it too seriously, okay?
But sure, it's one of the numbers, it's
rule number four, like I said, and that
is also why it's not the most important
rule, but it's one that you have to
look at.
Let's go back to the chart, Gaussian channel
strategy on the chart.
The next number you should look at is
the percent profitable trades.
You can also call it the win rate.
I will call it the win rate because
it's easier to say.
And in this case, it's 29.27%. Now,
is that good or bad?
And what is the rule we have for
it?
Well, let's think about it a little bit.
So if the strategy wins more trades, then
it should be a better strategy.
Well, not necessarily, because the question is when
it wins, how much does it win?
And when it loses, how much does it
lose?
So does it really matter how many trades
it wins?
Well, it's a psychological thing, right?
Because if you have a strategy, and let
me show you this right here, that is
losing a lot of trades and only then
makes one massive winning trade like this one
here, right?
But before that, you had one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight losing trades, would
you still use this strategy?
Because it's psychologically a massive problem, right?
So it is not so much a mathematical
issue, but it's more like a psychological issue.
So if you can choose a strategy that
wins more, it's better for you, because the
chances for you to stick to the strategy
and to use it for a long time
and benefit from the numbers is much higher
when the win rate is higher, right?
So yes, it's part of the calculation is
not the most important number, but I'm looking
at it as well.
And I do take it into account when
it comes to my overall decision making.
Well, this number is not disqualifying a strategy
necessarily.
So rule number five is not a particular
number that has to be above or below,
but it has to be better than the
other strategy that you're comparing for.
So the rule here is that higher is
better, but there is no particular number, it
has to be above.
It just has to be better than the
other strategy you're looking at.
And it also has to match your psychology.
So make sure that you can survive a
lot of losing trades if you're picking a
strategy with a low win rate.
Now, you know which numbers to look at,
how to look at them.
Now let's take all these trading strategies, turn
them on and check the numbers and figure
out which strategy is the best one.
And at the end of the video, I
will tell you one more thing that you
must do when evaluating trading strategies.
Stick around, let's go.
Now we're going to look at the improved
caution channel strategy, which is the one that
I've created in my last video by adding
the stochastic RSI to avoid a lot of
these losing trades.
If you want to know all about that
and simply watch my last video, I will
link it up top.
And so these numbers here look a little
bit different.
You see that the drawdown is way, way
lower.
The net profit is pretty much the same,
but the profit factor now is six and
the percent profitable trades is 50.
So it's way better, like without doing any
calculation, I can already tell you that is
way better.
But let's do the simple calculation where we
divide the net profit by the max drawdown.
And when doing that, we're getting to a
factor of 130, which is pretty good and
is way better than the previous caution channel
strategy.
Okay.
The other numbers you can check for yourself.
That's all fine.
And then the whole suit strategy.
Well, you can already see that the max
drawdown, the first number I'm looking at rule
number one is about 50%.
So I don't care about this whatsoever.
Okay.
So let's get out of here.
Then we have the hodl strategy with 76
% max drawdown.
Get out of here.
We have DCA, which is a bit better.
You can do the calculation.
We did that already.
The DCA strategy has a factor of 45,
right?
But it doesn't matter.
It's already pretty bad based on the, all
the other numbers basically.
And then we also have my own strategy,
which has these numbers and I'm just putting
it out there.
So you see how it could also look
like, right?
Which has these numbers over here.
And if we're doing the calculation, then you
will see that the factor between net profit
and max drawdown is actually only 125.
Whereas the Gaussian channel, the improved one here
was actually at 130.
So that looks a bit better, right?
So it looks like the improved Gaussian channel
strategy is better than my own strategy.
Well, is that the case?
Now I want to show you one more
important thing when it comes to evaluating strategies.
And that is to apply the same strategy
on different assets.
Because if it works on one coin, I
mean, I can make a strategy that works
even better than the Gaussian channel strategy on
Bitcoin and has a hundred percent win rate.
But isn't that overfitted to the coin?
Well, yes, of course it is.
And when a coin works super great on
one coin, then there is a risk that
it doesn't work on that same coin with
future data, right?
Because it is made for the past, it's
overfitted to the past.
But what if the future is a bit
different?
For example, Bitcoin now has an ETF, right?
Different players are now playing the game as
well.
So they might change the game, but you
don't know, right?
So you need a strategy that is general
purpose that can deal with that as well,
right?
Not only with the past, but also with
the future.
So that is why you have to also
take all of these strategies and apply them
on other coins.
And I will just look at the improved
Gaussian channel and my own, because the improved
one is the best one.
So I have less comparing to do.
I only have to compare two strategies with
each other because the other ones are already
out of the question.
And I'm using my own strategy here because
I want you to learn something specific.
And I don't know which other strategy I
can use to prove that same point I
want to prove in the coming segment of
this video.
If you know another strategy, then let me
know.
Come to Telegram and chat with me there.
So let's go to Ethereum, right?
Because why not, right?
Go to Ethereum.
You have the Gaussian channel strategy making, okay,
first, the max drawdown, 53%.
Screw that.
Now let's go to my strategy, 29.7,
let's say 32,500% profit.
Let's go way better without changing any parameters.
Okay.
So let's go to Solana.
This is the improved Gaussian channel strategy, almost
49% max drawdown with 10,544%
net profit.
The factor by the way is, I will
put it here on the screen is 215.
And let's go to my strategy.
We have a max drawdown of 37 and
a net profit of 20,914.
The factor again, I will put it here
on the screen is 565.
Okay.
That's a different universe.
And that's why you need a strategy that
is robust.
Okay.
Let's turn it off again and let's go
to Polygonmatic.
And we have the improved Gaussian channel strategy,
71% max drawdown.
Screw that.
That's too high.
Let's go to my strategy, 36.28 with
4,744% net profit.
So that is on a different level.
And that is why it's so hard to
create very good and robust strategies.
So make sure guys, why am I telling
you all of that?
Right?
I'm not telling you that so that I'm
saying use my strategy.
No.
Okay.
I'm telling you so that you can go
here.
And when you mess around with the settings
of the Gaussian channel strategy, then make sure
to not have the settings in such a
way that they work only for one coin.
Okay.
Make sure that they work for more coins.
That is actually the message over here.
Right.
And so once you manage to do that,
then you have a more robust version of
the strategy.
Okay.
So it doesn't mean the Gaussian channel, the
improved one is bad or the old one
is bad.
It's just that you need to figure out
the right configuration.
Maybe you need to add another indicator to
it, which we know how to do that.
Right.
Because we have the freaking AI video that
you guys love.
It's linked up above.
Okay.
So that is the message here, guys.
Make sure to not overfit your strategy to
one coin only.
Okay, guys.
Now you know how to evaluate a trading
strategy properly also on different coins.
And I want you guys to go bananas
with this because it has the potential to
change your life forever.
Okay.
Mess around, create a strategy that is not
overfitted, works on the coins that you like
more than one.
Yes.
More than one.
We want a robust strategy.
But please take this knowledge and apply this
knowledge.
Okay.
Don't just listen to my voice and the
guy's funny and drinks coffee and everything.
By the way, cheers.
I love this stuff.
But take this knowledge and actually apply it.
Okay.
Please make it happen and come to the
telegram group, share your questions, but also share
your successes.
Okay.
Share your freaking successes to also motivate other
people to do the same thing because not
everyone will have the same strategy.
So that's fine.
Right.
And this way you're giving back a little
bit to help other people, which is always
nice.
And if for some reason you want access
to my trading strategies, then go to autotrading
.vip. But hey, my calendar is full until
January already.
So make sure if you put some information
there about why you apply, then put something
interesting because otherwise I cannot move you forward.
Like it's very hard for me.
Okay.
A lot of people want access.
It's hardcore.
I'm in calls all day long during the
week.
That's why I'm making videos on the weekend.
Okay.
Having said all of that, if you want
to learn about automation, you want to automate
a trading strategy, which I think you should
because that's the way to avoid emotions and
all.
Then this is the next video you should
watch.