Most options traders make one fatal mistake without
realizing it, and this is the primary cause
of their failure.
In this video, S&B's head of options
trading shows you what that major error is
and how to correct it quickly and easily.
I'm Mike Bellifiori, and we're one of the
top proprietary trading firms located in New York
City since 2005 and proud to develop number
seven and even eight figure per year traders.
Watch, take notes, and learn from a professional
proprietary trader on our desk so you can
grow your trading account.
Hi, I'm Seth Fruhberg, and I'm the head
trader of S&B Capital's options trading desk
here in Manhattan.
And I can tell you from training professional
traders and working with thousands of retail options
traders like yourself from all over the world,
the absolute number one complaint that I get
from beginning options traders goes something like this.
They tell me it's hard enough for me
to pick stocks that I think are gonna
go up and be right about it.
But what drives me crazy is that when
I buy a call on that stock, which
is what I thought you were supposed to
do when you think a stock's gonna go
up, and that stock actually does go up,
why the hell does that call go down
most of the time?
In other words, I got the stock's direction
right, and I still lose buying a call
option on that stock.
Is there any way to make money trading
options?
You can't imagine how many times I've heard
this exact complaint.
And so the purpose of today's video is
to be honest with you and tell you
that if you keep buying calls on stocks
that you think are gonna go up, you're
most likely going to keep having this exact
same experience, which is gonna get very frustrating.
But there's an easy way out of this
exact dilemma.
And once you implement it, you're gonna be
amazed at how much your options trading will
turn around.
And I can assure you that once you
understand this one basic principle, and you follow
what we're teaching you in this video, if
you do get the direction right on the
stock, you will make money on the options
trade.
So stick around because this is obviously very
important for you to understand.
Now, before we get into the strategy we'll
be teaching you in today's video, if you're
absolutely brand new to options trading, and you
don't know much about how options work, we've
put together a video for you to understand
options basics.
And if you click the video appearing on
your screen right now, it will lay out
the groundwork for you to understand the option
strategy that we'll be sharing with you in
this video.
Then when you're finished, you can come back
and watch the rest of this video.
This month, May of 2024, has had an
extremely bullish start with the S&P 500
up 5.3% through just the first
half of the month, ending on May 17th,
last Friday, which is a blistering start to
the month with the bulls fully in control
after a fairly mild pullback that took place
in April.
And so the all-time high that had
actually been set back in March of 2024
was exceeded on May 15th.
And so every day offers the opportunity for
the SPY to break yet another record to
the upside as the market remains convinced that
the Fed is gonna start reducing interest rates
without a serious slowdown in the economy, the
soft landing that everyone was hoping for.
And whether the market is eventually right about
this outcome or wrong, it's been acting like
that is exactly what's gonna happen.
And so May has undoubtedly been a really
bullish month.
Just the kind of month that you'd think
buying calls each day a few points above
where the SPY is trading is bound to
give you a winning outcome.
After all, we already know it's been a
blistering rally so far.
So we don't even have to worry about
the direction of SPY.
We already know it.
So let's go back and see exactly how
this would have played out knowing ahead of
time that SPY was going to go up
most of the days.
And let's assume that we have a $2
,000 count to start with.
Okay, so let's start first thing just as
the market is opening on May 1st and
with SPY opening at 501.70, we pull
up an options chain that expires that same
day, May 1st.
And you'll notice that there's a column called
Delta that you'll see on any brokerage platform
that supports options trading.
And so we're gonna look for the call
option, which is as close as we can
get to at least 20 deltas, which in
this case is the 506 call as you
can see.
And we're gonna buy five of those for
a price of 59 cents.
And so to explain what's going on here,
what's known as an options delta is a
mathematically arrived at prediction of how much an
options price is likely to move based upon
how much the stock price moves.
And depending on how volatile the market is
expected to be on any given day, the
20 delta call can be really close to
where the stock is trading, sometimes just a
few points away.
And on other days, it could be a
little further away.
And so on this day, it was a
little more than four points above where the
SPY opened that day.
Okay, and so from a cashflow standpoint, what's
happened is that the price of the calls
were 59 cents, but remember, each SPY call
option represents 100 shares of stock.
So we multiply that by 100 and we
bought five of them.
And so the final cost to us is
$295, as you can see from the calculation.
And so by the end of the day,
the SPY had indeed rallied off the open,
but then sold off in the afternoon, closing
at 500.83. And so we're gonna start
a record of each of these trades through
the first half of May.
And as you can see, with the stock
closing at 500.83, the call option expires
worthless, right?
Because no one is gonna exercise the option
to buy SPY at 506 when you can
get the shares in the open market for
500.83. And so that call just expires
with zero value and you lose your trade,
of course.
Okay, so let's move to the second day
of May.
And with the stock opening up at 503
.09, we're gonna go ahead again and buy
five of the 506 calls, which again are
at or above 20 deltas, which this time
is just three points above the market.
And we paid 215 for those.
And as you can see, after initially selling
off, the market rallied for the rest of
the day, closing at 505.02. But our
call was up at 506.
And so this time the market rallied strongly
off the open.
We bought calls at the open and we
got nothing to show for it because the
market closed below our call strike price again.
And so that becomes another loss, even though
we were absolutely right about the market's direction
that day and bought calls as a result.
And so updating our record, we end up
with another loss of $215.
Now on the third day, the 20 delta
call was 513.
We paid 285 for five of those, but
the SPY closed at 511.31. And so
even though the SPY was up $6.28
that day, we still lost money on the
trade.
Okay, so May 3rd was a Friday.
So the next trading day was Monday, May
6th.
And so on that day, the 20 delta
call was at 515, for which we paid
$165.
But this time the market really rocketed up
and closed at 516.57. And so this
one is a win because as you can
see from the calculation, the SPY's closing price
was $1.57 above the call strike price.
So each call's value is $1.57 at
the end of the day.
So we multiply that value times the 100
shares it gives you the right to buy
at 515.
And because you own five of those calls,
the final value of the calls is 785.
And to determine the profit on the trade,
we subtract out the original cost of the
options for a final profit of $620.
But then as you can see, we had
another loss on May 7th.
And then on May 8th, something interesting happened.
On that day, the 20 delta call was
517 and the SPY closed at 517.19.
So you think, hey, that's a good thing.
The SPY closed above our strike price by
19 cents.
But then you calculate it out and you
realize that for those five calls to require
a total cost of $190 at the beginning
of the day, that meant each option would
have been priced at 38 cents initially.
And at the end of the day, the
SPY closed 19 cents higher than the 517
strike price.
So all five options had a value of
$95 at the close, but we paid $190
for them, meaning that even though we were
right about the market direction, and we bought
a call that expired with value, the trade
still lost because the SPY didn't really rally
by enough to make the option worth more
than what we paid for it in the
morning.
And so again, we have a loss, even
though we were right about just about everything.
Okay, so at this point now, so as
not to be too tedious, we'll just show
you the rest of the record, which you
can do for yourself if you happen to
have options backtesting software.
And as you can see, other than wins
on May 9th and May 15th, all of
the rest of the trades were losses.
And so to summarize, the call buying campaign
resulted in three wins, 10 losses, and an
overall loss of $265, which comes to a
negative return of 13% in a very
bullish period for the SPY.
And so at this point, we have to
ask ourselves, do options even work?
Should we just bag this idea of trading
options to express our directional predictions on a
stock, or is there another solution?
Well, let's try something else and we'll see.
So let's go back to May 1st again,
the same day we started our call buying
campaign.
And on that morning, instead of buying the
20 Delta call, we'll go ahead and try
something completely different.
Remember, put options only have value if the
stock closes below the put strike price on
the day that it expires.
But if the stock price closes above the
put strike price, then the put expires with
zero value, the opposite of a call option.
So if on May 1st, instead of buying
the 20 Delta call, we go ahead and
sell five put options at the first strike
price below a 40 Delta put, which in
this case, as you can see, is the
500 put, which has a Delta of 36
.67. And you'll notice that the 500 put
is actually pretty close to where the market's
opening up that day at 501.70. And
in fact, on most days, the first strike
below 40 Delta will usually be just a
point or two below where the market opened.
And so let's go ahead and sell five
of those, and then move down two strikes
to the 498 puts and buy five of
those.
And when we do that, we are entering
into what options traders refer to as a
put credit spread, where you sell put options
higher up on an options chain and buy
put options below those on the same options
chain.
And so in the case of this strategy,
instead of spending cash to buy calls, in
this case, as you can see for the
calculation, we're actually gonna be receiving cash because
the puts we sold were priced at $1
.29, but the puts we bought were priced
at 69 cents.
And so netting it down, the five put
credit spreads bring in $300 for which your
broker will require you to have at least
$700 in your account in order to execute
this trade, which is also the trade's worst
case scenario loss.
And so moving to the end of the
day, as you'll remember, SPY actually closed lower
where it opened, closing at 500.83. And
so even though the market closed below where
it opened, let's take a look at the
outcome of our put credit spread trade.
And after taking into consideration the $300 that
we originally collected, the rest is pretty simple
because both the 500 short puts and the
498 long puts both expired worthless because the
SPY closed above both their strike prices, resulting
in us just pocketing that $300 as our
trade win.
So instead of losing our entire call premium,
as we did when we bought the call
on the open using the previous call buying
strategy on May 1st, we ended up keeping
our entire premium that we received, selling the
put credit spread for a full win of
$300 on that first trade.
And so we'll now start keeping a record
of the put credit spreads that we sold
located right below 40 deltas each day, as
opposed to the call buying strategy we were
using earlier.
And so let's turn to this next day,
May 2nd.
And in this case, we're selling the 502
and buying the 500 puts and collecting $260
with a worst case scenario loss of 740.
And as we saw previously, the SPY bounced
that day to 505.02. And so our
outcome is gonna be pretty much the same
as our first trade where both puts expired
well below the SPY closing price, thus expiring
worthless.
And again, allowing us to pocket the initial
$260 that we collected.
And so if we keep going through this
same exercise every day through to May 17th,
just like we did before, selling the nearly
40 delta put, usually just a point or
two below SPY's opening price, and buying the
put two points below for protection each day,
first thing in the morning, here are the
results that you'll see if you backtest this
for yourself.
And you can see it's quite a different
story where we literally had no losses.
And the only thing of any note actually
is that on the two highlighted occasions, May
13th and May 16th, the SPY actually closed
below the short puts location.
And so right before the market closed on
those days, once it was obvious that the
SPY was going to close below the puts
price, strike price, we would go ahead and
just buy those puts back to close the
trade.
And the cost of buying those back is
netted out of the profit on the trade
because the profit is always calculated by taking
the initial premium you received and reducing it
by any payments to close the short position
because that is cash outflow, which resulted in
lower profit numbers, you'll notice for those two
trades.
But those were the only two trades where
we even needed to do that.
And the reason we needed to do that
is because in all the other cases, the
SPY closed above the short put, so there
was no need to do anything, but pocket
our initial premium, whereas if the SPY is
about to close in the money, then you
need to buy the puts back to close
the trade.
Otherwise, you'll be assigned 100 shares of SPY
at your short put strike price times the
number of options that you have sold.
And that's not the purpose of this exercise
to actually own SPY shares.
So we just buy it back and close
the trade before that happens.
And so what's interesting is that you'll notice
that while SPY closed lower than where it
was when we entered on those two occasions
highlighted in yellow, we still made money on
the trade, which of course is essentially a
bullish trade where you were hoping the SPY
rallies as much as possible, which will then
cause our options to expire with no value,
allowing us to pocket the initial cash we
received at the outset of the trade.
And we're pointing this out to emphasize just
how powerful the put credit spread trade is,
that even if the stock goes down after
we enter the trade, we still have an
opportunity to win this otherwise bullish trade.
It's amazing.
And so when we summarize the outcome of
this trade, winning all of them with a
profit of 2,685 and a return of
well over 100%, it's obviously no contest in
a bullish month like the first half of
May this year.
And just to drive home how dramatically different
this outcome is, take a look at this
comparison between the two approaches.
And in this scenario, there's obviously no contest
with selling put credit spreads being far superior
in every single category.
And so what I'd like you to take
away from today's video is not that put
credit spreads will always perform better than buying
calls because they actually won't in certain conditions,
but rather that if you are bullish and
you're right, that selling slightly out of the
money, put credit spreads will always win on
a day where the market closes higher than
it opens.
While on the other hand, buying calls, as
we saw from this example, will fail and
fail a lot, only winning a few times
in this case, even though on most days,
we were absolutely right about the direction of
SPY, but not by enough for the calls
to close with any value at all.
And even when they did close with value,
we still lost one.
And even if the stock does manage to
exceed the strike price of the call, that
still does a guarantee that you'll win the
trade because you still need to recover the
premium you paid for the call.
And so the break even for a long
call is actually higher than the call's strike
price.
And so that's why you keep losing so
often when you try to buy relatively inexpensive
calls if you're bullish.
And that's because buying calls have this huge
hurdle.
The stock has to get, first of all,
beyond a strike price for you to make
any money at all in the trade, whereas
with the out of the money put credit
spreads, if the stock closes up, flat, or
even down a little compared to where it
was at the open, you will make money
in all of those cases, which as you
can see from this example, has a huge
effect on the win rate, which in turn
drives profitability and return in almost all cases,
let alone the way that it builds your
confidence as a trader.
So now you know what you've been doing
wrong and why your options trading has been
so inconsistent.
And now you know easily how to turn
things around to dramatically increase your win rate
on options trades if you're even a little
right on a stock's direction.
Pro options traders are well aware of the
edge embedded in put credit spreads and love
to trade them as a result.
Now, if you'd like to learn three more
options strategies that our pro traders use, including
the unique options trick that allows you to
make money while you wait to buy stocks
or ETFs at the price you want, and
the options income strategy that allows you to
make consistent money whether the market goes up
or down or sideways, and how to make
money on a stock or index trade even
if you're wrong on the direction, then click
the link that's appearing right now at the
top right-hand corner of your screen.
That will open up the free workshop registration
page in a new window.
So don't worry, you won't lose this video
or you can register directly for free at
optionsclass.com.